<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z (old posts, page 36)</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index-36.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-03-07T01:11:34Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-36.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-35.atom"/>
  <link rel="previous" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="current" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="prev-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-35.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-36.html"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Using Emacs 40 - Atomic Chrome</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-40-atomic-chrome/</id>
    <updated>2018-01-31T07:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-01-31T07:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-40-atomic-chrome/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org1432f66" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org1432f66"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org1432f66"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thanks to everyone who voted for topics or commented with suggestions
for videos. I'll try to get to them in the coming months.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today is just a quick hit on Atomic Chrome - an Emacs package and
browser extension that allows you to edit web form inputs with Emacs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org1fd9c1a" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org1fd9c1a"&gt;UPDATE&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org1fd9c1a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I forgot to mention that you can set a shortcut key, at least in chrome rather than
clicking on the icon. This makes things much smoother.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All you have to do is:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;chrome://extensions&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the bottom of the page you'll see a button to set &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;keyboard shortcuts&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set the shortcut for Atomic Chrome&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wyPZws66Sic" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="emacs" label="emacs"/>
    <category term="learning" label="learning"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>On Textbooks</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/textbooks/</id>
    <updated>2018-01-27T14:28:44-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-01-27T14:28:44-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/textbooks/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org0e22892" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0e22892"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0e22892"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought I'd answer Alfred Thompson's recent post on &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/01/thinking-about-cs-textbooks.html"&gt;using
textbooks&lt;/a&gt;. Like Alfred, I've never used textbooks particularly
effectively. Even when I taught math I mostly used them as a resource
for problems. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also agree with Alfred in questioning the "flipped class" model or
as I like to call it "homework" for reasons similar to Alfred's. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even back in the Pascal days of APCS getting textbooks was an ordeal
in NYC. First, the book had to cover both the A and AB parts of the
class since I rarely had budget to buy two books for a class, then
they had to be sold by the high school division of the publishing
house eliminating many college texts and finally we had to get the
books on the "NYSTL list" so we could buy and pay for them. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I finally found a book I liked that covered the full year by Nance and
Naps. By then I knew that I wouldn't really work it into the class but
I felt that it explained things, the data structures and algorithms in
particular very well. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's one thing I always look for in a text book. If I'm not tightly
integrating the text then I want the text to be a worthwhile resource
for the student. If a kid doesn't get it in class I want the text book
to be a second chance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When we moved to C++ we moved to Nance and Naps for the language and
Nance and Lambert for the Data Structures. Somehow I got the school to
fund both books. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Everything changed when the AP class went to Java. I never found a
Java based book that covered the data structures in a way I liked but
finding a text was a problem even beyond that hurdle.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All of the Java based texts tightly integrated with some project or
library provide by the author. It was just like the AP case study. If
the case study worked well into your course and the way you taught it
was great, otherwise it was a bear to deal with. I settled on Lewis
and Loftus which integrated their own graphics library but always as
an add on to each chapter rather than tightly integrated.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For my homebrew classes, I've never found a single textbook. The nice
thing today is that there are so many resources already
available. Tutorials, videos, online practice sites like codingbat and
more. There are also a number of authors who make their books
available online for free. I use one - &lt;a href="https://automatetheboringstuff.com/"&gt;Automate the Boring Stuff with
Python&lt;/a&gt; in one of my classes but I purchased a copy for myself and
encourage my students to do so as well if/when they're able to based
on economic situation. Usually I can cobble together a good set of
resources for the students that are both free and probably superior to
any single text book out there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All of this said, it's important that students have resources
independent of the teacher. If you can get a good textbook, that can
be it but fortunately, in this day and age we have many great
alternatives.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Is Teaching CS Hard?</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-teaching-cs-hard/</id>
    <updated>2018-01-21T16:56:52-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-01-21T16:56:52-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-teaching-cs-hard/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org60426af" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org60426af"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org60426af"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last week, Mark Guzdial asked &lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/2018/01/19/what-does-it-mean-for-computer-science-to-be-harder-to-learn-than-other-stem-subjects/"&gt;What does it mean for Computer Science to be harder to learn
than other STEM subjects?&lt;/a&gt; as a follow up to his &lt;a href="https://cacm.acm.org/blogs/blog-cacm/224105-learning-computer-science-is-different-than-learning-other-stem-disciplines/fulltext"&gt;ACM Blog post&lt;/a&gt; this
month and the ensuing discussion.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You should read both posts but here's how Mark started off the follow
up:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I made an argument in my Blog@CACM Post for this month that “Learning
Computer Science is Different than Learning Other STEM Disciplines,”
and on Twitter, I explicitly added “It’s harder.”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When you talk about how hard or easy it is to teach a subject you can
do so at many levels. college, high school, middle etc.. Since most of
my career has been as a High School guy, let's focus there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I do in fact believe that it is hard to teach CS, at least to do it
well but is it harder to teach then other STEM subjects?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's see how we're doing in those other subjects. I took a look at
the New York State &lt;a href="https://data.nysed.gov/reportcard.php?instid=800000081568&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;createreport=1&amp;amp;regents=1"&gt;Regents Exam&lt;/a&gt; results from 2015/2016. I'm certainly
not a believer or supporter of standardized tests but they're a
convenient measure for the sake of this post.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Only 58% of test takers scored 65 or higher on Integrated Algebra and
only 41% scored 3 (proficient) or higher on the Common Core version
with far more students taking the Common Core exam.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Higher performing schools frequently offer Algebra in 8th grade but in
the lower performing districts, students frequently take it over the
course of two years. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Geometry regents boasts a passing rate of about 40%. Trig does a
little better.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The science regents exams look a little better but overall, these are
not terrific results, particularly on the classes that are required
for graduation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It seems that those other STEM fields aren't so easy to teach after all.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand we have CS. If you listen to all the press releases
and media attention on APCS-P from this past year it would seem that
CS is easy to teach and learn. We have all these high school students
mastering a "college level" course and we can prepare teachers to be
master CS instructions with just a bit of in-service professional
development.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The truth is, of course that CS isn't easy to teach. When you're a
summer or after school program or even an elective it's easy to create
a fun experience using shiny tools to self selecting students but when
you have to take everyone and prepare many of them to succeed in more
advanced classes we have a real challenge. We really should be looking
at retention in more advanced CS classes rather than just passing the
intro ones. Most students won't go beyond the intro class in any given
subject but the ones that do must be well prepared. Unfortunately, I
fear that the people who will get the blame when kids drop CS later on
will be the teachers of the more advanced classes regardless of who,
if anyone, is at fault.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teaching CS is hard. It's brand new and very open ended.  When
programming a solution to a problem kids start with a blank
slate. They don't have the library of patterns, vocabulary or &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/programming-idioms"&gt;idioms&lt;/a&gt;
needed to build solitions. There are many ways a teacher can scaffold
the learning. Code tracing, analogies, Parsons problems and more but
the truth is teachers strong in both content and pedagogical knowledge
are still in rather short supply and as Mark wrote on his blog the
body of knowledge on teaching CS is just not that mature.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, Algebra students usually had a first look at some
of the topics prior to the class and much of the class can be
"learned" through memorizing relatively short procedures and
patterns. This might not lead to a depth of understanding but it does
get you past standardized tests. On the science side, the Living
Environment exam is really just a reading test.  On the other hand,
we're supposed to start teaching proof to students in Geometry and
that's really hard to do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, teaching in general is hard and teaching CS is no exception. At
least it is if you're doing it right.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
