<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z (old posts, page 35)</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index-35.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-01-31T13:04:55Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-35.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-34.atom"/>
  <link rel="previous" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="current" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="prev-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-34.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-35.html"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Breaking down problems and writing</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/whats-next/</id>
    <updated>2017-12-14T12:14:33-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-12-14T12:14:33-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/whats-next/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This question appeared on Facebook a few days ago:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Does anyone have an effective way to teach students how to break down
a problem into steps and then solve each step one by one? I think my
students are struggling with a large question and breaking it in
subsequent parts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were some good suggestions. I wanted to add something but didn't
have time then so I thought I'd write it up now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As an aside, it took me forever to find the post again over on
Facebook. If there's a way to mark posts or save a direct link I'd
love to hear it. I had to look through all the CS Ed groups I belong
to manually until I found it again.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I read the program I was reminded of a PD session we had to
attend back at Stuyvesant. Back then the fad was &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Writing_across_the_curriculum"&gt;Writing Across the
Curriculum&lt;/a&gt;. Every teacher in every class was to give some significant
writing assignment, evaluate it and provide feedback. Let's forget the
fact that most of us never had any training or preparation to do so.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On that PD day the guest speaker was &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Zinsser"&gt;William Zinsser&lt;/a&gt;. The first thing
he said was that what we were being asked to do by our principal was
bunk. He then proceeded to give advice on  simple good writing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The procedure he recommended following was to ask yourself (or have
the student ask themselves) "what does my audience need to know next?"
That's your next sentence. Then ask the question again. Rinse and
repeat until done.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was simple and it made sense. It also applied to introductory CS
problems. When starting out, students have a limited CS / programming
tool box so a good question for them to ask when trying to solve a
problem is not only "what do I need to do next? but also "what can I
do next?" 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When students have a limited CS vocabulary and set of idioms - loops,
conditionals, functions, whatever, there will only be so many things
they can do to move a problem along. If they go through the things the
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;can&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; do they will likely fall on to what they &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;should&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's similar to doing a proof in geometry. Students have a set of
givens. Given that set, what can they do? They only know so many
theorems at the beginning. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over time, they'll recognize patterns and develop as problem solvers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're part of the AP CS A teachers facebook group you probably saw
the question. Many good answers were posted. I just wanted to add this
thought to the collection.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="problem-solving" label="problem solving"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New York State moving forward with CS Teacher Certification</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/NY-CS-Certificate/</id>
    <updated>2017-12-12T19:57:37-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-12-12T19:57:37-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/NY-CS-Certificate/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last April I woke up early and trekked up to Albany along with a few
of my Hunter College colleagues to share our thoughts on K12 Computer
Science teacher certification with the Board of Regents. We gave a
presentation to the Regents Higher Education Committee and afterwards
had a chance to talk with some of the Regents as well as other members
of the New York State Department of Education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I left feeling that our proposals were well received and I think
everyone present - both the Hunter and NYSED contingents hoped that
things would move forward on this important issue.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward to today, December 8, 2017. I was up at the crack
of dawn. Driving in the dark in the snow from NYC to Albany to once
again attend a Board of Regents Higher Education Committee
meeting. This time, the agenda item was:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Proposed Amendments to Part 30 of the Regents Rules and Section 52.21
and Part 80 the Regulations of the Commissioner of Education Relating
to a New Certification Area and Tenure Area for Computer Science 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No discussion or debate this time around just the proposal. If I
understand the process correctly, this should come up again at the
March meeting at which point it will be voted on. If approved, it
looks like we'll have a pathway towards certification for CS teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I haven't had a chance to dive into the details but at the meeting a
few key points came up:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As the proposal indicates this will be a subject area in which a
teacher can be certified and be awarded tenure.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be a traditional pathway for new teachers - Bachelors /
Masters degree
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an alternative pathway for people entering from the
workforce
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an extension for teachers with another license so they
won't have to give up tenure in their current license.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an "individual evaluation" pathway which sounds to me
like it could catch people who fall through the cracks.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There looks to be a sensible ramp up period - until September 2022
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's a grandfathering provision that looks to last 10 years.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This sounds like a smart sensible plan. Multiple pathways, shallow
ramp up and provisions to protect existing teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, the devil is in the details. What's an approved program?
Can a grandfathered teacher teach all CS classes or just intro ones?
etc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I said, I haven't had a chance to dive into the details yet but
this is very exciting.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Prior to the meeting I was chatting with a few other people
attending. One, a &lt;a href="http://www.uft.org/"&gt;UFT&lt;/a&gt; representative was very excited about the
prospect. Another contingent, a group from &lt;a href="https://www.nysut.org/"&gt;NYSUT&lt;/a&gt; was very much against
a new certification area. Their position was that this would create a
teacher shortage because no one would have a CS license and no one
would get one due to the difference in salary between teaching and the
tech industry. I've already written on how I feel that this is a &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry"&gt;red
herring&lt;/a&gt;. What shocked me though was their feeling that "we already
have many non-CS teachers effectively teaching CS across the
state. They're doing a great job and don't need any additional content
or pedagogical knowledge." I think they're wrong and I also think that
when we as a community talk about how our summer professional
development is all that's needed, we undercut CS education and
the teaching profession as a whole.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any event this was a big step for New York. I tried to individually
thank as many of the participants as I could for helping shepherd this
along but could only speak to a few so I'll just give a blanket thank
you here to the NY State Board of Regents, Board of Education and
State Education department.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="certification" label="certification"/>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Making contest problems and writing tests</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-2017-making-tests/</id>
    <updated>2017-12-11T19:39:16-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-12-11T19:39:16-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-2017-making-tests/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'm now well behind in &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt;. Traveling up to Michigan to see
my son and my brother and his family will do that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was planning on working to catch up but got distracted earlier by
&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/comments/7idn6k/question_why_does_the_difficulty_vary_so_much/"&gt;this thread&lt;/a&gt; on the Advent of Code subreddit. Specifically &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/comments/7idn6k/question_why_does_the_difficulty_vary_so_much/dqy08tk/"&gt;this comment&lt;/a&gt;
by &lt;a href="http://was.tl/"&gt;Eric Wastl&lt;/a&gt;, the contest creator. The thread is about the level of
difficulty of the various problems and Eric's comment talks about some
of the factors that go into creating a good collection of problems for
a contest and the difficulties involved.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It made me think of a conversation I had twenty years ago with Rob
Kolstad. We were chatting at a programming competition while the
students were hacking away. We were discussing that there were only so
many questions that a typical high school or college competition can
ask:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Mathy question
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recursion / divide and conquer etc.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graph stuff
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dynamic Programming
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and I think one or two more. The actual questions were just window
dressing on these fundamental question types. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can see this in many competitions including Advent of Code -
particularly if you look over all three years. This is not a
criticism. I love Advent of Code and think that Eric and the people
he's working with are doing a great job . Read Eric's comment to get a
deeper dive into what he thinks about as a contest designer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also got to thinking how similar creating a competition is to
creating an exam. Maybe that's because I'm currently writing the final
my students will take in a couple of days. In class tests are
certainly not the best of assessments but they do have their place and
in any event, they're frequently  required by school or departmental
policy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are many similarities between what teachers consider when making
tests to what contest designers consider. What concepts and techniques
must the students use? Are the problems too similar? Do they ramp up
in difficulty? Are they all or nothing or can a student incrementally
work their way to a solution? Does one problem lead into another? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's no big reveal or surprise here today. Just something I've been
thinking about. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of busy days coming up but maybe over the weekend I can get
back to Advent of Code.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="assessment" label="assessment"/>
    <category term="contests" label="contests"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
