<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xmlns:fh="http://purl.org/syndication/history/1.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z (old posts, page 40)</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index-40.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-09-05T21:31:45Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-40.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-39.atom"/>
  <link rel="previous" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-41.atom"/>
  <link rel="current" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="next-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-41.atom"/>
  <link rel="prev-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-39.atom"/>
  <fh:archive/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-40.html"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Certification The Old Way</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/certification-the-old-way/</id>
    <updated>2018-07-02T17:18:24-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-07-02T17:18:24-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/certification-the-old-way/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org2914da7" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org2914da7"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org2914da7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've taken part in a few conversations and read more than a few
threads on teacher certification exams recently. Specifically, CS
teacher certification exams. There are a bunch of them floating
around. There's the &lt;a href="https://www.ets.org/praxis/prepare/materials/5651%0A"&gt;Praxis&lt;/a&gt; offered by ETS, the one from the &lt;a href="https://www.nestest.com/TestView.aspx?f=HTML_FRAG/NT315_PrepMaterials.html%0A"&gt;National
Evaluation Series&lt;/a&gt;,  the &lt;a href="https://www.west.nesinc.com/TestView.aspx?f=HTML_FRAG/WA073_PrepMaterials.html"&gt;Washington Evaluator Test Series&lt;/a&gt; one and then
there's what's &lt;a href="https://www.weteachcs.org/"&gt;going on in Texas&lt;/a&gt;. NY State says it will eventually
develop their own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have mixed feelings about exams like these. From what I've seen some
of the content seems fine and the "stuff you have to know for the
test" isn't necessarily the worst in the world. As a one time
gatekeeper, I'm not necessarily happy with them but they can provide a
test for a basic threshold of knowledge with out too much focus on
test prep.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, they're just the tip of the iceberg, many states including
New York make their teacher candidates also take other exams. In NY
candidates must take the &lt;a href="https://dianeravitch.net/2013/06/03/what-is-edtpa-and-why-do-critics-dislike-it/"&gt;edTPA&lt;/a&gt; which is expensive for the teacher
candidate but a big money maker for Pearsons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All of this came out of NCLB back in the day which also created
requirements like "must complete an approved program" as opposed to
just accruing a bunch of relevant education and content credits which
in turn led to more courses like &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/math-for-math-teachers/"&gt;Math for Math Teachers&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For you youngsters out there (which I guess is most of you), I thought
I'd share what it was like back in the day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back then, New York City certified it's own teachers as opposed
to now when everything's done directly through the state. The system
was, in my opinion far superior. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I came in as a career changer - I was doing computer work at the
time - and I came in as a math teacher since there was no CS. Since
math was an area of need it was a little easier for me to get my foot
in the door than it would have been for say an English teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start I went down to the Board of Education in Brooklyn armed with
my college transcript and waited in line. I then met with someone who
evaluated my transcript. Normally, to get started, I would have needed
a certain number of education credits and a certain number of content
(math) credits. I think the magic number was 24 for the content. Since
math was an area of needed you could get started with a TPD license
(Temporary Per Diem) which required no education credits going in. You
had to get 18 graduate education credits within the first, I think two
years and take the National Teacher Exam. You also got one period off
to be mentored which was a pretty sweet deal. Of course it wouldn't be
that simple. I only had 16 math credits so fell short but the
evaluator decided to give me credit for a couple of my more mathy CS
classes like Algorithms to get me over the hump.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I then went to another line to get a brief mini physical and at some
point I was fingerprinted and I had my TPD. The BOE then ran a one
week "learn to teach" bootcamp and I was left to find my own job which
I was fortunately able to do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, I had my foot in the door but as a TPD I had no job protections. I
was observed at least 6 times a year and could be fired at will. In
fact, TPD's were annually given pink slips in the spring and had to be
rehired again in the Fall if their schools wanted them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I got my 18 education credits over the next two years and took the NTE
which was both the easiest and hardest exam I ever had to
take. Easiest content wise but hard because it was a FULL DAY of non
stop writing and my hand was cramped up into a club by days end. That
got me to the next level - the PPT - Preparatory Provisional License,
I think.  This allowed me to be appointed. Once appointed you had job
retention and seniority rights. Not tenure, but a step closer and you
did get some legit job protections. If you started the process with
education credits to go along with content credits you could have
started directly with the PPT. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The final step to get that appointment with the PPT is that you had to
go for an interview with the &lt;b&gt;Board of Examiners&lt;/b&gt;. This was the good
part. After work one day I went down to Brooklyn Tech, waited my turn
and then was ushered into a classroom. A typical panel would have a
principal, an assistant principal in your subject area, and a couple
of teachers, again in your subject area. They could grill you on
anything they wanted. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They could ask you general teaching questions (usually cached in a scenario):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how do yo u handle a mixed level class,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how do you handle a disruptive student&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Preparation questions:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how would you motivate a  class on the Pythagorean Theorem?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How would you turn a lesson on solving quadratics in to a hands on
lab experience?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
or content questions:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;solve this calculus problem…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Derive this theorem…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't remember how long the session lasted but afterwards I left and
a couple of weeks later, I had my PPT and was appointed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were a couple of last steps - tenure, which pretty much just
happened since my AP and Principal were both happy with my performance
and I had to get my Masters. Back then you could get a Masters in
anything so I decided to get it in CS rather than Education. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
There was a lot to like about the old system. I've never been a big
fan of a lot of the education credits one has to get and while I still
needed a number of them, I'm glad I had the option to take mostly
content credits. I also like what amounted to being evaluated face to
face by an individual rather than an amorphous bureaucracy. I also
loved the mentoring I got but while the system gave me the class
relief time to allow it to happen I think much of the value was due to
my colleagues at Seward Park High School without whom I would have
washed out. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The biggest thing I liked was the Board of Examiners. I found it
somewhat stressful since I was never a math guy but the idea that
you've got to prove yourself to a bunch of local city educators was
HUGE. You weren't expected to give the "correct for the test" answer,
you had to convince people that you might have to work for or with
that you got the goods.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm sure we'll never go back to the old days but I thought the current
generation might be interested in hearing what it was like back in the
day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Talking about CS teacher certification at CSTA 2018</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csta-2018/</id>
    <updated>2018-07-01T19:57:06-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-07-01T19:57:06-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csta-2018/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org59368bf" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org59368bf"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org59368bf"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I mentioned in my last post, this coming weekend is the Computer
Science Teachers Association (CSTA) conference. I've been a member of
CSTA since the beginning but this will be only the second time I've
made it to the annual conference.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The CSTA conference might be the largest conference specifically for
k12 computer science teachers and that makes it different from
conferences like SIGCSE which is for CS education and education
research at all levels or ISTE which seems to be more of an Ed Tech
conference.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I really enjoyed the conference last year but as the sessions seemed
to be weighted towards beginning CS teachers and towards the CSTA
standards I found most of the value in the "hallway track" when I got
to meet and chat with CS teachers from all over the country.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Glancing at the program, there looks to be a bunch of interesting
sessions and this time more sessions that I think I'll personally be
interested in . 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm also giving a talk. New York State just approved and created K12
Computer Science Teacher Certification and we're currently making
plans to roll out our Masters and Certificate programs for CS teachers
as soon as we get state approval. The Masters program will be largely
for preservice teacher candidates and the certificate program for in
service teachers certified in other areas. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The talk will cover a bit of the history of CS Education in New York,
what the state is doing and mostly what where building at Hunter and
why. It should be a fun talk. I'm hoping for some people from other
states attend so we can have a rich discussion during the session.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, if you're going to be at the CSTA conference, I'd love to see
you either at my session or at the conference in general. I'll be
spending most of my non session time there with my friends at GitHub
education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For those of you can't make it, I hope to blog about the weekend and I
hope others do as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="csed" label="csed"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Using Emacs Episode 50 - presentations</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-50-presentations/</id>
    <updated>2018-06-30T14:10:24-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-06-30T14:10:24-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-50-presentations/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org37b1bdd" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org37b1bdd"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org37b1bdd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next weekend I'll be attending the Computer Science Teachers
Association's &lt;a href="https://www.csteachers.org/general/custom.asp?page=2018Conference"&gt;annual conference.&lt;/a&gt; It's probably the biggest conference
focussed on K12 Computer Science education. This year, in addition to
attending, I'll be giving a talk on preservice and inservice CS
teacher preparation programs. I'll be talking about the new New York
State certification requirements along with what we're rolling out at
Hunter College. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This means putting together a slide deck for the session. When I have
to work collaboratively with non-Emacs users, I will usually go to
Google Docs for presentations. It works and the collaborative aspects
are nice but tools like Google Docs and Powerpoint are designed around
composing slides manually. I much prefer to use a tool where I can
focus on writing my presentation and have the tool turn it into a
presentation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Org-mode is of course the ideal tool. As an outliner, it lends itself
to organizing a talk:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;* topic 1
   the content for slide one
* topic 2
   the content for slide two
* topic 3
   etc.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I can embed code, tables, images, and more. I can also cycle
visibility so I can focus on individual sections. Org-mode also has a
number of export options to take a plain org file which is just ascii
with markup and export it as a presentation. In the video, I'll take a
quick look at &lt;code&gt;ox-beamer&lt;/code&gt;, which exports to a Beamer presentation in LaTeX and then a PDF,
&lt;code&gt;epresent&lt;/code&gt; which presents right in Emacs and finally &lt;code&gt;ox-reveal&lt;/code&gt; wich
creates a &lt;code&gt;reveal.js&lt;/code&gt; presentation. I ultimately decide to continue to
use &lt;code&gt;ox-reveal&lt;/code&gt; as it's pretty simple and flexible and I can also directly serve
the final presentation from my own laptop, a usb drive, or directly
from GitHub. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Check out the video to see how. If you want more information on using
&lt;code&gt;ox-reveal&lt;/code&gt; check out my earlier &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-11-reveal"&gt;Using Emacs post and video&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;





&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bRoSpJ23Kzk" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="emacs" label="emacs"/>
    <category term="presentations" label="presentations"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hunter CS - a lot of progress in a short time</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/</id>
    <updated>2018-06-29T17:41:05-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-06-29T17:41:05-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org5c6917c" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org5c6917c"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org5c6917c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I was back on campus for an early orientation session for
Hunter's incoming Daedalus CS honors students. It was the first time
all of us got to meet face to face. The students I met with will be
my third cohort. I got to thinking how far we've come in under three
years. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hunter's had a strong but little known undergraduate
CS program for as long as I've known. Much like any program, we've got
our strengths and weaknesses but you go through our program and
academically you'll be as well prepared as from anywhere else. We have some
challenges being a commuter school, a liberal arts school and a school
not commonly thought of for CS but the core has always been there.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hunter has been making a concerted effort to up its computer science
game and my joining the team has been part of that. The Daedalus
program is an honors scholarship program. It's similar to the well
known CUNY Macaulay program but it's specific to Hunter and specific to
CS. Our kids get scholarships, laptops, special classes (with me),
activities and events and more. Our first cohort had 12. This past
year we had 23 but a funny thing happened right after we started. Hunter's
Macaulay CS students heard about what was going on and wanted in. The
end result was that last years cohort had a total of 27 students
as we invited the incoming Hunter Macaulay CS students into the
fold. This year, we're up to about 50 total and it looks to be a very
strong group. To be honest I'm a little
scared of growing this quickly. The kids will be great but it will be
a challenge building the community across multiple classes. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm really pleased with the first two cohorts performance both in
class and out. They're progressing well through the academic program
and are ahead of schedule in terms of internships and outside
activities but I'm even happier that they've been working to level up
Hunter CS as a whole. They started a once a week Dojo last year where
all Hunter CS students could hang out and work on tech projects and
have a speaker series on tap for this coming year. For my part, I've
got a couple of new ideas up my sleeve but I'm going to keep them
under wraps for now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Three years ago Hunter wasn't so much on the map for CS inclined high
school students and while there's much work to be done, many of our
incoming cohort members chose us over other programs that have
traditionally been considered CS strongholds.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the same time, our efforts to connect Hunter CS to the NY Tech community have begun to
raise our profile on the other end of the pipeline.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's still a long rode ahead but I thought I'd give myself a day to
look back on how far we've come in a short time. Having a great public college option for CS
education is critical for NYC. This was one of the things I left Stuy to
accomplish and we're well on our way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="college" label="college"/>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>PD for people who know CS</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pd-for-cs/</id>
    <updated>2018-06-27T14:41:59-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-06-27T14:41:59-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pd-for-cs/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orga9212ce" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orga9212ce"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orga9212ce"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I saw a couple of tweets from Sarah Judd this morning:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;A lot of CS Ed PD assumes you are new to CS. I really want CS Ed PD for people like us that came from a CS background and want to understand the pedagogy for CS in particular better. Do you know of some?&lt;/p&gt;— Sarah Judd (@SarahEJudd) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SarahEJudd/status/1011785286693552139?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;June 27, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Yes! I love SIGCSE and CSTA. I just feel like... Math teachers don't get PD that starts with "and this is how you add and subtract!" and I'd love more CS PD that assumes the content is there, and can focus on the pedagogy.&lt;/p&gt;— Sarah Judd (@SarahEJudd) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SarahEJudd/status/1011966102795059200?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;June 27, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It wasn't the first time I've heard this refrain. Last year I attended
my first CSTA conference. I had numerous conversations with CS
teachers on the fact that everything was on an intro level in terms of
both content and teaching. Further conversations with local teachers
with stronger CS backgrounds led me to run a professional development
session at Hunter this past election day for more experienced CS
teachers at schools that offered more than the basics.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While it's not surprising that most of the PD opportunities for CS teachers are
rather rudimentary given that nationally most programs are new and
most teachers are new to the subject but there are a few deeper
reasons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start, there are big players in the CS Ed movement that are pushing
curricula and specific programs and that leads to scripted PD for
their products and not depth of knowledge nor deep pedagogical content
knowledge let alone basic pedagogy. Add to this the fact that many of
the "thought leaders" in the space don't have experience teaching CS
at the K12 level and in many cases don't have a background either in
teaching nor tech and you can see where the problem comes from. On top
of this we have the erosion of respect for teaching as a profession
where reformers are trying to take the teacher out of teaching and are
trying to reduce pedagogy to following scripts. This problem goes well
beyond CS Ed but as the new kid on the block it probably hits us
hardest.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any case, preparing beginners is both necessary and appropriate for
the time being but we can and must do a better job than what's
currently "state of the art." At the same time we have to do something
with the CS teachers who indeed do have strong content knowledge but
don't feel comfortable with imparting that knowledge.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what should we do?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For new teachers the solution will ultimately have to come
from pre-service programs but what we end up getting is going to
largely be dictated on what's required by individual states. If states
merely require passing an exam like the Praxis CS exam which, from
what I can gather isn't a horrible content exam then we're going to
see CS teachers bumble through their early to mid careers while trying
to figure out how to teach CS much like I did way back when. If they
end up endorsing pre-service programs that are focused on specific
curricula - APCS-A for teachers, APCS-P for teachers, &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/math-for-math-teachers/"&gt;Math for Math
teachers&lt;/a&gt; if you will but for CS, we're also not going to get strong
well prepared pedagogues. On the other hand if you can design a
program that has a strong pedagogical component to go along with the
content, you have a chance. Even with a well designed program
implementation will still be a challenge. Who will teach it? Education
professors who don't have CS backgrounds? CS professors with little
pedagogical training? Neither of those groups necessarily have any
real experience as actual K12 teachers. If you can find honest to
goodness experienced, strong K12 CS teachers to teach your pedagogy
courses that's a big win but that's going to be hard in most cases. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think we designed a great program at Hunter and have a practical and
strong implementation plan. If you're going to be
at CSTA2018 you can hear all about it and why we designed it as we did
in the talk I'm giving. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For the more experienced I don't have a universal answer but I can say
what I'm planning. Teachers in NY have to complete 100 CTLE hours
every five years. For beginners, there are plenty of options, at least
content wise. For teachers who know CS, not so much. I was at a meetup
talking to a few friends a couple of weeks ago and one mentioned that
they get most of their hours in Math for America CS
workshops. Unfortunately more than a few of my CS teacher friends who
are in MFA tell me that the CS content in these workshops, while they
do satisfy the hours, are somewhat lacking on the CS / CS pedagogy
side.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's what I'm planning - we (Hunter) will host a once a month
dinner/session for CS teachers who are a little farther along CS
wise. I haven't worked out all the details yet but I've got a few tech
companies that are already interested in sponsoring and helping out
should we need anything and we'll probably set most of our agenda for
the year at the first session where I'll make my best guess at a
useful agenda. This is something I'm pretty excited about. It should
help create a network of more experienced CS teachers which will both
help bolster that segment of the community and provide a long term
resource to newcomers and it should be a lot of fun.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In some ways, this is why I ended up joining Hunter. Regardless of
what the city and state do, we're going to prepare the teachers and if
you have a well prepared teacher, you've got a shot.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="csed" label="csed"/>
    <category term="pedagogy" label="pedagogy"/>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Using Emacs Episode 49 mu4e-conversation</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-49-mu4e-conversation/</id>
    <updated>2018-06-21T13:28:41-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-06-21T13:28:41-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-49-mu4e-conversation/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org892f4be" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org892f4be"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org892f4be"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've been using Emacs for email for a couple of years now. Not for
everything, for now my personal email is still Gmail but work is sent
and read through Emacs. I'm currently using &lt;a href="https://www.djcbsoftware.nl/code/mu/mu4e.html"&gt;mu4e&lt;/a&gt; and while it has a
few quirks and limitations, I like it very much. You can take a look
on how I configure and use it &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-39-mu4e/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other day I saw &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/emacs/comments/8qryri/mu4econversation_single_buffer_fullthread_display/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; thread on Emacs about a new package -
&lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/ambrevar/mu4e-conversation"&gt;mu4e-conversation&lt;/a&gt;. It's a package that deals with email threads.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's pretty cool. You can invoke it whenever you're in the headers
view you can just run &lt;code&gt;M-x mu4e-conversation&lt;/code&gt; and it combines all the
email messages in the current thread into a single buffer. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's pretty nice. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can navigate between messages in the thread with &lt;code&gt;C-c C-n&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;C-c C-p&lt;/code&gt; and use most if not all of the usual mu4e goodness but on
top of that you can also toggle what the author calls tree mode by
hitting &lt;code&gt;V&lt;/code&gt;. Tree mode turns the thread into an org-mode tree - also
extremely cool.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On top of this, you can also make mu4e your default viewing mode by
setting a single variable with &lt;code&gt;(setq mu4e-view-func 'mu4e-conversation)&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Although it's very cool, I'm not sure if mu4e-conversation will find
its way into my workflow or not and probably won't know for a
while. This is mostly due to the fact that it's summer so work email
slows down and I won't have too many long threads to play with this
on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'll report back once I give it a fair shake but in the meantime if
anyone out there has had the time to play with it, let us know what
you think.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/V5efS8uXANI" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="editing" label="editing"/>
    <category term="emacs" label="emacs"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How I Grokked OOP</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/how-i-grokked-oop/</id>
    <updated>2018-06-14T12:15:41-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-06-14T12:15:41-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/how-i-grokked-oop/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org52c16b8" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org52c16b8"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org52c16b8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Time to get back to CS and CS Ed related blogging.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last week, in Garth Flint's post about his &lt;a href="https://gflint.wordpress.com/2018/06/01/747/"&gt;summer plans&lt;/a&gt;, Garth
mentioned wanting to get his head around Object Oriented Programming
and possibly taking a course to help him get there. I thought I'd talk
a little about how I got my head around OOP here and some of the
difficulties I faced then and what people might face now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Nowadays, kids are faced with OOP pretty early on. If they take APCS-A
they're using Java which is Object Oriented. Same if they start
at a college using Java. If they start with C++ or Python they may or
may not see objects early on. In any event, the nature of that first
course doesn't really lend itself to really grokking OOP. Even if a
student takes a class prior to APCS-A or it's college equivalent,
they're pretty y raw. Small programs with just a few constructs don't
really show the uses of OOP. Both inheritance and interfaces can feel
forced in a first year course and when the examples are artificial and
wonky and their are easier ways to accomplish the same task, it's hard
for a student to really buy into the paradigm.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, in all fairness, I'm not a big fan of Object Oriented Programming
and it's usually not the first tool I go to. That said, it's a useful
tool and it has it's place.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I cut my teeth in the 1980s. I went to the Courant Institute at
NYU. The core language back then was Pascal which had a number of
limitations including only supporting single file programs. Somewhere
along the line I taught myself C which most professors were happy to
accept assignments in. I never heard of OOP in my formal
schooling. Some time near or soon after I graduated I had heard of
this C++ thing but hadn't used it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After working my way through school I spent some time as a developer
at Goldman Sachs. I was the only guy on my team doing Windows 2.1
development. Windows 2.1 was built on top of DOS. It's big improvement
over Windows 1.0 was that it supported overlapping windows. Pretty cool.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/8/8f/Windows_2.1.png" alt="Windows_2.1.png" width="300px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I learned to program Windows like everyone else:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.charlespetzold.com/oop/pw1.png" alt="pw1.png" width="200px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was all done in C. The big project I was on was for Global
Equities. Specifically, supporting trading of Japanese Warrants. I had
to write a trading system and in doing that implement among other
things a mini spreadsheet in C from bare metal.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was probably going to be the most complex thing I designed and
built from scratch to date. I had a bunch of cells that were
associated with either rows or columns or both and all sorts of
complex interactions. I needed a way to manage complexity and even
though I didn't use the term at the time, manage state. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
C doesn't have a lot of fancy in language constructs to help and I was
somewhat on an island - I taught myself C and there weren't any
experienced C / Windows programmers in my group or on my floor so I
had to figure things out on my own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's what I came up with, or rather something like what I came up
with – it was close to 30 years ago and I don't even remember 100% of
what it was supposed to do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I decided to create a single file for each concept -
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cell.c / cell.h for cells&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;row.c / row.h for rows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sheet.c / sheet.h for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In each, I would do something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* sheet.c */&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* things declared here are "global" but limited to this file **/&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sheet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sheets&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* an array of the sheets */&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* functions that will be made available to other files */&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* return a pointer to the named sheet */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sheet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;sheet_get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* implementation */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* create a new sheet */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sheet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;sheet_create&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;rows&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* implementation/&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* functions that will only be used internally */&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sheet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;allocate_sheet_memory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;rows&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/*implementation*/&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* etc */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* sheet.h */&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;   Note that only the headers for the exterrnally available stuff is included&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;*/&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sheet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;sheet_get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sheet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;sheet_create&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;rows&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The idea is that everything about a sheet is in &lt;code&gt;sheet.c&lt;/code&gt; and only a
few functions are made available to the rest of the program via the
header file. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Shortly after I designed the program, I started to delve into OOP at
the encouragement of some colleagues. I read Meyer:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1392538685l/3328934.jpg" alt="3328934.jpg" width="200px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and the first edition of Booch: 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.pearsonhighered.com/assets/bigcovers/0/8/0/5/0805353402.jpg" alt="0805353402.jpg" width="200px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I realized that in a way I was implementing singleton objects in
C. The file declared the object. The functions I exposed via the
header files were public, the other functions private and the "global"
variables that were local to the file, private class variables.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There was no inheritance but it did help me encapsulate functionality
and state. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It turns out I saw something like this when I briefly looked at Ada. I
think it was called Object Typed Programming - objects with only a
single instance and no inheritance. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The books gave me the official names for things but the project I was
developing gave me the context to where it all made sense. I had a
problem to solve that didn't lend itself to a low level imperative
language but you work with the tools you have and this is what I came
up with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Unfortunately, it's harder for beginners as projects are smaller and
while there are good small example of OOP there's also so much going
on in a course like APCS-A. It gets more convoluted when you're using
Python or C++ as you might be shown Objects in a C++ class while
professor is really teaching C with Objects rather than doing things
the C++ way. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One thing that helps is using a language or tool where objects make
sense. NetLogo - used in Stuy's intro course is a nice one. Turtles
and patches - the inhabitants of the NetLogo can be viewed as
objects. I'd draw heavily on NetLogo analogies when teaching APCS at
Stuy. There are also tools like BlueJ which is tied closely to objects
and is probably terrific at giving structure to help objects make
sense but I don't like those types of tools for other reasons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, it is just a tool and to be honest, I'm not
really a big fan of OOP. I'll use it but it's not my go to paradigm.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'll leave you with this video which talks about why:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QM1iUe6IofM" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Giving control of NYC's specialized schools to a political appointee</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat-part2/</id>
    <updated>2018-06-04T08:00:40-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-06-04T08:00:40-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat-part2/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgda4fee7" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgda4fee7"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgda4fee7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I shared my thoughts on Bill de Blasio's plans to "fix" the
selection criteria for New York City's specialized high schools. If
you haven't read the post, you can find it &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was going to get back to CS and CS Ed related blogging today but
there's more to the story.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In spite of what BdB stated, it's not enough for him to switch to another
measure - the middle school state exam along with some modifiers. This
is about ending the exam altogether and not replacing it with anything
better. Here's a link to information on the proposed legislation for
&lt;a href="https://legiscan.com/NY/bill/A10427/2017"&gt;New York Assembly Bill 10427&lt;/a&gt; including links to the actual text.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's a lot of beurobabble but the end game is to basically allow
the chancellor (not sure if this means city or state) to do whatever
they want.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here are some of the key points:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seats would ultimately go to the top 5 to 7 percent of each middle school's
class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These students would have to also be classified in the top 25% city wide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top is defined by a composite score of multiple measures as
determined by the chancellor which means anything goes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remaining seats will be filled by
lottery of all students with a 3.7 GPA or greater.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's not clear how the students would be allocated to each of the
specialized schools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what does this all mean? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Multiple measures could mean the state test + average. It could mean
average + recommendation. It could be shoe size + favorite color. The
chancellor also decides how to weight these multiple measures. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This means that the politicians can do whatever they want to paint any
picture they want regardless of how their ideological and political
games hurt kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Any teacher, in fact, any rational adult  will tell you that middle
schools are not interchangeable. The top students at one middle school
are typically not at the same level as top students at another
one. I'm sure you can cluster middle schools in terms of the students
they graduate, what the students know and can do and the clusters will
likely fall on economic lines. This is the problem that BdB should be
addressing not how to rig the specialized school admissions stats. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even if this is done right, you're assuming an even distribution of
top gifted students across all the middle schools. If one school has
higher concentration of gifted students, they're out of luck. The end
result is that if you attend an SP or other gifted program for eighth
grade you'll likely be locked out of the specialized schools. What if
a particular middle school is attractive to all of our top math team
talent? Only a couple will get in to the specialized schools under the
new system since each school is allocated a fixed number of slots. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I guess this does make sense if you don't believe in gifted students
or gifted education but then why not just get rid of the specialized
schools to begin with rather than playing these games. This "solution"
will result in parents having to decide - do I send my kids to the
gifted middle school program and hurt their chances to get into a
specialized high school or do I try to find the lowest performing
school I can find and have my kid stand out. This is pretty messed up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, though, you have to remember that any change to
the process can help one group and hurt another. Stuy, for example has
46% of it's students on free or reduced lunch and is about 70%
Asian. If in the new system you're increasing the percent population
of an under represented group, you're likely reducing the percentage
of Asian students. So, you're creating opportunities for a number of as of yet
undetermined students (who might not be properly prepared for the
experience) at the expense of economically disadvantaged Asian
students who have proven to be prepared for the experience. Wouldn't
a better solution be to fix the opportunities presented at the middle
schools rather than rig the system of high school acceptance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Going further, a response on another blog noted that BdB probably
refused to do anything with the admissions criteria of the non big
three because they all had numbers that he would consider more
diverse. The commenter provided the Black / Latino percentages, I added the
free and reduced lunch numbers:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="border" border-spacing="10px"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;School&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Percent Black / Latino&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Free / Reduced Lunch&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Brooklyn Latin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;28%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;61%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSMSE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;26%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;46%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSAS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;17%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;25%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Queens Sci&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;12%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;64%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All the more reason to run some tests or analysis there. Of course, if
you look further you'll note that HSAS only has 25% of its students on
free or reduced lunch so is it really doing better than Stuy or Sci
with ~45% low income students  each  or Brooklyn Tech which supports
62% or are we to say that there's low income and then there's the
right low income?
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Certainly the education system needs work but the proposed legislation
is not a solution. It's taking a flawed but objective measure and
replacing it with essentially chancellor's discretion. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If the legislation passes, by the year 2022 we will have admissions to
what used to be some of the nations finest high schools determined by
a political appointee rather than an objective test.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a shame. It was very important to my wife and me to have our kids
go to public schools and I was very happy to have been able to
navigate the system with them from first grade through high school
graduation with only a few bumps along the way. With this nonsense
from the political left and the privatization push from the political
right (or actually both sides) pretty soon there will be nothing left.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="gifted" label="gifted"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Changing Admissions to the NYC Specialized High Schools</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/</id>
    <updated>2018-06-03T07:01:31-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-06-03T07:01:31-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgdb72ea1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgdb72ea1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgdb72ea1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, Bill de Blasio, the current Mayor of New York City outlined
how he would "fix" our specialized schools. The schools he was
referring to were the "big three" of Stuyvesant, Bronx Science, and
Brooklyn Tech and then five additional schools - The High School  for
Math Science and Engineering at CCNY, The High School for American
Studies at Lehman, Brooklyn Latin, The Queens Arts and Science High
School at
York College, and Staten Island Tech.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All use a single SAT style test, the SHSAT, for admission. The Big Three are
locked into that system unless there are changes made by the state
legislature. The Mayor can make changes to the admissions criteria of
the other five on his own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem, as stated by Chalkbeat writers Alex Zimmerman and  Monica
Disare is that: 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The city’s specialized high schools — considered some of the crown
jewels of New York City’s education system — accept students based on
a single test score. Over the last decade, they have come under fire
for offering admissions to few students of color: While two-thirds of
city students are black or Hispanic, only about 10 percent of
admissions offers to those schools go to black or Hispanic students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I normally don't write about things like this but given my history at
and with Stuyvesant I thought I should.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Before getting started, my biases - I believe in public schools, not
charters, I also believe that a system should have gifted programs and
magnet schools and also a mix of large comprehensive schools and
smaller niche ones. Additionally, while I do believe in gifted
programs I'm not sure at what point it makes sense to start offering
them. When we were looking at elementary schools for our own kids we
opted for a neighborhood public school rather than applying to the
district gifted program as we felt it offered a better overall
education. On the other hand, had our kids not made Stuyvesant, I'm
not sure what we would have done. Part of that was due to the fact
that the Bloomberg administration destroyed just about all the large
comprehensive schools so, other than that large test schools and
LaGuardia, good luck finding a school that was strong in the
humanities, sciences and offered a robust music program. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org2eb1006" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org2eb1006"&gt;The overall picture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org2eb1006"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For reference, here are &lt;a href="http://www.theschoolboards.com/showthread.php/4324-Specialized-High-School-SHSAT-Cutoff-Scores-for-2018"&gt;unofficial cutoff scores&lt;/a&gt; for the specialized
schools from 2018 along with the NY State data on free and reduced
lunch for 2017. Note that there's overlap between the schools. I
separated out SI Tech since geography probably affects it's numbers
more than the other schools and I separated the big three from the
remaining four because I think the three are all substantially larger. The
free and reduced lunch percent is important because I believe an
entire school qualifies for Title I funding if the number's
over 40 so while these schools are not populated entirely by low
income students, all but HSAS has a substantial number and there's a
chance, some say a good one that at best BdB's plans will merely
shuffle which low income kids get in rather than actually solving the
root problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="border" border-spacing="10px"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;School&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Lowest Score admitted&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;High Score&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Pct free or reduced lunch&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Stuyvesant&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;559&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;698&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;46&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Bronx Science&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;518&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;637&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;45&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Brooklyn Tech&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;493&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;668&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;62&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSMSE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;516&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;616&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;46&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSAS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;516&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;633&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Brooklyn Latin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;482&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;555&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;61&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Queens Sci&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;538&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;542&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;64&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;SI Tech&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;519&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;660&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;div id="outline-container-org23e0e41" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org23e0e41"&gt;The plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org23e0e41"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org69604f3" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org69604f3"&gt;Part 1 - test prep&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org69604f3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There's idea here is that test prep is rampant for SHSAT and that the
test can be gamed. This may or may not be true but if it is then it's
safe to assume that a lot of low income kids are doing test
prep either by prioritizing test prep programs in family budgets,
working off of an SHSAT test prep book or by attending a middle school
that has some form of prep. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There has long been a program on the books called "The Discovery
Program" which has a free city run test prep component and also a
summer component. The summer component is for low income students who
score within "a few points" of the school in question's cutoff
score. At the end of the summer, I believe the students retest and in
general make the school in question.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;This program is a good thing and should be reinstated&lt;/b&gt; but I don't
know if it will result in the changes that BdB is looking for. More
likely Stuy will get its discovery kids from Science and Science from
Tech. As there are already many low income students at all of the
schools there's no indication that this would increase the number of
under represented groups which is BdB's goal. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's also worth noting that there's a sizable chunk of Brooklyn Tech
students that don't perform particularly well on regents exams.
Everyone knows I'm not a fan of standardized tests and I don't
believe that students that score a "few points" lower on the SHSAT are
any less qualified to be in a specialized school but at the lowest
performing end of these schools, one has to ask how specialized is it
really?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org1c2c479" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org1c2c479"&gt;Part 2 - use state test scores instead of the SHSAT&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org1c2c479"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This &lt;b&gt;could be&lt;/b&gt; a &lt;b&gt;very&lt;/b&gt; good thing with one major caveat. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Twenty one middle schools produce over half the students that
ultimately are accepted to the specialized schools. For the rest,
there are a few reasons
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many students don't take the SHSAT.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There have been stories of schools steering kids away from the
specialized schools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's no culture in those schools of striving for specialized
school acceptance or attendance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The academic programs at those schools don't prepare students for
the SHSAT exam for reasons that we're not going to delve into here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All students already take the NY State middle school Math and English
exams. Yes, it would further raise the stakes for those exams but it
would ensure that the specialized schools are on the map for everyone, 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The big question here is "do the current state exams cover enough
material in enough depth to select and differentiate for gifted
programs." I don't know the answer to this question. If they don't
then using state test scores will be a disaster. If they do, then they
could be a suitable alternative.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgba9f00c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgba9f00c"&gt;Part 3 - admissions from every middle school&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgba9f00c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is the third part of BdB's proposal - guarantee admissions to the
top 10% of students at every middle school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This could be a real disaster either for the students or for the
schools. There's no question that students coming out of different
middle schools are at different levels of preparedness for the
specialized schools. Arguably the most obvious difference is that some
middle schools offer algebra and others don't. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For better or worse, the specialized school's curricula, classes, and
overall programs have evolved hand in hand with the exam. If you all
of a sudden end up placing a large number of students with a
different and arguable weaker academic profile into these schools one
of two things will happen. Either the students will struggle immensely
or the school will have to lower its standards. There's no two ways
about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you set standards for academic preparedness for the specialized
schools either by making a hard cutoff on an exam score be it state or
SHSAT and then spread those acceptances across all the schools maybe
it could work. If not, you're setting up students with high grades at
schools with weak programs up for failure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another problem is what to do with non-public school students -
private schools, charters which take public money but act as private
schools, parochial, and home school students. Where do they fall in to
this equation?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org0feac6f" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0feac6f"&gt;Is one measure bad?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0feac6f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So there you have my thoughts on BdB's specific proposals but I also
want to address his contention that a single measure is bad and makes
the comparison to colleges where they by and large use multiple
measures. This is a ridiculous comparison. Yes, colleges look at
multiple measures but after watching decades of Stuy students go off
to college, it's clear to me that the process is by no means fair or
consistent. Elite schools can easily game their acceptances and
they still can have 100% of their applicants with off the charts SAT
scores. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A single test might not be ideal but it can only be gamed by test prep
and test prep can be as cheap as buying a test prep book.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As to other measures that come up from time to time - interviews,
portfolios, essays - who does that help? The low income kid or the
well to do one?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're going to add another measure for admission it has to be
something that can't be gamed or politically influenced,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org21307c7" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org21307c7"&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org21307c7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Should the city address the fact that there are groups that are under
represented at the specialized schools? Certainly, or rather, the city
should address deficiencies in opportunities that are like the causes
of this under representation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Should the city be doing things differently? Also yes. Here are some
thoughts on what the city can and should be doing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org076106b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org076106b"&gt;Do the experiments in the non-big three.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org076106b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are five specialized schools that aren't covered by state
legislation. Why not run your experiments there. You've got  the big
three as a control group and what's more if you look at the
"acceptance score windows" in the table above, you'll see that there's
enough overlap that you can probably get some real data out of these
experiments.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why not change the admissions criteria for one or two of them and see
how it goes before jumping in whole hog. Figure out if anything works first.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org3408140" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org3408140"&gt;Check existing data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org3408140"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We've got SHSAT results and State Test score results along with
student grades for years. Why not study correlations between
them. Rather than making a specious claim about middle school grades
in NYC Public Schools vs state tests vs the SHSAT, run the
numbers. Take a look at student high school performance based on these
predictions. This shouldn't be guess work and city should have the
data to do better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd0a1c65" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd0a1c65"&gt;Fix the middle schools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd0a1c65"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This one is more pie in the sky because no politician really wants to
take this one but you've got to look at what's going on in the middle
schools and why. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I tweeted this the other day:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;would love to see this experiment - take the entire staff / faculty / admin of one of the 20 or so middle schools that are the primary feeders to the spec schls and swap them with another middle school and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;— Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/1003074760786501632?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;June 3, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The truth is that if you did this, the high performing school would
probably continue to be high performing and the low performing one
would still struggle. There's only so much a teacher can do. A school
with a disadvantaged population needs the resources to succeed - lower
class sizes for a start. Add wraparound services, extensive after
school and weekend opportunities - make the schools a part of the
community and maybe we can get somewhere.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another question relating to our schools in general is to look at
attrition rates to private schools - how many students in our under
represented groups are being siphoned off to private schools on
scholarship. I don't have any data for this. It could be an
insignificant amount or it could go a long way in explaining the
downturn in the numbers over the decades. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org6093a20" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6093a20"&gt;So where are we&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6093a20"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are a lot of changes I'd love to see in our public schools and I
do believe BdB's heart is in the right place. I'm concerned that some
of the solutions that he and other politicians come up with will hurt
the current low income students at the specialized schools and
unintentionally advantage the well to do while not helping those that
at least BdB may honestly want to help.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He should enact Discovery and research the State Tests but proceed
with caution. The test schools have always been and continue to be a
gateway for poor and immigrant students and any changes that are
proposed should be weighed carefully and &lt;b&gt;tested&lt;/b&gt; before taking steps
that could real harm when good is intended.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="gifted" label="gifted"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Tech or the Teacher</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tech-or-teacher/</id>
    <updated>2018-05-31T17:43:28-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-05-31T17:43:28-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tech-or-teacher/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgda89321" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgda89321"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgda89321"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Every morning one of the first things I do is quickly glance at my
emails and other notifications. I really should wait until I'm more
awake but old habits die hard. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As some of you know over the past couple of years I've been making a
series of &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs"&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; and related post on using my editor of choice,
Emacs. I've done 48 videos, have over 2500 subscribers on
YouTube and people seem to find some value from the series. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This morning one of my emails was a new comment on one of my videos:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thanks for not describing a single key combination and how that fits
into basic usage of org mode.  I was going to subscribe but if all
your videos are going to be about showing off how fast you are at
typing emacs commands on your annoyingly noisy keyborad, then no
thanks!﻿
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
My first reaction was "you know, you could have said something like
'if you slow down an actually say the keys it would be much easier to
follow and would be more valuable' and it would be much better received" but
then I started to think about instructional videos in general. I
started to make these videos for my students. I thought they might be
helpful and then found that the Emacs community by and large liked
them. They're not teaching anything deep or complicated just how I use
a programmable editor. Even so, I was reminded by this comment about
the limitations of videos and ed tech in general.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Videos provide some nice features - you can watch them at any time,
you can pause and replay, and in some cases you can watch at super
speeds. What you can't do is slow the video down and most importantly
you can't ask questions or interact with the instructor. You can leave
comments if the video is on a platform like YouTube but that's pretty
limited.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, if this was a class, we would have been able to
interact and I as the instructor would have had a much better chance
to make sure this "student" was up to speed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, this wasn't a class. I don't have the time to teach tools
like Emacs in class and since it is a mechanical skill, it can be
offloaded to a video. The video has the ancillary benefit of living on
and being discoverable and viewable by the public at large. This is a
good thing. Videos are tech and tech scales. Unfortunately, good
education doesn't. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Videos are tech and tech is the rage. Lots of people are working hard
to get more tech in front of our kids - usually at the expense of
having a great teacher. This is something we don't need. Technology is
nice but I'd rather have my kids in a small class with a knowledgable
teacher and a piece of chalk than all the tech in the world. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a computer science guy and a computer science teacher I think it's
good to remind myself that tech is cool but a good teacher is way cooler.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="edtech" label="edtech"/>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
    <category term="tech" label="tech"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
