<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z (old posts, page 19)</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index-19.atom</id>
  <updated>2016-05-08T08:56:19Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-19.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-18.atom"/>
  <link rel="previous" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="current" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="prev-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-18.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-19.html"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Hunter College - Honors CS</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs.html/</id>
    <updated>2016-03-29T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2016-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's been a while since my last post and a while since I started at
Hunter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Time to share a bit about what I've been up to.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the better kept secrets in New York City is Hunter College's
computer science program. It's been around for years and it's been
that way for years. In fact, when I was looking to get my masters
degree back in the mid nineties I carefully researched all of the
area's MS in CS programs. It came down to Hunter College and Courant
Institute at NYU. I was going to go with Hunter since the programs
seemed comparable and Hunter was far more affordable but I had to go
with NYU due to class schedules. Too many of the Hunter offerings were
to early in the day and I had my full time teaching job to consider.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hunter isn't currently offering their Masters program but their
Bachelor of Arts program is alive and well, it's just that people
don't know about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Part of my job is to change that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, not really, part of my job is to add my piece to the puzzle. The
rest will take care of itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My piece? It's all about creating a tech culture, tying into the NY
Tech ecosystem, and filling in the gaps that are shared by just about
every college computer science program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How do we do it? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The long term plan is that we're starting a new CS Honors program. In
the fall, I'll be teaching and mentoring a group of entering
undergrads. We'll have workshops, trips, activities. You name it. I'll
also be teaching them modified versions of our courses with the hope
of bringing some of my modifications back to the rest of the student
body. Things like integrating real tools and professional techniques
into what is already a solid academic program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the mean time, I'm getting to know Hunter's current CS students and
working to energize the existing community. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We already had an amazing event hosted at &lt;a href="http://yext.com"&gt;Yext&lt;/a&gt;. We had a panel and
mixer with representatives from about a dozen companies talking to the
kids about the possibilities ahead of them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We've also set up a couple of workshops in house.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm also starting to talk to friends at companies across the city to
plan out both curriculum and programs to set up our kids to
succeed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My goal is that within five years, I want people to realize that
Hunter CS is the place to be for CS Education in NYC. Not everyone can
afford the 40K and up private college tuition and there's no reason to
when you can get a great CS education with ties to the tech community
at CUNY prices.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you want to help, drop me a note. We're looking to start something
very special and you have a chance to be a part of it.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>DevOps, or You don't know what the F you're doing!</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-31-devops.html/</id>
    <updated>2016-01-31T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2016-01-31T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-31-devops.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Having just concluded almost a quarter century at one job in one
place, I've been reflecting on a number of things.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I accomplished, what I've failed to accomplish, highlights,
low lights and everything in between.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've also learned a lot over these twenty five years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One thing I learned is DevOps and System Administration. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back around 1993 or 1994 Stuy wasn't really on the internet. Yes, we
were able to scam stuy.edu even though we were a high school and yes
we did have a class B address block but no one really had access.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Somehow, Bruce, a student of mine at the time and I ended up with the
job of getting Stuy onto the internet. Bruce was one of our superstar
kids and people thought I had extensive experience setting up and
running networks. Truth be told I messed around a bit but there's no
way I would have hired myself for the job.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Nonetheless, we were off. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We were able to take one of the RS/6000 AIX workstations that were
supposed to be used as CAD stations and repurposed it as a server. We
made email accounts for everyone and were off.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Neither Bruce nor I really knew what we were doing but we figured
things out. I learned a lot from him and I'd like to think he also got
some benefit out of working with me. Fortunately, we seemed to have a
knack for &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Linux-System-Administration-Handbook-Edition/dp/0131480057/ref=pd_sim_14_2?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;dpID=61%2B57ajucML&amp;amp;dpSrc=sims&amp;amp;preST=_AC_UL160_SR117%2C160_&amp;amp;refRID=164V89GZMZM2X9M2S8AH"&gt;finding the answers&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Of course, we had our moments. Once, we got a critical patch
announcement from IBM. It said that if we needed the patch and didn't
apply it were were in big trouble but if our machine didn't need it,
applying the patch would kill our system. It was unclear whether we
needed the patch or not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After about a half hour research, we determined that we didn't need
the patch.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But applied it anyway :-(.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
D'Oh.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After a brief set of panic attacks and a bunch of fumbling around, we
did manage to restore things.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, Bruce and I ran the system for a year or so and as I said, I
learned a lot. Now, Bruce was close to graduating so I was starting to
worry that I'd have to figure this all out myself soon. That was a
seriously frightening thought. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I figured it would be good to bring in a couple of new super smart
students. As it turns out, Jon was one of them. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At one point, there was some problem and Bruce and I were going to
head to the office to try to figure it out. Jon asked if he could come
and watch. I thought that was a great idea so I agreed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We all went to the office and Bruce and I went to work. After about
fifteen minutes, Jon blurted out:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"I just figured how you guys do it!!!"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
"You guys have no idea what the F you're doing!!!!!"
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We all cracked up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He was absolutely right. We had no clue. We didn't know what we were
doing but we had become pretty good at figuring things out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Truth be told, that really is the norm. If you already knew how to
solve the problem, well, then it really wouldn't have been a problem
to begin with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, you learn to figure it out. It's something I learned not to be
afraid of a long time ago. I hope that it's something I've been able
to convey to my students.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Debugging deployment</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-23-debugging-deployment.html/</id>
    <updated>2016-01-23T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2016-01-23T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-23-debugging-deployment.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
SoftDev students are hard at work on their final projects. By now,
they all have fairly complex code bases. This limits how much I can
help them with debugging.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are some problems, though, that they have to contend with that
even with experience, are hard to spot. Notably because the very
tools you use to debug these errors are part of the problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last week, this happened twice. Both cases were brought to me by
really strong students which just goes to underscore how insidious
these problems can be.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Here's a fake code snippet of a &lt;a href="http://flask.pocoo.org/"&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt; application that illustrates
both problems.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="org-src-container"&gt;

&lt;pre class="src src-python"&gt;&lt;span class="linenr"&gt; 1: &lt;/span&gt;from flask import Flask, render_template
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt; 2: &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt; 3: &lt;/span&gt;app = Flask(__name__)
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt; 4: &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt; 5: &lt;/span&gt;@app.route("/")
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt; 6: &lt;/span&gt;def index():
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt; 7: &lt;/span&gt;    return "hello"
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt; 8: &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt; 9: &lt;/span&gt;@app.route('/test/&amp;lt;some_data&amp;gt;')
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt;10: &lt;/span&gt;def test():
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt;11: &lt;/span&gt;    picture_url = build_url(some_data)
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt;12: &lt;/span&gt;    result = api_test(picture_url)
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt;13: &lt;/span&gt;    do_something(result)
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt;14: &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt;15: &lt;/span&gt;if __name__ == "__main__":
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt;16: &lt;/span&gt;   app.debug = True
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt;17: &lt;/span&gt;   app.secret_key = "some secret key"
&lt;span class="linenr"&gt;18: &lt;/span&gt;   app.run(host="0.0.0.0", port=8000)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
First, the "easy" one. The student was trying to deploy the
application. We use &lt;a href="http://gunicorn.org/"&gt;Green Unicorn&lt;/a&gt; to deploy our applications,
ultimately on &lt;a href="http://digitalocean.com/"&gt;Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt; servers in the cloud. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The student was using the correct command:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="org-src-container"&gt;

&lt;pre class="src src-shell"&gt;gunicorn -W 4 -b 0.0.0.0:8000 app:app
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
but it wasn't working. It ran, but whenever he went to the site, it
came back with an error.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He had to change:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="org-src-container"&gt;

&lt;pre class="src src-python"&gt;if __name__ == "__main__":
   app.debug = True
   app.secret_key = "some secret key"
   app.run(host="0.0.0.0", port=8000)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
to
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="org-src-container"&gt;

&lt;pre class="src src-python"&gt;app.secret_key = "some secret key"
if __name__ == "__main__":
    app.debug = True
    app.run(host="0.0.0.0", port=8000)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Normally, when developing and testing our applications, we use the
test server that's bundled with Flask. The line that reads
"app.run…" takes care of this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When running the application as a "main program" - "python app.py" the
if statement is true and it runs the indented lines, setting the
secret key which is required for session management.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When running under &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;gunicorn&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, the &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;gunicorn&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; server loads the
application as a module and then runs it. In this case name isn't main
so it never sets secret key and so we have a problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Pretty subtle and even though we did cover this in class, it comes up
pretty rarely so it's not an easy catch.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then there was this problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The setup for this one's a little more complicated. The group was
using a facial recognition api. You provide the API with the url to an
image, it fetches it and does recognition.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's also important to note that when Flask is running, it will serve
files from a static directory, so, if I'm running my flask server on
myhost, port 800 and you stored an image named picture.jpg in the
static directory, going to:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;verbatim&gt;
 http://myhost:8000/static/picture.jpg
&lt;/verbatim&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
would get that image.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The group did things right. They ran the Flask test server to serve
the static files and then wrote a small python program to test the
api:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="org-src-container"&gt;

&lt;pre class="src src-python"&gt;picture_url = build_url(some_data)
result = api_test(picture_url)
do_something(result)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Everything worked fine. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But, when they put this code in as a route in their web app (as in the
top code fragment), it froze. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They couldn't figure it out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The code worked as a "stand alone" but not in the web app.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once again, the built in Flask development server.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The development server runs in a single thread / process. This means
it can only do one thing at a time. When they ran their test as a
separate program, the api they used made a request to their app to
serve up the static picture file and it worked.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When they ran from the Flask application itself, their app made a call
to the web api (line 12) and then blocked while waiting for the
response. The web api tried to request the image from the Flask app
but it was blocked – &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;deadlock&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Again, the solution was to run the web app using a server that could
handle multiple requests - gunicorn.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once again, that solved the problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Both of these problems were fairly subtle and very hard to catch -
even with experience. I remember the hours I lost when I was learning
this stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some times kids get caught up in algorithms or poor code design but
sometimes, it's just the tools.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
