<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z (old posts, page 20)</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index-20.atom</id>
  <updated>2016-05-26T14:36:04Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-20.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-19.atom"/>
  <link rel="previous" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="current" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="prev-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-19.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-20.html"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Advanced Placement - Because We Don't Trust Teachers</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-we-dont-trust-teachers/</id>
    <updated>2016-05-07T06:59:40-04:00</updated>
    <published>2016-05-07T06:59:40-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-we-dont-trust-teachers/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/college-board/"&gt;Yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I ranted on about the College Board. This led to a Facebook
hosted discussion which got me thinking a little more:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Advanced Placement exams basically exist because we don't trust our
high school teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I usually use phrases like "society doesn't trust" but let's
personalize it this time – for parents, think about whether or not you trust your
kids teachers? Do you a large private, unaccountable organization
more?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you teach an advanced placement course, in order for your class to
be listed as AP you have to submit your syllabus to the college board
for approval. This sounds like they're setting a standard but it's
not. I can point to a bunch of teachers who have submitted identical syllabi
where sometimes it's accepted but ofttimes it's rejected. This is the
syllabus we submitted originally for Stuy. Yes, we have high achieving
kids, but given the fact that the syllabus was approved originally and
that Stuy students just about all score 4 or 5 on APCS-A should tell
you something about the level of care or competence of the College
Board.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then you teach the class and in May, one to two months before the end
of the semester the kids take the AP exam - you don't see results
until the summer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In theory, if the kids do well they can receive placement or
credit. The problem is, fewer and fewer schools are giving credit,
when they do, it might not help due to the way undergrads pay for
courses and placement can generally be achieved by appealing to
college departments or by taking college administered placements.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back to the trust thing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In college, you take a course, the final exam is created by the
professor or a group of professors and it's graded by the people that
teach the course - possibly as a committee. Kids final grades include
these exams but a student can fail a final or even miss one and still
pass the class whereas an AP exam is a one shot deal and even if you
"pass" you might not get anything from it. I'm not even getting into
questioning the quality and content of the exams. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Kids get their grades and college credit. There are no outside
"standardized exams" and we trust that the professors and the colleges
are educating our kids. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, in high school, teachers make their lessons, teach their classes,
create, administer, and grade final exams and kids get grade - but not
for college level classes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know multiple high school physics, chemistry, math, and computer
science teachers who are far better at teaching than their college
counterparts yet my friend the math teacher isn't trusted to assess
his calculus students for the purpose of college credit - we don't
trust him but we trust the faceless entity known as the College
Board. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Think about that for a minute.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You trust your child's teacher with your child's well being every
day but you don't trust him to say whether or not your kid knows
calculus?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is a real problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have a friend who frequently doesn't quite finish the BC Calculus
test topics because he actually teaches the material in depth –
instead of "follow the scripts" the kids go through proofs and
derivations. It costs the kids - I know a number of them who got a 4
on the BC exam rather than a 5 but come the end of June when the class
is done, they know more calculus more deeply than a lot of kids who've
taken the class in college. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The lines of college have been blurred with more and more "remedial"
classes being taught at the college level and more and more "college
level" being taught in the high schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a really sad state of affairs when we trust our professors - many
of whom are hired more for research than for their teaching chops
and we don't trust our teachers during our kids more formative years.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Remember, school is all about profit, wait no, I mean testing, no, I mean...</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/college-board/</id>
    <updated>2016-05-06T07:03:36-04:00</updated>
    <published>2016-05-06T07:03:36-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/college-board/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
It's important to remember, the college board is about making money
for the college board. It's not about supporting teachers and it's
certainly  not about educating kids.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Kids took the AP Computer Science A exam last week and the College
Board just released the free response questions. There seems to me
more chatter about them in social media than in past years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm just left wondering how AP became the be all and end all.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From where I stand, the College Board, who runs AP, SAT, and PSAT
exams is all about making money for the College Board - they're a
non-profit in name only.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's all about market share and dominance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looking at APCS A, it's not a great exam or course. At Stuy, I taught
a super-set of the old AB and pretty much ignored the parts I didn't
like (that is, the case study) but many schools can't do that. In my
case, most of the schools my kids went to didn't award credit, even
for a 5. They did sometimes award placement but I've had just as many,
if not more kids gain placement just by showing their work to the CS
department at their chosen school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now they're rolling out APCS Principles. I do get the fact that many
schools don't have people to roll their own courses, but I'm not
overly impressed by much of what's come out. I think what we've
developed is stronger and time proven.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Regardless, and moving beyond just CS, the College Board has somehow
bamboozled the public to think AP = Good. Colleges are awarding less
and less credit but everyone's telling the kids to take more and more
AP classes. What's worse, somehow US News and World Report magically
became an authority on school ratings and now the more AP classes your
kids take the better.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know of at least one school with a highly lauded principal boast
about all his kids came in behind in math and by their senior year
passed honors calculus. Looking at the data unfortunately showed that
while all his seniors took the class, all failed, scoring below
a 3. It made the school look great but I'd argue that it was child
abuse.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The principal of course parlayed that gig to an even higher profile
one.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, you could just file the stupid paperwork so that you can run
classes labeled as AP and have kids take the classes but not the exam
but the College Board's working on that - there are rumblings in NY
on using &lt;a href="http://www.chalkbeat.org/posts/ny/2016/04/13/new-york-considering-using-scores-on-ap-exams-and-sat-subject-tests-in-teacher-evaluations/#.VyyRlN9vGAk"&gt;student AP scores in teacher ratings&lt;/a&gt;. Using student test
results for teacher ratings is already a bad idea - using AP is even
worse.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, to really get the cash cow going, AP is entering deals with
agencies and municipalities for large scale testing – in NY students will have to take the
SAT and &lt;a href="http://nymag.com/daily/intelligencer/2015/10/nyc-will-give-free-sat-testing-to-hs-juniors.html"&gt;take it for free&lt;/a&gt;. Then there's code.org's deal free PD for
school's that have their kids take &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-19-code-org-college-board.html/"&gt;yet another meaningless exam&lt;/a&gt;, the
new PSAT/8-9.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, none of this is free - it's our taxpayer money hard at work
being shuttled right into the college board.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What are we getting? Tests that they create and control and are
EXTREMELY secretive about that don't tell us anyhting that we don't
already know about our kids. Oh, and teachers lose instructional time
and have to &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-13-psat.html/#.VyzHNN9vGAk"&gt;proctor&lt;/a&gt; these exams instead of teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Great deal if you can get it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, what's the value of this – more meaningless tests for the
kids. I don't know if there's a record of this anywhere but in the
pre-internet day, I remember watching a news report where a College
Board representative stated that the SAT was a valid predictor of one
thing - how students would do on future SAT exams.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, were left with more money flowing to an outside company with
students taking more meaningless tests.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wish more schools showed the backbone that Fieldston, an elite
private school in NY had when it &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/01/nyregion/high-school-drops-its-ap-courses-and-colleges-don-t-seem-to-mind.html"&gt;dropped A.P. courses&lt;/a&gt; over 10 years
ago. They still seem to be well regarded as a school and their kids do
just fine in terms of college acceptance.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
