<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z (old posts, page 34)</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index-34.atom</id>
  <updated>2017-12-25T13:27:39Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-34.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-33.atom"/>
  <link rel="previous" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="current" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="prev-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-33.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-34.html"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Using Emacs 38 - dired</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-38-dired/</id>
    <updated>2017-11-24T09:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-11-24T09:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-38-dired/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org48b9f45" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org48b9f45"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org48b9f45"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The 38th installment of Using Emacs is about &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;dired&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, Emacs' built
in mode for navigating and working with directories.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not a dired power user and in fact am just now making a real
effort to explore it and work it into my daily workflow and
with that in mind, I'd love to hear some configuration and
use suggestions from people who use it regularly.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's the configuration I use:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;use-package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;dired+&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:ensure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:config&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;require&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'dired+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
which merely adds dired+ into the mix.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also started playing with &lt;a href="https://github.com/joddie/pcre2el"&gt;pcre2el&lt;/a&gt; which allows me to use the more
usual regex syntax in place of Emacs regex syntax in both dired and
other places. This is a big win for me since I never remember all the
escaping rules for Emacs regex.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;use-package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;pcre2el&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;:ensure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;:config&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;pcre-mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Finally, abo-abo and jcs have both written about new features in ,
Ivy/Swiper/Counsel that allow you to use ivy-occur to dump results
into a dired buffer (&lt;a href="http://irreal.org/blog/?p=6760"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://oremacs.com/2017/11/18/dired-occur/"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;) but to get that to work, I needed to
install &lt;a href="https://github.com/mhayashi1120/Emacs-wgrep"&gt;wgrep&lt;/a&gt; and also had to install and setup &lt;a href="https://github.com/junegunn/fzf"&gt;fzf&lt;/a&gt; which looks to be
useful.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;use-package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;wgrep&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:ensure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;setq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;counsel-fzf-cmd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"/home/zamansky/.fzf/bin/fzf -f %s"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To help get started here are links to a couple of cheat sheets:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/refcards/pdf/dired-ref.pdf"&gt;dired reference card&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://harryrschwartz.com/assets/documents/dired-cheatsheet.pdf"&gt;another dired cheat sheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'll probably use dired more frequently but again, would love to hear
how other people are using it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Fg7HmmRYWy8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="emacs" label="emacs"/>
    <category term="learning" label="learning"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Motivating and understanding quicksort</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/quick-sort-starting/</id>
    <updated>2017-11-21T10:34:05-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-11-21T10:34:05-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/quick-sort-starting/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org5a8f8dd" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org5a8f8dd"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org5a8f8dd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thks question was posed the other day - how can one get students to
truly understand the quicksort algorithm?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've written a few posts about quicksort. The last time I did a &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-03-12-select-to-sort.html/"&gt;lesson
writeup&lt;/a&gt; on the subject I wrote about first looking and quickselect and
then moving to the quicksort. The class was first faced with the
problem of writing a routine to find the Kth smallest item in an
unsorted data set. The first solution was n&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; and then refined to a
quickselect. This led directly to the quicksort. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I liked the lesson and I think it worked well when I taught it but
that was partly due to the overall tenor of that particular group of
students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A similar approach develops the quicksort in a similar way but is
both more direct and accessible.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The motivating problem is to put one item in a data set in its proper
place. You could select one person in class and arrange the class so
that the selected student is in their proper size place, that is
everyone shorter on one side, taller on the other. You could also do
this for age. A similar exercise could be done with any number of
manipulatives.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This operation of arranging the rest of the set around one selected
item or person is very easy and in fact it's trivial to show that this
can be done in linear time. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once we've done this arrangement, we can discuss what we can infer
from this new arrangement. We can now tell that:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;everyone to the left of the "pivot" is less than the pivot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;everyone to the right is greater&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pivot element is at its true location if the list were
sorted. That is, if we started arranging around item k, then we've
moved item k to the kth location in the dataset.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From here it's a small jump to the quicksort algorithm, just repeat
the process on the left and right data sets.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This approach not only makes the algorithm and its development clear
and simple but it also can be used to illustrate the worst case n&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
behavior. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The whole thing, minus the coding, can also be done as an unplugged activity.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In case anyone's interested, I also wrote a post on subtle
implementation errors when writing the quicksort (&lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-03-17-subtle-errors-sorting.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) and also
looking at the qucksort from the point of view of different
programming paradigms (&lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-03-14-sorting-from-top-and-from-bottom.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="algorithms-unplugged" label="algorithms. unplugged"/>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="programming" label="programming"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hunter CS and NY Tech - it takes a village</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-tech-kickoff/</id>
    <updated>2017-11-19T19:09:33-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-11-19T19:09:33-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-tech-kickoff/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf3adf97" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgf3adf97"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgf3adf97"&gt;

&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hunter-tech/hunter-tech1.jpg" alt="hunter-tech1.jpg" align="center" height="400"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="figure-number"&gt;Figure 1: &lt;/span&gt;The NY Tech community and Hunter CS at Yext&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
One of my goals when I came over to Hunter was to help establish
Hunter CS as the place to be for CS in the city. Hunter already had a
solid CS program before I joined but it isn't well known. It also
doesn't have an established tech culture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's an ambitious goal but if it can be done, what a game changer. A
lot of people talk about equity, diversity, and social justice but if
we can establish Hunter as the place to be for CS in NY, what a
win. An affordable, accessible institution where you can get a great
CS education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The truth of course is that I can't accomplish this - at least not by
myself. I'm just one person. Fortunately, there are so many wonderful
people in the New York Tech community that want to help bring
opportunities to the kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last Thursday evening we got the ball rolling. Twenty five
representatives from the tech community got together at &lt;a href="http://yext.om"&gt;Yext&lt;/a&gt; with
about a dozen of our Hunter College CS students. The conversation
started with a discussion of perceptions of Hunter and the students
sharing what their experiences were like. By the end we were all
brainstorming as to how we can work together to best prepare Hunter
students to become members of the New York Tech community. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know the students left the evening energized and I did as well. I
hope our friends in Tech felt the same.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hunter-tech/hunter-tech-max-jess.jpg" alt="hunter-tech-max-jess.jpg" align="center" height="400"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="figure-number"&gt;Figure 2: &lt;/span&gt;Max talking about Hunter to Jess and the rest of the table&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had representatives from (in alphabetical order)
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Animoto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beeswax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Civic Hall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eBay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genacast Ventures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JW Player&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meetup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MongoDB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Motivate (Citbike)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quentin Road Ventures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two Sigma&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Union Square Ventures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workbench&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yext&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
at the event and then there were plenty of people who want to be part
of this who couldn't make it on Thursday.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I told the participants at the event that I can't make this happen. I
can merely get the people together who actually can. I'm grateful to
all my friends who are now a part of this and I'm looking forward to
working with  them, my students and my colleagues  to create 
a Hunter CS to Tech Community pipeline that's second to none.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="tech-community" label="tech community"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Moocs - High Production value, Bad Questions</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/moocs-bad-questions/</id>
    <updated>2017-11-10T07:55:09-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-11-10T07:55:09-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/moocs-bad-questions/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgef0eda1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgef0eda1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgef0eda1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most mornings, I start my day with a workout. Sometimes I run,
sometimes I use my bike trainer. Dealing with plantar
fasciitis since last June, it's mostly been the bike. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I occupy the time by either watching YouTube videos or catching up on
&lt;a href="https://cacm.acm.org/"&gt;Communications of the ACM&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.americanscientist.org/"&gt;American Scientist&lt;/a&gt;. I'm about 6 months
behind on both.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Inspired by some talk in one of the CS Ed Facebook groups, I thought
I'd use the time to start going through some MOOCs. I started with
Udacity's Intro to Information Security. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm only in lesson 4 but it's pretty light weight and generally well
presented but I keep seeing the same thing that pisses me off about
moocs. At the end of the day the video is just a lecture and what's
worse, a lecture with no feedback loop. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Don't get me wrong, I love the fact that Udacity and the others have
their material up online and that I can get to it free of charge but I
don't love the fact there are people that still believe putting a computer
in front of a kid is better than a teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think this quiz question is pretty representative of what I'm
talking about. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/mooc-question.png" alt="mooc-question.png" align="center" height="400"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="figure-number"&gt;Figure 1: &lt;/span&gt;Typically bad mooc question&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's just a silly inline quiz question and not a particularly
important one but it pisses me off.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start with, it uses the word  &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;could&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;  not &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;did&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;. That means
that every answer is correct. In fact an asnwer  choice like
"we're more secure because we have this really good engineer named
Stanley" could be given and would be a correct answer since  the
vendor &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;could&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; base their claim on Stanley's awesomness, it would
just be a bad idea. Unless you remember the specific ad campaign, you won't
know the answer  and even if you did, internally, they could use any
justification they want.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It reminds me of when my brother was in grade school and he had a test
question of:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Can you name all 50 states in the United States of America?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My brother's answer was "no." He was correct. I don't remember if the
teacher agreed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To be fair, I'm just watching the videos and it's possible that the
readings clarified the question but even so, this is a very bad
question.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yes, it's just a silly quiz but it is indicative of the problem with
any online learning resource and I and I'm sure others find it
frustrating. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't want to come down hard on the lecturer or whomever made the
quiz question. In a class I might ask a question poorly but I have an
immediate feedback loop and can fix things right then and
there. Frustration doesn't build and in the case of holes in  important
conceptual material deficiencies don't develop.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also don't want to come down on free resources that I use and
benefit from.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These types of issues seem small and the autodidacts that succeed in
using MOOCS work around them but if you look at these materials
critically as a teacher it's plain to see that their no substitute for
the real thing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Professional Development beyond Scratch</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/election-day-pd-2017/</id>
    <updated>2017-11-07T19:08:58-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-11-07T19:08:58-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/election-day-pd-2017/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd193e2c" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd193e2c"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd193e2c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today was Election Day. One of the few days each year when students
stay home and teachers spend all day attending what is generously
known as professional development.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Years ago I was in a room with a few colleagues when my friend Dave -
one of the best math teachers I know said "you know, every time we
have a PD day in NJ and my wife and I have to scramble to take care of
the kids I get a little annoyed but then think I shouldn't get annoyed
since they're spending the day doing all sorts of valuable PD." He
then said "but then I realize that their PD is probably about as
useful as our PD and I get really angry."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There you have it. This is not to say that there is no good PD but it
seems that the professional development opportunities provided by our
schools have over the years ranged from useless to insulting with
maybe a small bright spot here and there. Historically it's been worse
for CS teachers because we get lumped in with math teachers and have
to spend the day learning about tools and techniques we'll never use
or discussing curricula we never teach.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, when I spoke to JonAlf about rescuing the Stuy teachers for the
day and hosting them at Hunter, he and the other CS teachers were
pretty excited. It wasn't as though I had the magic PD answer but I
was going to provide a space and we'd figure out together what would
be productive and valuable for them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As it turns out, I've been spending a good amount of time these past
few weeks visiting high schools to talk about Hunter CS and when I was
at Bronx Science the topic of Election Day PD came up and I thought
that it would be nice to get the Bronx Science and Stuy teachers
together. After thinking about it more, I recalled that there were few
good PD opportunities for CS teachers who taught advanced classes as
opposed to all the CS PD floating around these days at more of a
beginner level.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I thought that we could change this. In the end, I hosted PD today and
had teachers from Stuyvesant, Bronx Science, Brooklyn Tech, and the
Manhattan Hunter Science High School in attendance. I invited teachers
from a few more schools but in the end we had those four schools and
seventeen teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The original agenda was:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;09:00 - 10:00 : Each school describes it's program and courses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:00 - 11:00 : An intro to Git and GitHub for the classroom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:00 - 11:45 : Sharing neat lessons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:45 - 12:00 : Presentation by &lt;a href="http://chicktech.org"&gt;ChickTech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12:00 - 01:00 : Lunch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;01:00 - End   : Small group lesson and curriculum work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Oh boy did I mess up on the timing. The description and
discussion of school programs took all morning. It was interesting to
hear how each school's program evolved and how they fit into the
school's culture. Brooklyn Tech, for instance is a school where
students declare majors. This has a big impact on what classes kids
have to take and are able to take. This is very different from Stuy or
Science where kids programs are more open ended or MHSHS which is a
much smaller school and has restrictions related to size. It was also
interesting to note Brooklyn Tech's decision to have every student
take APCS-P. Interesting because Brooklyn Tech is one of the country's
largest high schools and most of them should have done well on the
exam. That gave NYC around 1,400 passing AP scores in one shot. On
the other hand none of the other schools present today offered APCS-P
but did have their own intro CS class that students took prior to
APCS-A.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We finished the morning with a visit by Heather from
&lt;a href="http://chicktech.org"&gt;ChickTech&lt;/a&gt;. ChickTech is a non-profit dedicated to retaining women in
Tech. It works with both girls in K12 and also those in industry. My
hope was to get a conversation started and see if there were some
potential avenues of partnership between the organization and the
schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After lunch, the group decided that we should do the Git/GitHub
workshop and JonAlf obliged.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Overall I think the day was a success. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My hope is that today's attendees can form a core group of CS teachers
who teach more advanced courses and we can form something of a support
group for each other. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I plan to try to facilitate future meetings and hopefully we'll be
able to attract more teachers to our group.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All in all I'm very happy with how the day went.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="pd" label="pd"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
