<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-06-14T18:26:50Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-39.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>How I Grokked OOP</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/how-i-grokked-oop/</id>
    <updated>2018-06-14T12:15:41-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-06-14T12:15:41-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/how-i-grokked-oop/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd370799" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd370799"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd370799"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Time to get back to CS and CS Ed related blogging.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last week, in Garth Flint's post about his &lt;a href="https://gflint.wordpress.com/2018/06/01/747/"&gt;summer plans&lt;/a&gt;, Garth
mentioned wanting to get his head around Object Oriented Programming
and possibly taking a course to help him get there. I thought I'd talk
a little about how I got my head around OOP here and some of the
difficulties I faced then and what people might face now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Nowadays, kids are faced with OOP pretty early on. If they take APCS-A
they're using Java which is Object Oriented. Same if they start
at a college using Java. If they start with C++ or Python they may or
may not see objects early on. In any event, the nature of that first
course doesn't really lend itself to really grokking OOP. Even if a
student takes a class prior to APCS-A or it's college equivalent,
they're pretty y raw. Small programs with just a few constructs don't
really show the uses of OOP. Both inheritance and interfaces can feel
forced in a first year course and when the examples are artificial and
wonky and their are easier ways to accomplish the same task, it's hard
for a student to really buy into the paradigm.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, in all fairness, I'm not a big fan of Object Oriented Programming
and it's usually not the first tool I go to. That said, it's a useful
tool and it has it's place.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I cut my teeth in the 1980s. I went to the Courant Institute at
NYU. The core language back then was Pascal which had a number of
limitations including only supporting single file programs. Somewhere
along the line I taught myself C which most professors were happy to
accept assignments in. I never heard of OOP in my formal
schooling. Some time near or soon after I graduated I had heard of
this C++ thing but hadn't used it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After working my way through school I spent some time as a developer
at Goldman Sachs. I was the only guy on my team doing Windows 2.1
development. Windows 2.1 was built on top of DOS. It's big improvement
over Windows 1.0 was that it supported overlapping windows. Pretty cool.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/8/8f/Windows_2.1.png" alt="Windows_2.1.png" width="300px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I learned to program Windows like everyone else:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.charlespetzold.com/oop/pw1.png" alt="pw1.png" width="200px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was all done in C. The big project I was on was for Global
Equities. Specifically, supporting trading of Japanese Warrants. I had
to write a trading system and in doing that implement among other
things a mini spreadsheet in C from bare metal.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was probably going to be the most complex thing I designed and
built from scratch to date. I had a bunch of cells that were
associated with either rows or columns or both and all sorts of
complex interactions. I needed a way to manage complexity and even
though I didn't use the term at the time, manage state. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
C doesn't have a lot of fancy in language constructs to help and I was
somewhat on an island - I taught myself C and there weren't any
experienced C / Windows programmers in my group or on my floor so I
had to figure things out on my own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's what I came up with, or rather something like what I came up
with – it was close to 30 years ago and I don't even remember 100% of
what it was supposed to do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I decided to create a single file for each concept -
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cell.c / cell.h for cells&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;row.c / row.h for rows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sheet.c / sheet.h for&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In each, I would do something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* sheet.c */&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* things declared here are "global" but limited to this file **/&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sheet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sheets&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* an array of the sheets */&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* functions that will be made available to other files */&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* return a pointer to the named sheet */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sheet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;sheet_get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* implementation */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* create a new sheet */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sheet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;sheet_create&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;rows&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* implementation/&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* functions that will only be used internally */&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sheet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;allocate_sheet_memory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;rows&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/*implementation*/&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* etc */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* sheet.h */&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/* &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;   Note that only the headers for the exterrnally available stuff is included&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cm"&gt;*/&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sheet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;sheet_get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sheet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;sheet_create&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;rows&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cols&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The idea is that everything about a sheet is in &lt;code&gt;sheet.c&lt;/code&gt; and only a
few functions are made available to the rest of the program via the
header file. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Shortly after I designed the program, I started to delve into OOP at
the encouragement of some colleagues. I read Meyer:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1392538685l/3328934.jpg" alt="3328934.jpg" width="200px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and the first edition of Booch: 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.pearsonhighered.com/assets/bigcovers/0/8/0/5/0805353402.jpg" alt="0805353402.jpg" width="200px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I realized that in a way I was implementing singleton objects in
C. The file declared the object. The functions I exposed via the
header files were public, the other functions private and the "global"
variables that were local to the file, private class variables.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There was no inheritance but it did help me encapsulate functionality
and state. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It turns out I saw something like this when I briefly looked at Ada. I
think it was called Object Typed Programming - objects with only a
single instance and no inheritance. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The books gave me the official names for things but the project I was
developing gave me the context to where it all made sense. I had a
problem to solve that didn't lend itself to a low level imperative
language but you work with the tools you have and this is what I came
up with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Unfortunately, it's harder for beginners as projects are smaller and
while there are good small example of OOP there's also so much going
on in a course like APCS-A. It gets more convoluted when you're using
Python or C++ as you might be shown Objects in a C++ class while
professor is really teaching C with Objects rather than doing things
the C++ way. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One thing that helps is using a language or tool where objects make
sense. NetLogo - used in Stuy's intro course is a nice one. Turtles
and patches - the inhabitants of the NetLogo can be viewed as
objects. I'd draw heavily on NetLogo analogies when teaching APCS at
Stuy. There are also tools like BlueJ which is tied closely to objects
and is probably terrific at giving structure to help objects make
sense but I don't like those types of tools for other reasons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, it is just a tool and to be honest, I'm not
really a big fan of OOP. I'll use it but it's not my go to paradigm.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'll leave you with this video which talks about why:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QM1iUe6IofM" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Giving control of NYC's specialized schools to a political appointee</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat-part2/</id>
    <updated>2018-06-04T08:00:40-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-06-04T08:00:40-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat-part2/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org0e4b023" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0e4b023"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0e4b023"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I shared my thoughts on Bill de Blasio's plans to "fix" the
selection criteria for New York City's specialized high schools. If
you haven't read the post, you can find it &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was going to get back to CS and CS Ed related blogging today but
there's more to the story.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In spite of what BdB stated, it's not enough for him to switch to another
measure - the middle school state exam along with some modifiers. This
is about ending the exam altogether and not replacing it with anything
better. Here's a link to information on the proposed legislation for
&lt;a href="https://legiscan.com/NY/bill/A10427/2017"&gt;New York Assembly Bill 10427&lt;/a&gt; including links to the actual text.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's a lot of beurobabble but the end game is to basically allow
the chancellor (not sure if this means city or state) to do whatever
they want.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here are some of the key points:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seats would ultimately go to the top 5 to 7 percent of each middle school's
class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These students would have to also be classified in the top 25% city wide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top is defined by a composite score of multiple measures as
determined by the chancellor which means anything goes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remaining seats will be filled by
lottery of all students with a 3.7 GPA or greater.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's not clear how the students would be allocated to each of the
specialized schools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what does this all mean? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Multiple measures could mean the state test + average. It could mean
average + recommendation. It could be shoe size + favorite color. The
chancellor also decides how to weight these multiple measures. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This means that the politicians can do whatever they want to paint any
picture they want regardless of how their ideological and political
games hurt kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Any teacher, in fact, any rational adult  will tell you that middle
schools are not interchangeable. The top students at one middle school
are typically not at the same level as top students at another
one. I'm sure you can cluster middle schools in terms of the students
they graduate, what the students know and can do and the clusters will
likely fall on economic lines. This is the problem that BdB should be
addressing not how to rig the specialized school admissions stats. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even if this is done right, you're assuming an even distribution of
top gifted students across all the middle schools. If one school has
higher concentration of gifted students, they're out of luck. The end
result is that if you attend an SP or other gifted program for eighth
grade you'll likely be locked out of the specialized schools. What if
a particular middle school is attractive to all of our top math team
talent? Only a couple will get in to the specialized schools under the
new system since each school is allocated a fixed number of slots. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I guess this does make sense if you don't believe in gifted students
or gifted education but then why not just get rid of the specialized
schools to begin with rather than playing these games. This "solution"
will result in parents having to decide - do I send my kids to the
gifted middle school program and hurt their chances to get into a
specialized high school or do I try to find the lowest performing
school I can find and have my kid stand out. This is pretty messed up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, though, you have to remember that any change to
the process can help one group and hurt another. Stuy, for example has
46% of it's students on free or reduced lunch and is about 70%
Asian. If in the new system you're increasing the percent population
of an under represented group, you're likely reducing the percentage
of Asian students. So, you're creating opportunities for a number of as of yet
undetermined students (who might not be properly prepared for the
experience) at the expense of economically disadvantaged Asian
students who have proven to be prepared for the experience. Wouldn't
a better solution be to fix the opportunities presented at the middle
schools rather than rig the system of high school acceptance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Going further, a response on another blog noted that BdB probably
refused to do anything with the admissions criteria of the non big
three because they all had numbers that he would consider more
diverse. The commenter provided the Black / Latino percentages, I added the
free and reduced lunch numbers:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="border" border-spacing="10px"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;School&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Percent Black / Latino&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Free / Reduced Lunch&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Brooklyn Latin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;28%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;61%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSMSE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;26%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;46%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSAS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;17%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;25%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Queens Sci&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;12%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;64%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All the more reason to run some tests or analysis there. Of course, if
you look further you'll note that HSAS only has 25% of its students on
free or reduced lunch so is it really doing better than Stuy or Sci
with ~45% low income students  each  or Brooklyn Tech which supports
62% or are we to say that there's low income and then there's the
right low income?
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Certainly the education system needs work but the proposed legislation
is not a solution. It's taking a flawed but objective measure and
replacing it with essentially chancellor's discretion. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If the legislation passes, by the year 2022 we will have admissions to
what used to be some of the nations finest high schools determined by
a political appointee rather than an objective test.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a shame. It was very important to my wife and me to have our kids
go to public schools and I was very happy to have been able to
navigate the system with them from first grade through high school
graduation with only a few bumps along the way. With this nonsense
from the political left and the privatization push from the political
right (or actually both sides) pretty soon there will be nothing left.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="gifted" label="gifted"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Changing Admissions to the NYC Specialized High Schools</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/</id>
    <updated>2018-06-03T07:01:31-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-06-03T07:01:31-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org5647c3a" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org5647c3a"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org5647c3a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, Bill de Blasio, the current Mayor of New York City outlined
how he would "fix" our specialized schools. The schools he was
referring to were the "big three" of Stuyvesant, Bronx Science, and
Brooklyn Tech and then five additional schools - The High School  for
Math Science and Engineering at CCNY, The High School for American
Studies at Lehman, Brooklyn Latin, The Queens Arts and Science High
School at
York College, and Staten Island Tech.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All use a single SAT style test, the SHSAT, for admission. The Big Three are
locked into that system unless there are changes made by the state
legislature. The Mayor can make changes to the admissions criteria of
the other five on his own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem, as stated by Chalkbeat writers Alex Zimmerman and  Monica
Disare is that: 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The city’s specialized high schools — considered some of the crown
jewels of New York City’s education system — accept students based on
a single test score. Over the last decade, they have come under fire
for offering admissions to few students of color: While two-thirds of
city students are black or Hispanic, only about 10 percent of
admissions offers to those schools go to black or Hispanic students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I normally don't write about things like this but given my history at
and with Stuyvesant I thought I should.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Before getting started, my biases - I believe in public schools, not
charters, I also believe that a system should have gifted programs and
magnet schools and also a mix of large comprehensive schools and
smaller niche ones. Additionally, while I do believe in gifted
programs I'm not sure at what point it makes sense to start offering
them. When we were looking at elementary schools for our own kids we
opted for a neighborhood public school rather than applying to the
district gifted program as we felt it offered a better overall
education. On the other hand, had our kids not made Stuyvesant, I'm
not sure what we would have done. Part of that was due to the fact
that the Bloomberg administration destroyed just about all the large
comprehensive schools so, other than that large test schools and
LaGuardia, good luck finding a school that was strong in the
humanities, sciences and offered a robust music program. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org7a9b65e" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org7a9b65e"&gt;The overall picture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org7a9b65e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For reference, here are &lt;a href="http://www.theschoolboards.com/showthread.php/4324-Specialized-High-School-SHSAT-Cutoff-Scores-for-2018"&gt;unofficial cutoff scores&lt;/a&gt; for the specialized
schools from 2018 along with the NY State data on free and reduced
lunch for 2017. Note that there's overlap between the schools. I
separated out SI Tech since geography probably affects it's numbers
more than the other schools and I separated the big three from the
remaining four because I think the three are all substantially larger. The
free and reduced lunch percent is important because I believe an
entire school qualifies for Title I funding if the number's
over 40 so while these schools are not populated entirely by low
income students, all but HSAS has a substantial number and there's a
chance, some say a good one that at best BdB's plans will merely
shuffle which low income kids get in rather than actually solving the
root problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="border" border-spacing="10px"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;School&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Lowest Score admitted&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;High Score&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Pct free or reduced lunch&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Stuyvesant&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;559&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;698&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;46&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Bronx Science&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;518&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;637&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;45&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Brooklyn Tech&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;493&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;668&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;62&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSMSE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;516&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;616&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;46&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSAS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;516&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;633&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Brooklyn Latin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;482&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;555&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;61&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Queens Sci&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;538&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;542&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;64&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;SI Tech&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;519&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;660&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf0f6f49" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgf0f6f49"&gt;The plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgf0f6f49"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf35161e" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgf35161e"&gt;Part 1 - test prep&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgf35161e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There's idea here is that test prep is rampant for SHSAT and that the
test can be gamed. This may or may not be true but if it is then it's
safe to assume that a lot of low income kids are doing test
prep either by prioritizing test prep programs in family budgets,
working off of an SHSAT test prep book or by attending a middle school
that has some form of prep. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There has long been a program on the books called "The Discovery
Program" which has a free city run test prep component and also a
summer component. The summer component is for low income students who
score within "a few points" of the school in question's cutoff
score. At the end of the summer, I believe the students retest and in
general make the school in question.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;This program is a good thing and should be reinstated&lt;/b&gt; but I don't
know if it will result in the changes that BdB is looking for. More
likely Stuy will get its discovery kids from Science and Science from
Tech. As there are already many low income students at all of the
schools there's no indication that this would increase the number of
under represented groups which is BdB's goal. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's also worth noting that there's a sizable chunk of Brooklyn Tech
students that don't perform particularly well on regents exams.
Everyone knows I'm not a fan of standardized tests and I don't
believe that students that score a "few points" lower on the SHSAT are
any less qualified to be in a specialized school but at the lowest
performing end of these schools, one has to ask how specialized is it
really?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb920711" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgb920711"&gt;Part 2 - use state test scores instead of the SHSAT&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgb920711"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This &lt;b&gt;could be&lt;/b&gt; a &lt;b&gt;very&lt;/b&gt; good thing with one major caveat. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Twenty one middle schools produce over half the students that
ultimately are accepted to the specialized schools. For the rest,
there are a few reasons
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many students don't take the SHSAT.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There have been stories of schools steering kids away from the
specialized schools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's no culture in those schools of striving for specialized
school acceptance or attendance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The academic programs at those schools don't prepare students for
the SHSAT exam for reasons that we're not going to delve into here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All students already take the NY State middle school Math and English
exams. Yes, it would further raise the stakes for those exams but it
would ensure that the specialized schools are on the map for everyone, 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The big question here is "do the current state exams cover enough
material in enough depth to select and differentiate for gifted
programs." I don't know the answer to this question. If they don't
then using state test scores will be a disaster. If they do, then they
could be a suitable alternative.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org0607368" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org0607368"&gt;Part 3 - admissions from every middle school&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0607368"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is the third part of BdB's proposal - guarantee admissions to the
top 10% of students at every middle school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This could be a real disaster either for the students or for the
schools. There's no question that students coming out of different
middle schools are at different levels of preparedness for the
specialized schools. Arguably the most obvious difference is that some
middle schools offer algebra and others don't. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For better or worse, the specialized school's curricula, classes, and
overall programs have evolved hand in hand with the exam. If you all
of a sudden end up placing a large number of students with a
different and arguable weaker academic profile into these schools one
of two things will happen. Either the students will struggle immensely
or the school will have to lower its standards. There's no two ways
about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you set standards for academic preparedness for the specialized
schools either by making a hard cutoff on an exam score be it state or
SHSAT and then spread those acceptances across all the schools maybe
it could work. If not, you're setting up students with high grades at
schools with weak programs up for failure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another problem is what to do with non-public school students -
private schools, charters which take public money but act as private
schools, parochial, and home school students. Where do they fall in to
this equation?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org33995ae" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org33995ae"&gt;Is one measure bad?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org33995ae"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So there you have my thoughts on BdB's specific proposals but I also
want to address his contention that a single measure is bad and makes
the comparison to colleges where they by and large use multiple
measures. This is a ridiculous comparison. Yes, colleges look at
multiple measures but after watching decades of Stuy students go off
to college, it's clear to me that the process is by no means fair or
consistent. Elite schools can easily game their acceptances and
they still can have 100% of their applicants with off the charts SAT
scores. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A single test might not be ideal but it can only be gamed by test prep
and test prep can be as cheap as buying a test prep book.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As to other measures that come up from time to time - interviews,
portfolios, essays - who does that help? The low income kid or the
well to do one?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're going to add another measure for admission it has to be
something that can't be gamed or politically influenced,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd4640da" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd4640da"&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd4640da"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Should the city address the fact that there are groups that are under
represented at the specialized schools? Certainly, or rather, the city
should address deficiencies in opportunities that are like the causes
of this under representation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Should the city be doing things differently? Also yes. Here are some
thoughts on what the city can and should be doing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org9ac1e5e" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org9ac1e5e"&gt;Do the experiments in the non-big three.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org9ac1e5e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are five specialized schools that aren't covered by state
legislation. Why not run your experiments there. You've got  the big
three as a control group and what's more if you look at the
"acceptance score windows" in the table above, you'll see that there's
enough overlap that you can probably get some real data out of these
experiments.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why not change the admissions criteria for one or two of them and see
how it goes before jumping in whole hog. Figure out if anything works first.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbb91a4a" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgbb91a4a"&gt;Check existing data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgbb91a4a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We've got SHSAT results and State Test score results along with
student grades for years. Why not study correlations between
them. Rather than making a specious claim about middle school grades
in NYC Public Schools vs state tests vs the SHSAT, run the
numbers. Take a look at student high school performance based on these
predictions. This shouldn't be guess work and city should have the
data to do better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org6b83d00" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org6b83d00"&gt;Fix the middle schools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6b83d00"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This one is more pie in the sky because no politician really wants to
take this one but you've got to look at what's going on in the middle
schools and why. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I tweeted this the other day:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;would love to see this experiment - take the entire staff / faculty / admin of one of the 20 or so middle schools that are the primary feeders to the spec schls and swap them with another middle school and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;— Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/1003074760786501632?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;June 3, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The truth is that if you did this, the high performing school would
probably continue to be high performing and the low performing one
would still struggle. There's only so much a teacher can do. A school
with a disadvantaged population needs the resources to succeed - lower
class sizes for a start. Add wraparound services, extensive after
school and weekend opportunities - make the schools a part of the
community and maybe we can get somewhere.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another question relating to our schools in general is to look at
attrition rates to private schools - how many students in our under
represented groups are being siphoned off to private schools on
scholarship. I don't have any data for this. It could be an
insignificant amount or it could go a long way in explaining the
downturn in the numbers over the decades. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org0ad1cca" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0ad1cca"&gt;So where are we&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0ad1cca"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are a lot of changes I'd love to see in our public schools and I
do believe BdB's heart is in the right place. I'm concerned that some
of the solutions that he and other politicians come up with will hurt
the current low income students at the specialized schools and
unintentionally advantage the well to do while not helping those that
at least BdB may honestly want to help.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He should enact Discovery and research the State Tests but proceed
with caution. The test schools have always been and continue to be a
gateway for poor and immigrant students and any changes that are
proposed should be weighed carefully and &lt;b&gt;tested&lt;/b&gt; before taking steps
that could real harm when good is intended.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="gifted" label="gifted"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Tech or the Teacher</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tech-or-teacher/</id>
    <updated>2018-05-31T17:43:28-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-05-31T17:43:28-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tech-or-teacher/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org17c1276" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org17c1276"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org17c1276"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Every morning one of the first things I do is quickly glance at my
emails and other notifications. I really should wait until I'm more
awake but old habits die hard. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As some of you know over the past couple of years I've been making a
series of &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs"&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; and related post on using my editor of choice,
Emacs. I've done 48 videos, have over 2500 subscribers on
YouTube and people seem to find some value from the series. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This morning one of my emails was a new comment on one of my videos:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thanks for not describing a single key combination and how that fits
into basic usage of org mode.  I was going to subscribe but if all
your videos are going to be about showing off how fast you are at
typing emacs commands on your annoyingly noisy keyborad, then no
thanks!﻿
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
My first reaction was "you know, you could have said something like
'if you slow down an actually say the keys it would be much easier to
follow and would be more valuable' and it would be much better received" but
then I started to think about instructional videos in general. I
started to make these videos for my students. I thought they might be
helpful and then found that the Emacs community by and large liked
them. They're not teaching anything deep or complicated just how I use
a programmable editor. Even so, I was reminded by this comment about
the limitations of videos and ed tech in general.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Videos provide some nice features - you can watch them at any time,
you can pause and replay, and in some cases you can watch at super
speeds. What you can't do is slow the video down and most importantly
you can't ask questions or interact with the instructor. You can leave
comments if the video is on a platform like YouTube but that's pretty
limited.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, if this was a class, we would have been able to
interact and I as the instructor would have had a much better chance
to make sure this "student" was up to speed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, this wasn't a class. I don't have the time to teach tools
like Emacs in class and since it is a mechanical skill, it can be
offloaded to a video. The video has the ancillary benefit of living on
and being discoverable and viewable by the public at large. This is a
good thing. Videos are tech and tech scales. Unfortunately, good
education doesn't. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Videos are tech and tech is the rage. Lots of people are working hard
to get more tech in front of our kids - usually at the expense of
having a great teacher. This is something we don't need. Technology is
nice but I'd rather have my kids in a small class with a knowledgable
teacher and a piece of chalk than all the tech in the world. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a computer science guy and a computer science teacher I think it's
good to remind myself that tech is cool but a good teacher is way cooler.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="edtech" label="edtech"/>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
    <category term="tech" label="tech"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Teaching recursion early? Make sure to use a good tool.</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/recursion-early/</id>
    <updated>2018-05-30T08:42:29-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-05-30T08:42:29-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/recursion-early/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org6ae8c83" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6ae8c83"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6ae8c83"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I replied this tweet yesterday and thought I'd expound a bit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;We started kids using scheme on 10th grade at stuy so did recursion early. Not everyone got all of it but it think it made things much easier for those that you more CS later.&lt;/p&gt;— Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/1001508028439519233?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;May 29, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We introduced recursion very early in our intro course at Stuy and I
think it worked well. In that course we started by using Racket (nee
Scheme) as the first programming unit. Originally we
started the kids out first using NetLogo or StarLogo and followed with
Scheme but after a few years we switched the order.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wouldn't always recommend Scheme for a first course and in fact
frequently don't but given how the Stuy course was introduced and
developed it made sense and worked. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Was it worth doing things this way? I think so. Prior to that intro
course becoming a requirement I got to see students coming in from
different pathways to APCS. Some came in raw with zero formal
experience, some self taught, some through that intro course and some
having taken another more traditional intro programming course or
experience. The kids who started on Scheme had no more difficulty
mastering loops and iteration but had an easier time getting to the
more advanced recursive techniques. This wasn't a surprise - it wasn't
their first rodeo. This also jived with reports I read at the time
that felt that when students did recursion first, iteration was just
as easy but when they did iteration first, recursion was harder. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can of course make a strong case that recursion isn't necessary
for a kid that isn't going to study more CS. I'll merely argue that
what we did at Stuy worked with that population and I wouldn't change
it. At the same time, I've helped a number of teachers design classes and programs
where we agreed that recursion first was not the way to go.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any event, it wasn't that I specifically wanted to do recursion
early but rather, there were a number of things I wanted to do with
the class for which Scheme made sense and recursion was just one of
them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some reasons to like (or for some, to dislike) Scheme early:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's functional – everything is a function. While this is
technically not true, we can fudge it a bit at this level. You put
things in parens so instead of add(a,b) you write (add a b) or
really (+ a b). You can also do (+ a b c). Things that would be
statements are also functions: (if Booelean TruePart FalsePart) is the &lt;b&gt;if&lt;/b&gt;
statement. For example &lt;code&gt;(if (&amp;gt;= a b) a b)&lt;/code&gt; returns the larger of a
and b.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because it's functional it avoids the issue kids have with &lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt; being
for assignment rather than comparison.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has great support for list processing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recursion is much more natural.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's a super simple language with simple rules and a simple, small  syntax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, Scheme isn't perfect and some people dislike the above
reasons. It's also easy to come up with a number of other good reasons
not to use a language like Scheme. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the recursion front, it makes things much easier. There are no
loops so recursion develops as a natural form for repetition:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;define &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; 
	    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;* &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;- &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)))))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This defines a function that takes one parameter and returns
&lt;code&gt;x*(x-1)*(x-2)...&lt;/code&gt;. It repeats, but never ends. This leads to adding
a base case:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;define &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;&amp;lt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;* &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;- &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))))))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Which is your basic factorial function.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since this use of recursion for repetition  develops naturally as we
introduce language concepts it's easier for kids to get their heads
around it as opposed to when they've seen loops already and have an
"easier" alternative. You can make the case that you could introduce
recursion this way in a language with loops like Python but once loops
are available and particularly when loops are idiomatic, students will
find them and getting them to think recursively will be more
difficult.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Scheme and most other functional programming languages also have
strong support for lists and list recursion. This means you don't have
to limit yourself to mathy problems. Think about a todo list:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the market&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buy a gallon of milk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If they have eggs, get a dozen (heh heh)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Processing a todo list is really a recursive problem:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the list is empty you're done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take the first item off  the list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recurse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once you start working with lists, you can play with all sorts of
recursive examples.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the Scheme unit the big project is creating a sentence
generator. The kids don't know it but they're learning about grammars
and in fact are writing a recursive descent parser - they just think
they're writing a program that creates silly sentences. It's a really
nice project that uses recursion in a way that's different and I'd
argue more fun and interesting than the usual approaches. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I chose Scheme for a variety of reasons. I also chose NetLogo for
specific reasons. Unlike Scheme (or most other popular learning
languages), NetLogo is really all about agent based parallel
processing. There are concepts that we can explore easily and in depth
with NetLogo that would be tremendously difficult in any other
language and at the same time, there are things that are easy to
explore in other languages that Netlogo doesn't lend itself to.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, in the end, this post really isn't about when to teach
recursion. It's more about how languages lend themselves to solving
different problems and teaching different concepts in different
ways. If all you have is a hammer, everything looks like a
nail. Fortunately, we can do better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="pedagogy" label="pedagogy"/>
    <category term="recursion" label="recursion"/>
    <category term="scheme" label="scheme"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Is Cs for All Worth Doing</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-cs4all-worth-doing/</id>
    <updated>2018-05-26T16:18:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-05-26T16:18:38-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-cs4all-worth-doing/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org24edba7" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org24edba7"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org24edba7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last time I mentioned the pushback on CS for All. While many people
are all in for CS for All, resistance is coming from many
areas. There's resistance from teachers of other subject areas, people
who think it's merely job training for the tech industry (which it can be if done poorly),
people who feel it will be implemented at the expense of other
important subjects already on the chopping block like music and art,
and others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I started the intro course at Stuy I tried to design something
that would be of value to all Stuy students and also inspire some to
continue on to more advanced CS classes. The class has been a
requirement for well over a decade at this point. I know that not
everyone loved the course but as they say, the proof is in the
pudding. It clearly got more people into the pool as gender numbers
for our more advanced CS courses got and remained much better since
the intro class became a requirement. I can't tell you how many people
now in tech have told me that they never considered CS and only got
into it from our intro course.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, we had CS for All at Stuy before there was a CS for All and if
exposing more kids to CS was the only benefit it would have been worth
it but there's more. In addition to getting more people and more
underrepresented people into tech, I've had scores of kids in a huge
range of fields come back to exclaim the value of having been forced
to take our intro course. These kids became authors, lawyers,
entrepreneurs, (non CS) teachers, journalists, venture capitalists,
Wall Street people, (non CS) professors and researchers, and more.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The benefit of being in the latter stages of a career is that you can
look back at years of results and see the good and the bad.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's no doubt in my mind that the battle to get a good CS course to
every Stuy student was one worth fighting and winning.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="csforall" label="csforall"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Should CS for All be implemented at the college level?</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csforall-in-college/</id>
    <updated>2018-05-25T16:23:23-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-05-25T16:23:23-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csforall-in-college/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org8f1c202" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org8f1c202"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org8f1c202"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There's been a lively discussion on pushback to CS for All at the K12
level over on Facebook. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; started a sub thread asking if CS
for All should first be implemented at the undergrad level rather than K12. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's an interesting question and as good as anything to get me out of
my month long non-blogging rut.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark was right when he said that if Colleges implement CS for All, K12 will 
likely do so to follow - just look at AP. Colleges have been saying
that students should take more AP classes (while giving less credit)
and we all know where that's led. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, can colleges really do CS for All, what does it
mean and what would it look like.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Much like there is no single K12 - it's 50 states and who knows how
many independent school districts, there won't be a single CS for All
at the college level but let's think about how things could play out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Many colleges have distribution requirements. Students must take one
course from bucket A, two from bucket B etc. Many schools that I've
looked at already  count CS courses in one of their distribution
buckets. This doesn't mean every student will take CS but in theory
means they can. Colleges could in theory create a required CS bucket
or even a required CS course but I don't think it's as easy as
that. It might be at a private institution but while I don't know all
the ins and outs of Hunter's governance rules I do know that adding a
universal student requirement is a HUGE undertaking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So my take is that while it might be easy for a private college
to add a CS requirement I'm guessing other public institutions are
more similar to Hunter and it's not going to be an easy task.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Regardless, let's say we have a required class on the books. Will we
have the capacity to teach it? It seems that schools are struggling to deal
with their existing CS majors and running sufficient electives and
courses for them. Just a month or so ago there was an article about a
college ending its CS minor due to lack of resources. It doesn't sound
like a radically different problem then that faced in K12. Maybe it's
harder given that at least in NY, there is &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall"&gt;room for a required CS
course&lt;/a&gt; if you can find the teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even so, assuming we have the capacity to enroll every undergrad in a
CS course what would that be? I think most people would be in
agreement that it shouldn't be CS 101. Maybe existing pre-major
courses but even there I don't know if that's always the best
path. There could be a great pre-major course to give students the
basics and lead some into the major but what about a CS course for
students in majors that need some deeper but focussed programming
skills. The appropriate course for them isn't the same as a
general/pre-major course. Using Statistics as an example, at Hunter,
many majors require a statistics course which is off loaded to the
Stats department. Each major has slightly different requirements. Over
years, the end result is a course that it seems that nobody is happy
with - a least common denominator course. CS for All at the college level
could give us a least common denominator course that doesn't serve
anyone.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, if you have the resources, none of these are issues. A well
heeled private institution can run tons of sections of specialized
classes no problem but this means just like on the K12 level we'll
get the CS for All tale of two cities that I see coming in NY where
the rich schools have good programs and the poor get a substandard
experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With all of this said, I'm finally getting to the big red flag with
college CS for All and it's an issue that everyone conveniently
ignores. I'm talking about teacher quality. One of my big takeaways
from SIGCSE is that college faculty are well behind K12 teachers in
terms of pedagogy and I don't see this changing anytime soon. This is
to be expected given that professor's career advancement is really
based on research. Having a good teacher is always important but it's
even more important for non-major students since a student in the
professor's major will at least be passionate about the subject
area. To me, this is not a recipe for success.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One can certainly make the claim that we aren't any better off right
now at the K12 level because we don't have teachers who know either
the subject nor how to teach it and at least at the college level they
know the subject matter. This is very true and it's why pre-service CS
teacher preparation is so critical to getting this right even though
it will take time. That's something that both Mark and I have been
vocal about but more on that subject next time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="csed" label="csed"/>
    <category term="csforall" label="csforall"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Is there room for CS for All</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/</id>
    <updated>2018-04-29T16:29:04-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-04-29T16:29:04-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org2156df4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org2156df4"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org2156df4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A fear revolving around CS For All concerns where will the money
come from and how will we fit in the new classes. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One suggested solution is to integrate CS into other subjects. I
thought I'd write today about why I don't think the fear is valid and
while integrating CS into other classes can have value, it probably
isn't a long term solution for CS education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's start with the integration solution. The idea is to bring CS
into an existing class. &lt;a href="http://www.bootstrapworld.org/"&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;, a program I've written about before
and one of the programs I like does this, primarily in Algebra. The
idea is that this supports the student's learning Algebra while
exposing them to CS. It's a nice program but a math teacher using
Bootstrap shouldn't be confused with a computer science
teacher. They're bringing some CS to their student and engaging the
students in a different way mathematically and that's all great but in
general you can't take two classes worth of material and concepts and
fit them into one class and the number of teachers who are truly
knowledgable in any two academic subject areas both in content and
pedagogical content knowledge is few. I'm guessing that one of the
reasons that Bootstrap works in Algebra is the alignment of the
toolset and Algebra and how you can teach it. The other is that
Algebra is frequently given more time for fewer topics. In some
struggling schools, students might have two years of algebra or a
double period so there's time to add in some CS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm all for cross curricular work. You can look at applications of
science in math classes, do mathy work in a CS class, run stats and
data analysis in math and CS classes on materials from History classes
and all of this is great. You can even create great combined curricula
where you do indeed teach multiple subjects in an integrated way but
to think that you can take what is typically taught in two different
classes and you can combine both so that they're taught in one class
with one teacher sounds fishy to me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, at the end of the day, if you go the integration approach you're
either going to have to dedicate a similar set of resources both in
time and personel to having independent courses. The alternative is
that CS will be the second class subject.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, let's look at actually bringing in CS For All as a separate
course. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here are the New York State Graduation Requirements &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Subject&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Number of semesters&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;English&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Soc Studies&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Science&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Math&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;LOTE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Arts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Phys Ed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Health&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Electives&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It can be difficult to fit Phys Ed in since it has to be offered every
semester so let's double the Phys Ed requirement to 8 semesters. What
is actually normally done is to have 7.5 periods of science a week and
2.5 periods of Gym.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This means that the basic student program uses 48 class slots and
includes 7 elective slots.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In terms of exit exams, students have to pass the following Regents:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any single math (Algebra, Geometery, Alg 2 / Trig)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any single Social Studies (US History or Global History&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any single Science (Living Env (bio), Chem, Phys, Earth Science)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any additional Regents exam&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The requirement of passing a single Math regents is what leads to the
extra time allocated to Algebra that I mentioned when discussing
integrating CS into Algebra above.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To get an Advanced Regents diploma you have to pass additional exams -
both history, all three math, three science and maybe more.  
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Using a Typical 7 period plus lunch day, we have room for 56 single
semeter classes in a high school career. This means that assuming
students aren't failing too many classes, even with the extra Phys Ed
allocation I mentioned above  we can easily fit computer
science into our day. In fact, we can technically fit in four full
years assuming a student doesn't have to repeat any class. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So in New York state we certainly have the time but what about the
budget? That's not an issue either. The state also requires that
students recieve 5.5 hours of instruction a day exclusive of
lunch. At 47 minute periods, that translates to students being
assigned 7 instructional classes a day which means we can't just give
the kids the required 44. We have to fill all 56 available class slots
over those four years. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course it's not really that simple. Students fail classes and have
to repeat them and some classes might be assigned more time than
others but it looks to me like we should be able to fit
computer science in without any big budgetary or scheduling
changes. The challenge will be finding the teacher and working the
internal politics and policies since as computer science comes in it
will mean removing some electives even if those electives are additional years
of science, math, or English.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Programs like &lt;a href="https://www.tealsk12.org/"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; and Bootstrap are important transitional programs
and even when we do have qualified CS teachers they will play an
important role - TEALS in providing industry support and resources and
Bootstrap by integrating curricular areas and over time as preservice
programs start to appear the rest will work itself out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;The state
lists by credits which are a year, I doubled the numbers to map to semesters&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="csforall" label="csforall"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Unfunded Mandates and CS For All</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/unfunded-mandates/</id>
    <updated>2018-04-27T08:43:09-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-04-27T08:43:09-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/unfunded-mandates/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org4e6858c" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org4e6858c"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org4e6858c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This morning, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; wrote about &lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/2018/04/27/lack-of-funding-leads-to-lack-of-teachers-leads-to-lack-of-cs-classes-we-may-need-to-change-our-strategy/"&gt;unfunded mandates and CS for
All&lt;/a&gt;. Unfunded mandates frequently wreak havoc on schools in a number
of ways but in the long run, I don't think it should have a severe
effect on CS for All. Rather, it could have a big impact on the number
of CS courses we offer beyond that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark relay's a story from the Cambridge Rindge and Latin School where
at the time many students wanted more CS classes but the school wasn't
planning on hiring a new CS teacher. The money quote is:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over 50 percent of students signing up for Level 2 [computer science] courses next year identify as African Americans,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No, I'm not talking about the diversity issue raised by the quote, I'm
talking about &lt;b&gt;Level 2 [computer science]&lt;/b&gt;. This implies that the
students already had &lt;b&gt;Level 1 computer science&lt;/b&gt;. Level 1 would cover
CS For All so now we're talking about CS electives vs other
electives. This is something I had to deal with for most of my career
even after we got a CS requirement at Stuy. It was always a battle to
hire enough CS teachers to meet demand. The hard part was politics -
there were always older more entrenched subject areas who would rather
force kids into their electives rather than allow them to take my CS
electives. This is a whole other kettle of fish than CS for All. It's
an issue for some schools now and will become a &lt;b&gt;BIG&lt;/b&gt; issue in five to
fifteen years when a single CS required course is more the norm. The
issue raised here is a new CS elective vs entrenched teachers and
classes which shuld lead to a discussion of the relative value of CS
electives vs other electives. That said, the reality is that it
usually comes down to school and local power and politics. Also to be
considered is the potential ebb and flow of interest - there might be
demand for 5 more CS classes and 5 less something else this year but
there might not be next year and then we're in real trouble staffing
wise.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Schools, public high schools in particular are zero sum endeavors. You
have a fixed number of periods a day, specific class requirements, and
certain mandates as to a the minimum and maximum number of classes a
student can take. In New York City, I believe students are required to
have a "full" schedule which basically means they can't come in for
English, Math, and History and then go home.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With CS for All, you're basically allocating reallocating some amount
of time to computer science. It might be hard to find a qualified
teacher. particularly in a small school where the population won't
support a full time CS teacher and it might ruffle the feathers of the
teachers that will be losing the time but it shouldn't make much of a
dent or really any dent on the budget.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark also raises the possibility of embedding CS into other subject
classes. &lt;a href="http://www.bootstrapworld.org/"&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; is a program that I'm rather fond of that does
just this in Algebra classes (although more recently they're working
to branch out into other subject areas). Even though I'm a big
Bootstrap fan I don't think that's the answer to CS for All or CS in
the high schools in general. I think that one of the reasons why
Bootstrap works so well is the alignment between the CS tool they use
and the way Algebra is or can be taught. Another reason is the fact
that while Algebra is the lowest level of the traditional high school
classes, it's frequently the one for which the most time is
allocated. Students in low performing schools might take Algebra over
two years or have a double period. This won't be the case for other
subject areas. What this means is that there's more likely extra time
to embed another subject, cs, into the Algebra class. Long term,
embedding CS into another subject area requires:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a teacher that really knows both subjects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;enough time so you can add all the cool CS content while still
preparing the students for both the next level of whatever subject
you're embedded in  as well as for whatever standardized
assessments come at the end of the year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I said, I'm a Bootstrap fan but I don't think that's the answer for
CS in K12.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back to the original topic there are certainly issues with
implementing CS for All but I don't think school funding is the
biggest hurdle. For me there are other big challenges. One is having a
supply of qualified teachers. In the long run as states outline CS
requirements and pre-service programs crop up this will work itself
out. Until then, yes, we will have an issue and yes it will take some
funding for stop gap and transitional teacher preperation. A second issue is
working the internal politics. Adding CS does mean removing something
else or more likely a piece of something else. The third one is what
I'm noticing in NY where CS for all seems to at times forget about
the CS. If we have knowledgeable teachers we can work around that one
but I still think that might be my biggest concern.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="csforall" label="csforall"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Pull Requests and Other People's Code</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pull-requests/</id>
    <updated>2018-04-26T19:07:02-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-04-26T19:07:02-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pull-requests/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org6726c03" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6726c03"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6726c03"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the things I've heard for years from former students - both
those looking for jobs and those looking to hire is that colleges
don't really do a good job preparing students for careers in
tech. Sure they teach the algorithms and the theory but ther are a lot
of missing pieces, particularly on the practical end. I'm certainly
not advocating turning CS programs into coding schools but there are
many low cost opportunities to bring practical real world best
practices in to the CS classroom. I most recently wrote about &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/testing-part2%0A"&gt;unit
testing&lt;/a&gt; and had earlier about using &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-4"&gt;GitHub as an educational
tool&lt;/a&gt;. I've been happy with the way I introduce students to Git and
how we use GitHub in my classes but I've never found a smooth way to
introduce Pull Requests. A pull request is basically a mechanism by
which one can suggest a change to a project even if you don't own
it. The project owner can then decide to merge it in or not. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Being comfortable with the pull request work flow is an important part
of contributing to open source projects. The basic process is that you
make a copy of the project you want to work on by forking it, make
your changes, then issue a pull request back to the project. For a
beginner, there are a lot of moving parts. Instead, I teach my
students branching and merging within a project. It's much easier and
arguably more useful for day to day projects. I'd like my kid to learn the
pull request mechanics but I haden't thought of a good way to do it. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've also wanted to give kids more real world experiences in class and
one experience they rarely get is working in other people's code
bases. In school you largely write your own projects be they group or
solo or work off a hopefully tried and true code base provided by the
instructor. In the real world you're frequently working off of someone
elses code and it's rarely in a polished state.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I finally found a way to kill both birds with one stone. A couple of
weeks ago my class' lab was rather lengthy. It involved reading in a
source file and reformating it in a sensible way. I knew most of the
students wouldn't finish it in the allotted time and even if they did,
this was an easy assignment to extend. On lab day I had students
create a new repo for this lab (normally they just add a folder in a
their "labs" repo) and get as much done as they could. The rule was
simple - push what you've got up to GitHub at the end of class and
then you can't push anything else. I also made it clear that I didn't
expect a completed lab..
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We continued the lab in the next class session. This time. I randomly
assigned repos to students so that they would fork someone elses
lab. They then had to complete the lab on the other students code base
and then issue a pull request back to the original
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was the first time I've tried this so it was a little
klunky. I'll do a much better job specifying the assignment and
instructions next time around but even so I think the class went
well. By the end of the class the students had sucesfully forked a
project, issued a pull request, and merged one in to their own
project. The only think I wasn't happy with was that many of the
merges happened automatically. I have to figure out how to set things
up so that there are merge conflicts since I want my students to
experience that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Overall,  I was very happy with the way things worked out. The
students were able to experience important real workd software
engineering techniques without removing any of the academic CS in the
class. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="git" label="git"/>
    <category term="github" label="github"/>
    <category term="software-engineering" label="software engineering"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
