<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xmlns:fh="http://purl.org/syndication/history/1.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z (old posts, page 16)</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index-16.atom</id>
  <updated>2016-08-23T14:27:19Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-16.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-15.atom"/>
  <link rel="previous" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-17.atom"/>
  <link rel="current" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="next-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-17.atom"/>
  <link rel="prev-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-15.atom"/>
  <fh:archive/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-16.html"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Looking under the hood</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-17-under-the-hood.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-10-17T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-10-17T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-17-under-the-hood.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Just had an interesting conversation with &lt;a href="http://chrisgrant.co/"&gt;Chris&lt;/a&gt;, one of our &lt;a href="http://cstuy.org/"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;
mentors. Chris is working with one of our more advanced groups of
hackers - they'll be creating a web based app that with ultimately be
deployed as mobile using &lt;a href="http://phonegap.com/"&gt;PhoneGap&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The question he had was "&lt;a href="http://angularjs.org/"&gt;Angular.js&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://backbonejs.org/"&gt;Backbone.js&lt;/a&gt;."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Chris and I have had this conversation before. I was explaining at the
time why I preferred to use Backbone.js over Angular in my SoftDev
classes. Part of the reason is that the current version of Angular is
already deprecated while the new version isn't ready for prime time
yet. This means I'd be teaching to a dead end. More importantly, Angular
is a much higher level framework than Backbone. There's a lot of
"magic" going on. Just a few short lines of code and you're done.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Backbone is much closer to the metal. It does less work for you so it
let's me drill down with the kids all the way to the source. This way 
the kids understand what's going on under the hood. As my buddy &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gerryseidman"&gt;Gerry&lt;/a&gt;
says, "never use a tool you couldn't write yourself." I personally
like low level tools like Backbone.js. If you have to get a job
done quickly, it might not be the right tool, but for teaching,
it's terrific.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think Chris was surprised when I said that a higher level tool like
Angular could very well be appropriate for our Saturday Hackers and
that I'd certainly support whichever direction Chris wanted to go in
with his team.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why  might it be right in this case?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mostly because the hackers only meet once a week. In our Saturday
sessions, we want our kids to learn, but we also need to create an
environment where they can continue to progress on their
projects. Some times, compromise is needed. Angular will let them get
up and running within the constraints of our program and the hackers
will still learn a lot, particularly with people like Chris mentoring them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's the balance we strive to achieve - a good amount of real CS but
tempered with the realities of a once a week program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We could go the way of many other CS programs out there and
just use tools that do 90% of the work but we like to think we have a
higher standard and I think that's what makes our team of teachers and
mentors special.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="pedagogy" label="pedagogy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Grading Autograders</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-16-graders.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-10-16T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-10-16T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-16-graders.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		The other day codehs made an announcement about their new
		&lt;a href="https://medium.com/codehs-product-updates/these-are-the-autograders-you-ve-been-looking-for-bda0fa8fd8a"&gt;autograder&lt;/a&gt;. Fellow CS Teaching veteran Alfred Thompson had his say up
		on his &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2015/10/autogradersfor-good-or-for-evil.html"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; where he talked about &lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt;'s comment on
		autograders leading to less creative assignments.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		I very much agree that autograders, due to their rigidness lend
		themselves to less creative projects, but thought I'd write up a few
		of my own thoughts on autograders.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		First and foremost, &lt;b&gt;I HATE GRADING&lt;/b&gt;. It's one of the worst parts of
		my job and grading projects is &lt;b&gt;really&lt;/b&gt; hard to do well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		You'd think an autograder would be a panacea. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		It's not. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		In addition to them being very nit-picky – got an extra space in your
		output? &lt;b&gt;FAIL&lt;/b&gt;. Wrong number of significant digits? &lt;b&gt;FAIL&lt;/b&gt;. Didn't
		handle all those "trick" cases? &lt;b&gt;FAIL&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		Since autograders typically check your output against a correct
		solution, it's going to be limited in what it can grade right and
		wrong and what's more, it's very limited in the feedback it can give.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		These are some of the limitations that lead to less creative
		projects but that's not my beef with the autograders.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		Why do we give assignments? To assess students? Yes, but also to
		inform our instruction. We need to grade the assignments ourselves
		because those assignments tell us about our students and teach us how
		best to work with them. What's more, we really don't just want to see
		that finished product, but rather, we want to see the process as
		well. Autograders can't help here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		I do use autograders – &lt;a href="http://codingbat.com/"&gt;codingbat.com&lt;/a&gt; and our own locally developed
		&lt;a href="http://bert.stuy.edu/pbrooks/SchemingBat/scheming.py"&gt;Scheming Bat.&lt;/a&gt; I use them for small homeworks and class assignments
		early on. For bigger stuff, I do it myself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		For advanced classes (AP and beyond) we're all about the GitHub. Not
		only can I grab the projects at any time but I can also see how
		projects were developed - logs, diffs, &lt;a href="https://github.com/vynl/vynl-v0/graphs/contributors"&gt;graphs&lt;/a&gt;. All give me insight
		into how the students working. Add in class lab time when I get to
		interact with the kids and I've got a good sense of my student
		computer scientists. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		In our intro courses, where they're not ready for GitHub, we use
		Dropbox for sharing and collecting assignments. Not quite as good but
		we can still see a lot.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		At the end of the day, if a teacher doesn't look at a student's work
		directly, a teacher isn't going to know everything there is to know
		about a student. I can't imagine a top English teacher not reading a
		student's essays. We're no different. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		It's time consuming and generally no fun but it's a big part of &lt;b&gt;real&lt;/b&gt;
		education.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="pedagogy" label="pedagogy"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Free labor for the College Board and more angst for the kids</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-13-psat.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-10-13T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-10-13T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-13-psat.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
I won't be teaching my regular classes tomorrow. I'll be
meeting all my kids but classes will only be 12 minutes long.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, how will my colleagues and I spend the rest of the day?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Proctoring the PSAT.&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This has always been a sore point with me. Back in the day, many
schools, Stuy included, offered the PSAT on the weekend. If you wanted
to proctor, you'd come in and get paid a little extra. As a kid, if
you wanted to take the exam you'd come in as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't remember when it changed but at some point it did. The DOE
decreed that if you offered the PSAT during the week on school time,
the DOE would pay for the exams. This was done under the ridiculous
idea that all kids taking a test that counts for nothing is a good
thing. You can make a claim that having taken the PSAT gives the kids
some familiarity with the SAT but the SAT's value as a predictor of
college success is questionable at best anyway.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, setting things up like this is a great deal for the College
Board. It looks like they get a $15 per kid cash cow every year from
the NYC tax payers. It's a hidden expense so no one complains but we
keep shoveling the money out the door.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What's worse is that we also provide the College Board with free
labor - rather then spend my day teaching my kids I'm working for free
for the College Board administering their test to my kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teachers do the work, kids suffer through the exam, and the College
Board laughs all the way to the bank.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Coding schools - or why I chose NYCDA</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-12-nycda.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-10-12T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-10-12T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-12-nycda.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of you might have noticed that a few months ago, I decided to
affiliate myself with &lt;a href="http://nycda.com/"&gt;The New York Code and Design Academy&lt;/a&gt; or NYCDA. I
took on the role of "Academic Director, Youth Programs." It's a part
time gig, at least for now and I'm helping them develop their programs
for middle and high school students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why did I choose them?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are a number of coding schools with varying levels of hype
around them. At their core, all are workforce programs. They take
people with little or no programming background and after a few months
of intensive training, they ship them off as web devs or the like.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have friends at many of these coding schools and related programs so
what was different about NYCDA that made me decide to work with them?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They know who they are, they know what they do, they know where they
want to go, and we all feel I can help them get there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let me explain.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most coding schools follow the same mold.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For one reason or another, a founder decides to start teaching a
class. This works pretty well so it starts to grow into a
business. For many of these coding schools, the teaching staff comes
from the program's own graduates.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The key point here is that most coding schools have little to no
interaction with real, experienced educators.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, why do they work? Well, to start, there's plenty of low hanging
fruit. Right now, as these programs are in high demand,  programs can
cream top applicants. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Many programs also have applicants complete
pre-work - that is a program of self study before starting the coding
school. This pretty much ensures that your classes are going to be
composed of hard working, intelligent self starters - that's a recipe
for a successful student body.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Given the student population and the fact that the skill set for an
entry level programmer can be taught fairly formulaicaly, it's a recipe
for success.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, I don't mean to imply that these schools are bad or doing bad
things - all of them are taking people and giving them a chance at a
new career. It's good and it's important. Even more so for
organizations that provide a step up for the have nots.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teaching kids is another matter. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For adults you're teaching a specific skill set for a specific job
market. For kids, you're setting a foundation and opening doors. You
can't just take your adult model and apply it to kids. Well, you can,
and it will even look good, but it won't have real substance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's what impressed me about NYCDA - when &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jeremysnepar"&gt;Jeremy&lt;/a&gt; came to me it was
clear - they knew what they did and what they did well. He also knew
that as they ramp up their youth offerings, it was important to
involve real, experienced educators - that it was about having true
expert teachers even more than it was curriculum. He understood that
while NYCDA is doing a great job, how much better could it be to
include CS educators who have been sending kids into industry
successfully for years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was even more delighted when my partner in crime JonAlf
Dyrland-Weaver - one of the best teachers I know, CS or otherwise,
agreed to teach one of our NYCDA youth courses this semester.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
NYCDA is the only coding school working to bring the best teachers out
there to their youth programs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's why I joined on and that's why I'm really excited for the
programs we're going to roll out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How it all began</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-09-be-a-cs-teacher.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-10-09T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-10-09T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-09-be-a-cs-teacher.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This past week, Garth Flint wrote a couple of posts on how he
got to be a CS teacher and on being a CS teacher. You can find them here:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gflint.wordpress.com/2015/10/07/so-you-want-to-be-a-cs-teacher-part-1/"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gflint.wordpress.com/2015/10/08/so-you-want-to-be-a-cs-teacher-part-2/"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They're both well worth a read.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It got me thinking about how I got my start.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I never planned on being a teacher. I figured I'd just work in
tech. After working my way through college, fresh CS degree in hand, I
landed at Goldman Sachs. I had other opportunities but the tech scene
was very different. You could (basically):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work for a financial house or insurance company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do niche consulting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;travel out of the city to Bellcore, AT&amp;amp;T or IBM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, I didn't drive and wasn't going to do consulting so I ended up
on Wall Street. I worked there for a bit but it didn't do it for me,
then tried a consulting gig. No better. Wall street never appealed to
me and at the time, more programming type jobs involved you working
alone on a computer in an office or a cube all day. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, for no particular reason, I decided to give teaching a go.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I always wonder, if I had come along a few years later if I would have
stayed in pure tech.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had zero teaching credentials but there was a math teacher shortage
at the time. By taking a couple of CS classes as math classes
(numerical methods, algorithms) they justified giving me temporary
license. I would have to take a handful of Ed credits within a couple
of years and later get a masters (which I knew would be in CS, no way
was I getting an Education degree).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I started at Seward Park High School as a math teacher. Best thing
that could have happened to me. I was working with an incredibly
diverse population - high achieving kids, low achieving kids,
immigrants, multi-generational Americans, delightful kids and kids on
parole. That's where I developed my chops.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Knowing that I was a CS guy the math chairman started having me teach
the basic programming course and later APCS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of years later, I was bumped to Stuy. Taught math and the
rest of my history can be seen &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/09/17/stuycs-spectator.html#.VhfhBt8qcbw"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Garth talks about requirements and Alfred Thompson, in his &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2015/10/an-inside-look-at-being-computer.html"&gt;link to
Garth's posts&lt;/a&gt; talks about the problems of CS teacher isolation. It
took a long time and it was hard work, but I started in a school with
no CS to speak and no CS teachers and now we have a required course,
between six and 10 CS teachers depending on the year, and a thoroughly
oversubscribed program. Of course, if you're at a small school, you
can't really do that. I remember in the early years, when it came to
course signup time, I'd have to visit every math class in the building
on one day to hock my courses. I'm glad those days are gone.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Garth also makes a great point about all there is to learn as a real
CS teacher. The best math teachers I know love doing math and love
solving problems but by and large, they're not learning new subfields
every year. Over my time as a teacher I've learned, either by choice
or necessity:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new fields such as
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relearning AI, which is radically different then when I was in
college&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data mining&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OOP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UX&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HCI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new languages
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Java&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C++&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Javascript&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Haskell (a bit)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perl&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And tons of technologies
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unix as a toolset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;system administration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;network administration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Git
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and many more.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, since I do work with many other CS teachers, I
might be a little bit of an outlier. Some of my colleagues also work
to keep current and learn new things while others are content with
their knowledge base and are happy to teach what they're currently
teaching. That's not to say that they don't work on their craft, but
rather, they're in a comfort zone of knowledge.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So what's next? As initiatives like CS4All progress, CS education will
become more formalized. You all know my fear about the current
efforts - CS Ed will go the way of Math Ed and we'll be left with Meh
CS education for all. If that's the case, and I hope I'm wrong, many
of Garth's issues will disappear. CS across the nation will become
more generic but more accessible and CS teachers will hopefully know
how to teach their courses but maybe not too much more. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even if that is the case, there will hopefully still be places for us
old time gluttons for punishment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I guess some people like the blues</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-01-fans.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-10-01T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-10-01T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-01-fans.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Funny story from yesterday.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Devorah, my better half, is an assistant principal at another high
school. Yesterday evening, she was at work late for "curriculum
night." Parents came to the school after hours to hear a variety of
presentations.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
During her presentation, Devorah mentioned her name, that she had two
former public school kids in college, and that's about it for the
personal info.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After the session, two parents approached Devorah to say "we're big
fans of your husband!"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since when do teachers have fans?????????
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I mean, I understand "my daughter/son was in your husbands class and
really enjoyed it," but "I'm a big fan?" She wasn't sure how to take
it. Obviously we both took it as an honor and compliment but we also
both got a chuckle out of the turn of phrase.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've already said that teachers aren't &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/12/14/rockstar-godfather.html#.Vg264t8Sr0o"&gt;rock stars, we're blues men&lt;/a&gt; so
I guess this shows that some folks still like the blues.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hacking Sessions - iterating until it's right</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-26-hacking-sessions.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-09-26T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-09-26T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-26-hacking-sessions.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hacking-sessions-2015/hs.jpg" alt="hs.jpg" width="480px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today we kicked off Hacking Sessions 2015. Saturday morning with sixty kids in a room
brainstorming ideas.  Soon they'll settle on teams and projects and
we'll be off for a semester of exploring CS and tech.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The next couple of weeks will be a little chaotic with groups
shifting, mentors figuring out which groups to work with and us, the
instructors launching each team on its way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is our third year running Hacking Sessions. We're setting things
up to have student teams exploring a project, technology, or
tool. Each team will have more experienced students mentoring them. In
some cases the mentors will also be new to the topic. Supporting both
the hackers and mentors are our instructors.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm pretty happy with our model but it took us a couple of iterations
to get here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Our first go round was Fall 2013. We had just started CSTUY and wanted
to get something started prior to launching a summer program. &lt;i&gt;SumAll&lt;/i&gt;
provided us with space and we were able to attract a small cadre of
kids. We had a few of our older students as teaching assistants and
ran the program with a mix of instruction and projects. Over the year
we saw that a Saturday program presents a number of challenges:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students have other obligations on Saturdays such as athletic
teams. This can lead to inconsistent attendance.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SATs also kill attendance
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can't count on the participants to work between the sessions.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lateness can be an issue early on a Saturday morning.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once a week makes building a community a challenge.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kids have enough classroom learning during the week. Saturday should
be a change of pace.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We learned a lot that year and ran V2.0 the following fall. Second
time around we had the advantage of bringing in kids from our summer
program to seed the culture. We also knew we wanted to move to more of
a project / mentor based model but due to space restrictions couldn't
really get to where we wanted to be.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That changed halfway through when SumAll moved to larger offices. By
the end of the year, I think we worked out most of the kinks. We
figured out how to get the kids into teams and pointing in the right
direction as well as  how to find the right mentors and provide them
with support. The only thing we weren't happy with was that the mentors
didn't have enough time to work on their own projects. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now we're in V3.0. Thanks to our &lt;a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/262929085/saturday-hacking-sessions"&gt;kickstarter&lt;/a&gt;, we're fully funded and
somehow word seems to have gotten out. Numbers are way up and I think
we've finally gotten the model down.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As with anything new, it takes time and revisions to get things right
but as long as one leaves the kids with a net positive and as long as
one can look at oneself with a critical eye, you eventually get there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looking forward to a great year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Suspension if disbelief and the Mikado</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-21-mikado.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-09-21T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-09-21T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-21-mikado.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was brought up on Gilberg and Sullvan. My father, who always wanted
to be an opera singer sang with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Light_Opera_of_Manhattan"&gt;LOOM&lt;/a&gt; back in the day and there was
always classical music playing. Either from the Hi Fi or my father
singing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Recently, there's been a kerfufle over what was to be &lt;a href="http://nygasp.org"&gt;NYGASP's&lt;/a&gt;
production of Mikado.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	My son, Natan wrote a terrific blog post on it and the suspension of
	belief in opera. It's long but well worth a read.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you like G&amp;amp;S or opera in general, take a look.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It can be found &lt;a href="http://seccorecit.blogspot.com/2015/09/imagine-if-you-will.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy. 
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Not in with the in crowd - concerns about NYC &amp;#35CS4All</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-18-in-crowd.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-09-18T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-18-in-crowd.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
	&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
	&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
			Earlier this week, Mayor Bill deBlasio announced some ambitious 
			&lt;a href="http://avc.com/2015/09/computer-science-for-all/"&gt;CS Education Plans&lt;/a&gt; for NYC. I posted a response &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2015/09/15/failed.html#.Vfx1Rp_0-Ak"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Now that a few
			days past, I thought I'd clear a few things up.
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			First and foremost, I hope my concerns are unfounded and I hope the
			plan is a tremendous success. 
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			What's got me bummed is not that I need to see my name in lights
			given that in many ways I've been a CS Ed trailblazer (although who doesn't
			like a little ego stroking), rather that in my humble opinion NY has
			squandered a great opportunity and resource and as a results, kids
			won't get nearly all they could.
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			This STEMs from the fact that NYC has been unwilling to engage us,
			StuyCS as a resource. We've got the most experience and success in
			building programs, training teachers, and teaching kids. What more
			could you ask?
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			I've repeatedly reached out to and repeatedly invited in key
			government and DOE players in an effort to try to get them to look at
			our work and leverage it to do more good for more kids but over two
			mayors and around fifteen years, the silence we get back is deafening.
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			Now, this isn't to say that I don't have some friends and supporters
			in the CS Ed space. I consider &lt;a href="http://avc.com/2015/09/computer-science-for-all/"&gt;Fred Wilson&lt;/a&gt;, the main man driving this
			from the tech sector side to be a supporter, ally and friend. His
			involvement is the key reason I think this whole thing might
			work. Likewise, many people in the tech industry who've worked with my
			graduates are very supportive of my efforts and my actual graduates are
			a wonderfully supportive family.
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			So why do the DOE and NYC people say they don't want to include us?
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			Here are some of the things I get back:
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;We want something that works for all students.
			&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			This implies that our stuff is purely a result of Stuy being a school
			with high achievers. My response? 
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;By saying all students but excluding high achievers, you can't mean
				all students.
			&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Other high achieving schools haven't developed anything near what
				we've built.
			&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			and it also ignores the fact that:
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Our nonprofit has had kids from around 40 to 50 schools and we
				get rave reviews from those kids and their parents.
			&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Our gender numbers far outpace the national averages.
			&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;We've had teachers move on to other schools and customize our work
				their.
			&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
	&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
	&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
			and this is just the teaching part. What about our success in
			designing an overall program or training teachers.
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			Of course it doesn't help that Stuyvesant's own administration has
			never recognized nor supported StuyCS.
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			You'd think that those with the keys to the castle would engage and at
			least consult with the people who've been doing this successfully for
			over 20 years.
		&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
	&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
	&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
			So who are these folk with the keys?
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			It's a mix of people. Some in NYC government, some in DOE, some Tech
			entrepreneurs, and running program. None have our experience or track
			record and a number have neither taught nor coded.
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			Why won't they really engage us? 
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			You're guess is as good as mine but I have my suspicions.
		&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
	&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
	&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
			Why am I concerned?
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			Because we have something to offer. NYC and DOE won't leverage us as a
			resource. What other missteps will they make as they try to bring
			CS4All.
		&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;
			I have no control over all of this, all I can do is work in my little
			corner of the world. If others want my help, my doors always open. If
			not, I know there will always be some parents, kids, and educators who
			get what we do and will benefit from it.
		&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I should be happy but feel like I've failed</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-15-failed.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-09-15T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-09-15T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-15-failed.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The NY Times just posted an article - the  mayor announced a 10 year
deadline by which time all NYC public school students will be taking
CS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I should be happy. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I feel thoroughly defeated.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As many of you know, I've struggled for years to try to bring CS
education to more kids and to train more teachers. You also probably
know that over the years, I've become pretty good at this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why am I feeling so down about this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Because despite my best efforts I'm no closer to my goal than day one.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Stuy is no closer to recognizing CS. I'm still a just math teacher
and the DOE has given the job of running CS education to person after
person none whom had any real CS experience and few who have had any
real teaching experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I see plans based on dropping in curricula and quick fixes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I see programs run by people still wet behind the ears with respect to
CS Education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sometimes I feel like I'm the only sane person in the room, or maybe
I'm the loony. I'm not sure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Probably because I don't play well with others. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So I feel defeated.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Defeated because I know I have something to offer that the kids of NYC
deserve.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Defeated because I know they're not going to get it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm already looking to leave Stuy and public education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Maybe this is just another sign that it's time.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
