<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z (old posts, page 18)</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index-18.atom</id>
  <updated>2016-04-17T00:52:38Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-18.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-17.atom"/>
  <link rel="previous" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="current" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="prev-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-17.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-18.html"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Leaving Stuyvesant</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-23-leaving-stuy.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-12-23T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-12-23T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-23-leaving-stuy.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Almost twenty six years. That's how long I've been a NYC public school
teacher. Most of that time at my alma mater, Stuyvesant. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of years ago, the school paper wrote up an overview of my
career. I re-posted it &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/09/17/stuycs-spectator.html#.Vnqfxh8Sr0o"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I'm somtimes amazed at where we are now
and how we got here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Regulars here also know my frustrations. To Stuy, I'm an
interchangeable, generic math teacher and the DOE has shown no
interested in supporting what we've built. I've also written about my
concerns with the direction the city's going with respect to K12 CS
education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was time for me to start the next phase of my career.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm happy to say that I will be joining Hunter College in late
		January. I'll be developing their CS Teacher Ed program and also
		working with their computer science undergrads. I'll also have the
		opportunity to work with the Manhattan/Hunter Science High School and
		Hunter College High School.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		I also look forward to the opportunity to work more closely with my
		friends in the K12 Ed space.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		I'm very excited about this opportunity but it feels a bit weird after
		being in the same place for so long. I don't feel any special
		attachment to the institution that is Stuyvesant, my allegiance is to
		my current and former students and that community isn't going
		anywhere. Next year I'll still be working with terrific young people,
		just in a different location under a different name.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		I will miss the team that we've put together but even then, we get to
		continue our work with CSTUY.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		With the new year comes new opportunity and I can't wait.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Advent of Code - because I'm an idiot</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-17-im-an-idiot.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-12-17T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-17-im-an-idiot.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/advent/advent.png" alt="advent.png" width="480px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wish our kids believed us when we tell them that we have the same
programming troubles as they do. We stare at code for hours not seeing
problems that could be a simple as passing the wrong value. We spend
an inordinate amount of time trying to see the problem and then
realize that we just forgot something silly. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At this point, it's common for us CS teachers to tell each other "I
figured out the problem I was having – it's that I was an idiot."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last time, I talked about &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; and how I was somewhat behind
the curve. In part because I started late and in part because I've
been using it as an excuse to learn some Clojure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's how I burned over two days on &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/day/6"&gt;Day 6&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem is pretty straight forward. You have a 1,000 x 1,000 grid
representing a light board and you have to repeatedly do operations on
smaller rectangles on that grid. Turning individual lights on and off,
if you would.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If I were doing this in a language like C, I'd probably just take a
big block of memory and loop through the instructions but since I was
working in Clojure, I thought I'd try to do something in more of the
functional mode, that is, with immutable data types. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After a while, I was getting the feeling that it was going to be too
slow so I shifted to just modifying a big block of memory.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Try as I could, I couldn't get it to work. I was sure my algorithm was
fine - it wasn't a hard problem, but I couldn't get the right answer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After a while, I started looking at existing solutions and they were
basically the same as mine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was stumped. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Two days after the start, I figured it out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No matter how hard you try, if your problem specifies the data in the
form &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;row1,col1 row2,col2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, you're not going to get the right answer
if you decide that the input is in the form &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;row1,row2 col1,col2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;D'Oh&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Ok, after that the problem was pretty trivial.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hopefully I'll have some time to do problem 7 and beyond this weekend.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If there are any Clojure people out there, I'm putting my solutions up
on &lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/adventofcodeclojure"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; - I'd love some feedback on how to get more idiomatic.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Advent of Code</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-15-advent.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-12-15T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-12-15T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-15-advent.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/advent/advent.png" alt="advent.png" width="480px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Has everyone seen &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt;?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a site with a series of programming problems that are being
revealed one a day, a la an advent calendar. You can read more about
it &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/about"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I came to the party a little late so I'm only up to day 6.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Each problem comes in two parts. The second is revealed after you
complete the first. Both students and teachers are enjoying the
problems.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I like about the Advent of code, besides the one a day release,
is the fact that at least so far, the problems aren't super crazy
hard. They require a little thought but they seem very doable.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For me, that makes them a perfect platform on which to play with a new
language. I'm working through these in Clojure. I've been putting my
solutions up &lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/adventofcodeclojure"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I have no idea if my code is "good" Clojure but
it's been fun nonetheless.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, if you're looking for a nice set of small programming problems
and want to explore something new, check it out.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>We're Number One!! We're Number One!!!</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-19-were-number-one.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-11-19T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-11-19T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-19-were-number-one.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I woke up this morning to an email from my principal "Stuy is #1."
This followed a bunch of Facebook posts by friends and alums of a
similar vein. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was all about a couple of reports, &lt;a href="https://k12.niche.com/rankings/public-high-schools/best-overall/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/best-public-high-schools-in-america-2015-11"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It turns out
Stuy is ranked #1. Woo Hoo. We're awesome.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, everyone whooping it up now was quick to say "all those
rankings are meaningless" back when US News and World report ranked
Stuy way down on their list.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We all know what makes a great school: great students. At least in
terms of perception. Look at most of these lists and they'll be
dominated by high schools that take in high performing students. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Truth be told, in many ways, Stuyvesant isn't a special place, but
more on that down below.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In terms of the ratings and rankings they're meaningless but in a way
dangerous. I see it at Stuy. Under the current administration AP is
the word of the day. It's all Advanced Placement all the time.  Why?
That's one of the ways to rise up in the rankings. So are the school
surveys which is why there's been more pressure to get those done.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My feelings? AP is all about making money for the College Board. I'm
not a fan of "early college," I'm a fan of enrichment. I've said it
many times - if a course is such that it can be mastered equally well
by a 15 year old in 10th grade as by a 19 or 20 year old in college,
well, it really isn't college level. High achieving, well prepared
high school kids can do college level work in 11th and 12th grades but
probably not in all subject areas. Sure they can memorize, ape, and
mimic, but the depth of knowledge won't be there. Regardless, we
should trust schools and teachers to do it right. Schools can roll out
rigorous courses as good or better than AP. There's no real need for
the College Board seal of approval. Look at &lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/alex-mallory/private-schools-ap-tests_b_823616.html"&gt;Fieldston and other
private schools&lt;/a&gt; as examples.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We've been teaching our own introductory CS class at Stuy for
years. The entire team knows that it's far superior, at least for our
students, than the new AP CS Principles course yet our principal keeps
pushing the AP course. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've spoken to a number of administrators  from highly regarded schools
over the past couple of years and all are pushing test scores, AP
classes, and anything to get those rankings up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, there's a movement to make Stuy a generic school that happens to
have high performing students which brings me back to are we number
one or indeed are we special?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It certainly has a couple of things going for it. Great kids and a
large size. The large size ensures lots of electives. Stuy is one of
the few schools with a robust set of humanities classes, stem classes,
multiple music groups, and more. That's important. When I sent my kids
to Stuy a big part of the decision was due to the fact that they'd be
surrounded by smart kids whose interests range all over the place. The
kids come from all backgrounds. Also, my kids would be able to explore all
of their current interests and maybe even pick up some new ones.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
But then there's the other side. We have lots of electives and some
are great but then, some are lousy. Just like any other school we have
some amazing teachers and some garbage. For the most part, if you
switched Stuy's faculty and administration with another school, you
might lose a few special electives and gain a few different ones but
by and large people wouldn't notice the difference.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Regardless, Stuy and all similar institution should be charged with
something extra. We should be leaders in developing programs and
sharing them with other schools. We should be developing experiences
for our kids that are appropriate to their level of development, not
being happy with high regents scores or the fact that we had a bunch
of Intel semifinalists, many who probably would have accomplished
similar feats regardless of the school they attended.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Kowtowing to the rankings kills that possibility. To reach the top of
the charts you have to follow the book. If you want to lead, you have
to write the book.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It would be silly of me to judge my success by how many kids pass the
APCS exam. It's an easy test for them. I've worked hard not to create
classes because I like them, but because they make sense for our
kids. They sequence appropriately, and they give the kids
opportunities and experiences that they wouldn't get had they not
attended Stuy. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Unfortunately, since the late 90's I haven't had the luxury of a
supportive administration that shared my vision. As the school and the
system moves more towards the rankings you're going to see educational
leaders more and more marginalized and finally eliminated. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, is Stuy number one and is it special? As long as it's given the
same type of kids it's had for the past 100 or so years, the kids will
do fine. Is it really special? Well, unless it starts really think
about what the kids need and deserve, maybe not so much.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Other People's Code</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-11-other-peoples-code.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-11-11T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-11-11T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-11-other-peoples-code.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline1"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The coding on their project is reminiscent in many ways of an Ed
Sheerhan song. It left me in tears and very confused as to what the
author was trying to accomplish.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– a student commenting on their most recent project.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We had some fun last week. Well, OK, I had some fun. The SoftDev
classes had just finished a little project. Basically, a blogging
platform. Something that would tie together all the tools we've been
using. Flask, user management, an SQL database (SQLite), and a nice
looking front end. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was also the first real group project so the teams have started to
learn how to work together. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After some project demos, it was time for part two: NOSQL. We explored
MongoDB and then it was time for the project - clean up the
previous project through the use of techniques like template
inheritance and convert the database backend to MongoDB.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The catch? Each group would take another groups project and use that
as their starter code. The rules? They could modify and refactor but
they couldn't rewrite.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It threw the groups for a loop but I ultimately think they had
fun with this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Afterwards each group gave a write up to their starter group. What
made their life easier, what made it harder. We then circled up for
discussion as a class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was terrific.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, it was great that we've gotten to a point where everyone feels
comfortable giving each other constructive criticism. We've gotten to
the point where the class is a team.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Beyond that, I'm hoping that everyone got a lot out of the exercise.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As each group talked, common themes arose:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;consistent commenting is good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;variable names matter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unused code and files can be misleading&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;overall code structure, file names, and locations are important.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and much more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We're now going to start a discussion of coding style, standards, and
documentation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've got to say that I'm very happy how this little experiment worked
out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
