<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom</id>
  <updated>2017-04-12T18:07:08Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-28.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>GitHib as a tool for education</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-4/</id>
    <updated>2017-04-11T19:11:30-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-04-11T19:11:30-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-4/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
When I started using git and GitHub with my students it was a natural
progression having started with started with CVS and then, as
technology changed moving through Subversion and then Mercurial. It
was all about using sensible professional software development
techniques while making it easier for students to submit work and for
me to evaluate their submissions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over time, I found that git and GitHub in fact provided some extra
support for educators right out of the box.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-3"&gt;last github post&lt;/a&gt; I talked about using the results of &lt;code&gt;git log&lt;/code&gt;
and looking at diffs. Both provide ways of seeing what a student did
and when. The commit log and history make it easier to hold students accountable to working
through a project and not leavings for the last minute. The diffs make
it easier to see what's changed both to see progress and also to help
support students as they develop their projects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you use Emacs, as I do, you can use the &lt;a href="https://github.com/pidu/git-timemachine"&gt;git timemachine&lt;/a&gt; package
which does a great job visualizing changes:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/sigcse-github/timemachine.gif" alt="timemachine.gif" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Other editors might have a similar feature.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The contribution graphs also provide a quick snapshot which shows what
team members are contributing and when:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/sigcse-github/githubgraph.png" alt="githubgraph.png" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The punchcard graph is also useful to see when students actually do
their work.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/sigcse-github/githubgraph2.png" alt="githubgraph2.png" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
GitHub also make it easy to set up starter code or to have students
"take over" each others projects by forking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm very happy using git and GitHub as is but if you want more
support, check out &lt;a href="https://classroom.github.com/"&gt;GitHub Classroom&lt;/a&gt;. Had it existed when I started,
I'd probably have used it but since I had already gotten used to my
work flows I've stuck with raw git and github.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In case you missed the earlier posts describing the process I use to
introduce github to my classes here they are:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-1"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-2"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-3"&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm hoping some of you have found this set of four posts useful or at
least interesting.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="pedagogy" label="pedagogy"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A free multi-state clicker with built in redundency</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/thumb_clickers/</id>
    <updated>2017-04-01T17:23:21-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-04-01T17:23:21-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/thumb_clickers/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last Friday, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; wrote about the woes of &lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/2017/03/31/the-need-for-better-software-and-systems-to-support-active-cs-learning/%0A"&gt;using clickers&lt;/a&gt; in a
class. The amount of effort required to use his school's approved
clicker technology sounds ridiculous so while we need tools to better
engage students in large class settings we need better tools that can
be integrated into our classes more easily.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've never used clickers. On top of stories like Mark's, there are  a
number of problems with using clickers in a public school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can't force students to buy them and in NYC, until recently,
students couldn't use their phones (which they also might not have).
Forgetting the expense, if the school provides them, is it one per
student? If so, who's going to administer the clicker to student
mapping and how will that be communicated to the teachers. If college
tech infrastructures are sometimes lacking, high schools are orders of
magnitudes worse. The resources just aren't there. Then we have to
deal with loss and breakage.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If a teacher somehow gets a class set of clickers, they have to deal
with mapping clickers to students for all of their classes and make
sure the right student has the right clicker. Again, loss  and
breakage is a problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then you have to create the question content and hope that everything
works in class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The value added given the overhead just doesn't seem worth it
particularly since high school classes, while large, are not in the
hundreds and there are other methods of student engagement.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's what I use instead. It's not perfect but it's low cost and low
effort with a pretty high return.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The basic configuration, is a simple three state broadcast device.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not without its problems and I don't think it would work as well
in a large lecture but given the cost, it's well worth it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what is it?
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/fonzup.jpg" alt="fonzup.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Thumbs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Periodically, I'll poll my class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
&lt;img width="30%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/sidethumb.png"&gt;
&lt;img width="30%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/upthumb.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img width="30%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/downthumb.jpg"&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Thumb to the side? Everything's OK. Keep going as you're going. I get
it. Basically, things are good.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thumb up? Speed up, you're going too slow, I got it five minutes ago or
some similar big positive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thumb down? I have no idea what you're talking about.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's cheap, easy, quick, and once you can get your class to buy in,
you can get a quick sense of the class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The downsides?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The class has to have a level of comfort so that students vote
honestly and don't just give you positive feedback.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No data collection.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The upsides?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;quick
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cheap
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;works on any topic on the fly
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;even if the votes are artificially skewed towards positive, it does
forces the class to be at least a little attentive and to engage in
some physical response
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can get analog responses by allowing students to adjust wrist
rotation
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As to the redundancy? I've never had a kid leave their thumb at home
or lose it and even if they did, they've got a second hand.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/fonztwo.jpg" alt="fonztwo.jpg" align="center" height="200"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This also works in extreme environments. Try using a clicker or mobile
app with gloves or mittens on or underwater.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't teach large lectures so I don't know how this would work in a
huge class. I'd imagine it's still worth it given that it's so low
friction and low cost of entry even if it's not perfect.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="pedagogy" label="pedagogy"/>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIGCSE 2017 - a path to github part 3</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-3/</id>
    <updated>2017-03-30T14:02:31-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-03-30T14:02:31-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-3/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wanted to write this up earlier but, as so frequently happens all my
dormant work projects decided it was time to rise up and demand
instant attention.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When we left off, we had students pulling code and submitting homework
via github.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Form here, it's an easy step to have them working on a small project
in their own repo. In fact, sometimes, I'll jump right to a two person
project where one person creates the repo and invites the other (and
me) as a collaborator.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once here, it's important to emphasize the normal workflow:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;git pull&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;edit stuff with an occasional &lt;code&gt;git add&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;git rm&lt;/code&gt;,  or &lt;code&gt;got mv&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;commit
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and an occasional &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Regardless of how much you emphasize the workflow you're now going to
have to cover merges as well how to recover from problems by going to
an earlier revision.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For going back to earlier versions or otherwise recovering from
disasters, I don't show them the "right" way of doing things. I show
them a way that's easy to remember and reliably works without tons of
searching for answers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, given some repo, I have them clone a version under another
name:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git clone git@github.com:hunterdaedalus/classcode.git newdirname
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, they have the original repo and a clone under the directory
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;newdirname&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have them go into that new copy and use &lt;code&gt;git log&lt;/code&gt; to go through the
logs to find an earlier version that they want to go back to.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The log will look something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="verse"&gt;
commit 67eceb5e0a01ca5f5fb54ace65a4fe134f71edae&lt;br&gt;
Author: Mike Zamansky &amp;lt;zamansky@gmail.com&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;
Date:   Sat Feb 25 12:32:26 2017 -0500&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
    updated Makefile&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
commit 7efed10eb6015276b0cb82874ce786dc68a683ae&lt;br&gt;
Author: Mike Zamansky &amp;lt;zamansky@gmail.com&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;
Date:   Sat Feb 25 08:45:34 2017 -0500&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
    broke out main –&amp;gt; main and shapes&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
commit e8b5c240123a7cb17920d52b4aba9cf5787ddab2&lt;br&gt;
Author: Mike Zamansky &amp;lt;zamansky@gmail.com&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;
Date:   Sat Feb 25 08:36:29 2017 -0500&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
    added lab3 code&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
commit 6d5bcf866306334ddc5c6a48e8f49fb39ddbcb18&lt;br&gt;
Author: Some other coder &amp;lt;somone@somewhere.net&amp;gt;&lt;br&gt;
Date:   Sun Feb 19 19:29:51 2017 -0500&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Find the hash that they want to get back to and &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;checkout&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; that
version (you normally only have to use the first few characters of
the hash):
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git checkout 7efed10
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now they can grab what they want, copy it into the working copy of the
repo, &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;commit&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; the changes and &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;push&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; them back.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
For Merging, I start by having them do it manually. I'll have them
load the file in question into their editor and look for the chunks
that look like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="verse"&gt;
&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt; A&lt;br&gt;
lines in file A&lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;=====&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;
lines in file B&lt;br&gt;
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; B&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They'll manually make the changes, then save, commit and push back.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Later, I'll show them a couple of tools to help along the way. I
usually show ediff in emacs along with meld.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once they've been doing this for a while, it's easy to expand group
sizes. After that, I'll introduce &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;issues&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; via the github interface.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The last big topic is branches.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First I show basic branches and merging. Here's a pretty good &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Branching-Basic-Branching-and-Merging"&gt;run
through&lt;/a&gt;. Afterwards, I'll show how branching works in conjunction with
github. This is also a good time to emphasize that students have to
actually read the messages that git gives them when things don't  go
well. In most cases, the message will contain the exact thing to type
to fix the problem (such as linking a branch with a branch up on
github).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now is also the time to introduce pull requests and how to use them to
support code review. The general setup I recommend is one branch per
group member and a main "deployment" branch with group members
creating more branches as they see fit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's about it. I've followed this process, more or less, over a
semester, over a year, and over multiple years. It's worked for me, I
hope some of this helps you as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the next and probably last git/github post I'll talk about the
educational benefits that I've discovered along the way. After that,
I'll get back to some emacs videos, other SIGCSE stuff and my normal rants.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIGCSE 2017 - a path to github part 2</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-2/</id>
    <updated>2017-03-19T10:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-03-19T10:11:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-2/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;Note:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just for some quick context. The process I started to describe in the
last post and continue here chronicles what I did at Stuy with high
schoolers. Now that I'm at Hunter college, I'm adapting the process
but the overarching themes remain the same.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;Post starts here:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that your students have been pulling the classcode repo regularly
it's time to move to the next step - adding and pushing files to a
repo.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't claim to do this the "right way" or the best way but it's
worked for me and it's gotten my students up to speed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I ease my students into adding and pushing files using git through
homework submission. I create a single repo, usually named
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;submissions&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and make a folder for each student underneath looking
something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="verse"&gt;
.&lt;br&gt;
└── submissions&lt;br&gt;
    ├── abram_sarah&lt;br&gt;
    ├── chen_stuart&lt;br&gt;
    └── thompson_steve&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Before going any further, let me clear up one thing. The repo is
public so all the students have access to each others work. I'm OK
with that. We could have each student make their own repo and use git
&lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Tools-Submodules"&gt;submodules&lt;/a&gt; to make a submissions repo but administration is much
trickier and we lose the chance to build a culture of cooperation and
trust. We can lock down our submission systems as much as we want. If
students want to share assignments there's nothing we can do about
it. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My preference is to try to build a culture that minimizes bad
behavior and rewards good behavior. I'd rather see an incorrect
homework so that I can tell what we need to work on than a copied
perfect assignment. I'd rather see students cite each other, share
properly, and support each other than copy in the shadows. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not naive enough to believe that copying doesn't happen in my
classes but I still prefer erring on the side of openness.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once the repo is set up, I give all the students access. This is a
little onerous since I have to type each of their GitHub usernames
under the collaborators section of the submissions repo but I only
have to do this once a semester.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then I teach the workflow. Assignments go into a file or folder under
their directory named ##_name where ## is the assignment number
(01,02,03, etc) and name is the assignment name. The student workflow
is:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git pull
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git add (sometimes)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git commit
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git push
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since every student is working in their own directory, things
basically work.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first issue that students come up with is when another student
pushes before another student. The second student merely has to do
another &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;git pull&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; before proceeding. This provides an easy
introduction to dealing with the distributed nature of git.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There will occasionally be other issues when students don't follow
procedure exactly so I'll have to fix the repo every now and then but
nothing too bad and each time is a opportunity to show the class:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can pretty much always restore and fix things once you commit
them.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the specifics to fix things.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There will be a few bumps in the road but after a few assignments the
sailing will be pretty smooth.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, the students are a little closer to being fully
fluent using git, they're hopefully using each others code as
resources but in a proper way and since the students are all using a
consistent assignment naming convention I can use simple scripts and
shell commands to do all sorts of processing on assignments.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's the end of phase two. The next step  brings us to small
projects using git.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIGCSE 2017 - a path to github part 1</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-1/</id>
    <updated>2017-03-16T09:11:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-03-16T09:11:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-1/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Both at and prior to SIGCSE 2017, I promised to write up the steps I
take to introduce and use revision control systems in my classes. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This series is not meant to be a git or &lt;a href="http://github.com"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; tutorial. There are
plenty of those already (two of which I've linked to below).  This is
about the process I use with my students to get them up to speed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As with any new tool, there will be some resistance but once git saves
them once, they get religion. There will also be some bumps in the
road but at the end of the day, the students will be using a valuable
and necessary tool. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was also surprised at the ancillary benefits I got as a teacher by
using GitHub in particular. I'll talk about that at the end of the
series.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Here's part one. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm doing this with git and GitHub but there's no reason why other
systems and hosts can't be used. I'd also recommend that any educator
or student sign up for the assorted &lt;a href="https://education.github.com/"&gt;discounts&lt;/a&gt; offered by GitHub.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've followed this basic idea multiple times and done it over the
course of a single semester, a year, and even two years. Regardless of
time frame, the idea is the same. Make each step simple and relevant
and introduce complexity and roadblocks a piece at a time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;Step 1 - code distribution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To start, I don't even talk about version control. We start with code
distribution. For years, I've looked for efficient ways of sharing
code with my classes. Both code developed in class and code for
assignments. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've tried things like NFS, Dropbox, online code repositories like the
files section of systems like Moodle or Blackboard.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At Stuy, we've always had efficiency problems with NFS and Dropbox has
multiple problems ranging from students not being able to install the
client on school machines to the problems of the network hit when a
room full of kids are syncing at the same time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Uploading to a CMS system was also problematic - I'm a command line
wonk and hate going through slow web page menus to navigate a
filesystem and upload files. I also had to remember to get the files
off of whatever machine I was working on in class and then transfer
them to the CMS when I had a free moment.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enter git. Now, of course, if you're going to use git in the classroom
you have to know it. There are plenty of resources out there. Online
courses, articles, videos, and tutorials. Here are a couple:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://try.github.io/"&gt;https://try.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0fKg7e37bQE"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0fKg7e37bQE&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also want to point out that I just use raw command line git along
with native GitHub. GitHub has rolled out &lt;a href="https://classroom.github.com/"&gt;GitHub Classroom&lt;/a&gt; which adds
a layer of support for educators. I don't use it because, as I said,
I'm an old school command line wonk and also because I figured out a
sequence that worked for me and my students before GitHub Classroom
existed. Were I starting now, I'd take some time to look at their
current offerings before jumping in.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2-1" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-2-1"&gt;Set up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-2-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Before starting, make sure you register your ssh keys. &lt;a href="https://help.github.com/articles/generating-a-new-ssh-key-and-adding-it-to-the-ssh-agent/"&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; help page
has more information. You'll want to register an ssh key from every
machine you use - home, work, laptop. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Now go over to GitHub and make a new repository. I usually name it
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;classcode&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;. &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;BEGINNER NOTE:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; when creating the repo, make sure to
check the "initialize this repository with a README" box. If you don't
you'll be given a set of instructions on how to set things up once you
click &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Create repository&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; but it's easier and easier to follow if
you start with an initialized repo with a README.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I make the repo public – it's code I'm distributing – nothing to
hide here. If you aren't comfortable with that, just make the repo
private. If you've registered as a teacher with GitHub, you can set up
an organization and you'll be able to set up free private repos within
it. The other downside here is that you'll have to individually give
each student access to the repo. That's a mild annoyance but it only
has to be done once.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2-2" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-2-2"&gt;Teacher use&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-2-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next, clone out the repo. &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;BEGINNER NOTE:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; Make sure you check out
the ssh version not the https version. Just make sure that when you
click the &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;clone&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; button, it says "Clone with SSH." If not, just
click the "Use SSH" link in the same box. Students will clone the
using https.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From the teacher point of view, you can just start using the repo. My
work flow is typically:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;git pull&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; at the start of class
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;write code throughout class
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;git add&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;git commit&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, and &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;git push&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; at the end of class
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I use a similar flow when I want to add files in my office or at home.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2-3" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-2-3"&gt;Student use&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-2-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From the student point of view, assuming a public repo, they just have to clone the repo and
at the beginning of every class or work session, do a &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;git
pull&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;. That's all there is to it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2-4" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-2-4"&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-2-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That's it. The kids are now using GitHub – they're probably looking
at and poking around on the web site as well as pulling files to their
machines. You can also, in class, show things like &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;git status&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;,
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;git log&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, and &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;git diff&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; to set the stage for step 2 of this
process and beyond.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since the students aren't adding, committing or pushing, you probably won't
get any errors. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The only problem that could reasonably occur is if a student places a
file in their local copy of the repo with the same name as something
they haven't pulled yet. This is pretty easy to address and provides a
nice stepping stone lesson to again, set the stage for more complex
operations.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I'm happy with this as a first step towards git using GitHub. It
provides a nice way of sharing class code while gently introducing the
students to the tool.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The next step  is having the students add files to a repo. That's the
next post in this series.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIGCSE 2017 - Recap</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-recap/</id>
    <updated>2017-03-14T08:19:18-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-03-14T08:19:18-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-recap/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a high school teacher, I was never able to attend SIGCSE, the
conference of the ACM's Special Interest Group on Computer Science
Education. Between the number of instructional days I would lose and
the cost, I could never justify going. Instead I looked over the
proceedings and read many of the papers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now that I'm at Hunter, I was finally able to attend. This year in
Seattle, the conference ran from Wednesday through Saturday. I was
part of a panel on "Tools we can't live without." Over the next few
weeks, I hope to blog about a number of things I thought and talked
with people about over the conference including:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The path I use to teach git and why GitHub a good teaching tool
(my talk).
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The relationship of different CS Ed stakeholders - teachers,
researchers, organizations, etc.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teaching at the high school level vs college - perceptions and
reality.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The challenges of tech tool adoption in schools.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's going on in K12 CS Certification.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maybe some other stuff.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today, some overall thoughts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;The good&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As with many conferences, the "hallway track" along with receptions
sponsored by &lt;a href="https://csnyc.org/our-work/cs4all"&gt;the CS4All consurtium&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://tealsk12.org"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://code.org"&gt;Code.org&lt;/a&gt; were terrific. I
was able to finally meet in person many people who I've only known
virtually and got to know many more as well. I left the conference
with a much larger address book and a long list of follow up
items. Being in Seattle, I also enjoyed being able to spend time with
people from &lt;a href="http://tealsk12.org"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://code.org"&gt;Code.org&lt;/a&gt;, two of the CS Ed groups working hard
to do some real good (yes - I do like and support these guys even
though I call them out on things I disagree with, but that's the
subject of another post). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I attended sessions on CS certification, teacher preparation,
assessments, POGIL based instruction to name a few. They ranged from
valuable to interesting and to be honest, a couple of "what were they
thinking" but the overall experience was very much worth the trip. I
also got to speak to a number of wonderful students at the
poster sessions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The keynotes are also well worth a read (sorry if you don't have ACM
digital library access). &lt;a href="http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3025045&amp;amp;CFID=738971273&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=22106692"&gt;Jeannette Wing&lt;/a&gt; talked about the importance of
probability and statistics in CS Ed, and aspects of  &lt;a href="http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3025047&amp;amp;CFID=738971273&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=22106692"&gt;Gail Chapman&lt;/a&gt;'s talk
"Inspire, Innovate, and Improve…" keynote and &lt;a href="http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3025046&amp;amp;CFID=738971273&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=22106692"&gt;Mitch Resnick&lt;/a&gt;'s
"Fulfilling Papert's Dream" both spoke to the educator inside me. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;The bad&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest downside to me was that I found very little value added in
a number of the paper sessions over just reading the papers. Part of
this is probably because of my own over-inflated expectations given the
number of years I've waited to attend. Part of it though, was the fact
that sessions were so tightly packed that I didn't have time to follow
up with presenters before having to run to the next
thing. Unfortunately, in some
cases, it was because the presenter merely
"read" the paper much as a professor sometimes just reads the slides
or the book to his class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;Other thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One paper presentation I very much liked was &lt;a href="http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3017701&amp;amp;CFID=738971273&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=22106692"&gt;Exam Wrappers: Not a
Silver Bullet&lt;/a&gt; presented by &lt;a href="https://michellecraig.github.io/"&gt;Michelle Craig&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://pages.cpsc.ucalgary.ca/~bdstephe/"&gt;Ben Stephenson&lt;/a&gt;. I
actually came in late since I was hustling over from the Code.org
lunch. The result was that I didn't actually know what "Exam Wrappers"
were until well after the talk when I ran into &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jkhuggins"&gt;Jim Huggins&lt;/a&gt;. Exam
wrappers, in short, are merely when you require the students fill out something
for some credit when picking up their exams. The funny thing is that
it's a strategy that high school teachers have used for years without
a special name and we already knew the good and bad of it without the
research but that's not what I want to get at here. What I loved about
the talk, besides the fact that Ben and Michelle are clearly strong
presenters is that this was a negative result that was being
presented. I also loved the fact that they didn't present their
research as gospel but rather pointed out the strengths and weaknesses
of their approach - they made a case to what and why we should pay
attention to and what should be taken with a grain of salt.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was a major breath of fresh air after being exposed to so much
education 'research' over the course of my life that the author or
presenter felt was just as strong as a mathematical proof rather than
an indication based on a specific experience or small set of
experiences.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also felt a little weird at times during the week when west coast people seemed
to know me. I know I'm a loud mouthed curmudgeon and I go on my
periodic ed rants but given the dearth of comments on this blog I was
really surprised to get as many as "great to meet you in person after
reading your blog" or "we know you and your work" all week. It was
weird and somewhat humbling.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, another highlight f`or me was that I got to catch up with
some of family.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/sigcse-seattle.jpg" alt="sigcse-seattle.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Already planning to submit something to present at SIGCSE 2018 in Baltimore.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="csed" label="csed"/>
    <category term="cseducation" label="cseducation"/>
    <category term="teaching-cs" label="teaching cs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIGCSE 2017</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017/</id>
    <updated>2017-03-07T16:18:41-05:00</updated>
    <published>2017-03-07T16:18:41-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
Tomorrow morning I fly out to Seattle for SIGCSE 2017. For those of
you not in the CS Education space, SIGCSE is the ACM (Association for
Computing Machinery) special interest group for computer science education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've wanted to go for years but have never been able. It's hard for a
high school teacher to miss a week in mid March, particularly in
places with a school calendar similar to New York. NY city schools are
already closed for a week in February and then Spring Break is right
around the corner. If you're teaching an AP course with the exam in
early May, losing a week in March is really not an option. Even if you
can take the time, you'll probably have to foot the bill out of
pocket. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now that I'm at Hunter, I've got more flexibility in terms of schedule
and attending is probably even more important given my current roles.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm looking forward to the talks and events but probably even more
looking forward to seeing old friends, meeting new ones and seeing
face to face friends that til now I've only known through the web.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On Saturday I'll be part of a panel (thanks &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cscheerleader"&gt;Ria&lt;/a&gt;) titled "Tools we
can't live without." I'll probably talk about the way I use git and
GitHub and how I get my students up to speed but there are lots of
tools I can talk about.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I plan to write up a series of posts on how I use GitHub (and how it
evolved from other versioning systems) as well as thoughts about other
tools I've used and some I've struggled with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're going to be at SIGCSE drop me a line, I'd love to connect.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cseducation" label="cseducation"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Whiteboard interviews</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/whiteboard-interviews/</id>
    <updated>2017-03-05T08:54:10-05:00</updated>
    <published>2017-03-05T08:54:10-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/whiteboard-interviews/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
A few days ago, I saw a &lt;a href="https://theoutline.com/post/1166/programmers-are-confessing-their-coding-sins-to-protest-a-broken-job-interview-process%0A"&gt;piece&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dhh"&gt;David Heinemeier Hansson's&lt;/a&gt; tweet on
whiteboard interviews:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Hello, my name is David. I would fail to write bubble sort on a whiteboard. I look code up on the internet all the time. I don't do riddles.&lt;/p&gt;— DHH (@dhh) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dhh/status/834146806594433025"&gt;February 21, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not a huge fan of the whiteboard interview but I think many of the
tweets missed the point. Most of the whiteboard interviews I'm
aware of involve algorithmic problem solving while the tweets, at
least the ones I've seen all refer to things that indeed one would
look up. Things like API calls - not things that whiteboard interviewers
typically care about.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tim Bray takes that point of view and shared his thoughts in a
&lt;a href="https://www.tbray.org/ongoing/When/201x/2017/03/04/Whiteboard-Interviews"&gt;recent blog post&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The idea behind the whiteboard interview isn't all bad. The
interviewer has an opportunity to see how the candidate thinks and
works through a problem and in an ideal situation the interviewer is,
at least to a point, coaching the candidate to help them through the
process. It seems to me that the problem lies more in the types of
questions asked and the skill of the interviewer rather than the idea
that candidates work through a problem live.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'd imagine that whiteboard interview success skew towards candidates
who work well in isolation in a short period of time, have a good
amount of exposure to these types of algorithmic problems. Also those
who have practiced and trained specifically for the interview will
have a huge edge. For people new to the process, it can be very
stressful. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once a candidate has accepted a position, they'll likely be working
with a team, with additional resources, and with time to solve
problems. This is a very different environment.  The whiteboard
interview, much like the SAT is thus something of an arbitrary
gatekeeper that a candidate must prepare for and conquer rather than a
skill that they must develop that will make them a more productive
team member.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This whole process tends to advantage those with the time and
background to prepare - this is one of the places where the argument
that whiteboard interview hurt diversity come from.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I could be totally wrong but I seem to recall that the whiteboard
interview, at least in terms of external visibility grew out of the
legendary Google puzzle interview questions. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A tech giant like Google can interview however they like and they'll
still get the talent. They go to the most selective institutions where
candidates have already been culled for success. If they then interview 100
candidates and 10 of them would be good fits, as long as a couple
thrive through the whiteboard interview process, they'll get their
engineer. They'll miss out on a lot of great talent but they can cast
such a large net they'll fill there seats with productive employees. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, smaller companies will certainly miss out on great
talent if they follow the same approach.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Is there a better way?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some companies pre-assign mini projects and then discuss that at the
interview. Pairing could also be a lower stress alternative to the
technical interview. Another option would be to look at a candidates
existing projects. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
An interesting question is "why do so many companies use the
whiteboard interview?" I can't say for certain but I wouldn't be
surprised if it was a simple as "because Google does it."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For over 100 years, Stuyvesant high school required students study
mechanical drawing (drafting). The relevance of the subject lessened over the
decades and what was taught in many ways has become a joke. A typical
class during the CAD parts of the class might be going over the
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;cylinder&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; command in CadKey. That's like spending a day studying
the &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;edit&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; menu in Microsoft Word in an English class. If you can't
tell, I'm not a fan. Drafting at Stuyvesant is the vestigial organ of
the course of study. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My point isn't to bash drafting at Stuy but rather that there have
been any number of schools that require their students take drafting
even though it doesn't prepare students for, nor lead them to anything
else in the schools curriculum (which now can be said for Stuy's
drafting requirement). I've spoken to teachers and principals at these
schools and we go back and forth as I press them for the reason for
the requirement and ultimately, they tell me that their school
requires drafting "because Stuyvesant does." 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why do so many small companies employ the whiteboard interview?
Because the big kids do. The trouble is that the big kids can get away
with it, the smaller players on the other hand, are hurting
themselves. Even the bigger players would be well served to 
try to come up with an interview process that better assesses fit
rather than a course filter that while it does pull in talent misses
talent as well.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="interviews" label="interviews"/>
    <category term="jobs" label="jobs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Using Emacs - 32 - C++</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-32-cpp/</id>
    <updated>2017-03-04T08:00:26-05:00</updated>
    <published>2017-03-04T08:00:26-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-32-cpp/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This video is specifically for my students or any students out there
who are starting with C++ and emacs. The videos also longer than usual, coming in
at a little over 20 minutes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The big difference is instead of building on my &lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/using-emacs"&gt;existing config&lt;/a&gt;, the
code at the bottom is a complete standalone configuration. It's all
pulled from the main config with one additional package.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
By taking the code at the bottom and putting in into a file named &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;init.el&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; in a
directory off of your home directory named &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;.emacs.d&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and run emacs,
it will install everything and you'll be good to go.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you've been following this series, the only new package is &lt;a href="https://github.com/leoliu/ggtags"&gt;ggtags&lt;/a&gt;
and the configuration code is:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; tags for code navigation&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;use-package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;ggtags&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:ensure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:config&lt;/span&gt; 
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;add-hook&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'c-mode-common-hook&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
	      &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;when&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;derived-mode-p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'c-mode&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'c++-mode&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'java-mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;ggtags-mode&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For people new to the series, the top section sets up the emacs
package manager. After that we install:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="left"&gt;

&lt;col class="left"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="left"&gt;Package&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="left"&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="left"&gt;which-key&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="left"&gt;brings up contextual key binding help&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="left"&gt;auto-complete&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="left"&gt;just as the name says&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="left"&gt;flycheck&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="left"&gt;in line, live syntax checking&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="left"&gt;yasnippet&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="left"&gt;snippets and expansion&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="left"&gt;ggtags&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="left"&gt;source code navigation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="left"&gt;color-theme&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="left"&gt;moe-theme&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="left"&gt;just because&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The video also show me using &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;counsel-ag&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; which is part of the
swiper/counsel package. You can check that out &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-6-swiper"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; as well as some
other packages I use like &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;smartparens&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;hungry-delete&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and
probably a few more.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can look at my complete configuration or the other videos for
details.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're an experienced C++ developer and use emacs, please share
tips, tricks, and suggestions. I haven't done serious C++ work in over
a decade and while I did professional development in C in a past life,
never in C++.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The packages used here are not C++ specific - I use them for Java,
Python, Clojure, and Javascript development as well.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Here's the configuration code:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; set up package sources&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;require&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'package&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;setq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;package-enable-at-startup&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;nil&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;add-to-list&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'package-archives&lt;/span&gt;
	     &lt;span class="o"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"melpa"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"https://melpa.org/packages/"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;package-initialize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; Bootstrap `use-package'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;unless&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;package-installed-p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'use-package&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;package-refresh-contents&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;package-install&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'use-package&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; small interface tweaks&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;setq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;inhibit-startup-message&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;tool-bar-mode&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;-1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;fset&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'yes-or-no-p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'y-or-n-p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;global-set-key&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;kbd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"&amp;lt;f5&amp;gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'revert-buffer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; bring up help for key bindings&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;use-package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;which-key&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:ensure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt; 
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:config&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;which-key-mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; Auto completion&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;use-package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;auto-complete&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:ensure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:init&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;progn&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;ac-config-default&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;global-auto-complete-mode&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; on the fly syntax checking&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;use-package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;flycheck&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:ensure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:init&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;global-flycheck-mode&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; snippets and snippet expansion&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;use-package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;yasnippet&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:ensure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:init&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;yas-global-mode&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; tags for code navigation&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;use-package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;ggtags&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:ensure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:config&lt;/span&gt; 
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;add-hook&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'c-mode-common-hook&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
	      &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;when&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;derived-mode-p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'c-mode&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'c++-mode&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'java-mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;ggtags-mode&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; Theme&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;use-package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;color-theme&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:ensure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;use-package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;moe-theme&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:ensure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;moe-light&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7SQmleA4EMo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Relevant links:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Video series overview page:
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs"&gt;http://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code:
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/using-emacs/tree/master"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/using-emacs/tree/master"&gt;https://github.com/zamansky/using-emacs/tree/master&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="emacs" label="emacs"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Using Emacs - 31 - elfeed part 3 - macros</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-31-elfeed-3/</id>
    <updated>2017-03-01T08:00:26-05:00</updated>
    <published>2017-03-01T08:00:26-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-31-elfeed-3/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In &lt;i&gt;part 2&lt;/i&gt; I talked about how I used &lt;a href="https://github.com/abo-abo/hydra"&gt;Hyrdas&lt;/a&gt; to quickly navigate through
elfeed tags. It was a nice step up but the fact that I still had to
manually edit my configuration code for every new tag to update the
hydra was a problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Basically, I had to somehow or other, take a list of all the active
tags and with it build a &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;defhydra&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; command that will then make my
Hydra.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, emacs, being a lisp, has macros. I'm not talking about
keyboard macros which I talked about in &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-15-macros/#.WLbj5t9idKQ"&gt;episode 15&lt;/a&gt; but rather &lt;a href="http://wiki.c2.com/?LispMacro"&gt;Lisp
style macros&lt;/a&gt;. Macros let you transform code and then execute the
transformed code. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The example I give in the video:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;defmacro&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;infix&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;op&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="o"&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;op&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;infix&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;; evaluates to 11&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This transforms the &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;3+8&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; into &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;(+ 3 8)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and then evaluates it to
be 11.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We can use this idea with our Hydra.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We can use the call &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;elfeed-db-get-all-tags&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; to get a list of all
the tags in our database. I decided that if I had an uppercase letter
in the tag, I'd use the lowercase version of that letter as my "hotkey"
and if it didn't, I'd just use the first letter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, given a tag list of:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;active&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;blogs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;cs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;eDucation&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;emacs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;local&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;misc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;sports&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;star&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;tech&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;unread&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;webcomics&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'd want a "hotkey" of &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;b&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; for logs and &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;d&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; for eDucation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The routine &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;z/hasCap&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; tests to see if a tag has a capital letter in
it and &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;z/get-hydra-option-key&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; returns the final "hotkey:"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;(defun z/hasCap (s) ""
       (let ((case-fold-search nil))
       (string-match-p "[[:upper:]]" s)
       ))


(defun z/get-hydra-option-key (s)
  "returns single upper case letter (converted to lower) or first"
  (interactive)
  (let ( (loc (z/hasCap s)))
    (if loc
	(downcase (substring s loc (+ loc 1)))
      (substring s 0 1)
    )))
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;mz/make-elfeed-cats&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; takes a list of tags and returns a list of
items where each item is in the form expected by the hydra definition:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"t"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;elfeed-search-set-filter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"@6-months-ago +tagname"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"tagname"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;mz/make-elfeed-cats&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;tags&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="s"&gt;"Returns a list of lists. Each one is line for the hydra configuratio in the form&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     (c function hint)"&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;interactive&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;mapcar&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;tag&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;let* &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
		   &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;tagstring&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;symbol-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;tag&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
		   &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;z/get-hydra-option-key&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;tagstring&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
		   &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	      &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;list &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;append &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;elfeed-search-set-filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;list &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;format&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"@6-months-ago +%s"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;tagstring&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;tagstring&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="p"&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
	  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;tags&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, here's our macro:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;defmacro&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;mz/make-elfeed-hydra&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="o"&gt;`&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;defhydra&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;mz/hydra-elfeed&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class="s"&gt;"filter"&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class="o"&gt;,@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;mz/make-elfeed-cats&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;elfeed-db-get-all-tags&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"*"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;elfeed-search-set-filter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"@6-months-ago +star"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"Starred"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"M"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;elfeed-toggle-star&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"Mark"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"A"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;elfeed-search-set-filter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"@6-months-ago"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"All"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"T"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;elfeed-search-set-filter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"@1-day-ago"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"Today"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"Q"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;bjm/elfeed-save-db-and-bury&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"Quit Elfeed"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:color&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;blue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"q"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;nil&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"quit"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:color&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;blue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The line that starts with &lt;b&gt;*,@*&lt;/b&gt; calls the routine that builds lines
of code for all the tags in the database and the macro leaves me with
the defhydra I need.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I then redefine the hydra every time I need it, just in case tags
changed:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;(defun mz/make-and-run-elfeed-hydra ()
  ""
  (interactive)
  (mz/make-elfeed-hydra)
  (mz/hydra-elfeed/body))
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
and bind &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;mz/make-and-run-elfeed-hydra&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; to j and J in my elfeed
keymap (this code goes in the bind section of my use-package elfeed
section):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"j"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;mz/make-and-run-elfeed-hydra&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"J"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;mz/make-and-run-elfeed-hydra&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As long as I remember to name my tags in a way that they don't
conflict with one another I can quickly navigate all around elfeed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Macros FTW!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Here's the video:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5zuSUbAHH8c" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Relevant links:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Video series overview page:
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs"&gt;http://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code:
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/using-emacs/tree/master"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/using-emacs/tree/master"&gt;https://github.com/zamansky/using-emacs/tree/master&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="emacs" label="emacs"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
