<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z (old posts, page 38)</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index-38.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-05-30T12:49:46Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-38.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-37.atom"/>
  <link rel="previous" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="current" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="prev-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-37.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-38.html"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>TEALS Time</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teals-time/</id>
    <updated>2018-04-18T10:14:13-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-04-18T10:14:13-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teals-time/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orge12efc4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orge12efc4"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orge12efc4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Everybody know's I'm the Statler and Waldorf of the CS Education
world.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://media1.giphy.com/media/nPxVvyTWo1aIU/giphy.gif" alt="giphy.gif"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've been known to be "prickly," which is a nice way of putting it and
I'm openly critical of many programs out there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One program, however, that I very much like is &lt;a href="https://www.tealsk12.org/"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt;. They've been
around since 2009 founded by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/KevinKWang"&gt;Kevin Wang&lt;/a&gt;, a former teacher. The basic
idea was to have tech professionals go to a school on the way to work
and team teach a CS class with one of the school's teachers. The tech
person would provide the CS expertise and the teacher would provide
the education chops. They'd both learn from each other and the
students from both of them. I didn't know what to make out of it when I
first heard about them and in general, I am  pretty skeptical about drop in
programs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After a couple of years, I started hearing from my former students. As
it turns out, a number of them had independently discovered TEALS and
become volunteers. They all talked about how rewarding the experience
was and how much the kids were getting that they wouldn't have gotten
otherwise.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was sold.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
TEALS has expanded considerably in the decade since they started. Now
they support multiple classes at multiple levels, have different
models from the original team teaching to a model where the volunteer
is more of a general tech / programming resource and the teacher is
more self sufficient.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most importantly, they provide quality training and materials to both
the teachers and the tech volunteers. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No drop in program can ever replace well prepared knowledgeable
teachers but in K12 CS very few of those teachers exist and it will
take us years to produce them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Until then, TEALS is one of the best programs to get CS education to
our kids and even when we do get there, their ability to connect
schools with volunteers and resources can't be understated.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're a tech professional and want to do some real good, volunteer
with TEALS - here's a link to more information:
&lt;a href="https://www.tealsk12.org/volunteers/"&gt;https://www.tealsk12.org/volunteers/&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cseducation" label="cseducation"/>
    <category term="programs" label="programs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Math For Math Teachers - watering down CS Ed before we even start</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/math-for-math-teachers/</id>
    <updated>2018-04-14T10:44:36-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-04-14T10:44:36-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/math-for-math-teachers/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org484cc57" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org484cc57"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org484cc57"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last Thursday I attended an event - the release of "Priming the
Computer Science Teacher Pump: Integrating CS Education into Schools
of Ed." &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; wrote about it &lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/2018/04/16/finding-a-home-for-cs-ed-in-schools-of-ed-priming-the-cs-teacher-pump-report-released/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. You can also download the
actual report &lt;a href="http://www.computingteacher.org/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I agree with a number of the challenges in creating CS teacher
preparation programs that were outlined in the report and I also agree
with the idea that a strong CS teacher preparation program should
prepare teachers to teach any (and in the case of the programs I
designed, create new) curriculum but I wanted to focus on one specific
item that was brought up last Thursday. The item deals with how much
CS content a K12 CS teacher actually needs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The speaker at the event - I forget which one pointed out that a K12
CS teacher doesn't need the same content knowledge as a full CS major
let alone graduate student. This is something I wholeheartedly agree
with. The speakers throughout the event also emphasized that CS
teachers need enough content knowledge to be "generalists" and teach
any reasonable CS experience. Again, a point on which I agree.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The point that concerned me - not in terms of the presenters intent
but rather in how I feel things will play out was when the presenter
said something to the affect (and I'm paraphrasing here):
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Math teachers don't need the same level of math content knowledge as
math majors. That's why we have "math for math teachers."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was immediately reminded of a conversation I had once with a
colleague. He was looking over a student's college transcript and
noticed a course "Math for Math Teachers" and thought, "I always
thought that it was just math!!!!!"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To many teachers, titles like "Calculus for Math Teachers" like
those similar courses "Calculus for Poets" or, the famous "Math
for Trees" are code for watered down math for non-math majors courses. From what I can
gather many of these courses are more Math Ed courses than Math but
offered through a school's Mathematics Department rather than through
an Ed school or department. They make sure that candidates  fill the "enough graduate
math credits" bucket. Everyone goes along with a nod and a wink and
life moves on. I want to emphasize that there's nothing inherently bad
with many of these courses - many are quite good but they're content
heavy education courses masquerading as pure content courses. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I managed to avoid doing any of that in my programs current design but
I did have to add a graduate algorithms class that I'm not entirely
happy with - I feel that it's requiring a level of depth that K12 CS
teachers will never  need. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Across all subject areas we should just acknowledge that K12 teachers
don't need a huge amount of graduate subject area credits. In my view,
teachers need depth a bit beyond the most advanced core course their
students will take and a good deal of breadth. Wouldn't it be nice if
we didn't have to play this song and dance this dance of creating
"special" subject courses for teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The real thing to watch out for is how this is already playing out in
computer science. Colleges are starting to offer classes for K12
computer science teachers. I've seen a few course descriptions and
syllabi and spoken to a number of people involved with some of these
classes. It's typical to see something like "Java Programming for CS
Teachers" as opposed to a "first in CS sequence programming course
using Java." Look  under the hood and you'll find it's really "APCS-A
for teachers" - not creating a generalist teacher but rather  taking
us right back to preparing them to ape specific curricula and
sequences.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We can do better. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why Strong K12 Teacher Certification is Important</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</id>
    <updated>2018-04-10T17:39:30-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-04-10T17:39:30-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/strong-teacher-certification/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org0780bf8" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0780bf8"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0780bf8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
About a week ago New York State's new regulation creating a &lt;a href="http://www.crainsnewyork.com/article/20180327/NEWS/180329893/new-york-will-finally-have-certified-computer-science-teachers"&gt;K12 CS
teacher certification&lt;/a&gt; went live. Just the other day I was honored to be
interviewed by  &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mflamm_reporter"&gt;Matt Flamm&lt;/a&gt; of Crain's New York in a &lt;a href="http://www.crainsnewyork.com/article/20180410/TECHNOLOGY/180419999/asked-answered-teacher-changed-jobs-to-push-for-new-york-states-new"&gt;follow up piece&lt;/a&gt;
about it. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Having K12 CS teacher certification is big and having quality programs
that lead to certification is &lt;b&gt;HUGE&lt;/b&gt;. In my view, it's a game changer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's Focus on high school, my wheelhouse.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From a course offerings point of view it's the wild west. I don't mean
this as a bad thing, it's just that there's a huge range of offerings
from AP to home brew, physical computing, game based, cyber security,
you name it, there's a curriculum. The long and short of this is that
schools need teachers to teach all of these experiences. Without a
strong certification pathway we're going to be stuck with the current
training based model where teachers are trained to deliver canned
curricula rather than truly teach. With strong teacher preparation
programs teachers will be prepared not only to deliver all the
existing curricula but, arguable more importantly design their own
learning experiences appropriate for the populations they work with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is important and alone would make having CS certification
worthwhile but to me the BIG win is that it creates a viable career
path. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
People say we'll never find enough CS teachers because the tech
industry pays so well. I've never believed that. We find math teachers
even though many could flee to finance and chem teachers in spite of
big pharma's call so why can't we find CS teachers? Because we've
never provided a path into the profession and a viable career track. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Certification means that over time schools will be able to build CS
teachers and the discipline will be treated as the other
subjects. Prior to certification, a CS teacher might be cut if a
school's math department downsized. With certification, the career
track for a CS teacher is the same as the track for any other teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It also means that young people starting out who are interested in
both teaching and computer science will have a way of getting into the
profession - something that has never before existed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Having CS certification alone won't woo a
plethora of current tech professionals into teaching but over time,
we'll start to have CS Ed majors or CS majors pursuing CS ED Masters
degrees and entering the profession. This won't happen in a press or
election cycle but it will happen.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This all hinges on quality prep programs. I think I've hit the sweet
spot with what I've designed at Hunter. The critical components are of
course content and pedagogy. Teacher candidates must have both
sufficient depth and breadth in the subject and all the pedagogical
content knowledge that comes along with it. I don't agree with the
common approach of taking a course to teach a course - that is, having
courses like "APCS - Principles for teachers" or "APCS - A for
teachers."  I want my teachers to be able to teach any reasonable
curriculum or design their own so we'll be rolling out courses that
examine the commonly offerd curricula but prepare teachers for a whole
lot more.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's been an exciting week in NY CS Ed and there's a lot more to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="certification" label="certification"/>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Using Emacs Episode 47 - Magit</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-47-magit/</id>
    <updated>2018-04-07T09:05:36-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-04-07T09:05:36-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-47-magit/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org0403a9e" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0403a9e"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0403a9e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've been holding off on doing a &lt;a href="https://magit.vc/"&gt;Magit&lt;/a&gt; video for a while. Mostly
because I wasn't using it exclusively and also because there are
already a number of good Magit videos and resources out there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What changed? Along with the new version of Magin, Jonas Bernoulli
wrote up &lt;a href="https://emacsair.me/2017/09/01/magit-walk-through/"&gt;a walkthrough of the Magit interface&lt;/a&gt;. For whatever reason,
it all finally clicked. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In spite of what the documentation says, Magit &lt;b&gt;is not&lt;/b&gt; an interface
for git. Magit is a &lt;b&gt;command and control&lt;/b&gt; center for git. You can
launch it just to execute some git commands but you can also leave it
up and running in an Emacs window or frame as a constant project
overview.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Wow. Mind blown!!!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you use Emacs for Deveopment, you &lt;b&gt;have to&lt;/b&gt; use Magit. If you don't
use Emacs, you can load it on the side for Magit. If you're not a
developer, learn to code so you can use Magit!!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I tried to do justice to the package in the video. Magit along with &lt;a href="https://orgmode.org/"&gt;Org
Mode&lt;/a&gt; are arguably Emacs killer apps - enough in and of themselves to
justify using Emacs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Check out the video:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1IYsiHXR620" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="editing" label="editing"/>
    <category term="emacs" label="emacs"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Competitions and Hackathons</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hs-competitions/</id>
    <updated>2018-04-06T17:22:15-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-04-06T17:22:15-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hs-competitions/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org36b3fdf" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org36b3fdf"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org36b3fdf"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today's the last day of spring break. After the weekend it's back to
the grind. It really hasn't been much of a spring break. The rain and
the snow made for very little spring and between working on the Hunter
/ CUNY2X Internship program and reviewing applications for my Hunter
Daedalus CS Honors program there has been very little break.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today was no exception - I spent much of the day working but I did
take a few hours to head over to Cornell Tech on Roosevelt
Island. Why? To check out the &lt;a href="https://www.cs.cornell.edu/events/cornell-high-school-programming-contest"&gt;Cornell High School Progrmaming
Contest&lt;/a&gt; - first time in NYC.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was invited by my friend and organizer &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/diane_levitt"&gt;Diane Levitt&lt;/a&gt;. I only stayed
for an hour or so but it was shaping up to be a great event. It looked
like around a hundred kids from maybe a dozen or so schools and it was
run simultaneously with high schoolers on the Ithaca campus where the
competition has been running for a few years. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The format was similar to other high school programming competitions
I've been to. Teams of two or three sharing a single computer to solve
a number of programming problems that varied in difficulty. You can
check out a few "warm up" problems on the competition &lt;a href="https://www.cs.cornell.edu/events/cornell-high-school-programming-contest"&gt;site&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The competition reminded me of the &lt;a href="https://www.sjcny.edu/long-island/academics/programs-departments/mathematics-and-computer-science/programming-competition"&gt;St. Joseph's High School
Programming Competition&lt;/a&gt; held every spring but in NYC so more
convenient for city dwellers. I went to the St. Joseph's competition a
few times and I'm a big fan. I particularly like the awards luncheon
after the competition. If I were to make one suggestion to the
organizers there it would be to mix the seating at the luncheon so
that kids get to sit with and spend time with kids from different
schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These competitions contrast nicely with hackathons like &lt;a href="http://stuyhacks.com/%0A"&gt;StuyHacks&lt;/a&gt;
for which I acted as a judge a couple of months ago. Competitions are, well,
competitive. Hackathons can be but don't have to be. Competitions are
about solving problems, hackathons, building things. Each can speak to
a different kind of student. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Both competitions and hackathons have problems as well. On the competition
side we have:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schools with more developed CS programs dominate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A single strong student can carry a team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some kids don't like or do well in the competitive environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And on the hackathon side:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;24 hours of straight work is just a bad idea and a bad thing to
encourage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big advantage to teams that bring prefab code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big advantage to kids with experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Both types of events are great opportunities for young
programmers. They're celebrate academic work, bring tech kids together
as a community and when done right are
something of a CS party. Neither type of event speaks to all kids so
it's great to have both competitions and hackathons to go along with
other types of events available for our kids. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another thing I love abut the Cornell and St, Joseph's competitions
along with StuyHacks is that they're open to all schools and hence all
students. There's room for the novice and also the expert and you
don't have to be in a particular school or program to participate.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are other events beyond these three. There are online
competitions like &lt;a href="http://www.usaco.org/"&gt;the USACO&lt;/a&gt;, competitions on HackerRank and Topcoder,
&lt;a href="http://halite.io"&gt;Halite&lt;/a&gt; along with it's hackathon which is great but specialized and in
person ones that are farther away like the &lt;a href="http://pclassic.org/%0A"&gt;PClassic&lt;/a&gt; in Philidelphia
and Rowan's &lt;a href="http://elvis.rowan.edu/rupc/%0A"&gt;HS programming competition&lt;/a&gt; in New Jersey but it's great to
see great local opportunities like these emerging and hopefully
running for years to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="competitions" label="competitions"/>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="events" label="events"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tools and Complexity</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tools-and-complexity/</id>
    <updated>2018-04-05T18:55:21-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-04-05T18:55:21-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tools-and-complexity/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org10a8533" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org10a8533"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org10a8533"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt; wrote about &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/04/thoughts-on-where-cs-education-tools.html"&gt;CS education tools&lt;/a&gt; earlier today. I've
also been meaning to write on the topic but from a different point of
view.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I do my best to keep up with the latest and greatest in the CS world
both on the academic side as well as the professional one. That's not
really possible, but I do my best. When I have a small project to work
on I'll some times use it as an excuse to play with some recent
technology. Over December, I wanted to write an application viewer to
use for company / student internship matching. I started by looking at
&lt;a href="https://reactjs.org/"&gt;React&lt;/a&gt; but ended up using &lt;a href="https://vuejs.org/"&gt;Vue.js&lt;/a&gt; which I liked much more for a variety
of reasons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The viewer served it's purpose but I think it can be turned into a
much more comprehensive student / employer internship platform. I
tried to steal a few minutes over this past week's spring break to
start a rewrite using another toolset, Clojure, Clojurescript and
Reagent. I'm really liking the Clojure stack and using
Emacs and Cider for the IDE is really blowing me away. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I've noticed is that for every new language of framework you also
have to learn a whole set of ancillary tools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It didn't used to be that way. Back in the day, things were much
simpler. I remembering doing work at Goldman Sachs, it was as simple
as typing something on the command line like &lt;code&gt;cc file1.c file2.c
file3.c&lt;/code&gt;. I of course had to be cutting edge and use fancy modern
tools like &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/make/"&gt;Make&lt;/a&gt;. What's more, the tools I used in industry were very
similar to what I used in college. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We now live in very different times.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you go to the getting started guides for React or Vue it's pretty easy to
get hello world up and running but beyond that you start to fall in to
the Javascript tooling hole. To start you need either &lt;b&gt;npm&lt;/b&gt; or &lt;b&gt;yarn&lt;/b&gt;
just to manage packages and dependencies. Then you need a build system
or bundler like &lt;b&gt;webpack&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;browserify&lt;/b&gt;, or &lt;b&gt;parcel&lt;/b&gt; and that's not even
considering older options like &lt;b&gt;gulp&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;grunt&lt;/b&gt; and ancillary tools
like &lt;b&gt;babel&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A typical React or Vue project is going to need a &lt;a href="https://github.com/krasimir/react-webpack-starter/blob/master/package.json"&gt;project.json&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/krasimir/react-webpack-starter/blob/master/webpack.config.js"&gt;webpack.config.js&lt;/a&gt; file and sometimes some other files as well. Check
out the links. They're from a simple project template I found
online. Far from simple.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I was playing with Vue.js a couple of months ago, I ended up
using Webpack to convert the source code into the final JS, take care
of live-reloading, and in general manage the project. I still have no
idea how most of it works. I don't know if it's just me but I'm very
uncomfortable relying on tools that I really don't fully understand to
build my systems. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Clojure world is little better with Leiningen and Boot. If you
don't believe me, try to make heads or tails of &lt;a href="https://github.com/bhauman/figwheel-template/blob/master/src/leiningen/new/figwheel/project.clj"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While it's true that as a professional you'll likely use one set of
tools on a day to day basis and you'll eventually get to know them
that doesn't mean it's not a good idea to prepare kids for what's to
come.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
On the K12 side we have drag and drop languages, specialized learning
IDEs like BlueJ, simple cut down IDEs like Dr Racket and completely
online environments like repl.it. All great starter tools that
insulate beginners from the complexities to come. College's
might get closer to the "real world" but just a tad. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Don't get me wrong, I like many of the tools used in K12
classes and there's far too much complexity in the professional world to
throw at beginners. If we look at a student's entire school
career, classes are already so packed with material it would be hard to
really prepare kids for the real world within their classes. You could
take that tried and true teacher / professor technique of just
requiring it and having the kids figure it out on their own but that's
really just downright abusive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't have an answer for this one. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have my kids use tools like Git and GitHub early along with using
testing frameworks and external libraries. I also try to move my
students to a general purpose programmable platform like Emacs or
Vim. I think these are sound practices but students will still have a
big learning curve when they finally get to industry. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I really would love it to see the tooling become simpler and
documentation better. &lt;a href="https://github.com/parcel-bundler/parcel"&gt;Parcel&lt;/a&gt;, a Javascript bundler is one of the newer
kids on the block and is much simpler and cleaner than alternatives
like Webpack. The new version of Clojure has it's own command line
tool which is also simpler than the alternatives. Maybe we are already
moving in the right direction and this entire rant will become moot in a couple of years.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="csed" label="csed"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Passover April 1 And Indiana Jones</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/passover-april-1-and-indiana-jones/</id>
    <updated>2018-04-01T09:17:21-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-04-01T09:17:21-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/passover-april-1-and-indiana-jones/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org53ebf73" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org53ebf73"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org53ebf73"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've never done much in terms of the April Fools thing but frequently
enjoy other peoples shenanigans.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For those of you similarly inclined I share my son Natan's take on
that Passover staple, Echad Mi Yodea.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy: &lt;a href="http://seccorecit.blogspot.com/2018/04/a-historically-informed-echad-mi-yodea.html"&gt;A Historically Informed Echad Mi Yodea&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Do It The Dumb Way</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/do-it-the-dumb-way/</id>
    <updated>2018-03-30T08:24:09-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-03-30T08:24:09-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/do-it-the-dumb-way/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org803d762" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org803d762"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org803d762"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There's so much to like in the shape drawing lessons I talked about
in my &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/refactoring/"&gt;refactoring&lt;/a&gt; post that I thought I'd share a little more here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It can be argued that the most important things for a program to do is work. The
most clever, elegant, creative program is worthless if it doesn't
produce the desired result. All too often, beginners and hot shot beginners in particular try to
be too clever too early and get themselves into trouble. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When doing the shape drawing lessons the first couple of shape are
pretty easy
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class="example"&gt;

| ****            |    | *               |
| ****            |    | **              |
| ****            |    | ***             |
| ****            |    | ****            |
| ****            |    |                 |
|                 |    |                 |
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
but things get more interesting with the right justified triangle:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class="example"&gt;
----*       *
---**      **
--***     ***
-****    ****
*****   *****

&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For this triangle, students want to come up with the formula for the
number of spaces. They usually figure out something like this with
&lt;code&gt;h-i-1&lt;/code&gt; spaces and &lt;code&gt;i+1&lt;/code&gt; stars:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tri2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;""&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"-"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"*"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The formulas become harder to figure out as the shapes become more
complex and sometimes students get stymied.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The truth is that while they're struggling to find the perfect
solution, it's sometimes better to do it the dumb way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Consider drawing a trapezoid like this example of height 5 and
starting width 12:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class="example"&gt;
************
 **********
  ********
   ******
    ****
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A student could come up with the "formulas" for spaces and stars but
sometimes there's a more straightforward way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Consider the number of spaces on each line on the left hand side of
the shape. First line is 0 then 1, 2 etc. Why not start a variable
&lt;code&gt;spaces&lt;/code&gt; at 0 and increment it on each loop iteration.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For the number of stars, it's starting at the width and being reduced
by 2 each time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This leads to a solution similar to this (using the line routine from
the earlier refactoring post):
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;trap&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;""&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;spaces&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;stars&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;spaces&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;" "&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;lines&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;stars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"*"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;spaces&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;spaces&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;stars&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;stars&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This solution is simple to construct, simple to understand, and quite
frankly, hard to get wrong.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It can also lead a student to discovering a pattern or "formula" such
as what was used to solve the earlier problems. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This might seem to some as a cheap way out, the dumb approach -
creating extra variables and have them count along the way but I
don't. There's nothing wrong with simple and straightforward. Yes, you
could come up with an elegant formula but the bottom line is you need
something to count 0,1,2,3… so create a variable to do it. You need
something to count 12,10,8,… create one for that as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
 Now, I'm not advocating writing 100 if statements rather than a loop
but I think you get the idea.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The best solution is one that works and Sometimes the "dumb" approach is the best approach.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="pedagogy" label="pedagogy"/>
    <category term="software-engineering" label="software engineering"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ethics In CS Education</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-in-cs/</id>
    <updated>2018-03-25T16:59:36-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-03-25T16:59:36-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-in-cs/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org79446d6" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org79446d6"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org79446d6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've been meaning to write about ethics in CS education for a
while. Probably since I saw &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/02/12/business/computer-science-ethics-courses.html?smid=fb-share"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; in the NY Times but got sidetracked.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was reminded when I saw this tweet by Hadi the other day:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;This message is bigger than Facebook. Computer science faces an ethics crisis. That’s why &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/codeorg?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@codeorg&lt;/a&gt; covers ethics and digital citizenship in our computer science courses. (And we’re thankful that most of the largest tech companies support us) &lt;a href="https://t.co/roSkAzANQM"&gt;https://t.co/roSkAzANQM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Hadi Partovi (@hadip) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hadip/status/977673429485731840?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;March 24, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think we can all agree that bringing ethics and digital citizenship
and, frankly, citizenship in general to our students is important. What I wonder is
what approaches will lead to meaningful results and what methods will
lead us to checking off the "covered that" box.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm skeptical of throwing an ethics course into the curriculum as some
places seem to be doing. A class might be required, might fulfill an
elective requirement or it might just be an extra course. If it's
required, what does it replace or are you just going to add more to
the student load. If it fulfills an elective credit, will it be
perceived as "the easy course" as opposed to say, theory and if it's
just an extra course, who's going to take it? Will it just become
preaching to the choir. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Better is what Hadi mentioned in his tweet - embed ethics throughout
all of your courses and while I think this type of embedding is
important and I'd argue necessary, I'm still betting it won't be
enough to make a difference.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When teaching a course, teachers cover the curriculum but when you
drill down to where they focus their time, it comes down to:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what they think is important for the kids to know.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what they think the kids will need for that high stakes exam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If a teacher feels embedding ethical concerns is important they'll
spend time on it, if not, it will be lip service. Even if it's on the
high stakes exam, unless the teacher really believes that this is
important it will just be teaching to the test.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'd argue that it has to go even further since teachers can only do so
much. How many schools have honor codes and how many of us know
graduates from those schools who exhibit less than ethical behaviour.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So what do we do?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, of course we do have to embed ethical concerns across the
curriculum. Teachers should be armed with both the materials and time
needed to address ethical concerns but beyond that, we need teachers
for which ethical CS is important.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My friend &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ed_saber"&gt;Saber Khan&lt;/a&gt; has been facilitating a monthly #ethicalCS
twitter chat for close to a year now. I don't take part in too many
twitter chats but do recognize that they're important in raising both
awareness and community. I've also seen ethical CS issues more
frequently appear as conference sessions and professional development.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The next big step is to start at the beginning - pre service teacher
training and in my opinion, not with a course but rather embedding
ethical issues throughout teacher preparation. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If we want to crack this nut it can't just be from curriculum and from
the choir. Pre service CS teacher training is in it's infancy and has
not yet really found its form.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Much to my chagrin, a lot of CS Ed has gone the way of other Ed: Math
Ed, Science Ed, etc. and not in a good way. Let's see if we can make
sure that pre service CS teacher preparation develops to attract and
create great teachers for which ethical CS is part of their core. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="ethicalcs" label="ethicalCS"/>
    <category term="preservicexs" label="preservicexs"/>
    <category term="teachers" label="teachers"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sigcse2018 Proof</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-proof/</id>
    <updated>2018-03-23T16:24:21-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-03-23T16:24:21-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-proof/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd0b68e2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd0b68e2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd0b68e2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up from SIGCSE2018 is &lt;a href="https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3159609"&gt;Connect the Dots to Prove It&lt;/a&gt; presented by
Mark McCartin-Lim. This paper was presented during the same papers
session as &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-theory"&gt;MacCormick&lt;/a&gt; paper I wrote up previously and my reaction to
this one was similar to my reaction to MacCormick's.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My reaction to MacCormick was - "This is awesome but while he's talking
about redesigning existing theory courses, I think we can get a lot of
mileage out of bringing these ideas into lower level CS courses."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I felt similarly about this paper.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The premise is simple - proof is hard and teaching proof is
hard. Students don't know how to begin, what's allowed, what's not
allowed, what's sufficient etc. McCartin-Lim and his team developed a
software tool to present proof as a puzzle and to provide students
with necessary support. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The tool allows students to interactively construct a graph of their
proof. The graph helps students visualize the proof and the
relationships between the assumptions and assertions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's an example:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/sigcse2018-proof1.png" alt="sigcse2018-proof1.png" width="500px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And a more complex one:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/sigcse2018-proof2.png" alt="sigcse2018-proof2.png" width="500px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My immediate thought was that this should be reskinned as a high
school product and rolled out in Geometry classes. I've written before
about the fact that proof is &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/standards-who-for/"&gt;rarely taught&lt;/a&gt; and rarely taught well even
though it's supposed to be the star topic between Algebra and Trigonometry. A tool like this could
probably help. This made me think further of the disconnect between
K12 and higher education. McCartin-Lim talked about students having
difficulty learning proof but lost in the conversation is that
students should start building there proof related foundations in high
school and supporting them in those early years can go a long way to
alleviate problems that only surface at the college level.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
