<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xmlns:fh="http://purl.org/syndication/history/1.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z (old posts, page 8)</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index-8.atom</id>
  <updated>2016-05-23T17:14:41Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-8.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-7.atom"/>
  <link rel="previous" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-9.atom"/>
  <link rel="current" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="next-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-9.atom"/>
  <link rel="prev-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-7.atom"/>
  <fh:archive/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-8.html"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Hacking Sessions Resume</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-05-hacking-sessions-7.md/</id>
    <updated>2014-01-05T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2014-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-05-hacking-sessions-7.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2014-01-05-hacking-sessions-7/hackers.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to school last Thursday after almost two week off. Twenty four
hours later - Snow Day. I know this sounds a bit hokey, but I really
would have rather had school. I love a good snow day as much as the
next guy, but after a big vacation, I was really ready to get back to
work with the kids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday, hacking sessions were set to resume. Being in Manhattan,
getting around was pretty easy but we've got hackers from all over the
city from Staten Island to the Bronx. Needless to say, some boroughs
were easier to get around in than others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we were a small group - we were down two instructors and a TA but
Batya and Zach were in from college and helping out so instructors
actually outnumbered students!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did we do? Since the hackers are just starting on their projects,
this was a great opportunity to work one on one with them. Two of us
went over Javascript and SVG as an alternative to the HTML Canvas,
Zach worked with a couple of people on a Markov chain text generator
and so on. Even though the turn out was low, I'm really glad we got
back to business. Weather permitting, we should be back at full
capacity this coming Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's finally time to start talking to them about git.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Plans for the New Year</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-01-new-year.md/</id>
    <updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2014-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-01-new-year.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've never been one for New Year's resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I'm working on something specific, I might set a goal to finish it,
but the idea of goals for a year never struck a chord with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's one of the things that I find absurd about the current teacher
rating system - I have to decided on my three goals for the year. I
always have one goal with respect to my profession - to be better at
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any event, even though I don't have specific overall goals for me,
there are some projects that I plan on pouring myself into this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year closed with a lot of national hype over CS Ed. What remains
to be seen is where we go with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll continue to try to work within the system - try to convince the
new administration that supporting and replicating Stuy CS is something worth
doing but I've been burnt enough to know not to
put all my eggs in that basket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, I'm hoping to put a lot of time into
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-01-new-year.md/http//cstuy.org"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;. We're just about a year old and it's been a
slow road but we're making some real progress - and this is just as a
grass roots organization - it's just us and the StuyCS Alumni family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what are the plans?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;More Hacking Sessions&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started Hacking Sessions in October. Twenty New York City public
high school students getting together to geek out and do CS every
Saturday. We're off to a great start but there's a lot of work to be
done. We'd love to get more students involved in the coming semester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;Start Summer Hackers&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the big effort. A summer program. Since we designed and
implemented Google CAPE NYC back in 2010, I've known the effect you
can have with a strong summer program taught by master teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've got the teachers and the program, but it's still going to take a
lot of work.We have yet to finalize on a location (we have a tentative
offer for space but I'm hesitant to say anything until it's more
concrete) and we have to do it early enough so that we can get to the
students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we can get CSTUY's Summmer Hackers off the ground I'm pretty sure
we can use that to launch a community of both hackers and teachers
just as we've done at Stuy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;Get more people involved&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said that so far CSTUY has been grass roots only. In order for us to
succeed, we'll need to grow our community. The hope and plan is to get
the NY Tech community behind our efforts. I'm hoping that when they see
us taking our proven programs out from Stuy to the greater public
they'll come out in droves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least that's the hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, those are my goals for the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should be exiting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A New Year and a New look</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-12-30-new-year-new-look.md/</id>
    <updated>2013-12-30T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2013-12-30T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-12-30-new-year-new-look.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;We're practically at the close of 2013 and it's high time I wished
everyone wonderful things for the year to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also time for a new look to this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why the rewrite? Partly because I was tired of the look, but mostly
because, when I put it together, it was the first time I used that
toolset and was just figuring things out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm still no expert, but I thought it was time to clean things up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's still a &lt;a href="http://jekyllrb.com/"&gt;jekyll&lt;/a&gt; generated blog hosted on
&lt;a href="http://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub pages&lt;/a&gt; but instead of using
&lt;a href="http://getbootstrap.com/"&gt;Twitter Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; I decided to use
&lt;a href="http://weice.in/ivory/"&gt;Ivory&lt;/a&gt;. It's much smaller and only does the
basics. Even the menu I'm using was the result of some online
searching for CSS stuff. I figure that this way, I'll actually learn
more about styling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should be an interesting year. I've got a number of projects that
I'm working on. Some within Stuyvesant, some revolving around &lt;a href="https://cstuy.org"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;, and some I can't talk about right now. Hopefully I'll
be able to write about some of them in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm also hoping to write more this year. I only posted 30 times this
past year. On the other hand, that's up from 18 times in 2012 and only
4 posts in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to updates on CSTUY, pedagogical posts and the occasional
rant, I'd like to do a series on how I use tools like the Linux shell
and Emacs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll see how things go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I wish you all a happy and healthy new year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bucket Sorting</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-27-bucket-sorts.md/</id>
    <updated>2013-11-27T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2013-11-27T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-27-bucket-sorts.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In spite of the Java based annoyances I mentioned last time, I decided
to go ahead and do Radix sort with my AP students. I usually don't
cover it in AP Computer Science, but I like getting the kids to think
about using arrays as buckets as it's a new way of thinking for them and it does give a non-trivial application that combines ararys and ArrayLists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a nice little algorithm. You start with an Array of integers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/radix/array1.png" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/radix/array1.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, place them in buckets based on the least significant digit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/radix/buckets1.png" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/radix/buckets1.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then copy the numbers from the buckets back into the original array, keeping the order of the buckets (0-&amp;gt;9).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/radix/array2.png" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/radix/array2.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then repeat this process on the 2nd least significant digit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/radix/step2.png" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/radix/step2.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so on until we're done:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/radix/step3.png" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/radix/step3.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's a nice algorithm to teach on a number of fronts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we get to combine Arrays and ArrayLists. Since we'll always
have 10 digits, the "bucket list" is of fixed size, while the
individual bucket lengths vary. This leads to the Array of ArrayLists
and we've got a single platform to compare and contrast the two. Which
is better when and why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The algorithm itself is also worth talking about. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's relatively simple - we did it by hand before implementing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's got some history worth discussing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are a number of other questions we can approach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can we deal with negatives?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What about strings?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will it always work (what about floating point numbers).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we can talk about speed -- they're testing that now and we'll discuss our Radix sort vs the built in Arrays.sort() on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll do the n^2 and nLog(n) sorts a little later, but I think this
was a detour well worth taking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="apcs" label="apcs"/>
    <category term="pedagogy" label="pedagogy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Teaching Languages</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-23-teaching-languages.md/</id>
    <updated>2013-11-23T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2013-11-23T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-23-teaching-languages.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Java's never been my favorite language either for using or for
teaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a programmer, after starting with languages like Fortran
and Pascal, I really cut my teeth with C. More recently, Python has
been my go to language to get real work done. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a teaching point of view most languages have good points
and bad ones. When the AP class went from Pascal to C++ I lamented
losing the simplicity and the low cost of entry. On the other hand,
C++ gave us objects (not that I'm a big OOP guy), separate files, the
ability to use tons of real world libraries and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving to Java simplified things in a number of ways but removed
memory management. If we didn't teach that along with the stack frame
in our Systems class, I think our kids would be missing something very
important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of some of Java's limitations as a teaching language over the past couple of days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As posted earlier, I had my AP students create their own class to
mimic the Java ArrayList. Before introducing the ArrayList in Java, I
wanted to introduce generics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class myList&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; {
  T[] data;
  public myList() {
    data = new T[10];
  }
  // much more not shown 
}
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Turns out, you can no longer do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After doing some searching, there does appear to be a way to get this
effect but it was certainly not something I wanted to do with my
classes. I was looking for something more pedagogically sound - an
easy way to show the concept and a way to springboard to an ArrayList.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh well...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we finished ArrayLists and I was mapping out a plan for Monday. I
thought Radix sort would be cool -- we already introduced using an
array to tally votes when we did the mode. This seemed to be a natural
extension. It would combine Arrays and ArrayLists and illustrate when each is appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First the kids would set up an array of 10 buckets, each being an ArrayList:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class Buckets {
  ArrayList&amp;lt;Integer&amp;gt;[] buckets;
  public Buckets() {
    buckets = new ArrayList&amp;lt;Integer&amp;gt;[10];
    for (int i=0;i&amp;lt;10;i++)
      buckets[i] = new ArrayList&amp;lt;Integer&amp;gt;();
  }
  // much more not shown 
}
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Java type safety once again reared its ugly head. OK,
maybe not ugly to a programmer, but ugly to a teacher. You can't do
it. You can do it with an old school ArrayList without the generic:
&lt;code&gt;ArrayList[] buckets = new Arraylist[10];&lt;/code&gt; but of course, this
leaves you open to type mismatch problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, Java provides a convoluted workaround that might be fine
for a professional programmer, but for a student, it would be nuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might go ahead with the Radix sort lesson anyway, we'll see, but it
would be nice if I could teach this level of course without having to
fight the implementation language.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="apcs" label="apcs"/>
    <category term="pedagogy" label="pedagogy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Build it first</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-19-build_it.md/</id>
    <updated>2013-11-19T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2013-11-19T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-19-build_it.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The subtitle of this post is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and why my students are going to hate me tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When my good friend Gerry Seidman talks to my classes, he frequently
says "never use a data structure or algorithm you couldn't build yourself."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn't mean that you have to write everything from scratch, just
that you should have some knowledge as to what's going on under the
hood. I find that all too often young programmers just rely on APIs
and libraries and really don't know how their computers and programs are working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it's never too early to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've been spending time talking about arrays recently. Now, most of
my students have some exposure to Python and so we started talking
about the flexibility and power of the Python list vs the limited
facilities of the Java array.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to solve the problem and make Java easier to work with? Let's
write our own list class. We started simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class myList {
  private int[] data;
  private int numItems;

  public myList() {
    data = new int[5];
    numItems = 0;
  }

  // append to the end of the list
  public add(int d) {
    if (numItems &amp;gt;= data.length) {
      tmp = new int[data.length+data.length/2];
      for (int i=0;i&amp;lt;numItems;i++)
        tmp[i]=data[i];
      data = tmp;
    }

    data[numItems]=d;
    numItems = numItems + 1;
  }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;from there we added functionality such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inserting in arbitrary locations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Removing items from the list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Searching for an item&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting the item at a location to a value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course we were also able to talk about things like refactoring
out growing the array into a private method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And tonight the classes are changing the internal array from int[] to String[].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, what we're building is an ArrayList. Tomorrow we'll reveal
that little fact and of course the classes will all hate me, but then,
they'll really understand what's going on under the hood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="csed" label="csed"/>
    <category term="pedagogy" label="pedagogy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hacking Sessions - putting it all together</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-16-hacking-sessions-5.md/</id>
    <updated>2013-11-16T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2013-11-16T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-16-hacking-sessions-5.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/pairprog.jpg" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/pairprog.jpg" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Week 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, I lamented over the difficulties with only meeting once a
week. We went over a log of new material last week and I was happy
when today rolled around and the hackers would be able to start
putting things together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When writing a web app, you've got to know about all sorts of things -
for us it's HTML, CSS, Python, and the microframework,
&lt;a href="http://flask.pocoo.org"&gt;flask&lt;/a&gt;. That's quite a bit, particularly when
working with a group with a wide range of experience coming in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what did we do? We put together two partial web sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One had all the Python code, but was missing the HTML and CSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other had the HTML and CSS, but the Python logic was all missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was our hacker's mission to fill in the missing pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We liked the setup for a few reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each Hacker came in with different strengths and weaknesses. With this project, they could start with something they knew (picking the part with the "hard part" filled in) and then moving to a more challenging piece.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By looking at the other half of the project, they could find sample code for the pieces they were working on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hackers also had last weeks code as a reference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also introduced the hackers to pair programming - something I love
from a pedagogical point of view - but more on that in another post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I think the day went very well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also gave out our first assignment -- over the weeks, the hackers
will finish up their projects - next week we'll demo and give prizes
for the best.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hacking Sessions Week 4 - The challenges of once a week</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-11-hacking-sessions-4.md/</id>
    <updated>2013-11-11T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2013-11-11T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-11-hacking-sessions-4.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hacking-sessions-4/week4-tri.jpg" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hacking-sessions-4/week4-tri.jpg" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We just finished week 4 of CSTUY's Hacking Sessions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm really happy with how our hackers are doing - they're a great
bunch and even if they don't realize it yet, are making great progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, as an instructor and program designer I'm noticing the
differences between a once a week program and having a class every day
(note - I'm not the sole designer or instructor. I have a great team -
JonAlf, Sam, and Topher are three of the best teachers I've had the
privilege of working with - this post, however, is based on my
observations).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Once a week vs every day&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a big adjustment. In class, we only have 40 minutes but we get
it 5 days a week. Here we have 3 hours, but only on a single
morning. This means we can spend time on a large activity but once
noon rolls around, it's over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a student is confused, that confusion can fester for a week and by
the time we get to the next session we might not remember to clear
things up until the problem arises again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;They can run away&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In class, I know I have my students for a full term. We can bore them
or even annoy them a bit as long as we win them back. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of what we teach is boring. Other things are difficult and can be frustrating for students until we dedicate enough time for things to click. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you know you have the kids all term, you don't have to worry
about a bad day on your part or on the students. They'll be back
tomorrow. Meeting with people every day makes it much easier to
develop connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a once a week voluntary program you have to be more careful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;We can't count on work over the week&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm hoping that once we get a little further along the hackers will
want to work on projects over the week. That said, we know that
Hacking Sessions is extra curricular so when the hackers have big
assignments, SAT exams and the like, we have to take a back seat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the default for a Saturday program is that it's a partial restart
every week. That's a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Communication is tough&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the one that's vexed me most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we're only meeting once a week, it would be really great if we
can generate some online dialog in between. So far, it's been tough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in class, over the years, I've had mixed levels of success with
online communication. Some classes, some years, I've gotten great buy
in to an online class community. The dialog is consistent, varied, and
great. Other times, it's just the bare minimum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my classes I usually use a Google group but I'm becoming less and
less happy with that as a solution. For Hacking Sessions we've been
using &lt;a href="http://www.piazza.com"&gt;Piazza&lt;/a&gt; so far but in spite of its
popularity at colleges, I'm not feeling it. I find it both cluttered
and limiting. I think we're going to try Vanilla forums next. It's
pretty easy to host and fairly flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm hoping that in a few weeks we'll get past the basic tools and onto
some neat project and it'll be easier to encourage talk throughout the
week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Overall&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this is a new challenge but a fun one - designing and implementing
a once a week program. Bottom lining it - I think the hackers are
doing great and we're off to a really strong start. We'll make some
mistakes along the way but as long as we keep looking at what we're
doing we can adjust as we move along we'll continue to build a great program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hacking-sessions-4/week4-chris.jpg" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hacking-sessions-4/week4-chris.jpg" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Four to beam up</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-31-halloween.html/</id>
    <updated>2013-10-31T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2013-10-31T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-31-halloween.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/crew.jpg" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/crew.jpg" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

Today was Halloween. This year we were the crew of the Enterprise. The original series, that is.

&lt;div align="Center"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/9SQwjfzlpso" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

Overall, the school had a much more subdued spirit than past years but
it was fun. Certainly more fun for me than the past couple of years.
&lt;p&gt;
For those of you that don't know - I have a long history of going all
out for Halloween. Starting in October 1994 as Groo the Wanderer:

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/groo.jpg" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="30%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/groo.jpg" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

To Bob Ross:

&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/bob_ross.jpg" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="30%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/bob_ross.jpg" class="" alt=""&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/painting.jpg" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="30%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-31-halloween/painting.jpg" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

To many more. I've been Little Ceaser, Hulk Hogan, Duffman, The Hulk,
Fred Flintstone, The Jolly Green Giant, Homer Simpson and more.

Some of my favorites were caught on video. Here's a playlist with a bunch of them:
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?list=PL9KxKa8NpFxJYgovyJhF4HZRsAqYKBLiG" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I really enjoy costumes like this one because it's all about schtick
-- interaction with others in the school.

When it first started, I wasn't sure how the whole costume thing would
go over. Now, 20 years later, it's expected. Every year I've got to do
something good and something different. That's OK though, because it
has a great affect on the classes. True, most students know me before they enter my class due to reputation, good or bad, but after Halloween there's a noticable change in the class. All of a sudden I'm just a little less scary.

Looking forward to next year.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="community" label="community"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Floating Points</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-30-huffpost-floatingpoints.html/</id>
    <updated>2013-10-30T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2013-10-30T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-30-huffpost-floatingpoints.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">The other week I was invited by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/brandondiamond"&gt;Brandon Diamond&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/IlanaSufrin"&gt;Ilana Sufrin&lt;/a&gt;  to participate in &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/HuffPostLabs"&gt;HuffPost Labs&lt;/a&gt; podcast - Floating Points.
&lt;p&gt;
I've known Brandon for a while and he's a really awesome guy. He's a
techie for sure but he also understands the importance of community
building. Brandon and Ilana (also awesome but I haven't known her as
long) are at HuffPost labs and also are working on important
initiatives like &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/HackerUnion"&gt;Hacker Union&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
When they asked me to take part, I jumped. Here's the podcast:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/117454244&amp;amp;color=ff6600&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;show_artwork=true"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Chatting with HuffPost labs team before recording, we were talking
about the Stuy CS family. "Hey - I bet you know our guest from two
podcasts ago." Sure enough, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/amyquispe"&gt;Amy&lt;/a&gt; was
on Floating Points just a couple of weeks before. Here's her episode:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/115558553"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
