<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xmlns:fh="http://purl.org/syndication/history/1.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z (old posts, page 31)</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index-31.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-02-16T13:07:15Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-31.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-30.atom"/>
  <link rel="previous" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-32.atom"/>
  <link rel="current" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="next-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-32.atom"/>
  <link rel="prev-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-30.atom"/>
  <fh:archive/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-31.html"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Thoughts on non educator  influences on CS Education</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/outside-influences-on-cs-ed/</id>
    <updated>2017-07-29T11:40:02-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-07-29T11:40:02-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/outside-influences-on-cs-ed/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org4b8c199" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org4b8c199"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org4b8c199"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; blogged about a NY Times piece discussing
&lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/2017/07/28/silicon-valley-pushing-coding-into-american-classrooms-through-code-org-nytimes/"&gt;Silicon Valleys influence on education through Code.org&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark questioned the validity of the piece. If you don't read Mark's
blog and you're in CS Ed you probably should. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I tried to leave a comment on Mark's blog - not about the NY Times
article but rather my thoughts on why I think it's important that we
remain wary and vigilant to industry and outsiders influence and
impact on CS education and on education in general.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know if my comment is sitting waiting for Mark to moderate or
if I'm experiencing WordPress weirdness but since it hasn't shown up
there, I thought I'd share it here:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While the article might not make a strong case it's important to be wary of outside influences on education policies. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm a fan of a lot of what code.org does but speaking about outsiders in general…
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Bill Gates and Co. directly or indirecty gave us such delights like stack ranking teachers, improving, I mean evaluating, I mean firing teachers based on test scores of students they don't teach, more and more high stakes nonsense testing for kids, and  at least in NY the destruction of neighborhood schools. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They've also pushed the current charter movement that, aided by misleading stats appear successful but in truth are no better and frequently worse than public schools while not sharing back a single "best practice."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then we have private companies like the College Board and Pearson both of whom have an outsized influence on US Ed policy and curriculum.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't doubt the good intentions of code.org - as I said, I'm a fan. I am concerned when they and others take actions that can affect ed policy. I'm concerned when code.org representative pushes students to take an AP exam - not a great CS course with a great CS teacher but the actual exam. I'm even more concerned when code.org offers free PD when a school signs up for the PSAT8/9 - another high stakes meaningless test at taxpayer expense. For code.org it's a means to  get more CS ed out there. To me it's setting up a new cash cow for the college board at my expense and at students expense.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've seen many Ed Tech people, armed with the best intentions, enter the lions den – a school, district, or municipality only to see their best intentions corrupted in the name of cost cutting, profits, or politics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Three strikes and you're out or third time's a charm</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/three-times/</id>
    <updated>2017-07-21T17:38:19-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-07-21T17:38:19-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/three-times/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc48ee9c" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc48ee9c"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc48ee9c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CompSci4All/with_replies?lang=en"&gt;Brenda Wilkerson&lt;/a&gt;, Director of CS and IT education for Chicago public
schools was one of the keynote speakers at this year's CSTA
conference.  During her talk, she made a comment about it taking three
times through to get it right so if you're working hard and struggling
in your first year of teaching CS, it's not the time to give
up. Learning to teach takes time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
She's absolutely correct. I saw this in myself and I've seen this in
many other young teachers. First year through, your job is to
survive. This is when you rely on colleagues lesson plans, it you can
you shadow another teacher and in general do your best to give what
you can to your students while making it through the semester. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then, I often see something interesting. Year two is frequently a step
back. It was for me and I've seen this in many young teachers in many
subject areas. I'm guessing this happens because we feel we have a
year under our belt and then we overreach while trying to be
innovative and more effective.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In year three things start to improve again and then, if the teacher
continues to work at their craft, there's steady progress for years to
come. At the point, the teachers seem to better understand how to
experiment and grow as a teacher in a safer way while also
understanding that it's OK to have a bad day or even a bad unit -
there's usually time to recover.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's also interesting that while this progression is most obvious in
new teachers it also seems to take place with experienced teachers
teaching new courses. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All this means that teaching CS or any new subject takes time, effort,
and patience. It means young teachers shouldn't beat themselves up and
that supervisors need to be supportive and give the time and resources
to allow teachers to succeed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It also means that schools with high teacher churn - notably charter
chains create environments that are anything but conducive to allowing
society to build a cadre of expert teachers. It works for these
charter chains because they're exploiting the fact that they require a
small number of teachers as compared to large urban public schools so
can burn through teachers like gasoline and the fact that they're
judged only by standardized tests. The model is not sustainable if
privatizers get their wish and charters become the national norm.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, it's another reason for people to wise up to "leadership"
programs like Teach for America where candidates come in for a couple
years before moving on to "better" opportunities.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, if the third time's a charm, how about the flip side? After how long
a period of time should we expect CS teachers to really know their
subject area? I'd say three years is also probably right. Year one,
the teacher is just surviving but after that, I'd expect a teacher to
want to master their subject. When I taught math early on in my
career, I felt overmatched. Particularly at Stuyvesant. I was a CS
major, not a math major. What did I do? I sat in on colleagues
classes and did self study over the summer. Of course by the time I
got up to speed, at least to my standards, I was teaching compute
science.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, if you're a new CS teacher, why not take CS101 and data structures
over the summer instead of doing another scripted PD? Between local
and community colleges, at least in urban areas, this shouldn't be
a problem. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, is third time a charm? Three strikes and you're out? A bit of
both? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We have to give our new CS teachers the time and support to learn to
teach and to learn the subject area but at the same time, I think it's
reasonable to require that they do so given the resources.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>CS Ed advocates should pay attention to greater ed issues</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cd-ed-and-all-ed/</id>
    <updated>2017-07-18T19:51:40-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-07-18T19:51:40-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cd-ed-and-all-ed/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbb42e34" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgbb42e34"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgbb42e34"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For anyone involved in K12 CS education, the past few years have been
a wild ride. When I first tried to make inroads in the DOE decades ago
I couldn't get through the door. Now, CS Education is everyone's
darling. It's really amazing. It's been a combination of grass roots
efforts by teachers, non profit education efforts such as &lt;a href="http://teals12k.org"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt;, advocacy of
groups like &lt;a href="http://code.org"&gt;Code.org&lt;/a&gt; and amazing individuals like &lt;a href="http://avc.com/2017/06/bearing-witness/"&gt;Fred Wilson&lt;/a&gt; who has
probably done more to move the needle of CS Ed in NY than any other 10
people combined.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While everyone agrees that to do CS education right at the K12 level
we need great teachers and lots of them, everyone also knows that
teachers voices are often unheard. The voices with the greatest weight
belong to the large non-profits, principals, superintendents and
local politicians. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today's post is a plea to those with voices to think about the effects
of their advocacy for CS Ed to the greater education landscape.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started thinking about this recently as I've been developing the
CS teacher certification programs for Hunter College. As I spoke to
people across the nation I found that many of the efforts to
developing teacher certification are what I call the "you take it you
teach it" model. You take an abbreviated version of APCS-A and APCS-P
and you're a certified CS teacher. Just about every real educator feels
that this is ludicrous. Some feel that this can be a first step - get
these credentials to get in the door and then you have three to five
years to really learn your subject and craft. I'm good with that but I
have a problem with anyone who says "you take it you teach it" is good
enough and I've heard of a number of regions that are seriously
considering it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why is this so bad and, I'd argue, dangerous? Not merely because we'll
end up with substandard CS teachers for the foreseeable future but
also because it undermines the teaching profession as a whole.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's no secret that public education is under attack. A number of
states including Wisconsin, Arizona, Oklahoma, New York and Michigan
have considered relaxing the standards to become a teacher to address
a teacher shortage. In their twisted logic, the politicians and
"reformers" say that we can't find enough qualified teachers because
we've made it an untenable career so let's lower standards. You can
argue that any current state's requirements are overly cumbersome but
that's another conversation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When CS Educators say that all that's needed to teach CS is to sit in
on a two week APCS institute is saying that to teach any subject you
don't need content expertise. This is dangerous to education as a
whole and when power players in the CS Ed movement don't speak up
otherwise or even worse that the stance that "you take it you teach
it" is OK, we're undermining teaching as a profession. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We need our heavy hitters to publicly and privately say that we need a
short term entry into the profession but we absolutely need plans and
pathways so that at the end of the day we have the best prepared
teachers in our schools for CS and for all subjects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another issue is when as CS Educators we don't pay attention to the
whole child. I was at a meeting of CSTA people  from about thirty
states a few years ago. Someone asked "how can we advocate for CS when
the school might use it as an excuse to get rid of music?" Cameron
Wilson, at the time a lobbyist for the ACM said something to the
effect of "I'm not concerned with other subjects, my concern is
getting CS into the schools." I get it, he was employed to stump CS
but we have to remember that we're only a piece of the puzzle. We want
a seat at the table but we have to make sure that the table is
populated with everyone needed to provide a great education for our
kids. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A final issue I'll mention here is how so many CS educators are so
close to the College Board. It was very disturbing that so many CS Ed
players were pushing for more students to take the APCS exam. Not the
class, not some other CS class but the APCS exam. AP is an extremely
controversial subject among teachers and many of us feel that too many
kids take too many AP classes and certainly too many exams. Remember,
the College Board is the organization that pushes things like the
PSAT8/9 another meaningless but high stakes exam inflicted upon our
kids at taxpayer expense. I understand that AP makes things easy -
they have courses, curricula, etc. but we've given the college board
an outsized influence on CS education and we're not paying attention
to their outsized influence on education in general. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm just a small time teacher. I don't have a national voice. I'm
urging those that do:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look into what's going on in greater education. Look at the way
public education has been under attack and why.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look at the side affects of our choices - who we partner with and
what policies we push.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We might not agree on the right path but everyone with a voice in CS
Education should be having hard conversations about this and then
strongly advocating for the positions they feel correct.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Observing CS Teachers</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teacher-eval/</id>
    <updated>2017-07-15T20:13:38-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-07-15T20:13:38-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teacher-eval/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org6add37e" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6add37e"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6add37e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another set of tweets god me thinking:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;How do we help school administrators help and evaluate CS
teachers? asks &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/lsudol"&gt;@lsudol&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CSForAll"&gt;@CSForAll&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/csta2017?src=hash"&gt;#csta2017&lt;/a&gt;
Many don't understand CS&lt;/p&gt;— Alfred Thompson (@alfredtwo)
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo/status/884427047635795969"&gt;July
10, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;If the current system is any indication, checklists are not
the answer&lt;/p&gt;— Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/886220912110043136"&gt;July 15,
2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I get the intent. CS teachers should be evaluated by people who have
some clue about the subject. Leigh Ann's reporting that some people
are working on checklists got me wondering if it really matters? Sure,
it matters if teacher observations were actually set up to improve
instruction but given what we have in NY does it really?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In New York City, teacher observations are a major part of a teacher's
annual rating and the other part is still &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-09-06-why_i_might_no_longer_be_an_effective_teacher.md/#.WWqzc9_6yEI"&gt;that standardized test
nonsense&lt;/a&gt;. Teachers are observed at least 4 and commonly 6 times
or more per year. There might be pre and
post observation conferences.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sounds good but the system is amazingly flawed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start, the DOE uses the &lt;a href="http://schools.nyc.gov/NR/rdonlyres/8A4A25F0-BCEE-4484-9311-B5BB7A51D7F1/0/TeacherEffectivenessProgram1314Rubric201308142.pdf"&gt;Danielson Framework&lt;/a&gt; which provides a basis
for teacher evaluation. The framework is at best &lt;a href="https://tedmorrissey.wordpress.com/2014/03/23/fatal-flaws-of-the-danielson-framework/"&gt;flawed&lt;/a&gt; with even
Danielson coming out to say &lt;a href="https://tedmorrissey.wordpress.com/2016/04/27/danielson-framework-criticized-by-charlotte-danielson/"&gt;it's being misused&lt;/a&gt;. Of course I'm sure she
protested all the way to the bank. A teacher can be a "Danielson
style" teacher and be great but a teacher can also check all
the Danielson boxes and be mediocre at best. Likewise, some of the
best teachers I know break the Danielson mold and if a supervisor
rigidly adheres to the framework these great teachers would be found
ineffective.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To make matters worse, the rubric is so large that the DOE just
focuses on small parts which means even if the framework was
comprehensive and correct, teachers are only evaluated on a small
part.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When a supervisor evaluates a teacher, they have a checklist with the
rubric where they can rate a teacher 1 (ineffective), 2 (developing),
3 (effective), and 4 (highly effective) and write down some notes. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I guess the hope was to have some consistency but the truth is the
process is very subjective. I know a supervisor who gave a teacher a
ratings of 2 (which is basically failing) for the professional
development category even though the teacher fulfilled all contractual
obligations and then some. There are also supervisors who won't give a
rating of 4 out of principle. On the other side, I've met supervisors
loathe to give low scores.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The tweets at the top of this post refer to the current situation
where CS teachers are never observed and evaluated by supervisors who
are knowledgeable about CS. Even if someone designs a checklist -
something I'm skeptical about given the fact that there are so few
people strong in CS, experienced as teachers and with an eye for
teacher evaluation out there, if the application of the Danielson
framework is any indication, a CS checklist won't help.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Besides, CS won't be any different from any other subject. Since the
destruction of the comprehensive neighborhood high school we've had a
proliferation of small schools. Some people think that small schools
are universally better. They're wrong. You need a mix. One of the
problems with small schools is that you don't have subject area
supervisors. You have a principal and an assistant principal. The
result is that most teachers are evaluated by supervisors with no
subject area expertise and no subject area pedagogical expertise.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The old system, even though it was also subject to abuses was much
better - at least in the hands of a good supervisor. The observation
system is inherently flawed. Observations are snapshots out of context
and the mere presence of an observer changes the tone of the
room. That said, if a supervisor knows the heartbeat of their school
and has ongoing conversations with their staff, they can both ensure
teachers are doing an honest job and also help them to improve.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The method of observation also doesn't have to be complicated. My
first supervisor made it very simple. He said he looked for one basic
thing - "was learning going on?" The conversation would then go from
there. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sometimes you have to look beyond the lesson. In my first year, I
frequently observed a friend's history class. One day the class seemed
to do very little. It seemed like all talk and play. I talked to the
teacher about this. He said "that was what they needed today." He was
a master and he was right. You might drop in on his class to see
amazing instruction or you might come in and wonder why he wasn't
fired long ago but at the end of the year when you looked at how much
his kid learned and loved his class you realized that he was an
amazing teacher. No rubric or framework needed. Just the eyeball test.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They also used to have more peer observations.They had to be coordinated
by the department supervisor and he or she had to be in the loop but
the peer observation model helped cross pollinate ideas in a
department, build camaraderie and it also eased the workload of the
supervisor.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To answer Alfred's question from his tweet, how do we help
administrators help CS teachers? Get other teachers involved, keep an
open mind and look at the big picture.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="supervision" label="supervision"/>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A friendly reminder to use the right language when describing CS</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/languages-or-cs/</id>
    <updated>2017-07-10T21:17:47-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-07-10T21:17:47-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/languages-or-cs/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org190ca7e" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org190ca7e"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org190ca7e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was part of this conversation the other day:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;When science teachers asked me if I taught AP Java I'd always respond by asking them if they taught AP Microscope.&lt;/p&gt;— Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/883327927831711745"&gt;July 7, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I always use that line to emphasize that I teach CS - a way of
thinking and problem solving and looking at the world. The languages
we use in our classes are tools to help us communicate ideas not the
ends but rather a means.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've spent the past couple of days at the CSTA conference. It's been a
lot of fun. I've been spending the time with old friends and meeting
new ones and as everyone who knows me knows - I love talking shop. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I overheard a conversation today. One CS teacher describing what they
did to a few others. I overheard:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We teach Scratch then Swift and C++ and also teach Python
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I heard statements like this describing programs more than a couple of
times. I know we're at a conference of CS Educators but even in this
community we have everything from beginners getting their feet wet to
hardcore computer scientists to everything in between.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We shouldn't be teaching languages as an ends unto themselves and the
majority of us don't.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What many of us do, though, is take the easy path and use the name of
a programming language to describe what we do rather than really
define what we do. This is why we hear "I teach Java" or "I teach a
class in Swift" even when the teacher teaching Java might really be
teaching Object Oriented program design and development or data
structures or something similar just using Java as the language or
tool.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I too fall into this trap but I try to catch myself. I try not to say
"I teach Scheme" but rather I'll say "I teach Scheme. Actually, we're
studying functional programming using Scheme as the language but for
convenience, I'll just say Scheme for the rest of this talk…."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The words we use to describe our field set the tone. If we're sloppy
and say "we teach Java," it's just like biology teacher saying "I
teach microscope." 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As we try to define our field in the K12 space and seek equal footing
with established subject areas it's important that we use the right
language so that other educators and policy makers don't get the wrong
idea.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="csed" label="csed"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Self Certification - not a good idea</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/dont-self-certify/</id>
    <updated>2017-07-07T15:34:19-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-07-07T15:34:19-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/dont-self-certify/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org1db9e1d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org1db9e1d"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org1db9e1d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You've probably seen an image like this:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/dont-self-certify/self-signed.png" alt="self-signed.png" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's what you see when you try to access a secure web site but the web
site itself certified itself as being secure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When people see this on a professional site it sets off all manner of
red flags. We feel much more comfortable when go to a site and we
don't see that error. When we see the secure green lock in the url bar
indicating that this site is certified through an external trusted
source.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's take this a step further. If you needed surgery would you go to
a board certified surgeon or would you go to Dr. Nick Riviera or some
other "self certified" doctor? Likewise you wouldn't want to be
represented in court by someone who hasn't passed the bar. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We might not feel that these certification and licensing processes are
perfect but when we need the services of a doctor or lawyer, we're
happy these gatekeepers exist.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So we should all be extremely concerned with today's announcement that
the deal for mayoral control just brokered in NYC came with strings
attached and one of those strings looks to open the doors to give some
charter chains the ability to self certify their teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's a story on it in &lt;a href="http://www.politico.com/states/new-york/city-hall/story/2017/07/06/with-city-charters-poised-to-win-certification-deal-education-schools-fret-113243"&gt;Politico&lt;/a&gt; and one in &lt;a href="http://www.chalkbeat.org/posts/ny/2017/07/06/some-charter-school-teachers-could-become-certified-without-a-masters-under-proposed-new-suny-rules/"&gt;Chalkbeat&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One might think that some requirements to become a teacher are
ridiculous. I'll get to them later  but this is really giving the fox
the keys to the henhouse.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Charters appear to have extremely high rates of teacher attrition so
it makes sense that they want to control their teacher pipeline. This
alone should be a red flag against self certification but what else
are charter chains known for?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Misleading stats - claiming amazing passing numbers on standardized
exams while neglecting to mention that somehow or other big blocks
of students were removed from the school prior to the test year
(&lt;a href="http://www.shankerinstitute.org/blog/student-attrition-and-backfilling-success-academy-charter-schools-what-student-enrollment"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The gotta go list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forcing high levels of parent involvement (tough for single working
parents)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charging &lt;a href="http://www.houstonchronicle.com/news/education/article/KIPP-schools-collected-millions-in-unallowable-11257006.php"&gt;illegal fees&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Top this off with as taking resources from public schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Charters operate in anything but a transparent manner and we're
expected to trust them to prepare "highly effective" teachers? I don't
think so. Since there is no real accountability for charter schools -
they can easily game the system through student attrition, selective
admissions (by putting up barriers to enter the lottery) and test prep
they can pay lip service to teacher preparation and the public will be
none the wiser. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If we had a reasonable way of holding principals accountable and no,
test scores are not the answer then we could pretty much do away
with teacher certification. If principals were held to task to run an
effective school, something we can easily define but not measure, then
they would have every incentive to hire the best
teachers. Unfortunately we're nowhere near that place.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since we're not, we're left with the current systems of teacher
certification that has it's own slew of problems. A big part of it, in
my opinion is that schools of education have lost the high
ground. While there are some institutions doing great work, reputation
wise, schools of education are held in very low regard. Strong
teachers trade stories of the watered down content classes and waste
of time classes where professors share their pet theories of
education. I can't tell you how many times I've heard the new
definitive way to teach. At the same time, education research is
frequently held in low regard by teachers and the general public. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the one hand we have charters run by and support by non-educators
wanting us to trust them and on the other we have institutions that
are questioned by the teachers they produce and the general public.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What a mess.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know the answer. I'm working on teacher certifications
programs at Hunter and it's a balancing act. How much content is
sufficient and how much is too much. Can any of the general content be
streamlined or is it all necessary. If it isn't necessary do we need
it anyway to satisfy the bean counters?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you don't have enough then we're sending unprepared teachers into
the classroom. Too much and we'll drive potential teachers away.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As computer science education is defining itself we see similar
struggles. We have some people advocating certifications analogous to
existing teacher certifications. On the other extreme we have
advocates for two weeks summer training and you're a CS teacher. I'd
like to think that I'm advocating for the sweet spot. Strong content
knowledge not tied to a specific course and matching content related
pedagogy. Time will tell becomes the certification standard and time
will tell whose approach was right.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For now, it's important not to give away the store. Private charter
schools should not be the driving force behind teacher certification
and they certainly shouldn't be allowed to train their own teachers
and then 'teach' our students without much greater scrutiny.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org5f756c2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org5f756c2"&gt;Addendum:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org5f756c2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'm sure some of my friends will point out that private schools aren't
held to any particular standard for teacher certification. This is
true but private schools don't take public funds. Actually they do but
in my opinion, they shouldn't. I maintain that charter schools are
publicly funded private schools in that they take public money but
operate as private entities. As such they should be held under the
greatest of scrutiny and standards – they aren't
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="certification" label="certification"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Plea to AP teachers- don't measure yourself by your scores</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teachers-you-arent-your-test-scores/</id>
    <updated>2017-07-06T17:22:10-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-07-06T17:22:10-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teachers-you-arent-your-test-scores/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org0a0263a" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0a0263a"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0a0263a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
AP scores just came out. As usual, I see the posts and take part in
conversations where teachers talk about their results. Some are happy
about their results, some aren't, some don't really care.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I just want to make a plea to all AP teachers out there:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Don't let your value be dictated by the college board or any other
  exam.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I never really cared much about my students' actual AP scores. There
were a number of years when I never even saw the results. Of course, I
had a population that would do reasonably well regardless of teacher
so I was never placed under any pressure to "do better." One year -
while the APCS-AB exam was still offered, my principal called me down
to discuss the results to see if we could get more kids scoring 4s and
5s (which most of the kids already did). I told him that I thought
we were doing fine, explained why I couldn't advocate more teaching to
the test (such as more than paying lip service to the case study or
more rote practice on the multiple choice), and told him how I
measured our success as a program. He was happy with my answer and
that was that. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The AP exam is one test on one day and in my opinion the least
valuable measure of my students' achievement. This is one of
the reasons I was so dismayed by the CSEd community's efforts in
pushing the AP exams - not the class or the subject but the actual exam.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, how should you judge your success? That's up to you. I can only
tell you how I judge myself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First and foremost - and I know this sounds cheesy - are you a "force
for good" in your student's lives. Do you leave them in a better
place? Have you opened the door to a possible future for them? Have
you helped them grow? Beyond that, have they progressed in your
subject and as students in general.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've had kids "fail" the AP exam and go on to wonderful careers in
tech and come back to thank me for giving them their start. I've also
had kids that have gone into other fields but appreciate what we've
done for them. I've also had my failures and I do mean my
failures. Students I couldn't reach or couldn't figure out how to
help.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As teachers, we work day to day trying to improve but we can get a
great overview of how we're doing by using a much longer feedback
loop - looking at what our graduates are up to. When young teachers
would comment on former students coming back or running into them at
tech events that they would have graduates of their own in a few years
and invariably they do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To really evaluate how you're doing you have to go with the long
game. Very few people get that. I remember talking to a Google
Executive while I was designing CAPE 2010. He said something to the
effect of "I know we won't know if this program works for about ten
years but we'll have to come up with something short term to satisfy
the powers that be."  That so few "get it" and need instant feedback
is one of the reasons that our society is so test driven. We shouldn't
be. Our focus should be on helping the students learn and progress.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So don't get distressed over AP results and don't get to high on them
either. Certainly don't use them to drive what and how you teach. Let
your students and your conscience be your guide.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="ap" label="ap"/>
    <category term="apcs" label="apcs"/>
    <category term="csed" label="csed"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>CS Teachers - teacher first or content first</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teacher-to-cs-or-cs-to-teacher/</id>
    <updated>2017-07-04T16:39:43-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-07-04T16:39:43-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teacher-to-cs-or-cs-to-teacher/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orge2dd4be" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orge2dd4be"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orge2dd4be"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Is it easier to take CS people and teach them to teach or is it easier
to take teachers and teach them CS?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The question gets batted around from time to time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This time via twitter:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Some think it's easier to teach a teacher to teach CS than to teach a CS pro to teach. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;@alfredtwo&lt;/a&gt; is not one of them &lt;a href="https://t.co/QCUP8d8llZ"&gt;https://t.co/QCUP8d8llZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Diane Levitt (@diane_levitt) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/diane_levitt/status/881874056911388673"&gt;July 3, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Agreed. It takes a lot of work. More than a week long workshop.&lt;/p&gt;— Alfred Thompson (@alfredtwo) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo/status/882243591090962432"&gt;July 4, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The conversation was referring to blog posts by &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/06/become-computer-science-teacher-in-five.html?spref=tw&amp;amp;m=1"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://gflint.wordpress.com/2017/06/20/a-week-of-in-service-another-python-course/"&gt;Garth flint&lt;/a&gt;. 
Alfred's key point - one that I've spoken about before is that short
term professional development does not a CS teacher make.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As to the lead in question? I've seen both routes succeed and both
routes fail. Both can be heavy lifts but there's a missing part of the
equation that's never addressed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The claim is that it's easier to teach CS to a non-CS teacher because
they already know how to teach. The problem is, particularly in the
later grades that teachers of different subject areas have very
different tool sets. Sure, there are common factors – get the kids
involved, layer, spiral, etc. but you don't teach a CS lesson the same
way you teach a math lesson let alone a literature, history, language
lesson. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In a math class, it's common to have students write solutions to
problems up on the board. If you try that in a CS class, you'll be
waiting 20 minutes while the kids transcribe the problems. Likewise,
math homework will likely consist of a certain amount of repetitive
practice problems whereas a CS class won't have something directly
analogous. This is not to say that you don't have opportunities for
students to present at the board in CS class or that there isn't
worthwhile homework but rather that even at this simple level, there
are differences. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, if we're going to teach a non-CS teacher the CS content, beyond
the challenge of giving them the necessary depth and breadth of
content knowledge we have to teach them how to teach CS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've inventoried some of the techniques my colleagues and I have used
in our classes and the collected methods could easily fill a couple of
graduate education courses. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what's the answer to the question? It doesn't matter where you
start but if we want to do right by our kids we need to prepare them
in not two but three areas:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CS Content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CS Pedagogy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General education and pedagogy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Short term PD (professional development) won't do it and neither will
scripts for "teachers" to follow. It's going to take time, will, and
effort.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's hoping that municipalities look at the long game. It's fine to
do PD now to get something started but it's not enough. I wanted my
kids math teachers to know math and how to teach it. We should demand
no less from our CS teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Using Emacs 35 - Blogging</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-35-blogging/</id>
    <updated>2017-06-27T11:22:54-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-06-27T11:22:54-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-35-blogging/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org35f7326" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org35f7326"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org35f7326"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Very little new Emacs in today's episode of Using Emacs. The video
shows my old blogging workflow and what I'm playing with now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The only new Emacs covered is the &lt;a href="https://github.com/rejeep/prodigy.el"&gt;prodigy&lt;/a&gt; package which lets you run
services under Emacs. I use it to run &lt;a href="https://getnikola.com/blog/index.html"&gt;Nikola&lt;/a&gt;'s development server but
I think prodigy will also be useful when I start writing that knitting
application I promised my wife.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I started this blog, I used Jekyll. It was simple and worked with
GitHub pages. I wrote about why I transitioned to Nikola &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-04-14-i-hate-ruby/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-04-17-emacs-jekyll-nikola/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's not much more to say here so enjoy the video:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wSeTic9obKw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="emacs" label="emacs"/>
    <category term="learning" label="learning"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>On Retaining Teachers</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-retaining-teachers/</id>
    <updated>2017-06-25T11:35:08-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-06-25T11:35:08-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-retaining-teachers/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org15c9eac" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org15c9eac"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org15c9eac"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back in February, I shared my thoughts on &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry"&gt;losing CS teachers to the
tech industy&lt;/a&gt;. TL;DR - I don't think it will be a CS Ed problem. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That said, I do think that it will be hard to find good CS teachers
but the reason is because it will get harder and harder to find good
teachers in general.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are plenty of reasons why it's harder to become a
career teacher but I don't want to talk about those today. There are
also plenty of powerful forces working to destroy public schools and
teaching as a career but this post isn't about that either.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This post is my attempt to tell people what teachers are actually
looking for. Some people assert that merit pay or similar "real world"
incentives will keep good teachers teaching but teachers are a
different breed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, I can't speak for all teachers but I can talk about myself
and teachers I've known and worked with over the years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I never thought I'd be a teacher, it was just something I tried when I
was dissatisfied with Wall Street. I tried it, it stuck. I didn't feel
at the time that teaching was my calling but somehow or other, I made
a career of it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start, schools are not factories, companies, stores, or any other
type of business. Teachers spend most of their days with students and
little time with each other. Most of their time is allocated for
them. A high school teacher in NY will likely teach 5 class of 34 kids
each, have 1 period for lunch, 1 for preparation and 1 assigned to
some school task. You probably won't see your supervisor much. Mostly
at monthly meetings and when they observe you. Observations are
ostensibly for teacher evaluation and improvement but the system is
does neither well. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teachers also don't have the same types of career paths as a other
professionals do. If you want to remain a classroom teacher, there is
no career path. You could become an assistant principal or principal
but those opportunities take you away from the kids and from your
subject area. They say teaching is a calling and for career classroom
teachers it probably is. For those who spent a few years in a
classroom and left for what they see as greener pastures, maybe not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So instead teachers make a career by honing their craft, creating electives,
working with clubs and teams, or doing something similar that doesn't
remove them from the classroom.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my case, I developed some electives and one thing led to another
and I ended up where I am today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The career situation of the teacher is why things like merit pay never
work. As a teacher, I want, in fact need my colleagues to do well. I
might have your kids next year and if you do a poor job I'll end up
suffering with the results. Sure, I'd like to be recognized as one of
the better teachers but it's not healthy for my students, my school,
or my career if I'm pitted against my fellow teacher. We're all in
this together. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teachers do accept merit pay when it's forced on them though. As a
friend of mine once said - it's like the teacher lottery - the way
they assign the merit bonuses are based on those bogus state exams so
the distribution is pretty random, one year I'll get it, another year
someone else.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is not to say that teachers couldn't use a higher salary but even
then, teachers are not driven by the same motivations as business
people. I don't know of any teacher who feels that they'd work harder
for more pay or that they work any less hard if they're paid less.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teachers work and fight for their kids because that's what we
do. Right before I left Stuy for Hunter, the teachers and city agreed
to a new contract. All of a sudden I got a pay raise. I can tell you
that I was neither a better or worse of a teacher the day after the
contract went into affect than the day before.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My mentor and friend &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-07-rich-rich.html"&gt;Richard Rothenberg&lt;/a&gt; talked to me about the deal we
make with society as teachers early in my career. He said, once you
get a few years in and have some seniority you're pretty secure and
you're only worry has to be teaching. We don't do great in the good
times but we do OK. On the other hand, we still have jobs in the bad
times although, again, we don't do great. We put in a lifetime of
service knowing that we won't get any significant financial reward but
at the end of the day between our contributions and the city/state's
investments we'll get a pension and won't be out in the cold in our
retirement. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The point is that those of us meant to be teachers were never looking
for the fast track to the upper class. We work to make a difference
and want society to enable us to make that difference. Teachers don't
have to be paid like they are in "the real world" but they do need to
put a roof over their heads, send their kids to college and have a
vacation now and again.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not too much to ask but in this day and age it's apparently too
much to give.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
