<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z (old posts, page 30)</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index-30.atom</id>
  <updated>2017-06-25T19:20:44Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-30.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-29.atom"/>
  <link rel="previous" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="current" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="prev-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-29.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-30.html"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Designing a course with constraints</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/design-course-with-constraints/</id>
    <updated>2017-05-19T11:38:20-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-05-19T11:38:20-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/design-course-with-constraints/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the hats I wear at Hunter is to build a new &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs.html"&gt;CS Honors program&lt;/a&gt;
and to bring my particular brand of insanity to &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-important"&gt;Hunter College CS&lt;/a&gt; as a
whole.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday was my last class for the semester so I thought I'd write a
bit about the course.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For the Fall semester, I taught an intro programming course to the
entire cohort. For some in the cohort, this was their first exposure
to CS. Others had one or more classes under their belt. It was a
Python based programming class and a big part of it was to start
building the cohort into a community. I'm going to work on tweaking
what I taught for next time around but the constraints of designing
such a course are pretty common – an intro course where the students
all want to be there the level of previous experience varies to some degree.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Second semester was more of a challenge. The "next" course was CSCI
135, CS 100 - like APCS but in C++. I could teach that but since some
of my students had APCS credit, they didn't need 135. This would break
up the group. There was also the issue of the students getting credit
for the course without showing any proficiency in C++.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, Hunter requires students in 135 to take CSCI 136. A 1
credit programming lab. It meets once a week in a computer lab and the
students complete a weekly programming assignment. The lab meets for 2
hours. The instructor goes over anything that's needed for the lab
that hasn't been covered yet and then the students work independently
(with the instructors support) on the lab. Overall it works well. It
makes sure the students are spending at least a couple of hours a week
coding in a supported environment.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
How did 136 help me? I taught a 3 credit course where 1 day was
basically the lab component (what the students were to do in 136) and
one day was enrichment - the stuff I was going to do with them. This
enabled us keeping the cohort together and it also made sure that by
taking the class, the honors cohort members with AP credit would
indeed get up to speed in C++.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was happy with the basic structure. I was able to cover some topics
in project development, testing, debugging, and software engineering but the
designing and teaching the class proved to be challenging for a number
of reasons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One was timing. The lab class meets 1 day a week for 1 hour. My class,
2 days a week for 1 hour 15. This meant that if we were to keep the
lab to one day either the students would have less time or I'd have to
impose on them to stay late or come early. I wasn't happy with that
but given the inconsistency in the way the other sections handled lab
timings, I think it worked out OK.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some of the other difficulties included:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-1" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-1-1"&gt;The language was C++:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since the labs were to be done in C++, I had to use that as the
language for the class. That meant no "fun" libraries or frameworks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-2" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-1-2"&gt;The labs were solo assignments:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since the labs were solo projects and there was one per week it made
it very difficult to structure group experiences. I wanted to cover
things like group development, code review, working off of other
peoples code bases but this proved difficult with an outside separate
lab being handed down each week.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-3" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-1-3"&gt;Someone else dictated the language sequence:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The labs were designed to support what the students were learning in
135 and were only distributed a day or two before the week was to
start. This meant that I couldn't plan too far ahead and had to adjust
frequently. This should be easier next year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-4" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-1-4"&gt;Labs didn't match the supplemental material:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The best example of this was when we were talking about testing. We
ended up using &lt;a href="https://github.com/philsquared/Catch"&gt;Catch&lt;/a&gt; as a testing framework. The problem was that
right afterwards the lab (and also 135 project) didn't lend themselves
to using a testing framework like catch. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were more challenges but overall I think the class went fairly
well. I'll know more when I get feedback from the students and when we
all look back next year with some perspective.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's been an interesting experience designing a class that had to
interleave with another, existing class. I've designed many classes
over the years and I know that whatever you plan, it probably changes
once you're actually in the classroom and working with the kids, or as
Mike Tyson said: "Everyone has a plan until they get punched in the
mouth." This has been a little more of a challenge but I think the
first go through went well and that the course will get better and be
better defined as we go through a couple more iterations. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="curriculum" label="curriculum"/>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
