<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z (old posts, page 26)</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index-26.atom</id>
  <updated>2017-01-02T01:40:18Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-26.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-25.atom"/>
  <link rel="previous" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="current" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="prev-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-25.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-26.html"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Advent of Code 2016</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016/</id>
    <updated>2016-12-03T15:25:26-05:00</updated>
    <published>2016-12-03T15:25:26-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
Once again, it's time for &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; - a series of small
programming problems released once a day. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wrote a bit about it &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-15-advent.html/"&gt;last&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-17-im-an-idiot.html/#.WEMqBB9ieYQ"&gt;year&lt;/a&gt; and you can still find last years
problems &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/2015/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's only day three but so far, all of the problems look really nice
for students in APCS-A or any similar intro course. I'm thinking of
looking at a couple of the problems this week with my class at Hunter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I didn't think about this much last year but one thing I really like
about the competition is that each problem comes in two parts. You're
first presented with the problem and the input and once you put in the
correct answer, you're presented with part two.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This can be annoying at times, particularly when it requires a large
code rewrite but it also means that well designed, not too specific
solutions are rewarded. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not quite the same as changing the specs on a project mid way but
it does encourage thinking about more than just solving a super
specific problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Check out &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; and see if it's something you or your classes
might enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="apcs" label="apcs"/>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Selling out or getting a seat at the table</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/selling-out-or-a-seat-at-the-table/</id>
    <updated>2016-11-30T19:47:17-05:00</updated>
    <published>2016-11-30T19:47:17-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/selling-out-or-a-seat-at-the-table/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
The other day, a friend posited a question on Facebook (paraphrased):
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If called upon, would you take a job in an administration who's policies you strongly
disagreed with?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Would you go work for an administration that you reviled in order to
get a seat at the table? To try to affect change from the inside or
would you consider yourself a sellout or worse, publicly promote
positions you disagree with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tough question.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The original question implied national level positions. I've never and
will never breath such rarefied air but I have had such experiences
closer to ground level, both with DOE projects and also in
conversations with some charter chains.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My take?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Anyone that knows me knows that I've had various dealings with the NYC
DOE and also knows that those dealings never resulted in outcomes I
was happy with. Over my time at Stuy, I had many philosophical
differences with Tweed (a common nickname for the NYC DOE as they're
housed in the old Tweed courthouse) and these were times where I tried
to play nice to have a seat at the table.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once I was at a meeting that also included a number of tech industry
heavy hitters. After the meeting, one came over to me. He knew me
by having worked with my former students. I knew him by reputation. He
asked "do they really want our thoughts on this or are we just here so
that they can do what they wanted in the first place and then parade us out 
to say that they consulted experts in the tech industry?" I honestly
didn't know at the time but I had my doubts as to the DOE's sincerity
in being open to either my views or this CTO's As it turned out, they
just did want to parade us. Later in the process, I was told in a back
room that it would be wise of me not to publicly voice my thoughts
about the direction of one particular project.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So there you have it. I was given a seat at the table but only as long
as my views mirrored the views of those in power. Not really much of a
seat. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've also sat down with some charter chains - chains that I've been
more than happy to denounce publicly. Why did I take the meetings?
Mostly to find out if I was mistaken in my position and if so, maybe
I could help them. Every time I've had such a meeting, however, I've
left the table with my feelings unchanged and knowing that I would
never willingly help them as I felt their practices were harmful to
kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In one case, I took the seat but failed to affect change. In the other
I refused the seat. I'll always take a meeting and I'll always work
with someone who wants to help kids and who has an open mind but I've
found that the more powerful the player, at least in education, the
more likely they are to just want confirmation of their own bias.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You might get a seat at the table but you also might end up lending
your reputation to a cause you don't believe in.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
