<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xmlns:fh="http://purl.org/syndication/history/1.0" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>C'est la Z (old posts, page 5)</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/index-5.atom</id>
  <updated>2016-04-16T21:39:06Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-5.atom"/>
  <link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-4.atom"/>
  <link rel="previous" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-6.atom"/>
  <link rel="current" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index.atom"/>
  <link rel="next-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-6.atom"/>
  <link rel="prev-archive" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-4.atom"/>
  <fh:archive/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/index-5.html"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Schools, Snake Oil, and the SOTU</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-02-14-Schools-Snake-Oil-and-the-SOTU.md/</id>
    <updated>2013-02-14T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2013-02-14T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-02-14-Schools-Snake-Oil-and-the-SOTU.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I had the privilege of attending my second live State of the City
address. Mayor Bloomberg didn't spend as much time on education as he
did at last year's address but he did take a moment to give a shout out
to charter schools. It gets old hearing the same false story about how
charters are better than public schools. At least we have people
like &lt;a href="http://garyrubinstein.teachforus.org/"&gt;Gary
Rubinstein&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://dianeravitch.net/"&gt;Diane
Ravitch&lt;/a&gt; trying to set the record straight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's worse, when public schools are lauded, it seems that the ones
given the spotlight are selling the same snake oil as the charter
schools. Gary Rubinstein recently posted on one
case &lt;a href="http://garyrubinstein.teachforus.org/2013/02/13/the-status-quo-miracle-district/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
but I'd like to talk about another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week President Obama gave his State of the Union address. He
gave a shout out to P-Tech, a new school with a six year (9-14)
program. It's a partnership with IBM and students completing the six
years will have the opportunity to interview for a job at IBM (note,
that's an opportunity to interview, not an actual job). When I heard
the shout out, my stomach sank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P-Tech is being hailed as a new model for public education but for me,
it raised serious questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, when did we start considering a school, under two years in
existence, a success. The education reformers love to talk data yet
here's the President, lauding a school that's collected no data. I
personally feel that P-Tech is more style than substance but we won't
know either way for another six to ten years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any event, let's think about the possible outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best case is a student selects P-Tech in the 8th grade and leaves
six years later with a solid job at IBM. What's wrong with that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, since NY dismantled all the large schools, all that's left are
small "themed" schools. Since they're small, they don't offer a wide
range of electives, only ones in their theme. So, a youngster has
to &lt;b&gt;know&lt;/b&gt; that they want to do in 8th grade. Should a thirteen
year old be forced to make a decision like that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another question is will there be quality jobs waiting for these
kids? With more and more computing moving to the cloud, will there be
jobs waiting for these kids in NY six years after they begin? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have numerous other questions about P-Tech, but I really want to
focus on one more here and it's one that surprised me when I started
thinking about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not really a commentary on P-Tech but more on "early college" and
what we consider college level work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the President's shout out, I decided to see if P-Tech would have
something to say about it. I ended up reading a piece by Principal
Rashid Davis where he talked about fifteen of his students earning a
"C" or better in a college level course at City Tech, a CUNY school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first reaction was "that's really cool." Then I started to
think. My daughter's graduating high school this year. She's very
smart and capable and has always achieved academically. I wondered,
how would I feel if the courses she takes next year are at a level of
rigor such that she could have succeeded as a high school freshman? My
answer was that I would be very disappointed in the college.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She backed me up by saying that she felt, looking back at all the AP
courses she has taken, she probably wasn't ready for most of them in
her freshman high school year. My own observations back this up. At
Stuyvesant, we teach an enhanced version of the old AB AP Computer
Science curriculum. We teach this to students in their junior
year. Years ago, I had some sophomores enrolled and while a few
succeeded, most of the time, the kids just weren't ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't mean to say anything demeaning to Mr. Davis' students here,
but if our colleges are teaching courses in which a typical high school
freshman can excel, then  maybe they shouldn't be college level courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never really believed in the "early college" model anyway. We
teach A.P. computer science at Stuyvesant but most of our CS sequence
is designed to complement what our graduates will face in
college. We're giving them the missing pieces. Yes, there is overlap,
and I do believe we have a similar level of rigor but we strive to
give the kids something they won't get otherwise. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any event, at the end of the day what do we have? Plenty of snake
oil to go around.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Taking it out of the school</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-02-10-Taking-it-out-of-the-school.html/</id>
    <updated>2013-02-10T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2013-02-10T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-02-10-Taking-it-out-of-the-school.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">Inspired by the likes of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/JonSimantov"&gt;Jon
Simantov&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/davidblerner"&gt;David
Lerner&lt;/a&gt; as well as the greater Stuy CS family, a few of us have
been working on &lt;a href="http://cstuy.org"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;, Computer Science
and Technology for Urban Youth. Yeah, we backed into the
acronym. Let's bring Stuy CS out of Stuy so we can work on inspiring
a wider range of students.
&lt;p&gt;
Well, last Wednesday we had our inaugural event. Hosted
by &lt;a href="http://www.techstars.com/program/locations/nyc/"&gt;NY
TechStars&lt;/a&gt; (thanks Moisey), we invited 75 youngsters to an evening
of talks. The idea was to have five different speakers each deliver
words of wisdom and inspiration on a different but related topic.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

First up, John Lee of &lt;a href="http://schoolyourself.org/index.html"&gt;School Yourself&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.com/img/techstars-2-6/johnlee.png" rel="lightbox"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/johnlee.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

John talked about big data. Starting with a question "Who plays Chase
on House?" John showed that by looking at huge data sets we can,
relatively easily, come up with the answer. John showed that problems
such as question answering are really accessible to youngsters. They
might just be beginning, but they're not far away from being able to
do some really cool things.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Next up &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/moiseyuretsky"&gt;Moisey Uretsky&lt;/a&gt;. Moisey talked about his journey from
graduating high school through his college days, to starting
companies, successes, failures and the adventure along the way. Moisey was frank and engaging and really gave the kids a lot to think about.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/spikegronim"&gt;Spike Gronim&lt;/a&gt; was next. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;


&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/spike.png" rel="lightbox"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/spike.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Also talking about big data but Spike talked more about the dangers of
misinterpreting data and how different representations can yield very
different results. Spike also spent time giving career advice.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;


&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/spike2.png" rel="lightbox"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/spike2.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;


&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/TimNovikoff"&gt;Tim Novikoff&lt;/a&gt; gave a different perspective. Tim spoke about how his explorations in IOS development lead in a roundabout way to his doctoral studies and very interesting research.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Hitting cleanup was Gerry Seidman of &lt;a href="http://www.tactonic.com/company.html"&gt;Tactonic Technologies&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Gerry gave a whirlwind talk about many of the things he's worked
on. As he said "I don't have time to talk about anything, so I'll talk
about everything." Highlights included the latest touch technology he's
working on as well as vacation man++.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;f
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/vacationman.png" rel="lightbox"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/vacationman.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Gerry also dispensed words of wisdom to the audience.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/gerryadvice.png" rel="lightbox"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/techstars-2-6/gerryadvice.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

While each talk was different, there were common themes:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do something you're passionate about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build stuff and do stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Journey can begin in unexpected ways.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

It was a great first event. We're very excited about &lt;a href="http://cstuy.org"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt; and are looking to roll out more
programs including more talks, classes, mentoring, internships and
more. We're also planning professional development opportunities for
computer science teachers.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

We'll be putting some of the attendees' takes on the event up on the
CSTUY &lt;a href="http://cstuy.org/blog"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; over the next few days.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

To hear about our latest, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cstuyrun" class="twitter-follow-button" data-show-count="false" data-size="large"&gt;Follow @cstuyrun&lt;/a&gt; &lt;script&gt;!function(d,s,id){var
js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0];if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js";fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document,"script","twitter-wjs");&lt;/script&gt;
on twitter, sign up for our &lt;a href="http://cstuy.org"&gt;mail list&lt;/a&gt;
and keep an eye on the CSTUY &lt;a href="https://cstuy.org/blog"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why we script</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-01-24-why-we-script.md/</id>
    <updated>2013-01-24T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2013-01-24T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-01-24-why-we-script.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I tell my students "the cool thing about what we do is that if we're not happy with the way something works, we've got a shot at fixing it."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That came up this morning so I thought I'd share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I
recently &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.com/2012/12/09/real-projects.html#.UQFhh1L6s7x"&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt;
about the in-term projects my Software Development kids were working
on. Well, now it's time to grade their final projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code is up on GitHub. This morning I was faced with independently
going to every project page and cloning each one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.com/img/github-projects.png" rel="lightbox"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/github-projects.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not fun!!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There had to be a better way. Fortunately all the projects were under a single "organization" and a little digging into the GitHub API reminded me that I could use this url:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
https://api.github.com/orgs/stuycs-ml7-projects/repos 
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which brought up all this nice JSON data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/github-api.png" rel="lightbox"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/github-api.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little poking around in the data finds that each project url is part of a line that starts with "ssh_url." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a little wget, sed, grep and  sh magic later:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
urls=`wget --quiet -O - https://api.github.com/orgs/stuycs-ml7-projects/repos | grep ssh_url | sed "s/.*\(git.*\.git\).*/\1/g"`

for url in $urls 
do
  git clone git@$url
done
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as long as all the projects are under a single Github organization I can easily clone or pull them without having to navigate the Github web site. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commandline FTW!!!!!!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Investing in People</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-20-investing-in-people.md/</id>
    <updated>2012-12-20T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2012-12-20T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-20-investing-in-people.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A little over a year ago, I decided it was time to reach out to my
alums, a group I refer to as the "Stuy CS family" and try to get us
together. The most rewarding part of my job involves the relationships
I've developed over the years but is was always between me and my
alums and them to their classmates. This was an attempt to start
building a network that spanned the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, we had our fourth meetup. Somewhere between fifty and
seventy tech professionals getting together over pizza and drinks. Our
past meetups were always at bars - it was easy - send out an email
with an address, time., and date, and people show up. This time, we
really wanted to include the younger crowd, the 18-20 year olds so a
bar was out. I asked the family if anyone could host and Ethan came
through, volunteering &lt;a href="http://pave.com"&gt;Pave&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pave.com"&gt;Pave&lt;/a&gt; is a pretty neat company. The best way I can
describe them is that they invest in people. It's a place where
backers invest in prospects, not only financially, but socially as
well. I really like the idea and you should all check them out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" height="40%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/pave-justin.jpg" class="img-polaroid" alt=""&gt;

&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Justin talking to the family&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pave folks were really awesome, offering space, helping to
oraganize and also taking part in the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event was great and having it at a company rather than a bar or
restaurant had some unexpected side effects. Since there weren't
nearly as many chairs, people mixed more and as I said, this allowed
the younger set to meet the older alums.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="row" align="center"&gt;
&lt;div class="span4"&gt;
&lt;img width="70%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/pave-tom-ethan-larry.jpg" class="img-polaroid" alt=""&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Larry photobombing Tom and Ethan&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="span4" align="center"&gt;
&lt;img width="70%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/pave-mike-rosanna-jackson.jpg" class="img-polaroid" alt=""&gt;
&lt;div class="caption"&gt;Some of the still in college crowd&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being at Pave made me think that as a teacher, my entire career is
about investing in people. Not in the same way as Pave, but still. My
results aren't financial but in community. Although Pave does have a
financial component to it, I really think they "get it" and wouldn't
be surprised if they end up getting the community rewards as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Layers of a lesson</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-17-layers-of-a-lesson.html/</id>
    <updated>2012-12-17T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2012-12-17T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-17-layers-of-a-lesson.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/turtle-anim.gif" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
My last post I was talking about the fact that as teachers, our
knowledge and experience is frequently trivialized. The tenor of the
times is that anyone can design a course, anyone can teach, and in
fact, we don't even need teachers, just videos or computer based
systems. If you've ever tutored a friend, you're more than qualified. 

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
That might be a strong statement but everywhere you look you see
"education" programs designed and implemented by non teachers. It
seems that it's believed that teaching only involves the most
superficial of transfers of information.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Today, I thought I'd look at a lesson I taught the other week. How
I've seen similar material presented and how my colleagues and I might treat
the subject.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
We use &lt;a href="http://ccl.northwestern.edu/netlogo/"&gt;NetLogo&lt;/a&gt; in
our Sophomore level intro course. It's a highly parallel version of
logo. It's very visual, it's great for modeling and you can introduce
deep, meaningful concepts such as parallel processing in a gentle
manner.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Early on the kids have to learn how to manipulate the turtles. In
NetLogo you write a single program and it's run by all the turtles "at
once." The image above is one of their early "experiments." Have the
turtles wiggle out of the center, but when they get to an invisible
border, start spinning. They do a number of variations on this theme.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; 
A solution might look like this:

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;
; asked in a turtle context
to gospin
  ifelse abs xcor 

&lt;p&gt;
Let's call level one just talking about the solution by looking at the
program as a sequence of instructions. Specifically relating the
instructions to the problem, showing how it solves it, and that's it.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This is the simplest level. A book, video, or online courseware can
approach teaching at this level. A non computer scientist teacher or a
non teacher computer scientist could do so as well. Students might
learn a bit but I wouldn't hope for much inspiration or
creativity to come out of it.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Let's move to level two. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Here we might talk about "what the turtles are doing." They're always
doing something, either wiggling or spinning. This is a step in the
right direction. When done right, the students start thinking about
the problem in a more general sense but they're still looking at the
problem as something that exists only in the world of NetLogo. They
are more likely develop patterns than in level one, but it's still
limited.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Level three is where things get interesting. On the surface, the
problem is just a nice introduction to programming turtles in
NetLogo. At a deeper level, it's an opportunity to introduce the kids
to State Machines. A new way of thinking about problems and problem
solving.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Students understand the idea of a "state." For example, in class,
they're in a "seated state," maybe in a "note taking state," etc. It's
easy to see that they don't know what their day will bring but they
constantly make decisions based on their "state." Likewise, they can
think about the turtle as in a state. It's either in a wiggling state
or a spinning state and based on their situation they can either
continue in their current state or transition to the other one:

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/spin-state.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

This opens up a new way of thinking and it's easy to see how this
extends to other problems, for example, a ghost from pacman:

&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/pacman-ghost-state.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

A good teacher thinks about working across these levels. He adjusts
based on the class and looks for opportunities to develop these deeper
concepts.&lt;/pre&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Who's missing from the picture</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-12-whos-missing-from-the-picture.html/</id>
    <updated>2012-12-12T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2012-12-12T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-12-whos-missing-from-the-picture.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
So, it's Computer Science Education Week. Full of rah rah events and everyone's gung ho about teaching computer science.


&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
You all know that CS Ed is what I've dedicated most of my life to and
maybe that's why I'm "not feeling it" in terms of CS Ed Week. Let me
explain.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday there was
a &lt;a href="http://csedweek.eventbrite.com/"&gt;Twitter Conversation&lt;/a&gt;
led by a "national panel of thought leaders in the field." Click on
the link. If it's still active you can see the list of "facilitators"
they were highligthing.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I know some of the people and heard of some of the names and I do
respect some of them. The problem is that if you look down the list
you'll notice something missing. There are &lt;b&gt;zero&lt;/b&gt; K-12 teachers on the
list. None, not one. Some of the people on the list taught in the
past. I don't know how long and in what capacity, but there are no
current teachers. None of us current teachers are worthy "thought leaders?"

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This is a big danger with respect to CS Education. There are a small
handful of us on the ground, actually teaching, with a strong CS
background and with &lt;b&gt;real&lt;/b&gt; successes. 

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I know there aren't many of us. People with a strong CS background
that have decided to become career teachers but there are a
few. Stuyvesant barely had a single AP CS class when I started teaching
here and now we have nine teachers. We've exposed and inspired student
after student to CS. People dismiss us -- "You're Stuyvesant, you have
gifted kids." We do have great kids, but then why haven't programs like
ours sprouted up at other high performing schools? I'd like to think
I've had something to do with our success.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
So, here we have an incredibly successful program but no one wants to
engage us in terms of improving and developing CS Education. I know a
handful of other great CS Educators around the country. They've
similarly felt ignored, rebuffed, and unengaged. 

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I think the problem is twofold. First, our society has taken to
blaming teachers for society's woes and places little value in what we
do. Second, education is the one field that everyone thinks they're an
expert in. You went to school so obviously you're qualified to
teach. There's a huge difference in what I do and with giving a few
guest talks.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I've tried to engage NYC's DOE a number of times. According to Mayor
Bloomberg, the Academy for Software Engineering (afse) was my
brianchild but the DOE didn't pay any regard to my early suggestions,
I had no voice in the development process and when push came to shove,
the DOE decided to hire a consultant with a track record far more
limited than mine or my team's. I finally gave up asking how I would
be involved.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I'm also a CSTA member. In fact, I'm a NY State CSTA Advocate.  I've
reached out for help and to offer it over the years but responses
have been lukewarm at best.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I'm here, my colleagues are here. We want to do more but apparently
educators need not apply.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Back to the Twitter Conversation. Here are just a few tweets and some
comments:

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Tweet: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="blockquote"&gt;
More and more online resources like @codecademy mean computing clubs
without a highly trained CS Teacher are possible. #csedweek
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comment&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt; I like codecademy and like the fact that they're engaging
educators, but when I read this it screams to me "doesn't get it." I
just taught a lesson today that on the surface seems like it could be
covered by some automated service but there's so much going on between
the lines. 

It's like saying "we don't need history teachers, let them read a book or watch a movie." If the tweeter said that when commenting on teaching history, the tweeter would be laughed out of the room.

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tweet: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="blockquote"&gt;
YES! RT @ruthef If we want CS teachers, we need to increase teacher
pay and partner with industry to get tech into the classroom!
#csedweek &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Comment&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt; It has more to do with the lack of respect payed to
teachers. No matter how much you raise pay, it won't compete with
private industry. Also, what makes a great tech person doesn't
necessarily make a great teacher. You need that rare union of both.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tweet: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="blockquote"&gt;
One of the problems we have with CS Education is that not
enough research is bring done. Not teaching or results. #CSEdWeek
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Comment&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt; Research? How about talking to the teachers on the ground and
helping build more of them.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tweet: &lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="blockquote"&gt;
Encouragement works. There are amazing tech girls @superandomness
@temiri Just awarded 310 outstanding girls http://www.ncwit.org/blog
#CSEDWeek
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Comment&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt; Yes, but who are you encouraging. I've had many NCWIT winners
come from my program. Usually, the most deserving young ladies lose
out to young ladies who are lesser candidates but better essay
writers. In any event, we've already done the hard work at Stuy
inspiring the kids. By the time NCWIT gives the awards, we've already
done the hard work. How about helping us rather than taking credit for
our work.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are those of us out there who have succeeded in spite of a lack of support. Why not engage us, use as as models, or at the very least, study us and decide that we don't know what we're doing.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
So, where does this leave us?

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I'm still fighting the fight. I'm still trying to get NYC and
Stuyvesant to recognize CS as a department and help me train teachers
and build programs around the city, but I'm not hopeful.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Meanwhile the train lurches forward.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
About a year ago I was speaking to a friend of mine who's well placed
in the tech world. He had just met with a number of movers and shakers
about CS and technical education. His take away: if we go the way
they're looking to go, maybe we're better off not doing anything.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I share that fear. No one's pushing for CS Education harder than I am
but I fear that we will get "CS Ed" as opposed to CS, much like many
of us feel "Math Ed" has hurt math education in our country.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I'll close with the sentiment shared with my by another high level
tech person after another meeting with movers and shakers. He told me:

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
"There are a small handful of successes, like you at Stuy, but
basically, we're f*cked."
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Real Projects</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-09-real-projects.html/</id>
    <updated>2012-12-09T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2012-12-09T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-09-real-projects.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">This post was supposed to be about varsity academic teams but I wanted
to share something else first.

&lt;p&gt;
For years I was unhappy with our "research" course but due to the
misguided views of our past administration, I pretty much had to keep
it running. Over the same time, I was frustrated by the fact that
there was so much missing in our students computer science related
education. Specifically, kids don't really get to experience creating
large "real" systems from beginning to end. I was also frustrated by
the fact that the previous administration prevented me from creating a
course to address this problem.


&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Due to a particular set of circumstances, I was able to
convert our research course into what is now my "Software Development"
course.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
So far, I'm very happy with the results.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The classes just finished their latest projects. Over the course of
about three week, mostly on their own time, working around homework
and other obligations, student groups designed, developed, tested and
deployed a range of applications. 

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
All the programs
use &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-09-real-projects.html/flask.pocoo.org"&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt; as a web framework. Many
use &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-12-09-real-projects.html/mongodb.org"&gt;MongoDB&lt;/a&gt; to store data and they used a
range of web resources and apis. The students were a little limited by
the time frame of the project and the fact that I just started
teaching them how to use javascript mid project, but they really did a
terrific job.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
A few in particular were a lot of fun:

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://ml7.stuycs.org:7207"&gt;
&lt;img width="400px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/survival-guide.png"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;a href="http://ml7.stuycs.org:7207"&gt;Survival Guide&lt;/a&gt; used
Google Maps to help prepare you for all sorts of disasters ranging
from Hurricanes, to Alien Invasions, to the Zombie Apocalypse.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
A &lt;a href="http://ml7.stuycs.org:6202"&gt;Movie recommender&lt;/a&gt; That used
MoveDB, YouTube, and the NY Times API to find and show info about
movies and actors.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://ml7.stuycs.org:7203"&gt;
&lt;img width="400px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/recipe-pricer.png"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://ml7.stuycs.org:7203"&gt;Recipe Pricer&lt;/a&gt; scrapes &lt;a href="http://allrecipes.com"&gt;allrecipes.com&lt;/a&gt; for a
recipe then uses Google's shopping API to price out the ingredients
(with some interesting results).

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://ml7.stuycs.org:7205"&gt;
&lt;img width="400px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/stuy-page.png"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One group remade the &lt;a href="http://ml7.stuycs.org:7205"&gt;Stuyvesant
Home Page&lt;/a&gt; but since they're using a Twilio test account you won't
be able to see the really neat stuff they did.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
and

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://ml7.stuycs.org:6206"&gt;Tweet Stat&lt;/a&gt; tells you how well
your favorite celebrity spells.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This is just a sampling.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
You can see all of them at &lt;a href="http://ml7.stuycs.org/project2-results.html"&gt;Our Projects Page&lt;/a&gt; and all the code is up on GitHub (linked from the page).

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I'd encourage you to take a look. It would be terrific if you could
give the class feedback either by commenting here or on the project
page.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I can't wait to see what they do for their next projects.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Special thanks to Ben, Moisey and the entire &lt;a href="http://digitalocean.com"&gt;DigitalOcean&lt;/a&gt; team for providing us with server space for all of this.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Making Varsity part 1 - Athletics</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-29-making-varsity-pt-1.md/</id>
    <updated>2012-11-29T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2012-11-29T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-29-making-varsity-pt-1.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've never been a huge fan of the way we do varsity sports, and I say
this as a guy that coached for a number of years. In NYC, we're
governed by the Public School Athletic League or PSAL. Practice time
and lack of facilities make teaching difficult, but my biggest problem
is the fact that most teams cut, that is, if you're not in the top
"n," you're out. So, if our basketball team has, let's say 15 kids on
it, they get exclusive use of the gym every afternoon during
basketball season and no one else can receive coaching or be part of
the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I coached Stuyvesant's fencing team for a bunch of years and I think I
did a pretty good job. We won our share of city titles but while most
coaches ran teams in a traditional way I never cut anyone -- we might
have over thirty people in a tiny room trying to learn how to fence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can be competitive and we often won but high school should be about
exposing kids to new experiences and the exclusiveness of competitive
sports seems to be contrary to this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thats why I love Stuy's rowing club. I've been involved in the program
for about five years now. Prior to that many of my CS students were
involved and they kept saying "Z - you've got to check out the rowing
club." During good weather, every Wednesday, we go up to &lt;a href="http://www.villagecommunityboathouse.org/"&gt;the village community
boathouse&lt;/a&gt; at Pier 40 and row &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Whitehall_Rowboat"&gt;Whitehall
Gigs&lt;/a&gt; - old school wooden boats - 4 oars and a coxswain. We've
rowed up to the Intrepid and down to the Statue of Liberty. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a great activity and everyone's welcome. It's an athletic, team
building activity and very different from what our kids normally
do. It's an opportunity for our non-competitive kids to be involved in
a great athletic activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our competitive kids, they can enter our races. Everyone can take
part in local races (cancelled this year due to Sandy) and we usually
send our top crew and a younger crew to events outside the city. Just
two weeks ago, Stuyvesant sent two crews up to Hull, MA to take part in
The Icebreaker Northeast Regional Youth Rowning Championships. Our
kids got to meet and compete with kids from all over the northeast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;img width="400px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/icebreaker1.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you're wondering about how we do with the non-cut format - both of
our boats won their respective divisions (first fours, the top
division, and second fours). A mixed crew with Stuy alumi won the
first sixes division. And yes, that's Batya in the picture - she coxed
our first fours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;img width="400px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/rowingteam.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be great if kids had more athletic opportunities like this. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next post -- how this relates to computer science.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Alumni Day(s)</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-25-alum-days.md/</id>
    <updated>2012-11-25T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2012-11-25T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-25-alum-days.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The day before Thanksgiving is always fun. For as long as I can
remember, recent graduates descend upon Stuy. For the most part, they
mull around the senior bar but we get our share up in 301. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year was a little quiet but I got to see more than my share of
graduates over the weekend as I attended the 2002 and 2007 class
reunions. I've only been invited to a handful of reunions and really
consider it an honor when I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a great time at both events but here are some notes for those of
you organizing reunions in the future:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Name tags!!!!!! 2002 had them, 2007, not so much.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be a sport, give the teachers the open bar tickets (thanks 2007)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maybe I'm just an old fart, but people are there to reconnect - lower the volume on the music - particularly if you don't have a dance floor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've got to also give particular props to Gary He for keeping the class of 2002 crush lists for the past 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/crushlists.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between the two reunions and the alumni visits prior, I noticed a few
things. First. I was reminded that each years is like a separate
stratified layer. You might know a couple of students from the year
before or after, but that's about it. It's like groundhog day. Each
year has a similar assortment of personalities and archetypes and
exists in semi-isolation. I also noticed that while the graduates were
strongly connected to each other, not so much to the school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are two of the things that I've tried to address by creating &lt;a href="http://family.stuycs.org"&gt;family.stuycs.org&lt;/a&gt;. I'm hoping this
group can bring Stuy grads together across the years. The feedback I
got from people at both reunions was very positive. I'm also counting
on this community to give back to help us in our efforts to enhance
computer science education at Stuy and in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the lack of connection to the school, I do think things will get
better. Stuyvesant's new principal, Jie Zhang was at the 2002
reunion. The fact that she was there was huge. I can't imagine the
previous principal coming in to attend a class reunion. After all,
he's the principal that tried to keep the alums out of Stuyvesant on
multiple occasions. There was also a point in the evening when one of
our alums was telling Principal Zhang that many graduates wanted to be
more connected to Stuy but felt alienated. She seemed shocked and
emphasized that graduates should be welcome at and feel part of the
community. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a tiring weekend -- too many late nights, but a good one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sense good things to come.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Back to Work</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-02-back-to-work.md/</id>
    <updated>2012-11-02T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2012-11-02T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-11-02-back-to-work.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;h4&gt;On going back to work today&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since school was still out due to Sandy, we ran a second online class
yesterday. At the end of the session, which I'll summarize below, I
told the class what I wanted them to accomplish today and over the
weekend. One student queried "you mean no class on Friday :-(?" Alas
no -- while students aren't reporting to school this morning, teachers
are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course the logic as to why is far from sound. Some schools are
fine, some not, in our case, there's no subway service south of 34th
street or coming in from Brooklyn and we're located near the tip of
Manhattan. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are we going to do? Who knows. We don't have lessons to plan and
while Stuy has power, phones and internet are out. Professional
development? Even when planned extensively, I've found it to be mostly
useless (I always have to sit through math PD, for example, learning
how to use a graphing calculator). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we're going to report in for no real purpose. Best I can figure,
the city wants teachers in so they can call it a professional
development day then they can try to change things so that students
will report during Brooklyn Queens day next semester thus restoring
one instructional day lost this week. Not a bad idea to recapture the
day but to make teachers - coming from all over the area - trudge in
for no purpose just to play politics is distasteful but unfortunately typical. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add to the insult, not only are us teachers still in the dark as to
what's going on, we weren't even told when to report until after
midnight yesterday. I woke up at my usual 5:00am to exercise but first
checked my email -- waiting was an email from Chancellor Dennis
Walcot. I recieved it at 12:52 this morning. This was when I was first
told that I was to report to school at 10:00am. I can't believe this
decision couldn't have been made and emailed out a few hours
earlier. In any event, I'm waiting until 10:00 to get in - I've often
found the building locked when I've shown up before official opening hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now for the part of my job that I actually enjoy:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;How did yesterday's online class go?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today's class was a wrapup of a mini project -- basically an
add-a-line story site. You can see an unfinished version that two of
the students put together &lt;a href="http://ml7.stuycs.org:5200"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. You can
see more of the stuff we are using on our &lt;a href="http://github.com/organizations/stuycs-ml7"&gt;class github
page&lt;/a&gt;. The students are
using &lt;a href="http://flask.pocoo.org"&gt;Flask&lt;/a&gt; which is a python website
generator along with &lt;a href="http://www.mongodb.org"&gt;MongoDB&lt;/a&gt;. We had to tie
up some loose ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We again broadcast a Google+ hangout live through YouTube and we again
used a google doc as a chat space. This time we used the right hand
side bar for comments and only used the document for more permanent
material (a web refernce for example). It worked much better.  The
vertical flow of comments on the sidebar were much easier to track and
work with than a freeform document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session still had the time delay problem and the feedback loop is
still a killer but the students again seemed to enjoy the
experience. This is clearly not a replacement for in person teaching,
but again, better than nothing on a day off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;And a note on the Stuy CS Culture&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seniors were game for this experiment and would be happy to go
again today if we were able to.  They also continually surprise me in
little ways. When we started this mini project, we all had to learn
how to use MongoDB (myself included). At first I had a hard time
confirming that they had done the outside work to learn the MongoDB
specifics. Only as they continually gave me better alternatives to my
approaches did I know that they were on top of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, my sophomores were much less receptive to an online
class during the hurricane days. A handful wanted to give it a go, but
the majority never responded to my email. Why was that? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a few thoughts. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A big reason is that I've only been with my sophomores for a short
time. We haven't yet built the rapport and culture that exists in my
senior classes. I always notice a difference in class attitude around
Halloween but we really don't have the feeling of family until late
November or some time in December.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sophomores are in a required course, the seniors an elective. I
think this is secondary to the culture / rapport but I'm sure it has
an effect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I believe the seniors have a better understanding that what we're doing in class is to their benefit and the sophomores are still &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to have to pay more attention to the time line from when
students come into my class and when they become part of "the family."&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
  </entry>
</feed>
