<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>C'est la Z</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description>C'est la Z</description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 01:43:34 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>You have to trust the kids</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/trust-the-kids/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org45ea67b" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org45ea67b"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org45ea67b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A week or so ago I wrote about the event we had to kick off 
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-tech-kickoff"&gt;Hunter College's partnering with the NY tech community&lt;/a&gt; to build a
Hunter to tech pipeline. Each table had two Hunter students and a
group of tech professionals. Each table discussed the Hunter CS
experience and how the tech community can help support the
students. Towards the end of the event a colleague commented that it
was a great idea to have the students essentially run the tables and
how effective it was. I didn't see any other way to do it. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You have to trust the students. Put them in situations where they can
grow.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In addition to the event being a success overall, I think that for the
students it helped to break down barriers. These kids are soon to be
joining the tech community. They'll be interviewing for
internships and then jobs and the whole process can be rather
intimidating. By the end of the event the other week, there weren't
tables of students and professionals but rather tables of people all
having discussions on equal footing. It seems like a small thing. A
minor choice on how to run an event but it can have a subtle but
substantial impact in ways that are hard to see unless you look.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was also reminded of this when reading Alfred Thompson's post on 
&lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/11/how-some-schools-sabotage-computer.html"&gt;school tech management teams and CS teachers&lt;/a&gt;. Alfred wrote about the
possible tension between the needs of CS teachers and the needs of the
rest of the school and the obligations of the people that actually set
up and maintain the technology in a school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Years ago, at Stuy, I skirted the issue by taking on the
obligation of maintaining my own labs. This let me run Linux and
basically do whatever I felt we needed. It also meant my labs wouldn't
be set up for things like standardized testing. This came at a
price. I had to maintain it all myself. This is not to say that the
tech people haven't helped over the years. Some of them have been
terrific but other than swapping out bad machines it all fell on me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course this wouldn't have been possible if it really all fell to
me. It only worked because I was able to enlist the aid of students
who wanted to learn about building and running a Linux network. Sure I
showed them some things but largely we &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-31-devops.html"&gt;figured it out
together&lt;/a&gt;. Basically I trusted the kids with access and control and
gave them a safe place to learn and explore. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It worked amazingly well. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course there were plenty of headaches. There was the time when we
only had one AI/X server for the school and Jon somehow erased all the
shared libraries or the time when I think Paul or Ilya took away read
and execute access from all the system executables. I lost plenty of
sleep and pulled out much hair recovering from these messes and others
but I couldn't get too upset. They were learning, no one got hurt, and
truthfully they never committed any blunders worse than my own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Giving up control to the kids can be nerve wracking at times but it's
worth it. It's why I always found coaching more stressful than
competing back when I fenced. You can do everything to prepare your
athletes but when they're out on the strip, there's nothing you can do
to help. It's all on them. On the other hand, I've always been more
gratified with my athletes or students successes than with my
own. There's something special about enabling others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is not to say that we just turn our students loose.  We have to
set our students up to succeed. Set up the environment and the
circumstance and give the students the tools to work with. At the
event two weeks ago I knew that everyone in the room was a friend or
when I have students plan a hackathon and have them cold call a
company, maybe the company expects the call. There are all sorts of
things we can do behind the scenes to set out students up for success.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We set the stage and if we do it right, the kids won't
fail to impress.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/trust-the-kids/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2017 23:53:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Reunion Season</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/reunion-season/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org393708d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org393708d"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org393708d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thanksgiving is reunion season. Stuyvesant and I'm guessing other high
schools traditionally hold their reunions, at least the five and ten
year ones over the holiday weekend. It makes sense since grads who've
moved away might still be coming to town for family celebrations.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This year, I was invited to the Stuy07 ten year reunion. I considered
crashing the Stuy97 20 year but it was at the same time and too far
away.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm always really flattered and honored when I get a reunion
invite. I've been to my share but I was never the hip popular teacher
that gets invited to these things. On the other hand, I'm sincere,
honest, and loyal so when I do connect with students it's meaningful
and lasting. As one of my students remarked when I was nominated to be
graduation speaker a few years ago and I doubted I would be elected
"hey, you lead the most popular cult in the school" and I guess in
some way the community is a cult, or as I'd rather say, a family. In
any event, whenever I'm invited to a reunion I make my best effort to
attend.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I find the role of faculty at reunions as somewhat amusing – we're
something of a prop. The grads are there and should be there to
reconnect with each other. The teachers are and should be secondary.
From my point of view, there are three groups of students. The ones
that are now part of my alumni family - now friends who I'm in touch
with to varying degrees, the ones that never knew me and the ones that
knew me a bit. For the second and third groups, as a faculty member,
I'm there to remind them of the glory days as a representative of the
institution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As with all reunions I had plenty of "I was never in your class
but …" conversations. I also a number of "I majored in
fill-in-the-blank but just found my way back into tech
so….. thanks." I love these conversations - it gets someone
new into "the family." I also had one conversation that was really a
nice ego boost. One of my guys introduced me to his wife. She
immediately exclaimed "it's so great to finally meet you, he talks
about you all the time!" That was kind of weird until she went on
"…every time he talks about Stuy." That made more sense. It's like
all those times when me and my buddy Ben would reminisce about our
Junior High school days and we'd always get back to talking about
&lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-05-09-my-favorite-year-teacher.html"&gt;Herb&lt;/a&gt;, one of our best and favorite teachers and a major influence on
me while Devorah looked on confused. Eventually she met and got to
know Herb and it all made sense. Another grad added "you think we all
forget about you but you come up more than you know" so I take that as
a shout out to all of the teachers out there who never get to hear
back about how much they are remembered and appreciated.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With tools like email and Facebook it's easier to remain connected to
former students but it's always nice to connect in person. For the
StuyCS family, we have our periodic meetups but for the rest, I love
being included in class reunions and hope to be invited to more in
years to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>community</category><category>reunions</category><category>stuycs</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/reunion-season/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2017 11:41:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Using Emacs 38 - dired</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-38-dired/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org119355a" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org119355a"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org119355a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The 38th installment of Using Emacs is about &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;dired&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;, Emacs' built
in mode for navigating and working with directories.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not a dired power user and in fact am just now making a real
effort to explore it and work it into my daily workflow and
with that in mind, I'd love to hear some configuration and
use suggestions from people who use it regularly.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's the configuration I use:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;use-package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;dired+&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:ensure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:config&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;require&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'dired+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
which merely adds dired+ into the mix.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also started playing with &lt;a href="https://github.com/joddie/pcre2el"&gt;pcre2el&lt;/a&gt; which allows me to use the more
usual regex syntax in place of Emacs regex syntax in both dired and
other places. This is a big win for me since I never remember all the
escaping rules for Emacs regex.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;use-package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;pcre2el&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;:ensure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;:config&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;pcre-mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Finally, abo-abo and jcs have both written about new features in ,
Ivy/Swiper/Counsel that allow you to use ivy-occur to dump results
into a dired buffer (&lt;a href="http://irreal.org/blog/?p=6760"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://oremacs.com/2017/11/18/dired-occur/"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;) but to get that to work, I needed to
install &lt;a href="https://github.com/mhayashi1120/Emacs-wgrep"&gt;wgrep&lt;/a&gt; and also had to install and setup &lt;a href="https://github.com/junegunn/fzf"&gt;fzf&lt;/a&gt; which looks to be
useful.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;use-package&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;wgrep&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;:ensure&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;setq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;counsel-fzf-cmd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"/home/zamansky/.fzf/bin/fzf -f %s"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To help get started here are links to a couple of cheat sheets:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/refcards/pdf/dired-ref.pdf"&gt;dired reference card&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://harryrschwartz.com/assets/documents/dired-cheatsheet.pdf"&gt;another dired cheat sheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'll probably use dired more frequently but again, would love to hear
how other people are using it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Fg7HmmRYWy8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>emacs</category><category>learning</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-38-dired/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Motivating and understanding quicksort</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/quick-sort-starting/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org2eb047e" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org2eb047e"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org2eb047e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thks question was posed the other day - how can one get students to
truly understand the quicksort algorithm?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've written a few posts about quicksort. The last time I did a &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-03-12-select-to-sort.html/"&gt;lesson
writeup&lt;/a&gt; on the subject I wrote about first looking and quickselect and
then moving to the quicksort. The class was first faced with the
problem of writing a routine to find the Kth smallest item in an
unsorted data set. The first solution was n&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; and then refined to a
quickselect. This led directly to the quicksort. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I liked the lesson and I think it worked well when I taught it but
that was partly due to the overall tenor of that particular group of
students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A similar approach develops the quicksort in a similar way but is
both more direct and accessible.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The motivating problem is to put one item in a data set in its proper
place. You could select one person in class and arrange the class so
that the selected student is in their proper size place, that is
everyone shorter on one side, taller on the other. You could also do
this for age. A similar exercise could be done with any number of
manipulatives.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This operation of arranging the rest of the set around one selected
item or person is very easy and in fact it's trivial to show that this
can be done in linear time. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once we've done this arrangement, we can discuss what we can infer
from this new arrangement. We can now tell that:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;everyone to the left of the "pivot" is less than the pivot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;everyone to the right is greater&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pivot element is at its true location if the list were
sorted. That is, if we started arranging around item k, then we've
moved item k to the kth location in the dataset.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From here it's a small jump to the quicksort algorithm, just repeat
the process on the left and right data sets.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This approach not only makes the algorithm and its development clear
and simple but it also can be used to illustrate the worst case n&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;
behavior. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The whole thing, minus the coding, can also be done as an unplugged activity.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In case anyone's interested, I also wrote a post on subtle
implementation errors when writing the quicksort (&lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-03-17-subtle-errors-sorting.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) and also
looking at the qucksort from the point of view of different
programming paradigms (&lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-03-14-sorting-from-top-and-from-bottom.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>algorithms. unplugged</category><category>cs</category><category>programming</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/quick-sort-starting/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2017 14:34:05 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hunter CS and NY Tech - it takes a village</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-tech-kickoff/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org2163607" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org2163607"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org2163607"&gt;

&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hunter-tech/hunter-tech1.jpg" alt="hunter-tech1.jpg" align="center" height="400"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="figure-number"&gt;Figure 1: &lt;/span&gt;The NY Tech community and Hunter CS at Yext&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
One of my goals when I came over to Hunter was to help establish
Hunter CS as the place to be for CS in the city. Hunter already had a
solid CS program before I joined but it isn't well known. It also
doesn't have an established tech culture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's an ambitious goal but if it can be done, what a game changer. A
lot of people talk about equity, diversity, and social justice but if
we can establish Hunter as the place to be for CS in NY, what a
win. An affordable, accessible institution where you can get a great
CS education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The truth of course is that I can't accomplish this - at least not by
myself. I'm just one person. Fortunately, there are so many wonderful
people in the New York Tech community that want to help bring
opportunities to the kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last Thursday evening we got the ball rolling. Twenty five
representatives from the tech community got together at &lt;a href="http://yext.om"&gt;Yext&lt;/a&gt; with
about a dozen of our Hunter College CS students. The conversation
started with a discussion of perceptions of Hunter and the students
sharing what their experiences were like. By the end we were all
brainstorming as to how we can work together to best prepare Hunter
students to become members of the New York Tech community. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know the students left the evening energized and I did as well. I
hope our friends in Tech felt the same.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hunter-tech/hunter-tech-max-jess.jpg" alt="hunter-tech-max-jess.jpg" align="center" height="400"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="figure-number"&gt;Figure 2: &lt;/span&gt;Max talking about Hunter to Jess and the rest of the table&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had representatives from (in alphabetical order)
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Animoto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beeswax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Civic Hall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eBay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genacast Ventures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JW Player&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meetup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MongoDB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Motivate (Citbike)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quentin Road Ventures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two Sigma&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Union Square Ventures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workbench&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yext&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
at the event and then there were plenty of people who want to be part
of this who couldn't make it on Thursday.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I told the participants at the event that I can't make this happen. I
can merely get the people together who actually can. I'm grateful to
all my friends who are now a part of this and I'm looking forward to
working with  them, my students and my colleagues  to create 
a Hunter CS to Tech Community pipeline that's second to none.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>tech community</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-tech-kickoff/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 23:09:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Moocs - High Production value, Bad Questions</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/moocs-bad-questions/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org5d0254c" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org5d0254c"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org5d0254c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most mornings, I start my day with a workout. Sometimes I run,
sometimes I use my bike trainer. Dealing with plantar
fasciitis since last June, it's mostly been the bike. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I occupy the time by either watching YouTube videos or catching up on
&lt;a href="https://cacm.acm.org/"&gt;Communications of the ACM&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.americanscientist.org/"&gt;American Scientist&lt;/a&gt;. I'm about 6 months
behind on both.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Inspired by some talk in one of the CS Ed Facebook groups, I thought
I'd use the time to start going through some MOOCs. I started with
Udacity's Intro to Information Security. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm only in lesson 4 but it's pretty light weight and generally well
presented but I keep seeing the same thing that pisses me off about
moocs. At the end of the day the video is just a lecture and what's
worse, a lecture with no feedback loop. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Don't get me wrong, I love the fact that Udacity and the others have
their material up online and that I can get to it free of charge but I
don't love the fact there are people that still believe putting a computer
in front of a kid is better than a teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think this quiz question is pretty representative of what I'm
talking about. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/mooc-question.png" alt="mooc-question.png" align="center" height="400"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="figure-number"&gt;Figure 1: &lt;/span&gt;Typically bad mooc question&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's just a silly inline quiz question and not a particularly
important one but it pisses me off.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start with, it uses the word  &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;could&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;  not &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;did&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;. That means
that every answer is correct. In fact an asnwer  choice like
"we're more secure because we have this really good engineer named
Stanley" could be given and would be a correct answer since  the
vendor &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;could&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; base their claim on Stanley's awesomness, it would
just be a bad idea. Unless you remember the specific ad campaign, you won't
know the answer  and even if you did, internally, they could use any
justification they want.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It reminds me of when my brother was in grade school and he had a test
question of:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Can you name all 50 states in the United States of America?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My brother's answer was "no." He was correct. I don't remember if the
teacher agreed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To be fair, I'm just watching the videos and it's possible that the
readings clarified the question but even so, this is a very bad
question.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yes, it's just a silly quiz but it is indicative of the problem with
any online learning resource and I and I'm sure others find it
frustrating. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't want to come down hard on the lecturer or whomever made the
quiz question. In a class I might ask a question poorly but I have an
immediate feedback loop and can fix things right then and
there. Frustration doesn't build and in the case of holes in  important
conceptual material deficiencies don't develop.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also don't want to come down on free resources that I use and
benefit from.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These types of issues seem small and the autodidacts that succeed in
using MOOCS work around them but if you look at these materials
critically as a teacher it's plain to see that their no substitute for
the real thing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/moocs-bad-questions/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2017 11:55:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Professional Development beyond Scratch</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/election-day-pd-2017/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org30b65f3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org30b65f3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org30b65f3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today was Election Day. One of the few days each year when students
stay home and teachers spend all day attending what is generously
known as professional development.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Years ago I was in a room with a few colleagues when my friend Dave -
one of the best math teachers I know said "you know, every time we
have a PD day in NJ and my wife and I have to scramble to take care of
the kids I get a little annoyed but then think I shouldn't get annoyed
since they're spending the day doing all sorts of valuable PD." He
then said "but then I realize that their PD is probably about as
useful as our PD and I get really angry."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There you have it. This is not to say that there is no good PD but it
seems that the professional development opportunities provided by our
schools have over the years ranged from useless to insulting with
maybe a small bright spot here and there. Historically it's been worse
for CS teachers because we get lumped in with math teachers and have
to spend the day learning about tools and techniques we'll never use
or discussing curricula we never teach.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, when I spoke to JonAlf about rescuing the Stuy teachers for the
day and hosting them at Hunter, he and the other CS teachers were
pretty excited. It wasn't as though I had the magic PD answer but I
was going to provide a space and we'd figure out together what would
be productive and valuable for them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As it turns out, I've been spending a good amount of time these past
few weeks visiting high schools to talk about Hunter CS and when I was
at Bronx Science the topic of Election Day PD came up and I thought
that it would be nice to get the Bronx Science and Stuy teachers
together. After thinking about it more, I recalled that there were few
good PD opportunities for CS teachers who taught advanced classes as
opposed to all the CS PD floating around these days at more of a
beginner level.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I thought that we could change this. In the end, I hosted PD today and
had teachers from Stuyvesant, Bronx Science, Brooklyn Tech, and the
Manhattan Hunter Science High School in attendance. I invited teachers
from a few more schools but in the end we had those four schools and
seventeen teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The original agenda was:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;09:00 - 10:00 : Each school describes it's program and courses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:00 - 11:00 : An intro to Git and GitHub for the classroom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:00 - 11:45 : Sharing neat lessons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:45 - 12:00 : Presentation by &lt;a href="http://chicktech.org"&gt;ChickTech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12:00 - 01:00 : Lunch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;01:00 - End   : Small group lesson and curriculum work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Oh boy did I mess up on the timing. The description and
discussion of school programs took all morning. It was interesting to
hear how each school's program evolved and how they fit into the
school's culture. Brooklyn Tech, for instance is a school where
students declare majors. This has a big impact on what classes kids
have to take and are able to take. This is very different from Stuy or
Science where kids programs are more open ended or MHSHS which is a
much smaller school and has restrictions related to size. It was also
interesting to note Brooklyn Tech's decision to have every student
take APCS-P. Interesting because Brooklyn Tech is one of the country's
largest high schools and most of them should have done well on the
exam. That gave NYC around 1,400 passing AP scores in one shot. On
the other hand none of the other schools present today offered APCS-P
but did have their own intro CS class that students took prior to
APCS-A.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We finished the morning with a visit by Heather from
&lt;a href="http://chicktech.org"&gt;ChickTech&lt;/a&gt;. ChickTech is a non-profit dedicated to retaining women in
Tech. It works with both girls in K12 and also those in industry. My
hope was to get a conversation started and see if there were some
potential avenues of partnership between the organization and the
schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After lunch, the group decided that we should do the Git/GitHub
workshop and JonAlf obliged.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Overall I think the day was a success. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My hope is that today's attendees can form a core group of CS teachers
who teach more advanced courses and we can form something of a support
group for each other. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I plan to try to facilitate future meetings and hopefully we'll be
able to attract more teachers to our group.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All in all I'm very happy with how the day went.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>pd</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/election-day-pd-2017/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 23:08:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Early Interesting Problems - Happy Ladybugs</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/happy_ladybug/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc15e726" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc15e726"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc15e726"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We all love interesting problems. The trouble is that it's hard to
find suitably interesting problems for students when they're just
learning the basics. In the very beginning the problems practically
dictate the solution:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;loop over a list and add all the elements or calculate the sum of a
list of integers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine if  number is prime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert a word into pig-Latin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not that there's no thought involved in solving these but the
students already know the mechanics of solving these by hand so it's a
direct translation into a program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This isn't a bad thing and it is important but it's fun when we get to the next
level. I've found that a number of the &lt;a href="http://hackerrank.com"&gt;Hacker Rank&lt;/a&gt; archived
competitions have "easy" problems that can be a good fit for
beginners. One that I found and really like is &lt;a href="https://www.hackerrank.com/challenges/happy-ladybugs"&gt;Happy Ladybugs&lt;/a&gt; problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problems is basically as follows:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You get a string of letters. Each letter represents a ladybug of a
different color. Each letter also represents a location of the
ladybug.  A space (or underscore in the actual problem) represents a
free space. For example "AABC DDA" is a line of 2 A colored ladybugs
followed by a B colored one, C colored one, a blank space, 2 D colored and then one
more A colored. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can rearrange the line of ladybugs by swapping any ladybug with a
blank space.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A ladybug is happy if it is next to another ladybug of the same
color. The challenge is to determine if all the ladybugs can be made
happy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I like this problem because while it is non-trivial it is very
approachable. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To me, the key is that while you can rearrange the list you
don't have to. You only have to determine if it is possible to make
the ladybugs happy. You don't actually have to do so.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The edge cases are pretty easy to deal with - a string of length one
or two but then a little thought is required.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first insight is that if there are no spaces, you can't rearrange
the ladybugs so all you have to do is scan through the string to test
to see if every ladybug has a neighbor of the same color.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The next insight, and the big one is that if you have at least one
space you can arbitrarily re-order the string. You can show this is
possible  by using a single space to swap any two elements. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;space&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;someletter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;someletter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;someotherletter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;someotherletter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;space&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The final insight is that since you can arbitrarily re-order the
ladybugs as long as you have at least 2 of each color, you can make
them all happy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since my class is currently just starting dictionaries in Python we
solved this with lists and then transitioned to dictionaries.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's a dictionary based solution:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;are_happy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="sd"&gt;'''&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    This might miss some of the real edge cases in the hackerrank&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    problem. I haven't read the problem carefully in over a year and &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    forget what it specified for things like lists of only spaces,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    lists with only one bug etc.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    Also, the Hackerrank question uses an underscore (_) instead of a space.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    '''&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# handle a string of less than 2 ladybugs&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# handle the string of 2 ladybugs - both must be the same and not a space&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;' '&lt;/span&gt;


    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# handle the case of no spaces &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;' '&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# no spaces, every item must be next to one of the same color&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# so we loop from 1 to len-1 and for each item&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# check the one before and the one after&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# if we ever have an unhappy bug, we can just return False&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]:&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# if we ever get here every bug has at least one neighbor of the same color&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# if we get here it means there's at least one space so we can rearrange the bugs&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# however we please so as long as there are at least 2 bugs of each color&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# we can make them all happy&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# replace the spaces with "" since we don't want to count them&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Since we know they were in the string we can rearrange but&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# they're no longer needed&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;replace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;" "&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;""&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# tally up all the bugs to see if there are at least 2 of each&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;bugcounts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;bug&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;bugcounts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;setdefault&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# set to 0 the first time we see this key&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;bugcounts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bugcounts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;


    &lt;span class="n"&gt;counts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bugcounts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;values&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;())&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# if there is any value of 1 in the counts then there's a lone ladybug&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# that can't be made happy&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# so we return True (happy) if there are 0 counts of 1 in our list &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;counts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; 


&lt;span class="n"&gt;bugs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"abaccbe ff eggggggg"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bugs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;are_happy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bugs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I love problems like these. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I just wish there was an easy way to find all contest problems of a
certain level like "easy" or "medium." If anybody knows please share
in the comments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>problems</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/happy_ladybug/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2017 12:47:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Catskills Conf 2017</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/catskills-2017/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgfe78469" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgfe78469"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgfe78469"&gt;

&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/cc-2017/cc1.JPG" alt="cc1.JPG"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Fall in the northeast is a special time. It's the apple harvest, the
leaves change colors, and the
air is crisp and clean. One of the best places to enjoy it is up in the
Hudson Valley. That's why I love going to &lt;a href="http://catskillsconf.com"&gt;Catskills Conf&lt;/a&gt; each year.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've written about Catksills Conf before and I usually describe it as
"light tech conference meets summer camp."  I love the event but I
love being able to bring my students even more. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hunter's a great place but it's a commuter school. That makes it
harder for the students to get to know each other than if they all
lived in the dorms. Getting away as a group for the weekend helps us
jumpstart the process.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/cc-2017/cc-group.JPG" alt="cc-group.JPG"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/cc-2017/cc-bunkhouse.JPG" alt="cc-bunkhouse.JPG"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then there's the conference itself. In addition to a great assortment
of talks it has all the amazing extras.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/songadaymann"&gt;Jonathan "Song a Day" Mann&lt;/a&gt; has been with us all three years of the
conference to write summary songs for each day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iM2RmmJrBTI" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
There are hikes
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/cc-2017/cc-hike.JPG" alt="cc-hike.JPG"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Workshops like blacksmithing
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/cc-2017/cc-blacksmith.JPG" alt="cc-blacksmith.JPG"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
a live birds of prey show
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/cc-2017/cc-bop.JPG" alt="cc-bop.JPG"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
not to mention folk music and square dancing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All of this makes for a great experience but maybe the best part is
that everyone is living together in the &lt;a href="http://ashokancenter.org/"&gt;Ashokan Center&lt;/a&gt;. The conference
doesn't allow questions after talks because the speakers are all
living with the attendees for the weekend. We eat in the same
cafeteria, go on the same hikes, relax at the same bonfire, and sleep
in the same bunkhouses. As one of my students said:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There’s just something about sharing a conversation on the cloud
computing network with someone who’s visiting from London while
shooting basketball hoops in the middle of the woods that makes for a
real take away experience!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've had the good fortune to be able to bring my students up to
Catskills Conf in the Fall for each of the last three years. Here's
hoping that the tradition can continue for many more.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/catskills-2017/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2017 00:46:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>It's nice to be appreciated</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/nice-appreciated/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd706874" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd706874"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd706874"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today was my 50th Birthday. I'm usually pretty low key on birthdays
and today was no different. I got up, exercised, went to work, taught
my class and went back to my office for office hours.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What a great surprise when all of a sudden my students from last year
appeared at my office with a Happy Birthday a card and a cake:
&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/cake.jpg" alt="cake.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It felt pretty terrific. I wasn't expecting this and was really moved.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We don't make the big bucks but little things like this make me feel
pretty terrific as a teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/nice-appreciated/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 21:27:53 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>