<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>C'est la Z</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description>C'est la Z</description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/rss.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 18:20:56 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Standards - Who are they for?</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/standards-who-for/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org8f6985d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org8f6985d"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org8f6985d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The big push at last year's CSTA conference was the release of the new
CSTA K12 standards. It seemed that every other session was pushing
them in one way or another. I've been meaning to share my thoughts
about them or, more specifically, learning standards in general for a
while but with announcement about federal funding for CS coming from
the White House last week I thought it was time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Before diving into CS standards lets talk about math.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start I have yet to meet a math teacher that needs
"the Standards" to know what to teach. Some how or other math teachers know
they're supposed to teach in an algebra or geometry class. When NY
moved to "integrated math" teachers were able to re-sequence classes
without the benefit of "the standards" and when NY went back to
Algebra, Geometry, then Alg 2 and Trig, teachers had no problem
reorganizing classes again.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
New teachers didn't go to "the Standards" to learn the ropes. Schools
defined syllabi, teachers observed each other, shared resources, used
lesson plan books and in general knew what they were supposed to teach
and at what level.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my quarter century of teaching, always in a math department we
spent a lot of time talking about what we taught, when we taught it,
how we taught it and at what level but until common core was forced
down our throats we NEVER discussed "the Standards." We discussed our
students, where we thought we could take them, and how to get them
there. Somehow our students did alright.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
More recently, the push has been on "The Standards," common core in particular.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Common standards sound good - kids in every school will learn the same
things at the same level - but I contend that they aren't about
learning. They're about testing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's look at a few of the math standards. These were pulled directly
from the Common Core:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Derive the equation of a circle of given center and radius using the
Pythagorean Theorem; complete the square to find the center and radius
of a circle given by an equation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Use coordinates to prove simple geometric theorems algebraically. For
example, prove or disprove that a figure defined by four given points
in the coordinate plane is a rectangle; prove or disprove that the
point (1, √3) lies on the circle centered at the origin and containing
the point (0, 2).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Derive using similarity the fact that the length of the arc
intercepted by an angle is proportional to the radius, and define the
radian measure of the angle as the constant of proportionality; derive
the formula for the area of a sector.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These aren't about deep thinking and problem solving. They're about
very specific skills or techniques. They're also easy to put on a
test. Much easier then assessing a students real problem solving ability.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Common Core comes hand in hand with standardized testing which is then
used to punish students, teachers, and schools. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We keep hearing about individualized instruction - meeting the kids
where they are but the standards tell us that kids MUST know specific
things at specific times. You can't have both. In the best case, with
"the standards" we can only meet students "where they are" within
annual bands.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What has this led to? Narrowing curriculum for one thing. Since schools are
evaluated based on the standardized exam in core subjects focus
narrows and other subjects fall by the wayside. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Arguably worse is selective teaching within common core subjects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Take for example, Geometry. The course is really "Logic and Deductive
Reasoning using Euclidean Geometry as a Platform" but it's generally
called Geometry. This class is supposed to be about getting kids to
think. I've already shared a few standards above but let me tell you
about an open secret - many schools don't really teach proof -
arguably the most important part of the class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my last year at Stuy I graded Geometry regents for the city. I
graded exams for two highly regarded unscreened schools. One that was
lauded in a State of the Union address and the other equally hyped. I
graded all of each school's students geometry regents so it wasn't
just a sampling. Out of all the papers, only two or three scored more
than 2 out of 9 points for the proof question and most were entirely
left blank.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What happened? Proof is hard to teach and hard to learn but it's also
only a small part of the standardized exam. It's critical for a
school's survival and for the student to graduate that a passing score
is earned. Rather than spending a large amount of time on few points
and probably get a limited return I've been told that many schools
spend much more time on topics that area easier to teach and have more
weight on the exam. This makes the school look better and helps the
student graduate but arguably the most important aspect of the course
has been minimized.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
High stakes testing leads to gaming the system. Common core standards
come hand in hand with high stakes testing. We see the same with AP
exams - there are schools that force students to take exams even when
they are woefully prepared and mostly fail because this helps the
school shoot up in the ratings.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is what the common core math standards have given us. They're not
for teachers - we don't need them - we know what to teach and only
wish that the bean counters would indeed allow us to meet students
where they are. Standards are about testing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's move on to CS standards. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It might not be fair to compare CS to math since K12 math education
has been around much longer and is more well defined and in theory
having a set of standards gives us a common language to discuss,
compare, and contrast all the content providers and curriculum
developers out there. On the other hand, I also believe that with well
prepared teachers who understand content and pedagogy the value isn't
all that great. It's also worth considering the fact that nothing
really makes the CSTA Standard  writers special. There's no reason to
think that another group - be they a handful of teachers or a content
provider can't do a comparable job.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here are some selections from the CSTA standards:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Design and develop a software artifact working in a team. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Compare and contrast various software licensing schemes (e.g., open source, freeware,
commercial). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Design, develop, and implement a computing artifact that responds to an event (e.g., robot
that responds to a sensor, mobile app that responds to a text message, sprite that responds
to a broadcas
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Demonstrate the value of abstraction for managing problem complexity (e.g., using a list
instead of discrete variables). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Design algorithms u sing sequence, selection, and iteration. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Discuss techniques used to store, process, and retrieve different amounts of information
(e.g., files, databases, data warehouses). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Compare and debate the positive and negative impacts of computing on behavior and
culture (e.g., evolution from hitchhiking to ridesharing apps, online accommodation rental
services). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Use simple encryption and decryption algorithms to transmit/receive an encrypted
message. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Decompose a problem by creating new data types, functions, or classes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Evaluate algorithms (e.g., sorting, searching) in terms of their efficiency, correctness, and
clarity. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Use data analysis to identify significant patterns in complex systems (e.g., take existing data
sets and make sense of them). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's nothing wrong with these. They aren't specific enough to
develop lessons from but, they can provide a
consistent framework to discuss different offerings. Were the much
more specific, we'd have the same issue I railed about with the math
standards so this is a good thing. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Actually, in general, I don't have a problem with these standards. I
might agree with some parts and disagree with others but that's
neither here nor there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To me the big concern on standards is what will they actually be used
for. It's nice to think that it's a set of guidelines from which we
can develop strong local experiences but I think this is somewhat
naive. As states and the federal government bring CS Education into
the fold there's no reason to believe that CS will be special. CS Ed
will go the way of other subject areas. That means that whatever
standards governments adopt, they will likely be used for high stakes
tests rather than for true education. If you look to see how the
sausage is made you can see the harm standards and standardized
testing has wrought  in subjects like math. CS Ed won't be far behind.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While we should be proud of all the work that's going on in our
community it's more important now than ever to keep an eye on the
overall big picture and be aware of how work intended for one purpose
within the community can be used very differently by those outside of
it. This is particularly important for advocates  not in public schools. Public
schools educate the majority of American students so CS4All means
public schools. Standardized testing won't affect private schools (or
private charters in many cases) nor will they affect colleges and in
fact will be a boon to EdTech companies selling there wares. Many of
the loudest voices in CSEd come from these contingents - it's
important that they look to the greater issues, form their own
opinions, and then act on what they believe is right.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>ed</category><category>policy</category><category>standards</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/standards-who-for/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 18:05:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Programming Idioms</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/programming-idioms/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc49d4ee" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc49d4ee"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc49d4ee"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I just read Jeff Yearout's recent post titled &lt;a href="http://k12csteaching.blogspot.com/2017/10/the-beginners-garden-of-concepts.html"&gt;The Beginner's Garden of
Concepts&lt;/a&gt;. Not directly related but it got me thinking about
programming idioms.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've been using the phrase "programming idiom" for years to describe a
short useful recurring code construct. I didn't realize that it was
officially "a thing" until doing a web search on the phrase years
later.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As our students grow from newbies on I think it's helpful for them to
see recurring and related patterns and programming idioms gives us a
name to apply to many beginner patterns. An early idiom might be
"finding the smallest in a list:"
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dataset&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;min_index&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dataset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dataset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dataset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;min_index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;min_index&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another is the very similar and more general "do something on every
item in a list:"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dataset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# do something to or with dataset[i]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
By talking about constructs like these as idioms it helps students see
and develop coding patterns. It also helps them to build mental
abstractions. Each of the above idioms are a few lines of code but
each are also a single concept. Students learn to think of them as the
concept.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
When students learn about list comprehensions in python they'll
rewrite the "do something…" more like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dataset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
but the pattern or idea is the same.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Other early idioms might include swapping variables:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;tmp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tmp&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and loops until an exit condition are met:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;not_exit_condidtion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# do stuff&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;modify&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;variable&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;that&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;checks&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;exit&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;condition&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even more difficult concepts like recursion can be described in an
idiomatic way:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;BASE_CASE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;something&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;new_x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;modify_to_eventually_get_to_base_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;new_x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Patterns like these, or idioms, come up over and over again. We don't
have to explicitly mention them in our teaching but I think it's
helpful to our students if we do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>programming</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/programming-idioms/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 15:51:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>NYC CS4All - This Is Not The CS We're Looking For</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/this-is-not-the-cs-were-looking-for/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org910de83" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org910de83"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org910de83"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It's no secret that I'm something of an old curmudgeon in the K12 CS
Education world and I've been critical of a number of initiatives and
organizations over the years but I've been pretty quiet on the CS4All
movement in NYC Department of Education. I've had and any number of
concerns though.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This past week at the inaugural meeting of New York City's CSTA
chapter we got a taste of the &lt;a href="http://blueprint.cs4all.nyc/"&gt;NYC CS4All Blueprint&lt;/a&gt;. A highlight was
this video:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/224494221" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Along with the &lt;a href="http://blueprint.cs4all.nyc/resources/3/%0A"&gt;supporting web page&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
TL;DR - in a elementary school CS class, the students kept tapping out
drumbeats on the desk because they had drumming class the period
prior. Now the drumming teacher is teaching rhythms that match
segments of HTML so the students can tap and chant the line as a
memory aid. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sure, it's nice when teachers can work together to support each other
but at the end of the day this is a mnemonic aid to memorize
HTML. Nothing particularly innovative here. Mnemonics like this are
great until there are too many to keep track of or ones that are too
similar. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The part that saddened me was that this  was the video that was
chosen  as a highlight, an exemplar. It was OK but there was
nothing new or innovative. What was worse was that there was no
computer science.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The kids were memorizing HTML. As we watched the video, my neighbor
nudged me and asked "why are they memorizing HTML?" I would ask the
same question. Now, I do think that HTML or some other mechanism to
create content that can be shared with the world is important. Having
students get there work out in the word can be tremendously rewarding
and motivating. Also, although I'm not sold on it, some say that HTML
is a good stepping stone to CS but still. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's try an experiment.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Imagine that lesson but instead of HTML the kids were learning
Microsoft word so instead of a chant for &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a href=""&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; you have a
chant for putting a link into a word document or instead of a chant
for &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;somethingbold&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; you have a chant like
&lt;code&gt;control-b-typestuff-then-control-b&lt;/code&gt;. Same lesson, same technique,
still no CS. You could also say that this was just one video and maybe
most of the year is about real CS. Maybe, but then why highlight this
on the CS4All web site as a featured resource.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was disappointing but not surprising. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some will say that kids aren't ready for hardcore CS at that
age. That's fine. We can have that discussion but if CS is appropriate
for whatever grade was in the video then it should be real CS. We can
also have endless discussing about what that is but memorizing HTML is
not it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wondered if the video was representative so I looked at &lt;a href="http://blueprint.cs4all.nyc/resources/5/"&gt;another&lt;/a&gt;. It
turned out this was also a lesson on HTML and again the video could of
been about any number of subject areas. I will give this one credit
for highlighting that you can do "unplugged" activities but it wasn't
really a CS activity.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then there was &lt;a href="http://blueprint.cs4all.nyc/resources/15/"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. No video here but how we structure a CS
lesson. We have this outline:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Warm-up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mini lesson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Independent work time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share session&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Or, as we used to say back in the stone age:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do Now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instructional activity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;summary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Nothing new and nothing CS here. I used that model when I taught math
but deviated from it more and more as I developed my CS teaching
chops.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally I looked at &lt;a href="http://blueprint.cs4all.nyc/resources/24/%0A"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. For full disclosure I have to say that
Eric, the teacher, is a friend of mine and I &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;know&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; he's a dynamite
teacher and I know he knows his stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This video, however was all about differentiation. Just like the other
resources, there's nothing wrong with them per se but there's not
really about CS. You could reskin them for any subject. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also agree with a lot of what Eric says in the video but as CS
Standards take hold and standardized exams become the norm we'll find
that individualized instruction and meeting students where they are
is in direct conflict with the testing that comes with standards. I'll
talk more about that in my standards rant that I keep putting off
writing.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Sure, the resources site has  a page with concepts like algorithms and
many schools, for better or worse, in the upper grades just fall back
on AP offerings but the more I dig the more it's apparent to me that
CS4All in NY will be more about getting something into every classroom
rather than something appropriate and good.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>csed</category><category>curriculum</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/this-is-not-the-cs-were-looking-for/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 14:40:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Using Emacs 37 - Treemacs file browser</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-37-treemacs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org635a407" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org635a407"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org635a407"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've been meaning to get back to making Emacs videos but I've been
having trouble figuring out what to record.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
People have asked for &lt;a href="https://github.com/magit/magit"&gt;Magit&lt;/a&gt; but I only use the basics and I think
there are already some great videos on it out there. I'd also like to
get more comfortable with DIRED mode and then do a video on it but I'm
not there yet. I've also been looking into packages that manage
workspaces like Eyebrowse and Persp-mode but neither are really doing
it for my workflow.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This morning I saw an post on the &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/emacs/comments/7249jt/introducing_treemacs_a_modern_file_project/"&gt;Emacs subreddit&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href="https://github.com/Alexander-Miller/treemacs#treemacs---a-tree-layout-file-explorer-for-emacs"&gt;Treemacs&lt;/a&gt; - a
sidebar file browser similar to what the Atom editor has. It's pretty
slick. I particularly like the integration with &lt;a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/projectile"&gt;projectile&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I suspect I won't integrate a file browser side bar into my workflow -
I've probably spent too many years with Emacs built in buffer commands
but if like that type of interface, definitely check Treemacs out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ACg6RnVdw8k" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>emacs</category><category>learning</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-37-treemacs/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 24 Sep 2017 15:22:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Awesome Cs Revisited</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awesome-cs-revisted/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org0486a3b" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0486a3b"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0486a3b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Saw this tweet the other day so I though I would try to plug the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education"&gt;Awesome CS Education&lt;/a&gt; list I started on GitHub:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/csteachers?src=hash"&gt;#csteachers&lt;/a&gt;...didn't I see a list of CS teacher blogs here recently?&lt;/p&gt;— Pam Whitlock (@PamWhitlock1) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PamWhitlock1/status/910662628757864448"&gt;September 21, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;





&lt;p&gt;
To answer the tweet, the closet thing I know to a list is &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred
Thompson&lt;/a&gt;'s blog roll which is actually a post he wrote on his blog
in 2012. Unfortunately his list can be hard to find and is somewhat
out of date. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The idea of an "awesome" list is publicly hosting a simple site that
is community driven and anyone can suggest additions and edits. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I put up a starter &lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and a few people have contributed but I'd love
to get more people involved. Awesome lists have a number of advantages
over other repositories.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unlike blog posts, the site is easy to find.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unlike private mailing lists or Facebook, anyone can see the content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone can suggest additions (although you need to create a Github
account).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone can download or fork the site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's essentially plain text and is easy to edit (just read the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education/blob/master/contributing.org"&gt;contribution guide&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, there you have it. If you have a blog or resource to share please
submit a pull request. Over time this could be a terrific single
starting point for educators to get to a wealth of resources.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>pd</category><category>resources</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awesome-cs-revisted/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 20:34:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New Term New Tool - Thonny, a Python IDE</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/new-tool-thonny/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org4d99735" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org4d99735"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org4d99735"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last year I &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/new-term-new-tool-replit"&gt;wrote about&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://repl.it"&gt;repl.it&lt;/a&gt;, an online IDE that supports multiple
languages. At the time it had some rudimentary classroom support and
since I started using it, repl.it has become better and better. I
used it last year with my class because I had to start the year in a
lab where I couldn't easily install my own software. I'll continue to
use repl.it - mostly for it's ability to schedule publish and manage
assignments but when possible, I like having my students work
locally. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This year I'm excited about another tool - &lt;a href="http://thonny.org"&gt;Thonny&lt;/a&gt;. Thonny's a simple
Python IDE designed for beginners. I discovered it last year but at a
time when it was impractical for me to use with my students. This
year I can and I'm really liking it. I'm still an Emacs guy and will
continue to use Emacs for my python development (&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-12-python/"&gt;video 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-13-yasnippet"&gt;video 2&lt;/a&gt;) but
for beginners I think Thonny is the way to go.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some of Thonny's highlights:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An integrated Python 3 virtual environment making for ease of
installation and consistency across student installs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A debugger that shows how expressions are evaluated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great visualizations of function calls that make it easier to
understand the call stack and scope&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to look at memory to understand references.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Rather than go into the gory details in text, I put together this
video:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lWaCl0WjNZI" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>teaching</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/new-tool-thonny/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 11:31:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>I Believe CS Teachers are Smart and Capable</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org6880554" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6880554"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6880554"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
People sometimes accuse me of being an elitist CS snob that I feel that CS
teachers have to have advanced CS degrees. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not that at all. Rather, I feel that CS teachers are smart and
capable. Circumstances frequently result in a teacher in front of a CS
class with limited content and pedagogical content knowledge. It's not
ideal but it's reality. Of course I feel that we should do everything
to support and encourage these teachers but we should also insist that
after a reasonable period of time, they know their stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is why I hate it when I hear people in the CS Ed community say
something is too hard. Git's too hard. The command line is too
hard. Functional programming's too hard &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. That's all nonsense. At last
year's SIGCSE conference people from a state, I forget which, was
considering not using the Praxis exam for CS teacher certification
even though the state uses the Praxis exam for other subject
areas. They claimed that the praxis was too hard for CS teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/praxis.jpg" alt="praxis.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I haven't taken the Praxis exam but some friends have. It doesn't
appear to be unreasonable at all&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.2" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fn.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While I can certainly understand a teacher not knowing much when they
start - thrown in due to necessity I think it's ridiculous not to
insist that they ultimately get to real mastery.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A math teacher generally has to know math beyond calculus. Science
teachers have to have gotten through Orgo. English teachers have to
understand Joyce. &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;THIS IS HARD STUFF!!!!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.3" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fn.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think it's insulting to say that CS teachers aren't capable of doing
the same in their subject area.
'
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;whether or not any of
these topics are appropriate for a particular course is discussion for
another time&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.2" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fnr.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;although I'm not a big believer
in standardized exams for certification or in general.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.3" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fnr.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;There are plenty of
lousy teacher prep programs that don't ensure teachers learn the
subject matter they should but the good ones do.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 22:17:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Is the new Secret Sauce ever better?</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-the-new-secret-sauce-ever-better/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orga4ec6ec" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orga4ec6ec"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orga4ec6ec"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I read &lt;a href="http://nancyebailey.com/2017/09/05/xq-super-schools-business-working-to-end-public-high-schools/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; piece earlier today on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/NancyEBailey1"&gt;Nancy Bailey&lt;/a&gt;'s blog. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
TL;DR (although it really isn't too long so you should read it) - it's
on Laurene Powell Jobs, her efforts to "reform" education and why
she's misguided as are most of the well to do non-educators working
hard to change and in many cases privatize public education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Laura posts a nice list of simple, common sense ways to improve
education. I'll repost them here:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For years, research has shown that high school students need more sleep. They should have later start times. .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smaller class sizes would help.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure teachers don’t have so many preparation plans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;End advanced placement classes (IMHO).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve career-technical classes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide rich extra-curricular activities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bring back life skill classes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include a social justice curriculum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include students on the disciplinary board.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide civics education.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure students get opportunities to participate in the arts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work to include the community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure students have access to counselors, and school support staff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every high school should have a great library, a real librarian, and technology and books.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looks very much like what those elite private schools that those rich
non-educators send their kids to.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other day I also overheard a conversation between two
professors. One noted that they had just taught a course totally
online for the first time and that the professor really had fun doing
it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These got me thinking more about all the secret sauce and magic
bullets coming from tech to save education - things like MOOCS or  "personalized"
learning system.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started to wonder - have these &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;ever&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; been pushed on public
schools because they're better or rather because they cut costs (or in
the slightly better case to reach a student that otherwise wouldn't
have any opportunity which, in a way is generally cost related).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I couldn't come up with a single instance. They're always a way to
replace what I consider personalized instruction – you know, when a
teacher has a small class and can personally deal with, learn about,
interact with, and teach the child. Kids spend hours in front of a
screen instead of working with others. Kids do a MOOC (or maybe drop
out of a MOOC) so that you can have your student/teacher ratio reach
ridiculous levels. I've never seen any tech solution rolled out to
public schools because it's better. Only to cut costs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How do I know that it's not better? Well, we have Nancy's list
above. It's what those rich people pay all that money to the elite
private schools for.  If all these solutions the Jobs and Gates of the
world were so much better, wouldn't they insist upon them  for their
own children? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Just some Friday food for thought.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><category>STEM</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-the-new-secret-sauce-ever-better/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 16:32:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Theseus's Curriculum</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/theseus%27s-curriculum/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd031b2b" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd031b2b"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd031b2b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With the school year starting I was originally planning on writing
about my class rules. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Instead I think I'll riff on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt;'s post today titled
&lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/09/curriculum-is-hard.html"&gt;Curriculum is Hard&lt;/a&gt;. I'm guessing I found curriculum design and
development daunting decades ago but at this point in my career it's
something I enjoy. In any event, Alfred got me to thinking - when is a
curriculum your own?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you grab a curriculum complete with lesson plans, assignments; the
whole kit and caboodle and you use it verbatim it's clearly not your
curriculum. It probably also isn't really teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What about the more common case. Math curricula has basically been set
for years. Algebra, Geometry &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/theseus%27s-curriculum/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and then Algebra 2
and Trigonometry. Most books seem to be sequenced in a similar way
and at least in the schools I know about, the math department has some
document listing a day by day list of topics. This makes sense since
you probably have more than one class of each type and you want some
cross class consistency. Particularly during the first weeks of the
semester when kids can transfer and then also at the end of term or
year. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When a teacher uses that departmental document are they using someone
elses curriculum?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What if they create their own homeworks and assigments?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most teachers I know use the department's curriculum but make their
own unit and day to day lesson plans. Most revise them each
semester. Typically these teachers do a little more here or a little
less there depending on a number of factors.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Are they creating their own curriculum?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What if they re-sequence the topics?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How about adding an enrichment topic?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back when I taught math I used the departmental syllabus, as many
texts as I could find, colleagues lesson plans and whatever I could
find but I always pulled it together to something I could call my
own. If I didn't, I wouldn't have been comfortable going in front of
my class. Was it my curriculum? They were certainly my lessons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, when designing a course I start from the end outcomes and work
backwards but when teaching a course, I still look at as many
resources as I can find. I'll pull a little from here, a little from
there and combine that with whatever I can come up with myself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, when is it your curriculum and when is it not? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're just delivering scripted lessons it's certainly not yours.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you know your stuff and you  take someone elses material, make it
your own and add it to your bag of tricks, I think it's now yours as
well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/theseus%27s-curriculum/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;which is really logic and deductive
reasoning using Euclidean Geometry as platform&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>currulum</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/theseus%27s-curriculum/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 22:41:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>CS Teachers - we need you to blog</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-blog/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org8a53e1d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org8a53e1d"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org8a53e1d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At this past year's CSTA conference, a few of us huddled in a corner
voiced a very common lament - "it would be great if more CS teachers
blogged." It really would be. We're still a relatively small
community and while there's some good conversation going on on
mailing lists and on Facebook, those aren't easily discoverable or
accessible and in the case of Facebook, there's a question of
ownership and permanence.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've been blogging on and off since 2010. Around 300 posts. Not super prolific
but I've been doing it long enough to maybe be able to share a bit of
perspective.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not sure exactly why I started. In part I was inspired by my wife
who at the time was blogging about her &lt;a href="http://squid-knits.blogspot.com/"&gt;knitting&lt;/a&gt;. I was also inspired
to share my thoughts after meeting some fellow CS teachers from across
the country at a &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-01-02-welcome.html"&gt;CSTA event in Chicago&lt;/a&gt;. It was stop and go for a while
and then I took a break. I was re-inspired months later after meeting
a couple of CS teachers at another CSTA event - &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=ben%20chun&amp;amp;src=typd"&gt;Ben Chun&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/purplespatula"&gt;Helene
Martin.&lt;/a&gt; Both terrific high school CS teachers at the time who are
unfortunately no longer in the classroom (unfortunate for the kids, I
wish Ben and Helene all happiness and success in all their
endeavors). We all agreed to try to write more and that got me started
again. I've been posting around 50 times a year since.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looking back to when I used blogger, I had 30 - 50 hits on some early
posts and that was mostly just me hitting the site. It didn't matter.
Writing has let me work through my thoughts. It also creates a record of
my thoughts and on how my thinking evolves over time. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over time, people have told me that they've found some of the things
I've written useful or helpful and I'd argue that when people disagree
with something I write, even if they don't comment and I've all I've
evoked is a reaction of "Z's full of crap," it's gotten them to
re-evaluate their own thoughts on whatever the subject and if it's
confirmation of their original beliefs, that's OK.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The important thing is that by blogging I'm getting my thoughts down
"on paper" and sharing them for the world to take or leave as they
please and the more of us who do this, the more we expand the sum
knowledge of CS teaches. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a dispersed community of CS teachers across the country, we need
more people blogging on public platforms not in silos like Facebook.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've heard reasons why teachers don't blog:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;I'm new and have nothing to write about&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sure you do – write a paragraph about your plans for the days lesson
or how it went. Vent your frustrations (but be careful not to get
yourself in trouble). Rave about some students work.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;I don't have time&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yes, this is a tough one. If you have to do PD time, maybe your
supervisor will let you use it for blogging. To be honest, when I'm
writing regularly it doesn't take that long. When I haven't written in
a while it takes longer. In any event. It's important and posts don't
have to be long
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;I'm not a great writer&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This blog is proof that you don't have to be. I'm stilted and ramble
and certainly no Shakespeare. I am the weakest writer in my household
and it's not even close. Even so, we all have something to share.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;I don't know how&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was thinking about proposing a session at next years CSTA conference
where I'd work the group through creating a github pages based
blog. In the meantime, there are a lot of easy ways to start out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://blogger.com"&gt;http://blogger.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordpress.com"&gt;http://wordpress.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and for those who want total control
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://jekyllrb.com/"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub pages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, there's my plea. If you're a CS teacher and you're reading this
please consider blogging. I assure you, we will all appreciate it and
benefit from it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>community</category><category>cs</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-blog/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 19:52:23 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>