<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description>C'est la Z</description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 15:33:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Moving to a new blogging platform</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/new-platform-hugo/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org930c203" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org930c203"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org930c203"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've been using &lt;a href="https://getnikola.com/blog/"&gt;Nikola&lt;/a&gt; to generate this blog since April 2016 -
shortly after I started at Hunter. Prior to that I used &lt;a href="https://jekyllrb.com/"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; for  a
bunch of that and it all started out as a Google Blogger blog.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I moved from Blogger to Jekyll because I wanted to control my content
and also because I wanted to user Markdown. Later I started using
&lt;a href="https://orgmode.org/"&gt;org-mode&lt;/a&gt; markdown for not only my blog but also for tons of other
things. Jekyll became a problem for me because I'm not a Ruby guy I
had issues maintaining Ruby ecosystem installs across all my
machines. Next came Nikola. It was easier for me to maintain because
it's written in Python but even so I've had some issues recently. Not
with Nikola but with other libraries. While I like Nikola I figured
this was a sign and it was time to learn something new.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This time, I'm going to try &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/"&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; written in &lt;a href="https://golang.org/%0A"&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt;. It has native support
for Org-mode  and overall looks pretty spiffy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'll shift over in a couple of days.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're a regular reader and you don't see a new post within a week
it would be a real help of you would let me know. Everything should
transision smoothly but you never know.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thanks!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/new-platform-hugo/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 11:37:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Blight Move</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/blight-move/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org77053e5" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org77053e5"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org77053e5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It was Jon and Amy's wedding. Jon was my student back in the day so
there were a handful of Stuy alums there to celebrate the
occasion. Some, like Jon, I had stayed in touch with and now count as
friends. Others, I knew but hadn't kept up with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was with a cluster of guests and for some reason the conversation
turned to chess computers. I started telling a  story about the my former
teacher &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-05-09-my-favorite-year-teacher.html"&gt;Herb Greenhut&lt;/a&gt;'s Talking Chess Challenger computer. You would
type in your move using modern algebraic chess notation using a kaypad
and the program would not only respond by displaying it's move in said
notation but also speak it in it's best &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0086567/"&gt;War Games&lt;/a&gt; voice.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
D5 TO E6 - PAWN TAKES ROOK
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Herb had a friend Dan,  who was a decent chess player but nowhere good
enough to compete with someone at the theoretical level of the Chess
Challenger at it's higher levels. Even so he came up not only with a way
to beat the computer but also to cause it to have a nervous breakdown.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Dan figured that the computer assumed a sensible opponent so when it
considered its next move it built a tree assuming the human player
would try to find strong moves. Dan would play crazy outlandish moves
so that the computer would have to spend all its time working through
game trees and then settle on a bad move having not found the right
move path. Dan didn't know anything about computer science, search
trees or Alpha Beta pruning but he was a smart guy and just figured it
out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At one point, he made a crazy move and the computer responded
something like "C4 TO E5" and all of a sudden, I hear blurted out from
a voice from across the wedding reception "BLIGHT MOVE!!!!!!!!"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I looked over and it was Mikey, a former student who I had not kept in
contact with who had finished the story. What had happened is that the
computer had started to create new pieces. In this case a "blight"
which we eventually determined could move as either a bishop or a
knight. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The cool thing to me was that this was a dumb story I told my classes in
1994 or 5 and here we were some twenty years later and Mikey
remembered it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You really never know what your students will remember about you or
your classes years into the future.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was reminded of this when I saw this tweet the other day:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;For anyone wondering, this poll was in response to the quote:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;"They may forget what you said, but they will never forget how you made them feel." &lt;a href="https://t.co/QHMXTxjeLA"&gt;https://t.co/QHMXTxjeLA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Adam Boxer (@adamboxer1) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/adamboxer1/status/1041051593255411713?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;September 15, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know the context of the quote but &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/adamboxer1"&gt;Adam Boxer&lt;/a&gt;'s reply in the
tweet stream seems to indicate that it comes from the thought that
they won't remember the content so it isn't important as long as the
kids feel good about themselves. The truth is that as a K12 teacher
we're responsible for both the students development in the subject and
also as a person and while people might not remember the name of the
teacher that taught them anything in particular and in spite of people
saying they learned "nothing in school" the truth is there's quite a
bit that most people do learn from their teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In terms of how students feel, I'm guessing there are some kids who
felt that I made them feel smart or capable and probably some that I
ended up inadvertently turning off but the majority probably didn't
feel much of an impact in terms of how I made them feel. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, it's pretty amazing the range of things they do
remember. Some academic, some ancillary, some just plain silly. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I heard through a secondary source that Liz, mamy years out still
remembers the recursive sock puppets I use. Since Liz is a successful
software engineer I'm guessing she remembers the recursion as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Blake told me last year that the short edit, save, test, commit cycle
I used made an impact on him. That's something I mention but really
mostly model in class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of years ago, when out in California, I was visiting with
Pawel who was in my class in the early 90s. He reminded me of a lesson
that really made an impact on him. It was on a day when I decided to
throw the planned lesson out the window and ended up working thorugh
how I would approach and try to solve one of the recent USACO problems
going from reading the problem to working solution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course they all remember the Halloween costumes but that's neither
here nor there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've had students tell me other things they remember. Sometimes, I
don't even recall saying them. That's an important point. It might be a
throwaway line for us as teachers but it can have a huge impact or at
least be really memorable for the listener.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's just another reminder of the impact we can have and the
responsibility we must take seriously as teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/blight-move/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 20:37:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Creating a school for CS</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/creating-a-school/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org8055370" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org8055370"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org8055370"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/09/do-we-really-need-cs-focused-high.html"&gt;Do we really need CS focused high schools?&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's the question Alfred Thompson asked partly in reaction to my
&lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/that-time-bill-gates-visited-afse"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; talking about Bill Gates' visit to &lt;a href="http://afsenyc.org"&gt;AFSE&lt;/a&gt;, a NYC public school
with a CS focus.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On both posts, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/reallymdp"&gt;Michael Preston&lt;/a&gt; shared some important and good points about
AFSE as a starting point and gateway that helped lead to CS4All in NYC
and also specifically about AFSE. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In response to Alfred's question I thought it was time I shared a bit
about what I was pushing for AFSE back when I was involved. I wasn't
able to talk publicly about any of this at the time because I was
warned very sternly by one DOE person involved that I shouldn't talk
to "outsiders" about my concerns or designs. In retrospect, since I
stopped getting replies to my emails and was apparently dropped from
email lists after they selected their founding principal, I probably
should have been more public about my critiques. On the other hand, I
should have been more politic internally prior to getting to that
point.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reading Alfred's post, what I was pushing for AFSE at the time cuts
right to Alfred's question so I thought I'd write about it today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Before starting though I want to be &lt;b&gt;absolutely clear&lt;/b&gt; about one
thing. This is not a critique of AFSE as it stands. There are some
great teachers and wonderful students there and I do what I can to
support both whenever I can. This is a post about my design vs the
DOE's design and later implementation. Also note that the numbers,
sizes, restrictions and designs are all based on NY state and NYC
requirements along with what one can typically do in a NYC public
school. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even though it's the least important issue with respect to a CS school
or not, let's start by getting the dirty word out of the way. Given
the stated mission of the school (at the time) I wanted a screen. Not
a "Stuy test" screen but something. Probably something more along the
lines of the screen used by the Manhattan Science Hunter High
School. We never got that far in discussing it. My contention was and
still is that if you want to produce "Google ready" software engineers
by high school graduation, particularly in a small school, you can't
start with kids 2 or 3 years behind in math. Now, if your goal isn't
"Google ready engineers" but rather to use CS to engage a population
that isn't otherwise engaged, I can get behind that and you don't need
a screen. It's important however to note it's a different mission.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The DOE would maintain that you don't need any screen and kids can
start out years behind and by the end of their senior year they'd be
years ahead. It doesn't work that way. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They'd ask tech people at meetings what they looked for in employees
knowing that they'd get back "teamwork, creativity etc." I would of
course follow up with "where do you look for these candidates" and
they'd say "MIT, Cal Tech, Harvard." 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The DOE insisted on no screen. This is fine but it's no surprise that
Google's not beating down the doors for AFSE graduates right out of
high school and the math regents show that you indeed can't take kids
from multiple years behind and end up with them multiple years ahead
given typical school resources. They're doing really good work there
but there's no such thing as a miracle school just hard work and
incremental progress. I have heard more than once that the founding
principal had lobbied for a screen so I feel my original assessment
was correct.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Next up, size. The DOE insisted on a small school focused on CS. They
wanted a school of around 136 kids per grade, which makes for 4
"homerooms," and that the school would focus on CS. My proposal was
very different. I advocated for a school with about 340 kids per grade
and not specifically focused on CS but rather with a great model CS
program - a Software Engineering Institute at the blah blah school if
you would.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A small school can't support a wide range of classes. With 4 classes
of kids per grade you don't have a lot of schedule flexibility in
terms of class levels or electives. You also have very few teachers
per subject - for a subject taught for a full year every year for a
single period, you'd have one teacher per grade in that subject. If
you're a school for CS you're not going to be able to offer a robust
schedule of music or arts classes. Likewise an arts school is going to
be hard pressed to offer a suite of science electives. Remember,
public schools are not flush with money and can't just offer loads of
courses for a handful of kids. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What we end up with is a school with limited offerings beyond CS and
we're asking kids to decide in 8th grade if that's the career path for
them. This is a hidden problem of all small schools. Kids shouldn't
have to decide on their future in the 8th grade. They should all be
able to go to schools that offer a wide range of subjects to a good
degree of depth. Only large public schools can do this. I know that
public schools come with their own problems but this is one of the
trade offs. I believe that having this selection done in 8th grade
along with the tech stereotypes and preconceptions is a big part of
the schools difficulty in appealing to girls.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now even if every student who applied and is randomly accepted into
AFSE does indeed want to be a CS person then we've also lost because
we've done nothing to get more kids into the pool. It could still
potentially function as a model school in terms of courses or possibly
pedagogy but it won't expose and inspire anyone new with respect to
tech.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's contrast that with what I proposed. I wanted around 340 kids per
grade or 10 "homerooms." How did I arrive at that number? It wasn't
just a guess. Schools like Stuyvesant or Brooklyn Tech are clearly too
large and impersonal but small 136 kids per grade schools are too
small. The 10 homeroom per grade school seems to be the best
compromise. There are enough teachers so that there's institutional
memory when one leaves, enough of them and students for a varied set
of electives. It also means that there are enough teachers to avoid
bad fits between teacher and student. At the same time, it's not so
large that kids get lost. I also spoke with some of the best
programmers I know - not computer programmers but people who schedule
students for classes in schools and this seems to be the best
compromise size range. Also, with this size you don't necessarily need
a screen if you want "Google ready" software engineers. There will be
enough of a range kids that come in behind and kids that come in ahead
can get what they need.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also didn't want it to be a CS school but rather a school with great
CS. That way it would appeal to a range of students. Kids who think
they want to do CS and those who don't. At the end of they day some of
the kids that think they wanted CS won't want it and those kids will
have other options. At the same time some of the non-tech kids will
take the required CS and find out that "this is neat stuff" and we get
to increase the number of people in the tent.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I still believe my design would have worked out better but that's not
to say that I don't think that AFSE has been and is important. As Mike
pointed out in his comment, AFSE was the first unscreened school to
offer legit and it did (and does) offer a place for CS kids that don't
get into or don't want to go to a place like Stuy which is very much a
large school and an unforgiving machine. It was also a showpiece that
helped pave the way for CS in all NYC schools. All of that's good.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I do regret parts of what went down between me and DOE. I don't regret
sticking to my beliefs in terms of school design but I would like to
have been able to handle the politics of the situation better. Had I
remained involved I think I had more to offer. I don't regret it too
much – at the time it went from the DOE telling me one week to "you
can have any role in the school you want" to the next week "we want to
introduce you to the person who we're making principal" and I
recognize that I'd have a hard time putting that aside now and the me
of a decade ago would have found it impossible. That said, I think
everyone would have been better off if both sides could have played
things better. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'd still love to have the chance someday to set up and run a school
of my design with my team. It'll probably never happen but it would be
nice.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
"
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>policy</category><category>schools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/creating-a-school/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 22:06:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>That Time Bill Gates Visited AFSE</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/that-time-bill-gates-visited-afse/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orge77d786" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orge77d786"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orge77d786"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
AFSE stands for the Academy for Software Engineering. It's a public
school in New York City with a stated focus on, well, software
engineering. I have some history with the school and its creation but
that's not what this post is about. In fact, this post isn't really
about AFSE at all. I plan to neither praise or critique the
school. This is about what Bill Gates &lt;a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/Education/My-visit-to-the-Academy-for-Software-Engineering"&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; about his recent visit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know the circumstances of the visit but I'm guessing it wasn't
a surprise. More likely it was a scheduled visit and the school, at
least to some extent put on the usual dog and pony show. Teachers
know all about this – the superintendent's coming - make sure your
bulletin boards are all set. Let's nudge the guest to the right
classes, let's make sure to show our best side. I could be wrong, this
could have been a surprise visit or Bill could have gone into random
classes talking to random students but that's unlikely. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Bill says that "Unlike some specialized schools there are no criteria
for admission." First, it's not a specialized school, it's a themed
school just as all NYs small schools are. That's just another way of
saying "small school that can't support a robust elective program."
Bill sounds to be still enamored with small schools. In the video
accompanying his post, Bill describes the school by saying "The idea
is it's a small high school with teachers that want to engage students
on a very personal level and come up with a personalized learning
plan…" I guess teachers at larger schools don't want to engage their
students at a personal level? Personal learning plan? That inherently
has nothing to do with small schools but it does sound like it has
something to do with software he can sell to other peoples kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Bill talks about it being a diverse school while noting that it's very
male heavy (80% in 2016) but I wonder what the culture of the school
is like compared to the greater tech community. Does it exhibit the
best of inclusive diversity or the worst or somewhere in between.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Bill also talks about the unique curriculum noting how a history
teacher might allow a student to make a web page instead of preparing
an oral presentation. This isn't unique at all. I know many teachers
across the city that do this. It also isn't necessarily a good or
bad thing without context. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The title of the piece is "How 3D printers are preparing students for
life after high school" and Bill gushes about a design class he
observed. A design class can be amazing and I'm guessing the one he
saw was, but the 3D printers are incidental. In fact, many educators
don't think they're particularly useful or valuable. They're
expensive, they break, they use consumables which cost money and
printing time make instant gratification impossible. Sure, they're
nice toys but when you're stretching your budget to its breaking
point are they really worth it?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I read this I kept wondering if Bill had really learned anything
from his past failures in coercing public education to his whims. Then
I got to this: "The school enrolls fewer than 500 kids, so class sizes
are small, " That's not how it works and if Bill was actually paying
attention or cared he'd know this. Small schools in NYC have around
544 kids. That's four grades of 136 student each. Each grade is made
up of four classes of 34 students each which is the NYC class size. It
doesn't matter if you have 500 in your school or 5000. The class size
will still be around 34 unless extra funds are available to lower
it. Bill further talks about teachers using a shared data portal and
advisors connecting with families and attributes all this to AFSE
being a small school when it really has to do with having more funds
per student and not the school size at all. He also doesn't seem to
notice how his small schools can't offer great art and music unless
they're art and music themed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why am I writing this? Because people like Bill Gates wield great
wealth and great power and Bill's past efforts in education have
hurt schools much more than they've helped them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Has he learned anything? As far as I can tell, not a thing. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I said this post wasn't about AFSE and it isn't but I will share a few
thoughts here at the end. As with all public schools with open
admission in NYC they face some pretty big challenges. They have some
great champions like founder and NYC mensch, Fred
Wilson along with other players in the tech industry. AFSE was also a
special project of the Bloomberg administration under which it was
created. I think this has meant that they've had resources that might
not be available as readily to other schools. Resources like the ones
mentioned &lt;a href="https://avc.com/2016/01/the-first-annual-afse-fundraiser/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It's great that the kids at AFSE have these resources
but sad that so many other kids don't.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As CS becomes a subject in all schools what will happen with AFSE?
Will they continue to be able to raise the necessary funds for the
extras?  Will it affect the kids who apply? Will it make them less
desirable to "techy" kids since CS will be available at many schools
or will it make it easier to get non tech types. Time will tell. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/that-time-bill-gates-visited-afse/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 19:09:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Do you need to know binary for CS?</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/why-binary/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgfd9899b" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgfd9899b"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgfd9899b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, Alfred Thompson asked &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo/status/1036982959587446784"&gt;"Why is it important for CS students
to understand binary?"&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter which led to a number of interesting
responses. Alfred summarized and wrote his own thoughts on &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/09/why-teach-binary-in-computer-science.html"&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wanted to add a comment but I already wrote a post for yesterday so
put it off until today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First let me say that you can have a very successful career in tech
and not really know binary or number bases other than 10. That career
could be as as programmer, software engineer, network specialist,
devops or in many other areas that fall on the CS side of tech.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You also can't really get through a CS program without learning about
binary. If you're self taught or go to a code school then that's
another story.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The question is, is it worth the time spent.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One can easily argue that systems - that is low level, close to the
metal knowledge is one of the two "latins" of CS, the other being CS
theory. You might not explicitly use either but they give you a
stronger foundation in everything. You also can't study systems without a
good knowledge of binary so if you want to do anything low level, you
need it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What about beyond those easy but not all to convincing to new students
answers?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's loo at a few things we can do with binary.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A big part of binary notation is that you can look at data as a string
of bits. You can also manipulate that data using things like &lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;not&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;xor&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At it's core &lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt; let's you turn off bits. &lt;code&gt;And&lt;/code&gt; any bit with a 0 and
it will become a 0. &lt;code&gt;And&lt;/code&gt; it with a 1 and it stays the same.
&lt;/p&gt;

\begin{array}{ccccc}
&amp;amp;1 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0\\
and &amp;amp;0 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1\\\hline
&amp;amp;0 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0\\
\end{array}

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Or&lt;/code&gt; is used to turn on bits. You &lt;code&gt;or&lt;/code&gt; any bit with a 1 and it gets
turned on. &lt;code&gt;Or&lt;/code&gt; it with a 0 and it stays as it was.
&lt;/p&gt;

\begin{array}{ccccc}
&amp;amp;1 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0\\
or &amp;amp;0 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1\\\hline
&amp;amp;1 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1\\
\end{array}

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Xor&lt;/code&gt; a bit with a 1 and the bit flips, with a 0 it stays the same.
&lt;/p&gt;

\begin{array}{ccccc}
&amp;amp;1 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0\\
xor &amp;amp;0 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1\\\hline
&amp;amp;1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1\\
\end{array}


&lt;p&gt;
What can we do with this? For one thing, image processing. Students
frequently play with images where each pixel is represented as a 24
bit color. Three bytes, one each for red, green, and blue. Each byte
is really 8 bits. We can use bitwise operations on the binary digits
to turn on or off color.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's say we have this rgb triple: (200, 15, 80) which in hexadecimal
is C8 0F 50 or 10111000 00001111 01010000 in binary. If we want to
turn off the reddest reds we could &lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt; the color with 00001111
11111111 11111111 or 0FFFFF:
&lt;/p&gt;

\begin{array}{cccc}
&amp;amp; 10111000 &amp;amp; 00001111 &amp;amp; 01010000\\
and &amp;amp; 00001111 &amp;amp; 11111111 &amp;amp; 11111111\\\hline
&amp;amp; 00001000 &amp;amp; 00001111 &amp;amp; 01010000\\
\end{array}

&lt;p&gt;
Yes, you could just use the base 10
values and keep on calling color setting and conversion functions but
if you understand binary it's quicker and easier and what's going on
will actually make sense. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course you probably wouldn't write out the binary but would rather
use the hex notation which once a student realizes is just 4 bit
groupings of binary becomes really easy. As a bonus, once you're used
to binary and hex those hexadecimal color values will all of a sudden
make sense.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is just the tip of the image processing and graphics iceberg with
respect to binary. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Related although I haven't played with it myself, I'd imagine you could use
these types of bitwise operations on images to play with
steganography.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Another use of binary is in cybersecurity. Things like buffer
overflows and blowing the stack all make much more sense if you know
how memory is arranged and that's easier to understand if you
understand binary, bytes, and word sizes. I do experiments with my
classes when we use C or C++ where they access arrays off the ends and
end up messing with neighboring variables. It seems like magic unless
you know about memory and to know memory you need to know binary.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How about image file formats? Many image file formats start with a
fixed size header. Here's the header definition for the GIF file
format:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Offset&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Length&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Contents&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;3  bytes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;"GIF"&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;3  bytes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;"87a" or "89a"&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;2  bytes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;&amp;lt;Logical Screen Width&amp;gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;2  bytes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;&amp;lt;Logical Screen Height&amp;gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;1  byte&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;bit0: Global Color Table Flag (GCTF)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;bit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;1..3:  Color&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Resolution&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;bit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;4:  Sort&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Flag to Global Color Table&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;bit&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;5..7:  Size&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;of Global Color Table:2&lt;sup&gt;(1+n)&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;1  byte&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;&amp;lt;Background Color Index&amp;gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;1  byte&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;&amp;lt;Pixel Aspect Ratio&amp;gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;?  bytes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;&amp;lt;Global Color Table(0..255 x 3 bytes)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;bytes  &amp;lt;Blocks&amp;gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;bytes  &amp;lt;Trailer&amp;gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;(0x3b)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The header info is defined bit by bit so you have to know about binary
and know how to manipulate data on a bit level. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Those were three biggies but there are other places where knowing
binary makes tons of sense:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;flag type parameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;understanding floating point numbers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using shifts for quick doubling and halving of data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Does this mean that binary has to be or should be in a first course?
No. Should it be somewhere? Certainly and rather than doing binary
because it's on the test or because "you should know it" you can pick
and choose your spots and cover it when it will be fun and interesting
for your kids.
&lt;/p&gt;











&lt;p&gt;
world
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>mathjax</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/why-binary/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2018 21:15:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Wishing all K12 teachers a great year</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/starting-school-2018/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org6a6a321" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6a6a321"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6a6a321"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today was the first day of school for all NYC teachers. Students come
back tomorrow. That's a quick turnaround. Some years, they get a day
or two before the kids come in. That's much easier.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first day is usually dominated by meetings. In a large school like
Stuy you'll typically have a long faculty meeting in the morning and a
department meeting in the afternoon. Not much time to actually get
ready for classes. You might think that it shouldn't be a big deal
since you had all summer but in NYC where budgets don't come out until
the summer for teachers not to know exactly what or when they're
teaching until the first day back.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Things started at Hunter college last week but things are different
there. I was excited to my students but the overall energy isn't the
same. We're two weeks in and I still haven't seen most of my CS
colleagues. In the high school, everyone comes back at once. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any event. It's an exciting time in what should be an exciting year
for CS teachers and students. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not going to rehash everything that's going on since I'm sure most
readers already already know what's going on but I'll add one
thing. Many New York teachers need ongoing professional development -
CTLE hours. It seems that teachers in specific programs like New York
City's Software Engineering Pilot (SEP) have a number of PD
opportunities provided to them and there also seems to be a good
amount of PD at the entry level. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There doesn't seem to be much for the teacher ready for that next
step. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To address this, we'll be offering once a month sessions through
Hunter for CS teachers who are ready to move beyond the basics both in
content and pedagogy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The plan is to start some time in October.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the meantime to all the teachers meeting their students tomorrow -
have a great semester!!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/starting-school-2018/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Sep 2018 21:33:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Class Rules</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/class-rules/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org60b9db4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org60b9db4"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org60b9db4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Classes started up again today so I thought I'd talk about my class
rules.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't seem to recall many class rules in college. Sure, there was a
grading policy governing homework and the like but not much beyond
that. In K12 there are usually more. When you can talk, how you set up
your notebook, how to do homework, bathroom policy etc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For years, I've used the same set of class rules and I always talk
about the rules with my classes. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't have a lot of rules. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Just two.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Don't be a bum and don't be a jerk&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img height="200" src="https://bamfstyle.files.wordpress.com/2016/04/dude6-main.jpg"&gt;

&lt;img height="200" src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1600/0*x6Y-uVduUOWmYngr.jpg"&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Not only are they good class rules, they're also good life rules. I
tell my classes that if they follow these two rules everything else
takes care of itself. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what do they mean?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Being a bum means you're doing something detrimental to yourself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You don't hand in an assignment? You're being a bum. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Don't prepare for an exam? You're being a bum.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Don't ask for an extension until right before a project's due because
you didn't even look at it until the night before? Bum.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Being a jerk means you're doing something detrimental to someone
else. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're meeting a bunch of friends to see a movie and you leave them
waiting for you on a cold corned February since you can't bother to be
on time, you're being a jerk.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Don't hold up your end of a group project? You're being a jerk. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hold up the class by asking the same question that was just asked and
answered, not because you didn't understand but because you weren't
listening? You're being a jerk. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have my students fill out an information form at the start of the
semester. I give them a day or two to do it but there is a
deadline. Don't fill it out on time and you're being a bum. You're
also being a jerk. Why? Because I use that list to set up my
grade book as well as mailing lists and other resources. If I don't
have the data from all my students I either have to wait on setting up
my systems or I have to go back later and manually add the
stragglers. Making more work for the teacher because you couldn't be
bothered to finish a two minute assignment? That falls under the "jerk" category.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Every interaction makes an impression and even small actions can have
effects on people that you don't realize. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You do something the right way, people will notice. You do things that adversely affect
people? They'll notice that as well. I want my students to start to
become aware of how they act, how they affect the people around
them, and the reputations they build through small actions - both
positive and negative.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We also talk about why I don't need to hear excuses when you violate
either of these rules. If you do things the right way - you don't act
like a bum or a jerk - you build your credibility. If at some point
later, something happens - you miss an assignment because a last
minute emergency - you've got the positive reputation so you don't
need an excuse. If you've been a bum all along, the excuse carries no
weight.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
None of this has anything to do with computer science but it does have
to do with our students growth as people so in many ways it's more
important. Do I make in impact with any of this? I can't be sure but
I think it's important enough to make the effort.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/class-rules/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 22:57:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Artifacts Have Stories</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/artifacts-have-stories/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org0b17966" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0b17966"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0b17966"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Earlier today I was asked about my avatar:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hero-z.jpg" alt="hero-z.jpg" height="250"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've been using it for most services for a few months now. It's an
image that I've had for ages. I started thinking about using it about
a year ago 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what's the story?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was back in 1993. I had just started at Stuy. I taught some CS when
I was at Seward Park but at the time, I was teaching all math at
Stuy. Mostly Geometry to ninth graders but also a smattering of
Algebra 2 / Trig and Linear Algebra. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The math department had the fourth floor and some of the third but
since I was the new guy I taught most of my classes in the hinterlands
of the 7th and 8th floor. At least I had great views of the lower
Hudson and the Statue of Liberty.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My math classes were somewhat more formulaic and structured than my
computer science classes would end up. Start with a "Do Now" while I
checked homework. Kids then present homework that they put on the
board. We then did the Do Now which hopefully led into the lesson. I
was never super strict but it was pretty structured. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In one class I had a young man, let's call him Charles since I don't
know if he's comfortable with my sharing his true identity. He sad in
the last two or three rows right next to the window on the south side
of classroom. Charles would constantly doodle throughout the
class. This never really bothered me. He was always prepared, did well
on all assessments and was also ready and able to take part in class
discussion regularly. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Apparently, his other teachers weren't as tolerant of his doodling. At
the end of the semester he gave me the picture. and said he really
appreciated me not hassling him about the doodling. I thanked him and
explained that since it didn't adversely affect his performance (and
might have helped) and didn't distract anyone else, why would I give
him a hard time
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The semester ended and I didn't think much more about it although once
I got my own office I put the picture in a frame and added it to my
collection of office trinkets. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last year, now at Hunter, I was looking at the picture and I wondered
what ever happened to Charles. I hadn't seen him after he was in my
class as a freshman. I had started to teach CS and we started to developed our
cult so I didn't end up keeping in touch with many of my students from
those freshmen math classes.  It turned out I was able to find him on
Facebook. I don't think he remembered me but he accepted the friend
request and we caught up. His family moved out of NY after his
freshman year so it made even more sense that I never saw him again.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I keep the picture because it's fun and also to remind me of the
circumstances under which I go it. I always appreciate it when a
student takes the time to say thanks even when they don't remember
anything about the class 30 years later. When I would get little gifts
during the holidays, if I'm being honest, I'll have to say that I
would frequently throw the gift card or present on the pile but I'd
keep and cherish the notes and letters. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the years, I accumulated quite a collection of esoteric from
former students. From the custom mouse pad with Dave, Spike, Igor, and
Oy on it to the Squirtle from Larry to Orion's pinhead, every artifact
has a story. They remind me of a person time and place. A connection I
had and in many cases I still have. It also creates a bridge to the
past both for me and my students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've been derided for hanging t-shirts donated by former students from
their companies when I had my own classroom at Stuy:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/shirts-307.jpg" alt="shirts-307.jpg" height="200"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Those naysayers are wrong. Each shirt has a story. It could be Joy's
Apple shirt and how she agonized over her employment options, Pawel's
Google shirt and his adventures going from Bloomberg LP to the French
West Indies to now being a senior programmer at Google or a Digital
Ocean shirt from Ben and Moisey and the stories they evoke are far two
numerous to list. They create a history and perpetuate the
culture. Each has a story.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looking back, I'm glad that I've kept many mementos from the
past. The objects are incidental but the stories give context and
inspiration to current students while at the same time reminding me of
my past and my shared journey with so many of my students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/artifacts-have-stories/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 21:35:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Software Longevity</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/software-longevity/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd198407" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd198407"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd198407"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Writing about &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/rite-of-passage-projects/#.W3l-fxhKhhE"&gt;old projects&lt;/a&gt; got me thinking of my first programming gig
and software longevity. It was a part time after school / full time
summer job at Arcus-Simplex-Brown. I started in my senior year in high
school and continued through most of my first year in college. It
wasn't my first job - that was being a delivery boy at &lt;a href="http://videoroom.net/"&gt;Video Room&lt;/a&gt;, an
independent video store that's survived from the old VHS/Betamax days
through DVDs and is still, somehow or other, surviving in this day and
age of streaming video. My job at Arcus-Simplex-Brown was my first job
as a programmer. I got it through my buddy Ben who got it from one of
our math teachers at Stuy. Ben had found a job closer to home so
passed this one along to me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Arcus-Simplex-Brown was (is?) a ticket printing company
&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://i.ebayimg.com/images/g/nxYAAOSwHUhaGYw3/s-l1600.png" alt="s-l1600.png" align="center" height="100"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://i.pinimg.com/originals/c1/f0/ec/c1f0ec2f524c9e3e65c5e8b50fc7226a.png" alt="c1f0ec2f524c9e3e65c5e8b50fc7226a.png" align="center" height="100"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
They also did tickets for sporting events like the Knicks and
Rangers at the Garden. More recently, this was 1983, they had started
selling computer printed tickets and that's where I came in. They had
a dot matrix line printer. Not the small kind used by personal
computer owners and small businesses:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align="center" height="100"&gt;
[[&lt;img src="https://global.epson.com/company/corporate_history/milestone_products/img/11_product.jpg" alt="11_product.jpg" align="center" height="100"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Printers like the &lt;a href="https://global.epson.com/company/corporate_history/milestone_products/11_mx80.html"&gt;Epson MX 80&lt;/a&gt; pictured above had a print head that
moved across a line at a time much like a modern desktop ink jet
printer. The difference was that it had a print head that had a matrix
of pins which fired and hit an ink ribbon which left the ink
impression on the paper.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Rather, they had a big heavy duty one where the print head went across
the entire width of the paper and it literally printed a line at a
time
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn8.bigcommerce.com/s-a1x7hg2jgk/images/stencil/1280x1280/products/21296/120659/printronix-p5008-800-lpm-proline-series-5-line-matrix-printer-1.35__97003.1490181342.jpg" alt="printronix-p5008-800-lpm-proline-series-5-line-matrix-printer-1.35__97003.1490181342.jpg" align="center" height="100"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and a computer attached. I think it was an old &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/North_Star_Computers"&gt;North Star&lt;/a&gt;
computer. It ran &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CP/M"&gt;CP/M&lt;/a&gt; which was like a primitive version of
MS-DOS. 64K of memory  and
two floppy drives. It had a basic interpreter built in and they
also had a basic compiler. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They had a program that was supposed to print the tickets but it
didn't really work. My first job was to get it working, It was a HUGE
mess of a program. God knows how many lines of BASIC code with a few
gosubs and a ton of gotos. I don't think there were too many
comments. It didn't help that in addition to having to deal with
custom theater seating plans and ticket policies you had to know all
sorts of magical incantations to get the printer to do the special
fonts correctly and I don't recall us having a printer manual so it
all had to be divined from the non-working code. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On top of all this, the program was so complex that only the simplest
test cases could be run via the interpreter interactively. Any real
change had to go through the compiler and it took about 40 minutes to
compile the program. Whenever I wanted to take a long break, I set up
a compile. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Somehow or other, I got the thing to work. The code started as a mess
and I didn't improve it any I really had no idea what I was
doing. Still, it did work and we were able to reliably print tickets
for all sorts of things.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I stopped working at Arcus-Simplex-Brown once I got a job at NYU. That
gig ultimately turned into a full time job which enabled me to work my
way through school. It was the right move but I had a great time and
learned a lot at Arcus.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I didn't think much about the work I did at Arcus over the years. I
finished college, went to Goldman, then some consulting and ultimately
 teaching career.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One day at Stuy, I noticed this:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/arcus-ticket.jpg" alt="arcus-ticket.jpg" align="center" height="400"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was now Spring 2012 - almost 30 years later. Judging from the dot
pattern  of the letters it looked like the same printer and was
probably the same program!!!!!!! I couldn't believe it. Stuy didn't
use these tickets back in my day so I was really surprised. It looked
like some horrible code I wrote as a kid was still being used
productively almost three decades later!!!!!! They could have
continued to use it because it basically worked or maybe because they
were afraid that touching it would break everything.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I don't remember what the code looked like but know it was
horrible. If I had it, I'd be to embarrassed to share and that's saying
something. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The lesson of all this? You never know how long your code is going to
live. It might surprise you. Hopefully in a good way. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All the more reason to do better than I did and learn how to do it
right. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/software-longevity/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2018 14:16:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Rite Of Passage Projects</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/rite-of-passage-projects/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org4e176fd" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org4e176fd"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org4e176fd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JCS's &lt;a href="https://irreal.org/blog/?p=7414#comment-4045190612"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on Irreal today brought me back. It was about &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brief_(text_editor)"&gt;Brief&lt;/a&gt; which
was the editing hotness back in the day. I played with it a little
really mostly used Emacs clones for real work when I was stuck on
MS-DOS systems. Usually either &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JOVE"&gt;JOVE&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epsilon_(text_editor)"&gt;Epsilon&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the comments Jon reminded me about the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MKS_Toolkit"&gt;MKS Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;
which brought most everyday Unix tools to DOS along with a shell and
a version of Vi. I didn't use Vi much and I only used their shell
until I wrote my own. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking about "rite of passage" projects. I was in
college in the mid to late 80s. It was the heyday of the
IBM-PC. Schools still used older time sharing systems like DEC-20s and
Vaxen but the PC was all the rage. The cool thing about them was that
you had full control and access to the machine and it was simple
enough to get your head around pretty much everything about it. The
downside was that MS-DOS was very limited and of course there was
little to no networking going on. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the one hand, you could dive into the low level machine language
stuff very easily. Get Norton's book:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://covers.openlibrary.org/b/id/7446489-L.jpg" alt="7446489-L.jpg" align="center" height="250"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and you're on your way. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand many student's graduated with no concept of time
sharing and the ramifications of sharing a system or resources were
foreign to many kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even though we always look back to the "good old days," in many ways
things weren't much different. I got a very strong background in
academic CS from NYU (Courant Institute) but just like today, there
was no real preparation for the real world.If you wanted to really develop your
coding chops you had to work on side projects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I seem to recall, a typical "rite of passage" side project was writing
your own shell. It didn't have to be anything as powerful as BASH or
ZSH but it would typically be much more powerful than DOS and much
more Unixy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I recall writing my first shell down in UC-49 of Tisch Hall when the
computer labs weren't busy. I wrote it in C which was what the cool
kids used back then. Specifically I used the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Williams_Company"&gt;Let's C&lt;/a&gt; compiler from the
Mark Williams company. This was before Turbo C 2.0 so Let's C was
pretty much the only game in town for a cheap Unix style C compiler
for DOS. There was also Run/C but that was a C interpreter, not a
compiler. I also used that to learn C. Funny story - I certainly
didn't know this at the time but Run/C was written by Peter
Brooks. Peter and I would later meet when he became my colleague at
Stuyvesant teaching CS and I now have the privilege of being able to
call him friend. I joke that I owe him ~ $100 for the interpreter from
back in the day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since this was on DOS, I couldn't do real Unix style pipes like 
&lt;code&gt;cat file | sort | uniq -c | sort -n&lt;/code&gt; but I did simulate it with redirection and temporary
files. It also supported aliases, simple scripts and I think a few
other things. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was pretty happy with it and used it for a couple of years. It was
also one of the first substantial programs I wrote. I learned a lot
from doing it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another "rite of passage" program that was common back then was a
text based window library. Somethig like ncurses that would allow you
to make text based windows and menus on the text only screen. I also
wrote one of these and actually got to use it for a project when I
started working at Goldman. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I guess the third "rite of passage" project I remember was writing a C
compiler but that was different because it was for a class. It was a
significant project but the class didn't really help with writing a
large program in general - it was all about the compiler and all the
theory behind it. Great course but not one in software engineering.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Nowadays the projects have changed. Text based windowing is long gone
and while I still think writing a shell is a useful and rewarding
exercise it's not scratching an itch the way it did back when we were
stuck on DOS. I guess writing a full stack web app is probably a
pretty typical one for students these days. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Any others?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C</category><category>cs</category><category>emacs</category><category>programming</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/rite-of-passage-projects/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 19:18:11 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>