<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description>C'est la Z</description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:24:44 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Is Teaching CS Hard?</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-teaching-cs-hard/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org25144c9" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org25144c9"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org25144c9"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last week, Mark Guzdial asked &lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/2018/01/19/what-does-it-mean-for-computer-science-to-be-harder-to-learn-than-other-stem-subjects/"&gt;What does it mean for Computer Science to be harder to learn
than other STEM subjects?&lt;/a&gt; as a follow up to his &lt;a href="https://cacm.acm.org/blogs/blog-cacm/224105-learning-computer-science-is-different-than-learning-other-stem-disciplines/fulltext"&gt;ACM Blog post&lt;/a&gt; this
month and the ensuing discussion.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You should read both posts but here's how Mark started off the follow
up:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I made an argument in my Blog@CACM Post for this month that “Learning
Computer Science is Different than Learning Other STEM Disciplines,”
and on Twitter, I explicitly added “It’s harder.”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When you talk about how hard or easy it is to teach a subject you can
do so at many levels. college, high school, middle etc.. Since most of
my career has been as a High School guy, let's focus there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I do in fact believe that it is hard to teach CS, at least to do it
well but is it harder to teach then other STEM subjects?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's see how we're doing in those other subjects. I took a look at
the New York State &lt;a href="https://data.nysed.gov/reportcard.php?instid=800000081568&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;createreport=1&amp;amp;regents=1"&gt;Regents Exam&lt;/a&gt; results from 2015/2016. I'm certainly
not a believer or supporter of standardized tests but they're a
convenient measure for the sake of this post.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Only 58% of test takers scored 65 or higher on Integrated Algebra and
only 41% scored 3 (proficient) or higher on the Common Core version
with far more students taking the Common Core exam.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Higher performing schools frequently offer Algebra in 8th grade but in
the lower performing districts, students frequently take it over the
course of two years. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Geometry regents boasts a passing rate of about 40%. Trig does a
little better.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The science regents exams look a little better but overall, these are
not terrific results, particularly on the classes that are required
for graduation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It seems that those other STEM fields aren't so easy to teach after all.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand we have CS. If you listen to all the press releases
and media attention on APCS-P from this past year it would seem that
CS is easy to teach and learn. We have all these high school students
mastering a "college level" course and we can prepare teachers to be
master CS instructions with just a bit of in-service professional
development.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The truth is, of course that CS isn't easy to teach. When you're a
summer or after school program or even an elective it's easy to create
a fun experience using shiny tools to self selecting students but when
you have to take everyone and prepare many of them to succeed in more
advanced classes we have a real challenge. We really should be looking
at retention in more advanced CS classes rather than just passing the
intro ones. Most students won't go beyond the intro class in any given
subject but the ones that do must be well prepared. Unfortunately, I
fear that the people who will get the blame when kids drop CS later on
will be the teachers of the more advanced classes regardless of who,
if anyone, is at fault.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teaching CS is hard. It's brand new and very open ended.  When
programming a solution to a problem kids start with a blank
slate. They don't have the library of patterns, vocabulary or &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/programming-idioms"&gt;idioms&lt;/a&gt;
needed to build solitions. There are many ways a teacher can scaffold
the learning. Code tracing, analogies, Parsons problems and more but
the truth is teachers strong in both content and pedagogical knowledge
are still in rather short supply and as Mark wrote on his blog the
body of knowledge on teaching CS is just not that mature.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, Algebra students usually had a first look at some
of the topics prior to the class and much of the class can be
"learned" through memorizing relatively short procedures and
patterns. This might not lead to a depth of understanding but it does
get you past standardized tests. On the science side, the Living
Environment exam is really just a reading test.  On the other hand,
we're supposed to start teaching proof to students in Geometry and
that's really hard to do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, teaching in general is hard and teaching CS is no exception. At
least it is if you're doing it right.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-teaching-cs-hard/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 20:56:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Reading and Writing Recs</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/reading-and-writing-recs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc1e86ec" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc1e86ec"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc1e86ec"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've been on both sides of the recommendation game. I currently read
all the recommendations for students who apply to my &lt;a href="http://info.huntercs.org"&gt;honors CS program&lt;/a&gt;
at Hunter and some of the ones written for the Macaulay Honors
program. I also read some for the CSTUY summer program. On the other
side, I've written hundreds if not thousands of recs for seniors when
I was teaching at Stuy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've been meaning to write about recs  and when I saw &lt;a href="http://avc.com/2018/01/some-thoughts-on-checking-references/"&gt;yesterday's post&lt;/a&gt;
on AVC.com I thought now would be a good time. While the situation is
not quite the same, much of what Fred wrote resonated strongly with
me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wrote a lot of recs at Stuy. In a year after I taught juniors I'd
typically end up writing for anywhere between 40 and 75 kids and each
kid would apply to between 5 and 15 schools. Some were accepted early
and in many cases you use the same rec without tweaking for all the
kid's applications but it's still an enormous load.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also don't think I'm particularly good at it. Writing doesn't come
naturally to. That said, I try to do an honest job.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first and most important thing I do is make sure each student
understands that I'm not trying to get that kid into their percieved
dream school. My job writing a rec is to contribute to a picture of
who they are as both a student and as a person. The hope is that the
college admissions people will be looking for best fit students and
that the picture the application creates makes the fit clear
&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/reading-and-writing-recs/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Beyond that, I try to say something personal in each rec. Recount a
particular project or event. It's hard. It might be easier for
English teachers - English classes allow for much freer discussions
and assignments where students can reveal more about
themselves. It's harder in subjects like Math and Computer
Science. I'd invariably be asked to write recs for a number of kids –
good kids that were quiet, did there thing but to be honest, never
did much to stand out. I don't necessity mean stand out in terms of
grades, I mean in terms of making themselves known - revealing who
they were. I also try to keep recs short. Readers have a lot of these
to go through. I don't want to add to their load.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Many teachers, including myself try to address this problem. We
interview the kids, have them write mini-essays and just plain
struggle when it comes time to write.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To make it more challenging, the deadlines are all together so you
have to get them all done in a short period of time and at the same
time not fall into the rut of having them sound all the same.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the reader side, similar to what Fred said about references, a lot
of it is about what isn't written and about how it's written. The
challenge is that my code as a reader might be different from the
teacher writing the rec. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The key thing I look for when reading is a connection between the
writer and the kid. Often I read a rec and could apply it equally well
to every applicant in the stack. I also know that when I write recs
I've been guilty of this and it really does nothing to help the
student. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also don't want to read about averages and test scores or anything
that's already covered in the application. I already get the numbers
and if a kid, let's say, volunteered at a community center, it's already on the
application. I don't want a teacher to mention it unless they
were involved or can otherwise add something that I wouldn't know just
from reading the appkication. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If I come away feeling that there's a connection between the teacher
and student that says a lot to me. It means the kid made an impression
on the teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For my Hunter Honors program I have an advantage (or possibly curse)
over when I read for other programs and this is similar to what Fred
wrote about following up on references. I know some of the teachers
writing the recs and I usually know teachers in the schools. Since the
number of applications I'm dealing with isn't huge, I can reach out to
my people and find out what's what. Last year I was able to justify
accepting a student based on additional information I was able to get
and now half a year later it's clear that the student is a terrific
fit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This would all be simpler if we didn't have to play games with
recommendations. When I was a teacher. rather than writing 50 - 70
recommendations, I'd rather have 20ish phone calls. One with each
school. I could briefly talk about the kids relative to each other and
to former students who went to any given institution and that's
that. It would be faster, easier, and fairer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/reading-and-writing-recs/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;Personally, I think the whole college application process is
both unfair and arbitrary but that's a discussion for another time.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/reading-and-writing-recs/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2018 12:49:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>APCS-P -  Bigger Intake Or Leaky Pipe</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/apcsp-bigger-intake-or-leaky-pipe/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbff84a9" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgbff84a9"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgbff84a9"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Advanced Placement Computer Science got top billing on Alfred
Thompson's &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/01/computer-science-education-things-im.html"&gt;Things I'm Watching in 2017&lt;/a&gt; post. Alfred talks about how
APCS-P exploded onto the scene and wonders what will happen with APCS
this year. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have some questions as well but mine won't be answered for years to
come, if ever. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Like it or not, the College Board has an out sized influence on K12
education. As long as people are convinced that AP=good there will be
a push for more and more AP classes and APCS-P is a perfect class to
push. CS is the hot topic in K12, the topic is getting a big push
from both politicians and industry, the class has no pre-requisites
and in spite of being called a college course is somehow appropriate
for a typical tenth grader.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The concern here is that at the end of the day. APCS-P is an exam or
rather an exam plus two other assessments. The quality can vary
greatly. I've heard of APCS-P implementations that seem pretty
rigorous and I've seen implementations that are, quite frankly, a
joke. The question is this: is APCS-P both motivating kids to go on to
the next level and just as importantly preparing them to succeed at
that level? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We might never know.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A high school might only offer APCS-P. If APCS-A isn't offered, we
might not know if the student went on to take more CS and we won't
know if the student succeeded or not. I've seen this with some very
high profile, popular, after school/summer non-profits. The kids have
a great time and the non-profits rave about how much their kids learn
but then the kids take a real CS class in school and drop like
flies. Was it the teacher/professor or did the non-profit set the kids up to
fail by convincing them they knew a whole lot more than they did and
that CS was super easy all the time. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If credit is given for APCS-P, it looks like it will be blanket
credit. CS majors and minors will still have to take all the same classes in
college and CS so it will be very hard to tell if APCS-P is
responsible for any uptick in CS. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, the College Board is going to make a lot of
money but if APCS-P becomes the standard high school CS course will
this leave us with true, quality CS4All? I have my doubts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ap</category><category>cs</category><category>cs4all</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/apcsp-bigger-intake-or-leaky-pipe/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 23:28:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Using Emacs 2017 Recap</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-2017-recap/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orga6e2f1a" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orga6e2f1a"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orga6e2f1a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This past year I recorded 14 Using Emacs videos. This is on top of the
25 videos I made last year. The fall off in production is
understandable. I got through my day to day configuration in the
late 20s and since then the videos have just been on things I've
rediscovered, things that became useful and things that I just found
interesting. It was also a busier year.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why did I start the series? Mostly for my students. There's the built
in Emacs tutorial and other beginner resources but how do you go from
the basics to a real working configuration? For years I would show my
kids Emacs and use it in class but there was never a path for them to
follow from beginner to craftsman. I hoped the videos would fill the
void.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It probably didn't. I don't think I'm getting greater Emacs adoption
from my students but on the other hand, I've found making the series
rewarding for other reasons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First and foremost, it's allowed me to be an active contributing
member of the Emacs community. I haven't written any Emacs packages
nor am I an active guy on any Emacs forums but this is a way I can do
my part. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Second, although there hasn't been a great deal of comments on the
videos or blog posts I've gotten to know a few people that I wouldn't
have gotten to know otherwise.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It also shows that that if you put things out there people might find
it useful. I don't know how many people saw my Emacs posts at the
start but a year and half later I've got 1,700 YouTube
subscribers. Sure, that's nothing compared to many YouTubers but 
for a guy making schlocky videos at his desk about an as much as I hate to admit it
non-maintream editor, I think it's pretty cool.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The question is what to make videos on moving forward? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I thought I'd throw it out to the community. Here's an embedded
poll. Feel free to suggest other topics either on the blog or
as a Twitter reply.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I can't promise I'll get to all or any but I'll certainly check out
the popular suggestions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="http://www.easypolls.net/ext/scripts/emPoll.js?p=5a46abd4e4b04ebe73ddc4de"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;a class="OPP-powered-by" href="http://www.objectplanet.com/opinio/" style="text-decoration:none;"&gt;&lt;div style="font: 9px arial; color: gray;"&gt;survey service&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>emacs</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-2017-recap/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 18:17:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>2017 in review - K12 CS Education</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2017-review-k12CSEd/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orge08351e" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orge08351e"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orge08351e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It's been a big year for K12 CS education. More and more states
looking into CS as a K12 academic area and all that entails, the
CS4All movement is well underway and the College Board launched a new
exam. These are just three of many big things that happened in the
past year.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm excited about the overall growth but concerned about a number of
issues. I've written about all of them in the past so won't rehash
here and in any event, the issues I'm concerned about are issues I
have no influence on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Instead I thought I'd look at some local CS Ed happenings. Things
where I have been able to contribute.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Probably the biggest thing happening that I've been involved with is
New York State's &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/NY-CS-Certificate/"&gt;moving forward on CS teacher certification&lt;/a&gt;. I
developed CS teacher preparation programs at Hunter and Hunter's been
one of the voices talking to the state. I'd like to believe I had some
small positive voice in this effort.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Related are the programs that are one piece of form and one committee
short of being approved. Very soon Hunter will have CS teacher
preparation programs - a full Masters program, a certificate program
and an Alt Cert program. While no program is perfect, I'm very proud
in what I designed and am confident that any teacher that completes
a Hunter program will be amazingly well prepared to teach CS. Not
just the popular curricula being offered today and not just the out of
the box curricula being lauded by others. Our teachers will be
empowered to create their own custom educational experiences
appropriate for their kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've said before that I believe in teacher over curriculum. A great
teacher can save the worst course but the best curriculum can't save a
weak teacher. No matter what happens with CS Ed as a whole, I know
that the CS teachers we prepare at Hunter will be top flight. Kids in
their classes will be alright regardless of what the education machine
tries to impose on them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other thing I've been working on, albeit in a limited way is
professional development. There's a lot of CS PD around but most of it
seems to be either for the younger levels or the intro levels. Very
little for APCS-A let alone beyond. This past November I was able to
host teachers from a handful of schools on Election Day for what
everyone felt was one of their more productive PD experiences. We're
following this up with another one in the Spring but this time we're
expanding. I've been talking to friends at &lt;a href="http://tealsk12.org"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; so as to get more
teachers and schools involved. There's a lot of value in connecting
teachers with each other and I hope that I'm helping to do that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm looking forward to 2018. I'm told that NYSED should vote on CS
certification in March and my programs should also be on the books
around then. The challenge will be building capacity since I can't do
this as a one man show.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm very proud of what we've accomplished at Hunter on both the
education side and the CS side. It's been a good year and I expect
2018 to be a better one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2017-review-k12CSEd/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2017 15:05:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>2017 in review - Hunter Undergraduate CS</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2017-review-hunter-cs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd2ea02b" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd2ea02b"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd2ea02b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I usually don't do year in review posts. At Stuy, not much changed
year after year so I never felt it worth summarizing the past and
projecting the future. At Hunter, now that I'm a couple of years in,
projects are really picking up steam so I think it's worth talking
about them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of my two major missions at Hunter was to build a CS Honors
program and raise the profile of Hunter's undergraduate CS program in
general. Hunter had a strong CS program before I joined the team it's
just that few people knew about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My goal is to see Hunter become the "go to" institution for
undergraduate CS in New York City before my time is done.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is an extremely important mission. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are other strong CS options besides Hunter but compare the costs:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Institution&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Annual Tuition&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;NYU&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;$50,464&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;NYY Tandon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;$48,750&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Columbia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;$54,504&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Hunter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;$6,530&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgabcc198" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgabcc198"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgabcc198"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hunter is about one tenth the cost.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
True, if you're wealthy this isn't a problem and if you're at the
bottom of the economic ladder you might get a full ride but if you
fall into that category where you earn more than the financial aid
people think is "poor" but are clearly not rich you're left in a bad place. This seems
particularly true for New Yorkers as our income seems higher than that
of people from other parts of the country but our cost of living is
higher as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My wife and I are both career public educators. No one would confuse a
family of two working teachers as upper class but we were granted no
financial aid for our kids. The alternatives without a great public
option are to have saved for our entire lives and now liquidate those
savings or go into tremendous debt.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This alone makes the mission critical. Add to that the accessibility
issue - elite private institutions only have to concern themselves
with whatever slice of the population they choose to accept. We are
charged with providing a top flight education to all - be they the
high achievers, the late bloomers, the struggling students or anyone 
else.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what's happened in the past year?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, the Daedalus honors program is developing nicely. In our first
year we had a cohort of 12. This past year 27. I haven't seen the
applicant pool yet - Hunter applications are open until the end of
January, but I'm hoping to bring in an even larger cohort this year. I
spent a good amount of time this fall visiting high schools to talk
about Hunter CS and CS options in general. Not as many as I'd like but
more than during year one. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had classes, trips, and special events but more important was that
the cohort is starting to form a community and the students want it to
be a community that includes ALL of Hunter CS, not just the honors
students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They've started a once a week Dojo where students can work on projects
and interact and we're starting an evening speaker series in
the Spring. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Overall there's a vibe of excitement and an energy around Hunter CS
that I've been told hasn't been there before.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my class, I've been introducing a number of real world practices
that are usually not covered in undergraduate CS and we're starting to
talk about bringing those practices into the non-honors sections.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, we've started to partner with the New York Tech
community. We're bringing together the Hunter students and the tech
professionals to raise awareness outside of Hunter of what our
students can do and to best prepare our students for their next
steps. These partnerships, in addition to internship possibilities
have led to us planning some great things this coming semester
incuding:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;workshops such as how to work on an open source project or how to do
a code review.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having industry mentors at our local Dojo sessions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mixer events to educate our students as to the variety of pathways
they can follow when they graduate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This past year set the stage but there will be some challenges moving
forward.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The biggest one is continued outreach to high schools. Getting to the
students and their parents to let them know that we have a great
program. It's also about convincing them to come to Hunter. Back in
the day CUNY was "the poor man's Harvard" but open enrollment in the
1970s killed that reputation. CUNY has been making it's way back and
Hunter has many excellent programs but reputations are decades in the
making and at Hunter CS we're just starting to get the word out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other big challenge will be with time. Right now, for the most
part, I'm a team of one. I have tremendous support from my colleagues
but they all have their own full time obligations and the overall
growth in Hunter CS has already put a strain on personnel and
resources.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In spite of the challenges, I'm not complaining. This has been an
exciting year for Hunter CS and an exciting year for me to be a part
of it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>hunter</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2017-review-hunter-cs/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 15:05:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Using Emacs 39 - mu4e</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-39-mu4e/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb74a0f9" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgb74a0f9"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgb74a0f9"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I generally use three email accounts. My personal one, work one, and
one for my non-profit. For a couple of years, I've been using mu4e
under Emacs for both my work and non-profit email accounts and gmail
for my personal account. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've had lots of requests for a video on what I do but I've been
hesitant for two reasons:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are parts of my configuration that are copied from others and
I really don't understand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I wasn't happy with the complexity and some of the tooling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While there are still parts of my configuration that I'm not 100%
clear on I've cleaned up the tooling and complexity by using mu4e only
for my work email for the time being and by switching to mbsync. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's a writeup on configuring things with video at the end.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Unless you run an email server on your local machine using mu4e can be
thought of as three parts.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the email from the server to the local machine using IMAP.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting up mu.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access the email locally from Emacs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org1b64cf7" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org1b64cf7"&gt;Part 1 Getting the email to your local machine using mbsync&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org1b64cf7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I found his terrific blog post by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/robstewartUK"&gt;Rob Stewart&lt;/a&gt; on setting up &lt;a href="http://www.macs.hw.ac.uk/~rs46/posts/2014-01-13-mu4e-email-client.html"&gt;mbsync and
mu4e&lt;/a&gt;. Read it over. I basically followed his directions for setting up
&lt;a href="https://sourceforge.net/p/isync/isync/ci/master/tree/"&gt;mbsync&lt;/a&gt;. To build from source under Linux, I used the sequence:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;./autogen.sh
./configure
make
sudo make install
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I followed Rob's instructions basically verbatim for the password and
authentication stuff so I suggest you do the same. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You'll also have to make sure to make the necessary email directories
manually. I describe all of this in the video.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb473065" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgb473065"&gt;Part 2 - setting up mu.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgb473065"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To set up mu, clone it from git://github.com/djcb/mu.git and build
it. You can find dependencies &lt;a href="https://www.djcbsoftware.nl/code/mu/mu4e/Installation.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and then follow the same sequence
used to build mbsync listed above.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Since I store my local email under a folder &lt;code&gt;Maildir&lt;/code&gt;  which is what
mu defaults to I can start using it by indexing my emails:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;mu index
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The video shows some examples of using mu from the command line and
you can look at the mu cheatsheet &lt;a href="http://www.djcbsoftware.nl/code/mu/cheatsheet.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc1a23f5" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgc1a23f5"&gt;Setting up mu4e in emacs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgc1a23f5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, you can set up mu4e in emacs. Take a look at Rob's
configuration in his post or my &lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/using-emacs/blob/master/mu4econfig-sample.el"&gt;sample&lt;/a&gt; config. You'll have to take a
few minutes to go through either and make the appropriate changes but 
the required changes should be cleared.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The video goes through all of this and then a brief demo of how I use
mu4e.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm very happy with it and plan to integrate my non-profit email and
maybe even personal email into it soon.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/newRHXKm4H4" frameborder="0" gesture="media" allow="encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>emacs</category><category>learning</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-39-mu4e/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2017 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fixing the Absent Teacher Reserve (ATR) situation</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/atrs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgdbe92b1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgdbe92b1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgdbe92b1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the New York City department of education a recurring hot topic is
the Absent Teacher Reserve or ATR pool. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A teacher or administrator in the ATR pool is a licensed, most likely
tenured teacher not assigned permanently to a school. Each year these
educators get shuttled from school to school and denied a chance to
actually settle in a position.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The ATR pool was created under the Bloomberg administration. Prior to
that, when there was an opening school transfers were basically
seniority based and when school had too many teachers the least senior
was excessed or basically out of a job until a school with an opening
could be found. The Bloomberg plan allowed teachers to use criteria
other than seniority for transfers but so as not to violate the
contract agreed to by both parties, teachers who were excessed, as
they might not be least senior, were kept on as employees and put in
the pool.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
ATR's would rotate from school to school. Sometimes for a couple of
week but more recently for a year at a time. When at a school for only
a couple of weeks they could only be used as subs or for grunt work
but even when there for a year they're treated like second class
citizens.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The ATR pool grew in size when the Bloomberg/Klein DOE went on the war
path, set schools up to fail and closed them left and right. If you
had the bad luck being at a close out school when it closed then, hello
ATR pool.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the years, the press, ed reformers and politicians have unfairly
bashed this group of educators. They've falsely claimed that these are
criminal teachers or unsatisfactory teachers. That's a blatant
lie. Teachers up on charges are removed from schools and await a
hearing in another draconian process set up to violate teacher's
rights. If a teacher is ultimately found guilty, they are disciplined
or fired. If exonerated, they're returned to their schools. In any
case they're not ATRs. Teachers that are repeatedly found to be
unsatisfactory are likewise removed (although the process here is
ridiculous and unfair as well).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
ATRs like any pool of teachers run the gamut. Some are great, some are
poor, many will fall in between. All are stigmatized and treated like
damaged goods.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
People ask, how can a good teacher get into the ATR pool? As I said,
be at a closeout school. In the year before I was able to bring my friend
and former colleague JonAlf over to Stuy, he was at Brandeis High
School - a
closeout school. I tried to bring him over that year but his principal
wouldn't release him. Had I not been successful in bringing him over
the following year he might very well have ended up in the ATR pool
and he's one of the best teachers I know. What about the teacher that
doesn't want to abandon those kids that the DOE abandoned when they
decided to close the school. That martyr teacher surely ends up in the
ATR pool but that's the type of dedicated teacher every principal
should want.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So now we have a bunch of stigmatized teachers looking for work in a
system that won't give them a chance. Not only due to them being
considered "damaged goods" but also because they're expensive to
hire. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When a school gets an ATR to them, it's free - the cost isn't added to
their budget - they keep them as extra manpower for the year and then
throw them out with the trash. At times, they get some credit for
keeping them a second year and even beyond they can get rid of them
whenever they want. Great way to bust the contract.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A clear example of this is Stuy's  current math chair. He's an ATR
Assistant Principal. They got him for free for the first year and I
believe at a 50% discount for the second and even now they can dump
him whenever they want. This is rubbish – he's either good enough for
the position or he's not. If he is, he should be given the job for
real and if he isn't then what is he still doing there. I'm not making
any value judgment on him or the department but it's either one or the
other.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, a big reason for this ATR mess is about budgets and money. The
problem is that it's a big lie. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The DOE pretends the we have a situation like this:
&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/atr1.png" alt="atr1.png" align="center" height="250"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The DOE has money and schools have money. The schools pay for their
teachers, supplies, and everything else but the ATRS are paid for by
the DOE. Of course this isn't the case. The truth is that the DOE pays
for everything:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/atr2.png" alt="atr2.png" align="center" height="250"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
ALL the money comes from the DOE.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the past the DOE has come up with poorly conceived and poorly
received plans on how to deal with the ATR situation but it's really
quite simple.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Start by recognizing that ALL the money comes from the DOE. Once you
do that you can address the problem:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assign the ATR to a school&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the school likes the ATR and the ATR likes the school, they keep
them and the DOE picks up the tab or rather adjusts the schools
budget to compensate. The DOE will continue to do so until a real
opening occurs at the school in the ATR's area at which point the
ATR fills the position officially and the budget is readjusted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the school or ATR don't like each other the ATR gets rotated,
however you create a 3 strikes (or maybe 2 or 4 or some number)
rule.
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the school keeps sending away ATRs semester after semester hit
them with a penalty or force an ATR placement when they have an
opening (assuming the ATR is amenable).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the ATR keeps declining positions after a set number of
schools force the placement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's it. Simple and solves the problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/atrs/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 13:01:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Breaking down problems and writing</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/whats-next/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc5ebedd" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc5ebedd"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc5ebedd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This question appeared on Facebook a few days ago:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Does anyone have an effective way to teach students how to break down
a problem into steps and then solve each step one by one? I think my
students are struggling with a large question and breaking it in
subsequent parts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were some good suggestions. I wanted to add something but didn't
have time then so I thought I'd write it up now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As an aside, it took me forever to find the post again over on
Facebook. If there's a way to mark posts or save a direct link I'd
love to hear it. I had to look through all the CS Ed groups I belong
to manually until I found it again.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I read the program I was reminded of a PD session we had to
attend back at Stuyvesant. Back then the fad was &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Writing_across_the_curriculum"&gt;Writing Across the
Curriculum&lt;/a&gt;. Every teacher in every class was to give some significant
writing assignment, evaluate it and provide feedback. Let's forget the
fact that most of us never had any training or preparation to do so.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On that PD day the guest speaker was &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Zinsser"&gt;William Zinsser&lt;/a&gt;. The first thing
he said was that what we were being asked to do by our principal was
bunk. He then proceeded to give advice on  simple good writing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The procedure he recommended following was to ask yourself (or have
the student ask themselves) "what does my audience need to know next?"
That's your next sentence. Then ask the question again. Rinse and
repeat until done.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was simple and it made sense. It also applied to introductory CS
problems. When starting out, students have a limited CS / programming
tool box so a good question for them to ask when trying to solve a
problem is not only "what do I need to do next? but also "what can I
do next?" 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When students have a limited CS vocabulary and set of idioms - loops,
conditionals, functions, whatever, there will only be so many things
they can do to move a problem along. If they go through the things the
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;can&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; do they will likely fall on to what they &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;should&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's similar to doing a proof in geometry. Students have a set of
givens. Given that set, what can they do? They only know so many
theorems at the beginning. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over time, they'll recognize patterns and develop as problem solvers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're part of the AP CS A teachers facebook group you probably saw
the question. Many good answers were posted. I just wanted to add this
thought to the collection.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>problem solving</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/whats-next/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2017 16:14:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New York State moving forward with CS Teacher Certification</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/NY-CS-Certificate/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgceffcf2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgceffcf2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgceffcf2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last April I woke up early and trekked up to Albany along with a few
of my Hunter College colleagues to share our thoughts on K12 Computer
Science teacher certification with the Board of Regents. We gave a
presentation to the Regents Higher Education Committee and afterwards
had a chance to talk with some of the Regents as well as other members
of the New York State Department of Education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I left feeling that our proposals were well received and I think
everyone present - both the Hunter and NYSED contingents hoped that
things would move forward on this important issue.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward to today, December 8, 2017. I was up at the crack
of dawn. Driving in the dark in the snow from NYC to Albany to once
again attend a Board of Regents Higher Education Committee
meeting. This time, the agenda item was:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Proposed Amendments to Part 30 of the Regents Rules and Section 52.21
and Part 80 the Regulations of the Commissioner of Education Relating
to a New Certification Area and Tenure Area for Computer Science 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No discussion or debate this time around just the proposal. If I
understand the process correctly, this should come up again at the
March meeting at which point it will be voted on. If approved, it
looks like we'll have a pathway towards certification for CS teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I haven't had a chance to dive into the details but at the meeting a
few key points came up:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As the proposal indicates this will be a subject area in which a
teacher can be certified and be awarded tenure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be a traditional pathway for new teachers - Bachelors /
Masters degree&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an alternative pathway for people entering from the
workforce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an extension for teachers with another license so they
won't have to give up tenure in their current license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an "individual evaluation" pathway which sounds to me
like it could catch people who fall through the cracks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There looks to be a sensible ramp up period - until September 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's a grandfathering provision that looks to last 10 years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This sounds like a smart sensible plan. Multiple pathways, shallow
ramp up and provisions to protect existing teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, the devil is in the details. What's an approved program?
Can a grandfathered teacher teach all CS classes or just intro ones?
etc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I said, I haven't had a chance to dive into the details yet but
this is very exciting.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Prior to the meeting I was chatting with a few other people
attending. One, a &lt;a href="http://www.uft.org/"&gt;UFT&lt;/a&gt; representative was very excited about the
prospect. Another contingent, a group from &lt;a href="https://www.nysut.org/"&gt;NYSUT&lt;/a&gt; was very much against
a new certification area. Their position was that this would create a
teacher shortage because no one would have a CS license and no one
would get one due to the difference in salary between teaching and the
tech industry. I've already written on how I feel that this is a &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry"&gt;red
herring&lt;/a&gt;. What shocked me though was their feeling that "we already
have many non-CS teachers effectively teaching CS across the
state. They're doing a great job and don't need any additional content
or pedagogical knowledge." I think they're wrong and I also think that
when we as a community talk about how our summer professional
development is all that's needed, we undercut CS education and
the teaching profession as a whole.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any event this was a big step for New York. I tried to individually
thank as many of the participants as I could for helping shepherd this
along but could only speak to a few so I'll just give a blanket thank
you here to the NY State Board of Regents, Board of Education and
State Education department.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>certification</category><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/NY-CS-Certificate/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 23:57:37 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>