<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>C'est la Z</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description>C'est la Z</description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Sep 2017 14:18:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Awesome Cs Revisited</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awesome-cs-revisted/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Saw this tweet the other day so I though I would try to plug the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education"&gt;Awesome CS Education&lt;/a&gt; list I started on GitHub:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="export"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;a href="&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/csteachers?src=hash"&gt;https://twitter.com/hashtag/csteachers?src=hash&lt;/a&gt;"&amp;gt;#csteachers&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;…didn&amp;amp;#39;t I see a list of CS teacher blogs here recently?&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&amp;amp;mdash; Pam Whitlock (@PamWhitlock1) &amp;lt;a href="&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PamWhitlock1/status/910662628757864448"&gt;https://twitter.com/PamWhitlock1/status/910662628757864448&lt;/a&gt;"&amp;gt;September 21, 2017&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
To answer the tweet, the closet thing I know to a list is &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred
Thompson&lt;/a&gt;'s blog roll which is actually a post he wrote on his blog
in 2012. Unfortunately his list can be hard to find and is somewhat
out of date. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The idea of an "awesome" list is publicly hosting a simple site that
is community driven and anyone can suggest additions and edits. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I put up a starter &lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and a few people have contributed but I'd love
to get more people involved. Awesome lists have a number of advantages
over other repositories.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unlike blog posts, the site is easy to find.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unlike private mailing lists or Facebook, anyone can see the content.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone can suggest additions (although you need to create a Github
account).
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone can download or fork the site.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's essentially plain text and is easy to edit (just read the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education/blob/master/contributing.org"&gt;contribution guide&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, there you have it. If you have a blog or resource to share please
submit a pull request. Over time this could be a terrific single
starting point for educators to get to a wealth of resources.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>pd</category><category>resources</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awesome-cs-revisted/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 20:34:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New Term New Tool - Thonny, a Python IDE</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/new-tool-thonny/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last year I &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/new-term-new-tool-replit"&gt;wrote about&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://repl.it"&gt;repl.it&lt;/a&gt;, an online IDE that supports multiple
languages. At the time it had some rudimentary classroom support and
since I started using it, repl.it has become better and better. I
used it last year with my class because I had to start the year in a
lab where I couldn't easily install my own software. I'll continue to
use repl.it - mostly for it's ability to schedule publish and manage
assignments but when possible, I like having my students work
locally. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This year I'm excited about another tool - &lt;a href="http://thonny.org"&gt;Thonny&lt;/a&gt;. Thonny's a simple
Python IDE designed for beginners. I discovered it last year but at a
time when it was impractical for me to use with my students. This
year I can and I'm really liking it. I'm still an Emacs guy and will
continue to use Emacs for my python development (&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-12-python/"&gt;video 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-13-yasnippet"&gt;video 2&lt;/a&gt;) but
for beginners I think Thonny is the way to go.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some of Thonny's highlights:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An integrated Python 3 virtual environment making for ease of
installation and consistency across student installs
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A debugger that shows how expressions are evaluated
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great visualizations of function calls that make it easier to
understand the call stack and scope
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to look at memory to understand references.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Rather than go into the gory details in text, I put together this
video:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="export"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lWaCl0WjNZI"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/embed/lWaCl0WjNZI&lt;/a&gt;" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/iframe&amp;gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>teaching</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/new-tool-thonny/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 11:31:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>I Believe CS Teachers are Smart and Capable</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
People sometimes accuse me of being an elitist CS snob that I feel that CS
teachers have to have advanced CS degrees. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not that at all. Rather, I feel that CS teachers are smart and
capable. Circumstances frequently result in a teacher in front of a CS
class with limited content and pedagogical content knowledge. It's not
ideal but it's reality. Of course I feel that we should do everything
to support and encourage these teachers but we should also insist that
after a reasonable period of time, they know their stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is why I hate it when I hear people in the CS Ed community say
something is too hard. Git's too hard. The command line is too
hard. Functional programming's too hard &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. That's all nonsense. At last
year's SIGCSE conference people from a state, I forget which, was
considering not using the Praxis exam for CS teacher certification
even though the state uses the Praxis exam for other subject
areas. They claimed that the praxis was too hard for CS teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/praxis.jpg" alt="praxis.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I haven't taken the Praxis exam but some friends have. It doesn't
appear to be unreasonable at all&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.2" name="fnr.2" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fn.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While I can certainly understand a teacher not knowing much when they
start - thrown in due to necessity I think it's ridiculous not to
insist that they ultimately get to real mastery.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A math teacher generally has to know math beyond calculus. Science
teachers have to have gotten through Orgo. English teachers have to
understand Joyce. **THIS IS HARD STUFF!!!!**&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.3" name="fnr.3" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fn.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think it's insulting to say that CS teachers aren't capable of doing
the same in their subject area.
'
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;whether or not any of
these topics are appropriate for a particular course is discussion for
another time&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.2" name="fn.2" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fnr.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;although I'm not a big believer
in standardized exams for certification or in general.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.3" name="fn.3" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fnr.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are plenty of
lousy teacher prep programs that don't ensure teachers learn the
subject matter they should but the good ones do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 22:17:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Is the new Secret Sauce ever better?</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-the-new-secret-sauce-ever-better/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I read &lt;a href="http://nancyebailey.com/2017/09/05/xq-super-schools-business-working-to-end-public-high-schools/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; piece earlier today on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/NancyEBailey1"&gt;Nancy Bailey&lt;/a&gt;'s blog. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
TL;DR (although it really isn't too long so you should read it) - it's
on Laurene Powell Jobs, her efforts to "reform" education and why
she's misguided as are most of the well to do non-educators working
hard to change and in many cases privatize public education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Laura posts a nice list of simple, common sense ways to improve
education. I'll repost them here:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For years, research has shown that high school students need more sleep. They should have later start times. .
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smaller class sizes would help.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure teachers don’t have so many preparation plans.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;End advanced placement classes (IMHO).
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve career-technical classes.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide rich extra-curricular activities.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bring back life skill classes.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include a social justice curriculum.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include students on the disciplinary board.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide civics education.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure students get opportunities to participate in the arts.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work to include the community.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure students have access to counselors, and school support staff.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every high school should have a great library, a real librarian, and technology and books.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looks very much like what those elite private schools that those rich
non-educators send their kids to.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other day I also overheard a conversation between two
professors. One noted that they had just taught a course totally
online for the first time and that the professor really had fun doing
it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These got me thinking more about all the secret sauce and magic
bullets coming from tech to save education - things like MOOCS or  "personalized"
learning system.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started to wonder - have these &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;ever&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; been pushed on public
schools because they're better or rather because they cut costs (or in
the slightly better case to reach a student that otherwise wouldn't
have any opportunity which, in a way is generally cost related).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I couldn't come up with a single instance. They're always a way to
replace what I consider personalized instruction – you know, when a
teacher has a small class and can personally deal with, learn about,
interact with, and teach the child. Kids spend hours in front of a
screen instead of working with others. Kids do a MOOC (or maybe drop
out of a MOOC) so that you can have your student/teacher ratio reach
ridiculous levels. I've never seen any tech solution rolled out to
public schools because it's better. Only to cut costs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How do I know that it's not better? Well, we have Nancy's list
above. It's what those rich people pay all that money to the elite
private schools for.  If all these solutions the Jobs and Gates of the
world were so much better, wouldn't they insist upon them  for their
own children? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Just some Friday food for thought.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><category>STEM</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-the-new-secret-sauce-ever-better/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 16:32:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Theseus's Curriculum</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/theseus%27s-curriculum/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With the school year starting I was originally planning on writing
about my class rules. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Instead I think I'll riff on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt;'s post today titled
&lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/09/curriculum-is-hard.html"&gt;Curriculum is Hard&lt;/a&gt;. I'm guessing I found curriculum design and
development daunting decades ago but at this point in my career it's
something I enjoy. In any event, Alfred got me to thinking - when is a
curriculum your own?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you grab a curriculum complete with lesson plans, assignments; the
whole kit and caboodle and you use it verbatim it's clearly not your
curriculum. It probably also isn't really teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What about the more common case. Math curricula has basically been set
for years. Algebra, Geometry &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/theseus%27s-curriculum/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and then Algebra 2
and Trigonometry. Most books seem to be sequenced in a similar way
and at least in the schools I know about, the math department has some
document listing a day by day list of topics. This makes sense since
you probably have more than one class of each type and you want some
cross class consistency. Particularly during the first weeks of the
semester when kids can transfer and then also at the end of term or
year. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When a teacher uses that departmental document are they using someone
elses curriculum?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What if they create their own homeworks and assigments?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most teachers I know use the department's curriculum but make their
own unit and day to day lesson plans. Most revise them each
semester. Typically these teachers do a little more here or a little
less there depending on a number of factors.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Are they creating their own curriculum?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What if they re-sequence the topics?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How about adding an enrichment topic?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back when I taught math I used the departmental syllabus, as many
texts as I could find, colleagues lesson plans and whatever I could
find but I always pulled it together to something I could call my
own. If I didn't, I wouldn't have been comfortable going in front of
my class. Was it my curriculum? They were certainly my lessons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, when designing a course I start from the end outcomes and work
backwards but when teaching a course, I still look at as many
resources as I can find. I'll pull a little from here, a little from
there and combine that with whatever I can come up with myself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, when is it your curriculum and when is it not? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're just delivering scripted lessons it's certainly not yours.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you know your stuff and you  take someone elses material, make it
your own and add it to your bag of tricks, I think it's now yours as
well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/theseus%27s-curriculum/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;which is really logic and deductive
reasoning using Euclidean Geometry as platform&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>currulum</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/theseus%27s-curriculum/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 22:41:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>CS Teachers - we need you to blog</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-blog/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At this past year's CSTA conference, a few of us huddled in a corner
voiced a very common lament - "it would be great if more CS teachers
blogged." It really would be. We're still a relatively small
community and while there's some good conversation going on on
mailing lists and on Facebook, those aren't easily discoverable or
accessible and in the case of Facebook, there's a question of
ownership and permanence.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've been blogging on and off since 2010. Around 300 posts. Not super prolific
but I've been doing it long enough to maybe be able to share a bit of
perspective.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not sure exactly why I started. In part I was inspired by my wife
who at the time was blogging about her &lt;a href="http://squid-knits.blogspot.com/"&gt;knitting&lt;/a&gt;. I was also inspired
to share my thoughts after meeting some fellow CS teachers from across
the country at a &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2010-01-02-welcome.html"&gt;CSTA event in Chicago&lt;/a&gt;. It was stop and go for a while
and then I took a break. I was re-inspired months later after meeting
a couple of CS teachers at another CSTA event - &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=ben%2520chun&amp;amp;src=typd"&gt;Ben Chun&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/purplespatula"&gt;Helene
Martin.&lt;/a&gt; Both terrific high school CS teachers at the time who are
unfortunately no longer in the classroom (unfortunate for the kids, I
wish Ben and Helene all happiness and success in all their
endeavors). We all agreed to try to write more and that got me started
again. I've been posting around 50 times a year since.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looking back to when I used blogger, I had 30 - 50 hits on some early
posts and that was mostly just me hitting the site. It didn't matter.
Writing has let me work through my thoughts. It also creates a record of
my thoughts and on how my thinking evolves over time. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over time, people have told me that they've found some of the things
I've written useful or helpful and I'd argue that when people disagree
with something I write, even if they don't comment and I've all I've
evoked is a reaction of "Z's full of crap," it's gotten them to
re-evaluate their own thoughts on whatever the subject and if it's
confirmation of their original beliefs, that's OK.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The important thing is that by blogging I'm getting my thoughts down
"on paper" and sharing them for the world to take or leave as they
please and the more of us who do this, the more we expand the sum
knowledge of CS teaches. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a dispersed community of CS teachers across the country, we need
more people blogging on public platforms not in silos like Facebook.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've heard reasons why teachers don't blog:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;I'm new and have nothing to write about&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sure you do – write a paragraph about your plans for the days lesson
or how it went. Vent your frustrations (but be careful not to get
yourself in trouble). Rave about some students work.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;I don't have time&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yes, this is a tough one. If you have to do PD time, maybe your
supervisor will let you use it for blogging. To be honest, when I'm
writing regularly it doesn't take that long. When I haven't written in
a while it takes longer. In any event. It's important and posts don't
have to be long
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;I'm not a great writer&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This blog is proof that you don't have to be. I'm stilted and ramble
and certainly no Shakespeare. I am the weakest writer in my household
and it's not even close. Even so, we all have something to share.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;I don't know how&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was thinking about proposing a session at next years CSTA conference
where I'd work the group through creating a github pages based
blog. In the meantime, there are a lot of easy ways to start out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://blogger.com"&gt;http://blogger.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wordpress.com"&gt;http://wordpress.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
and for those who want total control
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://jekyllrb.com/"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub pages&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, there's my plea. If you're a CS teacher and you're reading this
please consider blogging. I assure you, we will all appreciate it and
benefit from it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>community</category><category>cs</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-blog/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 19:52:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Teaching APCS-A for the first time</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teaching-ap-first-time/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I got  an email from a friend the other day. Among other things, he
mentioned that he would be teaching APCS-A for the first time this
year. He's a little trepidatious. He knows his stuff but he hasn't
really done much using Java.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was going to respond in an email but thought I might share here
instead.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
TL;DR - for all you APCS teachers who are new or new to Java - learn
your core CS, lean on your resources and support and it's OK to tell
your kids "I don't know, I'll get back to you.". Don't worry, you'll be great.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first time I taught APCS was some time around 1991 or 1992. It was at
&lt;a href="http://www.sewardparkhs.com/Famous-Alumni/"&gt;Seward Park&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.sewardparkhs.com/History/"&gt;High School&lt;/a&gt;. It was the AB curriculum - that is one
semester of programming in Pascal and one semester of Data Structures
and Algorithms.  Being a computer science major the core material was
never a concern. I had taken APCS the first time it was offered in May
1984 in Pascal and while most of my college and pre-teaching professional work
was in C, my college started it's CS sequence with Pascal. I was more
concerned with the actual teaching part. I had taught math for a year
and a half at that point but never CS and by any measure I was still
wet behind the ears. I never finished that first experience because I
was excessed to Stuy mid semester. I wasn't particularly happy with my
performance but looking back, I think I did a pretty good job given
the situation and my experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After teaching math for a year and a half I was back in APCS at
Stuy. Still in Pascal. I spent the next few years figuring out how to
teach CS and APCS in particular along with starting a couple of new
classes. When the College Board decided to move the AP class to C++ I
was happy, sad and a little worried. Pascal had a bunch of limitations
but I had never used C++. True, I was a C programmer at heart but I
had never really done the OOP thing. I did, as it turned out, design a
number of my C systems in an Object Typed design: I would use a single
file per "class" where local variables were de facto instance
variables and functions in the file were methods and each file was a
singleton class. I read &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Object-Oriented-Analysis-Design-Applications-3rd/dp/020189551X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1503519770&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=Grady+Booch"&gt;Booch&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Object-Oriented-Software-Construction-Book-CD-ROM/dp/0136291554/ref=asap_bc?ie=UTF8"&gt;Meyer&lt;/a&gt; on my own but I had no
schooling in OOP and no professional experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As it turned out, I didn't have to worry. I knew my CS and while it
took me a while to become comfortable with OOP, the class, and of
course I knew this from the get go, started from nothing and built
up complexity a step at a time. The worst that might have happened is
that some of my solutions might have been more C-esque than C++.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The move to Java was a little more jarring. Now we had a totally new
language. I couldn't fall back on C. It removed memory management and
explicit pointers and it had to be used in an Object Oriented
manner. I remember asking Mike Schidlowsky, a former student turned
friend who was the Java consultant on the Java edition of Sedgewick's
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Robert-Sedgewick-Algorithms-Fundamentals-Structures/dp/B008VR3ZH4/ref=sr_1_4?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1503520269&amp;amp;sr=8-4&amp;amp;keywords=schidlowsky"&gt;Algorithms&lt;/a&gt; book how to do something. It had to do with passing and
modifying arrays. In C there were a number of ways to accomplish what
I wanted to do. In Java, I couldn't figure out how to do it the way I
wanted. My friend Mike told me "you just don't do it that way in
Java." Again, it turned out that I didn't have to worry. The basic
coding was still the same as were the data structures and
algorithms. The only challenge was that I had to get into a Java OOP
mindset which it turned out wasn't that hard. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While I never really warmed up to OOP - I find other paradigms more
natural for me, I knew my CS and got more and more comfortable with
the Java (or C++) way of doing things as time wore on. Sometimes I
would say "I don't know" or "let's figure it out" but that's OK.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Nowadays, there are many more resources available for CS teachers. If
you're new, lean on them. Use the mailing lists, stackexchange,
facebook groups. Online resources like repl.it, codehs.com etc. Yes,
it's true that you'll be better next time around and even better years
down the road but right now, you're probably better than you think.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A number of my former students volunteer for &lt;a href="https://www.tealsk12.org/"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; - a really great
program that brings software engineers into the classroom to work with
non-CS teachers to deliver instruction. A number of my kids have
shared the following sentiment: 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know if I'm really helping
the teacher to become self sufficient or if I'm a great teacher but I
do know one thing - while I'm there, the kids are getting a hell of a
lot more than if I wasn't there." 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– Remember that as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ap</category><category>apcs</category><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teaching-ap-first-time/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 19:56:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Cost of AP Exams</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cost-of-ap-exams/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that I'm back from vacation and summer's winding down I thought
I'd start getting back to more classroom related posts. I still have a
few summer topics I want to write about – standards and side projects
in particular but I'm also looking forward to talking more about the
classroom since, after all, at my core, I'm a teacher. When I saw &lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/future_tense/2017/08/how_online_textbooks_could_help_more_students_take_ap_exams.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;
article in my inbox this morning I thought I'd talk about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the piece, Lindsey Tepe since more kids are taking AP classes and
they're very expensive, schools should look to lower other costs
related to AP classes so as to provide financial support so that
students can take that oh so important end of year exam:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While the College Board continues to reimburse about one-third of the
test cost for eligible low-income students, only about half of states
are now offering any further financial assistance for students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Ms. Tepe's solution? Lower text book costs. As a way of lowering
school costs, I'm all for it. I've used free online resources in lieu
of textbooks for years but the savings should go somewhere where it
can make a difference. Perhaps lowering class sizes. The fatal flaw in
Ms. Teps's piece is that it continues spinning the misplaced narrative
that AP Exams are a very important part of a child's education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's be reminded of something: The AP Exam is one thing - an exam - a
single test at the end of the year. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The narrative is that students should take more and more AP classes,
that they're somehow better for kids. Part of this is due to the
potential college credit and part is because the public has been
bamboozled by the ridiculous school ratings that give credit for AP
classes taken. Back in "the day," AP classes were basically early
college. You could then argue that they were the most rigorous classes
offered in a school. AP Calc was basically college Calc. Same for
APCS-AB, AP-Bio and the rest. Now, with classes like APCS-P aimed to
be accessible to typical high school students in the lower grades,
they can't (but still will) make that claim. In fact, at Stuy, my
former school, there are plenty of non AP classes that are more
rigorous than AP classes and the best AP teachers don't always cover
the whole syllabus because they're more concerned with their students
actually learning rather than scoring 5 on an exam.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the college credit front, if a student has a high probability of
saving money through AP credit then I'm all for it but otherwise, it's
just money going to the college board.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It seems ridiculous for me to have to write this but the important
part of a class is, you know, the class. Not the single exam given by
an outside agency at the end and graded after the semester concludes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My suggestion? Offer college level work to students that are ready for
it but don't push the AP exam. This would save a ton of money. What value
does the college board actually bring to the table? Remember, they're
making a pretty penny on all of this testing. A math teacher should be
able to teach calculus with or without AP. A good text being used by
that teacher in class - be it free or paid for is actually much more
important to a student learning calculus than a single exam taken at
the end of the year. I'd go further and say that I'd trust the
teacher's exam more than the college board's. If a teacher knows the
math but needs to see some sample syllabi, they're a web search
way. The same is true for most other college courses that have AP
equivalents and maybe even more so for computer science.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day it should be about students learning not about
students taking high stakes exams.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ap</category><category>csed</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cost-of-ap-exams/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 11:07:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ethics, Cybersecurity, ethics, curricula  and standards</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-cybersecurity-curricula-standards/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This morning, I read &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt;'s post on &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/08/cybersecuritythis-summers-computer.html"&gt;teaching
cybersecurity&lt;/a&gt;. as Alfred says, it's something of a CS Ed buzzword this
summer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another hot topic in K12 CS Ed this summer is the inclusion of ethics
in our CS courses courtesy of efforts like the #ethicalCS twitter chat every
Wednesday at 8:00 Eastern time  hosted by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ed_saber"&gt;Saber Khan&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Discussions about both topics include "where should we be doing this?"
"What should we be doing?" and of course "How?" 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking about designing curriculum from the top down -
that is, as dictated by outside forces: principals, superintendents,
states, industry or bottom up: a teacher sees a need and designs
something for their students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The best classes I've seen are those designed by a passionate teacher
from the ground up. I met  &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dougbergmanUSA"&gt;Doug Bergman&lt;/a&gt; at this past year's CSTA conference. He's terrific. I
think he came to the conference wanting to find out more about what
cybersecurity really meant. By the second day, he was raving about all
the amazing possibilities. I'd love to be in the class he develops.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, when topics or standards are forced down from
above, I've seen something entirely different.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've observed and been involved in cybersecurity discussions  with CS
teachers. The discussion goes something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Well, we do memory allocation in course XYZ so we can give a
homework assignment there.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can rewrite the story (theme) for the assignment in our data
structures class.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We already do a crypto assignment in algorithms so we're already
doing it.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've seen the same with groups of math teachers discussing
implementing common core. They talk about resequencing topics,
rewriting a few word problems or homework assignments but at the core,
the feeling is "we already know how to teach math."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It gets worse when there's a standardized or high stakes test at the
end of the tunnel and you get the "you need this for the test" type
units.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This might not be as big of a problem in K12 CS right now because so many
teachers are just learning their craft but in established fields such
as math or college CS, when an edict comes from above telling a
teacher how to teach, unless the teacher really believes in it, the
teacher will only pay lip service to it. If it isn't an issue in CS Ed
right now, it will eventually become one as our field develops legs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is arguably a bigger issue with Ethical CS than cybersecurity. If
the teacher doesn't really believe it's an important topic, we'll get
lip service at best and in the case of ethics, unless the teacher
really believes it and models it, the students will be able to tell
that it's a show.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't have an answer other than what my friend and mentor Herb
Greenhut told me many years ago "Solving the education problem is
easy. Hire good teachers and get the f*ck out of the way."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>curriculum</category><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-cybersecurity-curricula-standards/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2017 11:43:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Grit: A Kind Word and a Gun</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/grit-kind-word-gun/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back in May, I read this &lt;a href="http://avc.com/2017/05/grit/"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about Angela Duckworth and &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Grit-Passion-Perseverance-Angela-Duckworth-ebook/dp/B010MH9V3W/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1501543669&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=Grit"&gt;Grit&lt;/a&gt;. Grit
has become an education buzzword in the past few years so I figured I
should read Duckworth's book. It took this long because there was a
long waiting list at the New York Public Library to get the ebook. I'm
still not quite finished with the book but I thought I'd share some of
my thoughts on the book and the buzz.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first big takeaway is "you can get much further with a kind word
and a gun than with a kind word alone." Or in grit terms Duckworth
says a number of times that Grit is important but that other factors
such as talent do indeed come into play and towards the end of the
book she lists other character qualities that are arguably more
important than grit. I'll get back to grit + other qualities towards
the end of this post.  On the buzz side, all of that's forgotten - in
the ed reform world it's all grit all the time. We must teach it at
our low income schools and we should include grit in our evaluation of
teachers and schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Duckworth recently has come out to say grit shouldn't be used in
evaluating schools and teachers but as I mentioned &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/outside-influences-on-cs-ed/"&gt;a few days ago&lt;/a&gt;,
ed reformers have ways of taking arguably good ideas and using them towards
awful ends.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So we have a basic premise that hard work and sticktoitiveness is
important but so is talent. Talent alone won't get you as far as
talent and grit. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So in spite of the "ed reformers" take on grit, given Duckworth's
balanced perspective, I was hooked.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Where Duckworth started to lose me, however is when she dove into the
education landscape for examples.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First up is Teach for America. Certainly the founder, Wendy Kopp is
full of grit and Duckworth talks about teachers needing to be gritty
but when you talk about TFA, you're talking about a group that:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has a 5 week training program - not nearly enough to learn to teach
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has a 2 year commitment before moving to "better things"
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;encourages practices like scripted lessons
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
None of this sounds particularly gritty to me. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Duckworth also highlights the KIPP charter chain as an terrific
example of grit and the success that follows. She touts KIPP's
graduation rate neglecting to mention that like most other charters
claiming miracles, KIPP's stats should be eyed with scrutiny (&lt;a href="http://garyrubinstein.teachforus.org/2011/07/08/kipp-on-trickin-looking-at-the-raw-data/"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://garyrubinstein.wordpress.com/2016/01/22/whatever-happened-to-kipp/%0A"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://garyrubinstein.wordpress.com/2017/04/28/4th-best-high-school-in-new-york-is-a-kipp-school-that-doesnt-exist/"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;). I would have expected a researcher to dig a little deeper.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My friend, former colleague, and TFA alum Gary Rubinstein visited a
KIPP school in NY a few years ago. His take:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So what I saw there was not very impressive.  I didn’t see any classes
where teachers were getting that mythical period and half of growth in
one period.  I saw some good teaching, mostly average teaching, and
even some very bad teaching.  I saw a novice teacher struggle to
control a class of nine students.  They were walking all over him and
accomplished very little that period.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And in terms of KIPP's grit training:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;I also saw the ‘grit’ training program which amounted to the students
getting the teacher to define very clearly how little homework they
would have to do to still get their candy bar rewards.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, Duckworth holds up Geoffrey Canada's as another shiny example
failing to notice that again, the &lt;a href="http://garyrubinstein.teachforus.org/2013/05/12/canadas-legend-ary-ted-talk-lie/"&gt;Emperor has no clothes&lt;/a&gt; and if you
look at attrition, the results are far from stellar.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All of this left me thinking that if Duckworth was so off base with
these three example where I have some details of the behind the scenes
going on, how much can I trust the rest of the book?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In spite of this, I still agreed with Duckworth's basic premise so I
read on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Later in the book, Duckworth talks about developing grit. This quote struck me:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Like a lot of parents I had a strong intuition that grit is enahnced
by doing activities like ballet… or piano … or football…
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It struck me because it seemed funny coming from a researcher. It
reminded me of Christopher Alexander's "A Timeless Way of Building," a
book on architecture that is sometimes credit as the root source for
Object Oriented Programming. Alexander talks about how societies
throughout history and throughout the world "knew" how to build
certain structures – barns, homes with certain features, even
towns. Back in the day we didn't have engineering and architecture
schools but we figured out how to do these things and we figured it
out pretty much universally. Duckworth is basically saying "parents
know." It reminded me of my belief - "teachers know." This applies to
teaching content and teaching skills like grit. You can't script a
grit lesson. A good teacher knows when a student needs encouragement,
when a student needs to be coddled and when a student needs to be
redirected. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This post has been something of a ramble but I want to get back to 
grit and other qualities and how people are talking about grit as the
be all and end all and not just a component.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over on &lt;a href="http://avc.com"&gt;AVC&lt;/a&gt;, in the post that got me to read Grit, Fred closed with:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;If you hire and manage people, if you run start and run companies, if
you invest in people and their projects, then Grit is a book you
should read.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He's absolutely right but remember the whole person and what you've
prescreened for before you consider grit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Way back when discussions were ongoing about the design for &lt;a href="https://www.afsenyc.org/"&gt;AFSE&lt;/a&gt; -
before the DOE stopped returning my emails and froze me out of the
process I was at am meeting. A bunch of tech industry heavy hitters
were there. We were arguing over admission screening - did the school
need one. My position was that if you wanted to produce "Google ready"
engineers after high school you needed one. If that wasn't the goal
you didn't. One of the DOE representatives posed a question to the
tech people: "what qualities do you look for in a hire?" This elicited
responses like hard working, able to work with others, able to
communicate. The DOE person was proud to have made his point that
these tech companies weren't looking for talent, advanced skills
anything similar - grit was all you needed. I followed up - "and from
what schools do you look for the kids with these qualities?" - MIT,
Harvard, Cornell… and the tech people got it - they were already
screening for the academic stuff so all that was left to look for were
the other skills. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Should we look at grit? Certainly. Just remember that it's a piece of
the puzzle just like everything else.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>soft skills</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/grit-kind-word-gun/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 11:19:11 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>