<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about ap</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/ap.atom</id>
  <updated>2017-07-12T12:01:27Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/ap.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/ap/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>A Plea to AP teachers- don't measure yourself by your scores</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teachers-you-arent-your-test-scores/</id>
    <updated>2017-07-06T17:22:10-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-07-06T17:22:10-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teachers-you-arent-your-test-scores/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
AP scores just came out. As usual, I see the posts and take part in
conversations where teachers talk about their results. Some are happy
about their results, some aren't, some don't really care.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I just want to make a plea to all AP teachers out there:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Don't let your value be dictated by the college board or any other
  exam.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I never really cared much about my students' actual AP scores. There
were a number of years when I never even saw the results. Of course, I
had a population that would do reasonably well regardless of teacher
so I was never placed under any pressure to "do better." One year -
while the APCS-AB exam was still offered, my principal called me down
to discuss the results to see if we could get more kids scoring 4s and
5s (which most of the kids already did). I told him that I thought
we were doing fine, explained why I couldn't advocate more teaching to
the test (such as more than paying lip service to the case study or
more rote practice on the multiple choice), and told him how I
measured our success as a program. He was happy with my answer and
that was that. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The AP exam is one test on one day and in my opinion the least
valuable measure of my students' achievement. This is one of
the reasons I was so dismayed by the CSEd community's efforts in
pushing the AP exams - not the class or the subject but the actual exam.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, how should you judge your success? That's up to you. I can only
tell you how I judge myself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First and foremost - and I know this sounds cheesy - are you a "force
for good" in your student's lives. Do you leave them in a better
place? Have you opened the door to a possible future for them? Have
you helped them grow? Beyond that, have they progressed in your
subject and as students in general.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've had kids "fail" the AP exam and go on to wonderful careers in
tech and come back to thank me for giving them their start. I've also
had kids that have gone into other fields but appreciate what we've
done for them. I've also had my failures and I do mean my
failures. Students I couldn't reach or couldn't figure out how to
help.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As teachers, we work day to day trying to improve but we can get a
great overview of how we're doing by using a much longer feedback
loop - looking at what our graduates are up to. When young teachers
would comment on former students coming back or running into them at
tech events that they would have graduates of their own in a few years
and invariably they do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To really evaluate how you're doing you have to go with the long
game. Very few people get that. I remember talking to a Google
Executive while I was designing CAPE 2010. He said something to the
effect of "I know we won't know if this program works for about ten
years but we'll have to come up with something short term to satisfy
the powers that be."  That so few "get it" and need instant feedback
is one of the reasons that our society is so test driven. We shouldn't
be. Our focus should be on helping the students learn and progress.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So don't get distressed over AP results and don't get to high on them
either. Certainly don't use them to drive what and how you teach. Let
your students and your conscience be your guide.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="ap" label="ap"/>
    <category term="apcs" label="apcs"/>
    <category term="csed" label="csed"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
