<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about assessment)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/assessment.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 12:59:42 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Making contest problems and writing tests</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-2017-making-tests/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'm now well behind in &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt;. Traveling up to Michigan to see
my son and my brother and his family will do that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was planning on working to catch up but got distracted earlier by
&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/comments/7idn6k/question_why_does_the_difficulty_vary_so_much/"&gt;this thread&lt;/a&gt; on the Advent of Code subreddit. Specifically &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/comments/7idn6k/question_why_does_the_difficulty_vary_so_much/dqy08tk/"&gt;this comment&lt;/a&gt;
by &lt;a href="http://was.tl/"&gt;Eric Wastl&lt;/a&gt;, the contest creator. The thread is about the level of
difficulty of the various problems and Eric's comment talks about some
of the factors that go into creating a good collection of problems for
a contest and the difficulties involved.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It made me think of a conversation I had twenty years ago with Rob
Kolstad. We were chatting at a programming competition while the
students were hacking away. We were discussing that there were only so
many questions that a typical high school or college competition can
ask:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Mathy question
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recursion / divide and conquer etc.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graph stuff
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dynamic Programming
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and I think one or two more. The actual questions were just window
dressing on these fundamental question types. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can see this in many competitions including Advent of Code -
particularly if you look over all three years. This is not a
criticism. I love Advent of Code and think that Eric and the people
he's working with are doing a great job . Read Eric's comment to get a
deeper dive into what he thinks about as a contest designer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also got to thinking how similar creating a competition is to
creating an exam. Maybe that's because I'm currently writing the final
my students will take in a couple of days. In class tests are
certainly not the best of assessments but they do have their place and
in any event, they're frequently  required by school or departmental
policy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are many similarities between what teachers consider when making
tests to what contest designers consider. What concepts and techniques
must the students use? Are the problems too similar? Do they ramp up
in difficulty? Are they all or nothing or can a student incrementally
work their way to a solution? Does one problem lead into another? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's no big reveal or surprise here today. Just something I've been
thinking about. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of busy days coming up but maybe over the weekend I can get
back to Advent of Code.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>assessment</category><category>contests</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-2017-making-tests/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2017 23:39:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A test result is just a test result</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This past weekend was &lt;a href="http://catskillsconf.com"&gt;Catskillsconf&lt;/a&gt; - my favorite event of the
year. I spent the weekend up in Ulster County with a bunch of my
students. some great friends old and new, and Devorah. It was a great
weekend but I was mostly offline.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a result I missed a rather heated discussion in the CS Ed Facebook
groups. The debate was over whether or not Strong AP CSP exam results
are indicative of a good curriculum or good professional development (PD).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;TL;DR - NO!!!!!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Further, anyone who thinks that a set of exam results can tell you
that a particular PD sequence or curriculum is good shouldn't be
allowed to call themselves a teacher and I don't want them anywhere
near my kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I guess that language is strong, even for me but it's true.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tests are designed to assess students and many tests don't even do
that well. They shouldn't be used to measure something further
removed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The last time this idea made its rounds was using student test results
for teacher evaluation. They do that in NY. A judge called the
practice "capricious" and "arbitrary." My friend and former
colleague Gary Rubinstein showed a year or so ago that standardized
test scores varied enough from year to year so as to make the ratings
useless &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Using test scores to say a PD sequence is good? What if that PD
focused on test prep? What if it did nothing in particular? When I was
at Stuy and when I was at Seward Park the Calc teachers' students had
great AP results. I can tell you that none of those teachers had any
quality PD specific to AP Calc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Curriculum? My mentor and friend Danny Jaye told me many times - "A
great teacher can save a class from a  horrible curriculum but a great
curriculum will do nothing for a class with a horrible teacher." He
was right. Again, what if the curriculum encourages test prep. What if
pressure on the teacher encourages them to focus on test prep
regardless of curriculum or PD (see my recent &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/standards-who-for"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
An AP test measures one thing - how well the student did on the AP
test. There are so many variables that go into a class:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it first period at 8:00am?
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it the last class of the day?
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it before lunch or right afterwards?
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What about right after Gym.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's the mix of students - every class is different
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the teacher teaching the subject once a day? Two times? Five
times?
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How large is the class
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many other classes are the kids taking?
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The list goes on and on. There are so many contributing factors that
you just can't say "Good test results = good curriculum" or "good test
results = good PD."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Want to know if a curriculum is good - have experienced teachers who
know their subject run it a few times through and ask them. Same for
PD.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teachers know education a lot better than test makers, curriculum
developers and PD providers. How about listening to them for a change?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;sorry, I just got back from the weekend trip and am too tired
to find the link. You can go to his site and search and while you're
there, there's lots of good stuff to read.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>assessment</category><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 00:17:21 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>