<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about C)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/c.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 12:59:17 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Rite Of Passage Projects</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/rite-of-passage-projects/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org4e176fd" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org4e176fd"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org4e176fd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JCS's &lt;a href="https://irreal.org/blog/?p=7414#comment-4045190612"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on Irreal today brought me back. It was about &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brief_(text_editor)"&gt;Brief&lt;/a&gt; which
was the editing hotness back in the day. I played with it a little
really mostly used Emacs clones for real work when I was stuck on
MS-DOS systems. Usually either &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JOVE"&gt;JOVE&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epsilon_(text_editor)"&gt;Epsilon&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the comments Jon reminded me about the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MKS_Toolkit"&gt;MKS Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;
which brought most everyday Unix tools to DOS along with a shell and
a version of Vi. I didn't use Vi much and I only used their shell
until I wrote my own. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking about "rite of passage" projects. I was in
college in the mid to late 80s. It was the heyday of the
IBM-PC. Schools still used older time sharing systems like DEC-20s and
Vaxen but the PC was all the rage. The cool thing about them was that
you had full control and access to the machine and it was simple
enough to get your head around pretty much everything about it. The
downside was that MS-DOS was very limited and of course there was
little to no networking going on. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the one hand, you could dive into the low level machine language
stuff very easily. Get Norton's book:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://covers.openlibrary.org/b/id/7446489-L.jpg" alt="7446489-L.jpg" align="center" height="250"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and you're on your way. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand many student's graduated with no concept of time
sharing and the ramifications of sharing a system or resources were
foreign to many kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even though we always look back to the "good old days," in many ways
things weren't much different. I got a very strong background in
academic CS from NYU (Courant Institute) but just like today, there
was no real preparation for the real world.If you wanted to really develop your
coding chops you had to work on side projects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I seem to recall, a typical "rite of passage" side project was writing
your own shell. It didn't have to be anything as powerful as BASH or
ZSH but it would typically be much more powerful than DOS and much
more Unixy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I recall writing my first shell down in UC-49 of Tisch Hall when the
computer labs weren't busy. I wrote it in C which was what the cool
kids used back then. Specifically I used the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Williams_Company"&gt;Let's C&lt;/a&gt; compiler from the
Mark Williams company. This was before Turbo C 2.0 so Let's C was
pretty much the only game in town for a cheap Unix style C compiler
for DOS. There was also Run/C but that was a C interpreter, not a
compiler. I also used that to learn C. Funny story - I certainly
didn't know this at the time but Run/C was written by Peter
Brooks. Peter and I would later meet when he became my colleague at
Stuyvesant teaching CS and I now have the privilege of being able to
call him friend. I joke that I owe him ~ $100 for the interpreter from
back in the day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since this was on DOS, I couldn't do real Unix style pipes like 
&lt;code&gt;cat file | sort | uniq -c | sort -n&lt;/code&gt; but I did simulate it with redirection and temporary
files. It also supported aliases, simple scripts and I think a few
other things. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was pretty happy with it and used it for a couple of years. It was
also one of the first substantial programs I wrote. I learned a lot
from doing it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another "rite of passage" program that was common back then was a
text based window library. Somethig like ncurses that would allow you
to make text based windows and menus on the text only screen. I also
wrote one of these and actually got to use it for a project when I
started working at Goldman. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I guess the third "rite of passage" project I remember was writing a C
compiler but that was different because it was for a class. It was a
significant project but the class didn't really help with writing a
large program in general - it was all about the compiler and all the
theory behind it. Great course but not one in software engineering.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Nowadays the projects have changed. Text based windowing is long gone
and while I still think writing a shell is a useful and rewarding
exercise it's not scratching an itch the way it did back when we were
stuck on DOS. I guess writing a full stack web app is probably a
pretty typical one for students these days. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Any others?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C</category><category>cs</category><category>emacs</category><category>programming</category><category>projects</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/rite-of-passage-projects/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 19:18:11 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>