<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about email, emacs, tools)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cat_email-emacs-tools.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 21:25:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Using Emacs Episode 49 mu4e-conversation</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-49-mu4e-conversation/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org8a3b4fb" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org8a3b4fb"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org8a3b4fb"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've been using Emacs for email for a couple of years now. Not for
everything, for now my personal email is still Gmail but work is sent
and read through Emacs. I'm currently using &lt;a href="https://www.djcbsoftware.nl/code/mu/mu4e.html"&gt;mu4e&lt;/a&gt; and while it has a
few quirks and limitations, I like it very much. You can take a look
on how I configure and use it &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-39-mu4e/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other day I saw &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/emacs/comments/8qryri/mu4econversation_single_buffer_fullthread_display/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; thread on Emacs about a new package -
&lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/ambrevar/mu4e-conversation"&gt;mu4e-conversation&lt;/a&gt;. It's a package that deals with email threads.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's pretty cool. You can invoke it whenever you're in the headers
view you can just run &lt;code&gt;M-x mu4e-conversation&lt;/code&gt; and it combines all the
email messages in the current thread into a single buffer. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's pretty nice. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can navigate between messages in the thread with &lt;code&gt;C-c C-n&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;C-c C-p&lt;/code&gt; and use most if not all of the usual mu4e goodness but on
top of that you can also toggle what the author calls tree mode by
hitting &lt;code&gt;V&lt;/code&gt;. Tree mode turns the thread into an org-mode tree - also
extremely cool.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On top of this, you can also make mu4e your default viewing mode by
setting a single variable with &lt;code&gt;(setq mu4e-view-func 'mu4e-conversation)&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Although it's very cool, I'm not sure if mu4e-conversation will find
its way into my workflow or not and probably won't know for a
while. This is mostly due to the fact that it's summer so work email
slows down and I won't have too many long threads to play with this
on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'll report back once I give it a fair shake but in the meantime if
anyone out there has had the time to play with it, let us know what
you think.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/V5efS8uXANI" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>editing</category><category>emacs</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-49-mu4e-conversation/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2018 17:28:41 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>