<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about cheating</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cheating.atom</id>
  <updated>2017-12-22T12:59:43Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cheating.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cheating/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Collaborative Coding or Cheating</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/collaborative-coding-or-cheating/</id>
    <updated>2016-05-20T07:25:13-04:00</updated>
    <published>2016-05-20T07:25:13-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/collaborative-coding-or-cheating/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I haven't been teaching this past semester. That's why I haven't been
writing much about lessons. I miss working with students but that will
resume in the fall and this semester has allowed me to get a jump on
new projects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's also allowed me to look at some student issues from a bit of a
distance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One issue that keeps coming up is cheating. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some of it, classroom cheating. my friend &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cscheerleader"&gt;Ria&lt;/a&gt; recently asked a
question on Facebook about it. A nice thread ensued but unfortunately,
it's locked in the Facebook silo. I've got a lot to say on that and
hope to explore it soon but today let's focus on project
cheating - something that could just as easily apply to homeworks and
student essays and research papers as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One part of the question is on students using code they find out in
the wild. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred&lt;/a&gt; wrote a bit about it on his blog &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2016/05/copying-codesteal-from-best.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; where he points
out some pluses, some minuses, and raises some good thought points.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I want to keep it in the class - code sharing amongst students,
project and source code submission, and group projects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teachers have all sorts of options these days including:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using a CMS like Blackboard or Moodle
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dropbox based solutions
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emailing projects
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using development tools and sites such as git with GitHub, BitBucket
or other repository hosting services
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've always been a fan of having the kids learn real software
engineering skills along with the CS so Git, GitHub and public repos
have been my weapon of choice.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Interesting enough, I've gotten an earful both from fellow teachers
and professors and online for my stance on public repos. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I keep hearing "the kids will copy from each other" or something like
that. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As Alfred said in his post: "Students have been copying from
classmates for years."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Students who want to copy assignments have done so long before we've
been teaching CS and they'll be doing it for years to come. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Using a hidden submission system doesn't help and could hurt.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Far better to create an open environment. You get an opportunity to
talk about code sharing, attribution, learning from each other,
supporting each other, and where to draw the line.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On top of that, the students learn a real tool set and have a chance
to learn real development methodologies.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a win all around.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Will open repos stop cheating and irresponsible copying? Certainly
not. It could, however, raise awareness. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So what do I do on the cheating front?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Besides trying to create a culture where cheating is discouraged,
cooperation is encouraged but where students know the line, I will try
to keep them honest. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Frequently, the day a big project is due, I'll give a quiz on the
project. Students will have to describe parts of the project and what
they did. Either a student will have had to contributed or at least
will have had to have studied the rest of the teams code to pass the
quiz.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
GitHub also gives tools that help. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's the GitHub graph for a project:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/github-graph.png" alt="github-graph.png" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can see who did what and when. The teacher can drill down further
to examine the diffs – what code did each student write, when, and
from where. If two students submit very similar code, the commit
timestamps will even tell you who was first.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The tooling for teachers could be better but the infrastructure is
there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Technology isn't going to prevent cheating and more often than not, it
seems that measures taken don't stop the bad guys but inconvenience
those trying to do it right.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Much better to build a class culture where the kids want to do it the
right way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cheating" label="cheating"/>
    <category term="git" label="git"/>
    <category term="github" label="github"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
