<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about civic tech)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/civic-tech.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2017 20:38:39 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>PDF 2016 - How we lost the open web</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pdf2016-lost-in-the-silo/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent the last couple of days attending &lt;a href="http://go.personaldemocracy.com/"&gt;Personal Democracy Forum
2016&lt;/a&gt;, described on their landing site as:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The world’s leading conference exploring and analyzing technology's
impact on politics, government, and society.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's the reason why I haven't posted my latest Emacs video.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
PDF is a great conference and raised a huge number of important
issues. I'll probably blog about a few over the next few weeks. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One topic that I've already lamented about has been the way we as a
society are allowing so much information to be silo-ed in platforms
like Facebook.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I use Facebook as much as the next guy but it always irks me when I
see a CS Education post followed by rich discussion hidden within
Facebook's walls and not available for discovery to the outside world
and the future.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I generally don't get a lot of comments on my posts, but when I do,
more appear in the Facebook link to my post rather than publicly on
the post itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the conference, we watched a video by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hossein_Derakhshan"&gt;Hossein Derakhshan&lt;/a&gt; which
talked about the direction the web is moving in and the red flags it
should raise with all of us. He echoed my concerns and beyond but in a much more
eloquent way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm urging you to take the less than ten minutes to watch this
video. I know school's winding down for all of us but for those of you
who are teachers out there - share this with your students. I'm sure a
rich discussion will follow.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/oBLAZZd_Xqc" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description><category>civic tech</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pdf2016-lost-in-the-silo/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2016 18:41:32 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>