<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about college)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/college.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2018 19:54:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Hunter CS - a lot of progress in a short time</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgeeb0211" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgeeb0211"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgeeb0211"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I was back on campus for an early orientation session for
Hunter's incoming Daedalus CS honors students. It was the first time
all of us got to meet face to face. The students I met with will be
my third cohort. I got to thinking how far we've come in under three
years. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hunter's had a strong but little known undergraduate
CS program for as long as I've known. Much like any program, we've got
our strengths and weaknesses but you go through our program and
academically you'll be as well prepared as from anywhere else. We have some
challenges being a commuter school, a liberal arts school and a school
not commonly thought of for CS but the core has always been there.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hunter has been making a concerted effort to up its computer science
game and my joining the team has been part of that. The Daedalus
program is an honors scholarship program. It's similar to the well
known CUNY Macaulay program but it's specific to Hunter and specific to
CS. Our kids get scholarships, laptops, special classes (with me),
activities and events and more. Our first cohort had 12. This past
year we had 23 but a funny thing happened right after we started. Hunter's
Macaulay CS students heard about what was going on and wanted in. The
end result was that last years cohort had a total of 27 students
as we invited the incoming Hunter Macaulay CS students into the
fold. This year, we're up to about 50 total and it looks to be a very
strong group. To be honest I'm a little
scared of growing this quickly. The kids will be great but it will be
a challenge building the community across multiple classes. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm really pleased with the first two cohorts performance both in
class and out. They're progressing well through the academic program
and are ahead of schedule in terms of internships and outside
activities but I'm even happier that they've been working to level up
Hunter CS as a whole. They started a once a week Dojo last year where
all Hunter CS students could hang out and work on tech projects and
have a speaker series on tap for this coming year. For my part, I've
got a couple of new ideas up my sleeve but I'm going to keep them
under wraps for now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Three years ago Hunter wasn't so much on the map for CS inclined high
school students and while there's much work to be done, many of our
incoming cohort members chose us over other programs that have
traditionally been considered CS strongholds.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the same time, our efforts to connect Hunter CS to the NY Tech community have begun to
raise our profile on the other end of the pipeline.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's still a long rode ahead but I thought I'd give myself a day to
look back on how far we've come in a short time. Having a great public college option for CS
education is critical for NYC. This was one of the things I left Stuy to
accomplish and we're well on our way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>college</category><category>cs</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-year-two/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 21:41:05 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>