<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>C'est la Z (community)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/community.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2016 00:14:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>West coast trip - a nice close to act I</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;

&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/facebook.jpg" alt="facebook.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If I look at my leaving Stuyvesant and the NYC Department of
Education to join Hunter College as the end of Act I of my teaching
career, then our family's West Coast swing was a nice way to pull
down the curtain.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The impetus for the trip was visiting Batya - she's interning at
Facebook this summer and having an absolute blast.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The plan was to spend a few days in San Francisco, then a little south
to Mountain View, where Batya was staying, and then fly up to Seattle
for a couple of days.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, while out there, why not see if some of the StuyCS family
wanted to get together.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I knew I had a lot of former students out on the West Coast but still, I was
overwhelmed and humbled by the number of people who wanted to spend
time and catch up. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We kicked things off at Bloomberg Beta thanks to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/roybahat"&gt;Roy Bahat.&lt;/a&gt; Roy was
never actually my student but we've gotten to know each other over the
years and I value him as a friend and advisor. Roy provided the food
and the space and about 60 former students + a few old timers showed.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/bloomberg.jpg" alt="bloomberg.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of days later, we had a lunch meetup for the Googlers:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/google.jpg" alt="google.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and a happy hour at Facebook (sorry, no picture). Then in Seattle, a
nice dinner to close things out.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/seattle.jpg" alt="seattle.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Between these events there were some lunches, a barbecue at Batya's
place  and even a drive by visit with a former student at
Microsoft. Overall, it was easily over 100 students over the course of
the week or so we were out there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've often said that one of the things I'm proudest of is helping to
build the StuyCS family. A community of people spanning decades. Over
the week, we had events mixing students from the mid 90's to
youngsters currently in college and on their internships.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Seeing all these people meeting and supporting each other gave me a
"proud pappa" type feeling even though I didn't do any more than set
the stage for them getting together.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the week, the conversations were also great - not the straight
tech ones, but the ones that really made me proud of the crew. From
Seth talking about how to better get good CS Ed to more kids, to PJ
discussing why he feels it's so important to be an active mentor to
his young programmers and how to get them to be real thinkers, to
Mike, Sam, Kathy, and Leo discussing the disconnect between
privileged families and those struggling to get by. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What more could a teacher want than their former students being both
happy in their lives and careers as well as good people seeking to
make the world better for everyone.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The only thing that made me sad about the trip is that with all the
big events, I really didn't get a chance to spend the time I wanted
with everyone. I hope to do better next time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, I've now been at Hunter for one semester and things will really
ramp up in the Fall. I'm still a proud part of our StuyCS family and if
being a part of pulling it together is the legacy I left, I can live
with that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The trip was a nice symbolic way to lower the curtain on act 1. I'm
counting on the StuyCS family and all the other players to help so
that we can make sure act 2 is a success and we can build something
similar for more young people throughout the city and perhaps the country. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>community</category><category>teaching</category><category>tech</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 17:18:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Discussion Silos</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-03-discussion-silos.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In response to the past couple of days where my friends and fellow CS
Ed advocates Alfred Thompson, Rob Underwood, and I had a nice little
discussion via our blogs, Alfred wrote &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2016/01/when-blogging-works-for-educators.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's great when a number of voices in the community have an open
discussion but one of the things I found myself lamenting was the fact
that a lot of the discussion isn't truly accessible.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why not? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The silo known as Facebook.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have no problem with Facebook - I like it and use it daily - it's a great way to
keep in touch with former students turned friends. The problem is that
much like Las Vegas, discussions that happen on Facebook stay on
Facebook.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Recently I've seen a number of blog posts, some mine, some Alfred's,
some others where the post garnered nary a comment. Head over to
Facebook  and if you're friends with the right people, you might find
a lively, informative discussion. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In one case in particular, one post had independent, overlapping
discussions in at least three Facebook threads.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How much richer would the discussion have been  in a public forum
plus it would be left open for people to discover in the future.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Personally, I use &lt;a href="http://disqus.com/"&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt;. I like it since I can also follow people on
it and I can just embed the code in any page but others like what
Wordpress or Blogger uses for comment threads. In any event, it keeps
the conversation open.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Is this really a problem? Maybe not but I do wish people would look
beyond Facebook for discussions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's something I've been trying to get my students to do for
years. I've used a number of tools for class communication:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mail lists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Piazza&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;custom forum software like vanilla&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;slack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and haven't found anything that really does the job quite right. I'm
still looking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The kids use these but invariably end up also setting up a Facebook
group for my class and their other classes. I encourage this - they
certainly should have a forum that I can't see. How else can they plan
that surprise party for me :-). In all seriousness though, ideally
they should have a forum free of teachers but they should use the one
with the teacher as much as possible.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The real problem with the kids setting up Facebook groups every year
is that there's no institutional memory. I see the kids, year after
year, have to clear the same hurdles. If they started thinking outside
of the silo of their Facebook communities and just had an ongoing
community for each class - one that passed on from year to year, it
would be of tremendous value for them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, I'd like to encourage everyone out there to get our discussions
out into public forums. It would be terrific if more of us would blog
or blog more often and also to take the time to add to the dialog in a
public place.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>community</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-01-03-discussion-silos.html/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Halloween 2015 - the video</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-01-halloween-video-2015.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a teacher, sometimes your gut tells you to do something and it
turns out to be a really good idea.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's what happened in October, 1994. I decided to dress up as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Groo_the_Wanderer"&gt;Groo
the Wanderer&lt;/a&gt; for Halloween. I never dressed in costume for school
before and back then, no many did. A few students and very few
teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Afterwards, I noticed that my younger students - the ones that didn't
know me that well yet, really loosened up and so a tradition was born.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over each of the next 20 Halloweens, I did something
different. Sometimes solo, sometimes as a pair and more recently as
part of a team.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What started as a lark has now become something of an obligation but
it's still fun.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, with no further ado, let's go to the video tape:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="center"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/81qHI-iNkXg" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And of course, the full playlist:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="center"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?list=PL9KxKa8NpFxJYgovyJhF4HZRsAqYKBLiG" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>community</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-01-halloween-video-2015.html/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Inner voices</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-30-halloween-2015.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
div.half {width:50%;}
&lt;/style&gt;



&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/halloween-2015/inner-voices.jpg" alt="inner-voices.jpg" width="480px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's Halloween again. This time, "Inside Out." 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No video yet, but stay tuned.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For the time being, enjoy some of our past madness:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?list=PL9KxKa8NpFxJYgovyJhF4HZRsAqYKBLiG" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description><category>community</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-30-halloween-2015.html/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2015 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Something growing in the Hudson Valley</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description></description><category>community</category><category>misc</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015.html/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>CS Semi Formal</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-06-15-semi-formal.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today marked the last day of classes and time for the 8th annual Stuy
CS Semi Formal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What's the Stuy CS Semi Formal? It's another bad idea that we refuse
to let die. Eight years ago JonAlf joked that someone in class joked
that they should have a party and they should all get dressed up. My
thought? "YEAH!!! LET'S DO IT!!!!!"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Eight years later, still going strong.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We cleaned out and decorated the room - classed things up by serving
cheese, dried fruits, nuts and the like. Drinks served in fake plastic
"wine" glasses and we encouraged the kids to dress up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;Pictures from the first year -  2007&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p style="float:left"&gt;
&lt;figure style="float:left;padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img width="350px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/last-day-2015/semi-1.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img width="350px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/last-day-2015/semi-2.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="clear:both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;And from 2011&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
&lt;p style="float:left"&gt;
&lt;figure style="float:left;padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img width="350px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/last-day-2015/semi-3.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img width="350px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/last-day-2015/semi-4.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="clear:both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Kids can come and go any period they don't have any other class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a signature event and a fun time. Whats more is that throughout
the day you've got pockets of CS students all dressed to the nines in
all their other classes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For the first few years JonAlf and I did the heavy lifting but these
past two, it's all been the students - particularly Jenny, Miranda,
and Veronika (apologies if I'm missing anyone).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's just another event that makes StuyCS unique.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>community</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-06-15-semi-formal.html/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2015 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Just another day at StuyCS</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-08-antother-day-stuycs.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.photo {width:60%;}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;img class="photo" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/just_another_day/pic.jpg"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last post was a little heavy so just a short fun one for today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
"Just another day at StuyCS." That was the subject of the email Brian
sent with the photo above. What's going on?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We're working on advanced JavaScript while also looking at
&lt;i&gt;Backbone.js&lt;/i&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, as sometimes happens, Batya, while in her CS class up at college,
decided to open up a Google chat with me. This happens now and then. We try to
have some fun with it. We actually have a plan to mess with the kids
later this term, but I'll keep that to myself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, Batya, of course, was sitting in her CS class in college. I told
her what we were doing and continued with the lesson.  She responded
that Zach, her boyfriend and my former student said not to forget to
emphasize certain things. I also asked Batya if her professor was
having a chat with his kid while he was teaching. Everyone was having a
laugh.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then things got sillier. Another chat popped up. It was Natan, my son,
who happens to be in that class. So, the insanity continued on when I
get a video call -  it was from Aida sitting in row 1 - that's what you
see on the screen. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now it was getting a little ridiculous and it all started with Batya
and Natan. So, what's a a teacher to do? I had to contact their
parent, my wife, to tell her to discipline her children. That's the
third chat. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, just another day at StuyCS.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>community</category><category>misc</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-08-antother-day-stuycs.html/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2015 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Reunions part 2 - My Stuy, Your Stuy</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-30-reunions-2.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
About a month ago, I was at my 30 year high school reunion. Yesterday
I was at the class of 2009's 5 year one. Stuy 2004 also had their 10
year reunion last night.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's always nice to be invited to reunions - I know it's largely
dependent on who's on the organizing committee but it's nice to be
remembered.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/10/25/reunions.html#.VHuvPJ-c30o"&gt;Last time&lt;/a&gt; I wrote about Stuy reunions I noted how similar they all
are. It's something I've noticed over the years. The kids are all
unique but the vibe is the same. I tell people that the biggest
difference between my class reunion and the ones I attend as a teacher
is that I know more people when I'm there as a teacher. That's
probably more of a statement about me than the reunions or classes though.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Interesting to me was that I didn't really feel like I was at a Stuy
event. The people I chatted with were by and large part of our CS
family. We've got our own mailing list, have our own meetups and are
already a community that spans the years. It was nice to actually see
people, particularly the out of towners in person and it was nice to
speak to some of the people who are more comfortable lurking on our
list but it's not like we've been out of touch for the past five years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It really cemented my feelings that my Stuy really doesn't have much
to do with the actual school any more. It's the kids and teachers I
work with right now and the many graduates that I now consider
friends. It's also the CSTUY kids from the summer and the kids that I
hope to work with in the future. There are more than a few non-Stuy
people that are part of the community as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's my Stuy. On the one hand, it's pretty cool. We've got a
community that's around 700 people and spans almost four decades and
StuyCS is a known quantity in the tech world.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand it's kind of sad that I no longer feel passionate
about the institution that I attended as a kid and have worked at for
over 20 years.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>community</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-30-reunions-2.html/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hi, I'm Mike, I went to high school with....</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-16-weddings.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's how I introduce myself whenever I attend a former student's
wedding. It leads to all sorts of confusion.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even better was the time I was at the wedding of two former
students. I had just dropped around 65 pounds and was wearing my hair
differently. I sat at a table filled with former students that didn't
recognize me – they had no reason to expect me, out of context and
all. I joined the conversation - able to go toe to toe on stories of
"the old days at Stuy." It really confused them. We all had a good
laugh when I outed myself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the years, a many of my graduates have moved from student to
friend and I've shared life events with a number of them. Rule one is
that I don't reach out to them after graduation - that would just be
creepy. If, however, they reach out to me, then we stay in touch. As
an educator, even if it's a periodic note or update, it's something
that really touches me - it reminds me that even with all the teacher
bashing going on in this country, the kids, at least some of the time,
appreciate us.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This weekend was particularly memorable for me. I was at JonAlf and Jamie's
wedding. JonAlf falls in a special category. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He was a former student and also on my fencing teams. I don't remember
how much we stayed in touch, but it must have been enough for me to
know that he minored in CS and was teaching high school at Brandeis.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I heard Brandeis was being phased out and I saw we had a couple
of math openings, I tried to find him to bring him over to Stuy. You
try finding JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver in "the system." Is it Jon Dyrland?
Alf Weaver?  JonAlf Dyrland? Nothing worked. In any event I did
eventually find him. Unfortunately, I wasn't allowed to bring him on
in spite of his being a Stuy graduate with a CS background and a
successful teaching record. Nonetheless I kept trying and a couple of
years later I got him.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since then, JonAlf has been my partner in crime. A kindred spirit whom
I describe him as a younger hipper version of me although the hip bar
was set pretty low to begin with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In addition to the lunacy - The Blues Brothers, Austin Powers and
Dr. Evil, Clyde "Thluffy" Sinclair, the CS Semi Formal and all, he's
one of the best teachers I know.  A former student that I'm now proud
to call friend and colleague.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was touched to be included in the festivities this weekend. I'm
incredibly proud of JonAlf as a teacher, a person, and a friend. He
and Jamie looked so happy together and I just know that their union
will be as amazing as Devorah and mine has been.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So this post is my way of raising a glass to JonAlf and Jamie. 
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>community</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-16-weddings.html/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2014 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Rich and Rich - two legends on opposite sides of the hall</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-07-rich-rich.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
.leftborder {border-left:1px; border-style:solid;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We'll get back to CS content soon, but for now:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last Tuesday was Election day - no students in the school - a day
devoted to professional development. Traditionally, math team coaches
from around the city descend on Stuy for a day full of lectures,
discussion, and general catching up. I've never actually attended
these meetings. In the past, they were for math team coaches only and this
year, I was actually allowed to do something with the CS teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These meetings used to be organized by my late friend and colleague,
Rich Geller so it made sense that we took time at end of the day to
honor his memory and unveil a memorial dedicated to Rich and his
work. Rich was a legendary Stuy teacher, but more on that shortly.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I looked at Rich's memorial, I couldn't help and turn my head
around to gaze at another memorial - "Celebration" - created to honor
the memory of another legendary teacher that died before his time -
Richard Rothenberg.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Both of these men were friends and mentors. I thought I'd dedicate
this post to some of the things I learned from both of them.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="row"&gt;

&lt;div class="c6"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rich (Doc)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class="center"&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
 &lt;img height="250px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/rich-rich/doc.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Celebration - the Rothenberg Memorial&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Richard Rothenberg, known to me as Richie or Doc was the math chair
when I was a senior. He taught AP Computer Science that year and he
hired me back a few years later.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He didn't give me my first teaching gig. He knew that I had to go
somewhere else to develop my chops. We did stay in touch, though, and
he hired me two and a half years later.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Doc was an amazing teacher but he was also someone who worked 
tirelessly behind the scenes for the good of his students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I remember one year he heard that one our recent graduates got into
some trouble at college. Doc got wind of this and went out of his way
to contact the college on the student's behalf. The student never
knew. That was Doc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He also understood the "big picture."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was at a parents association meeting early in my Stuy career. All of
the assistant principals were taking turns talking to an audience of
Freshman parents.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Each got up  and started to brag about their program:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had n intel semi finalists last year
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our kids won whatever essay writing contest
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Six kids won gold medals in…
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Each AP was bragging about how awesome their department was but in
truth they were talking about a handful of excellent kids who would
have excelled no matter where they went. I'd guess Stuy or at least
Stuy's educational programs probably had very little to do with these
top kid's development and in any event, this wasn't really relevant to
parents of incoming students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then it was Richie's turn.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Richie got up and said the following:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Go home, hug your children, ask them how their days were.
Encourage them and support them.
Everything else will work itself out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That really stayed with me. So few teachers look beyond their field. I
remember talking to one of the best chemistry teachers I know - I
asked "what do you do knowing that most of your kids won't be and in
fact shouldn't be chemists?" The reply was that he looked at all his
students as though they all wanted to be and were going to be
chemists. Doc looked at his students as whole people first -
mathematicians second. That's one of the many lessons I learned from Doc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="c6 leftborder"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rich (Richard)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class="center"&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
 &lt;img height="250px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/rich-rich/geller.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Rich Geller Memorial Display&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Richard Geller was never my teacher. He was my colleague and friend.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He introduced me to fine dining and wine. We talked food, biking, and
teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Rich had a reputation for being unyielding and strict. Many students
went into his class in fear but just as many came back after
graduating to thank him.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I remember one of our mutual students saying:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I need to be in Mr. Geller's once every three terms to keep me in good
habits. Then I need a couple of pushover teachers in between to pump
up my GPA.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He was a top math teacher but his students learned much
more. Responsibility, respect, having care and pride in one's work,
and more.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Rich was a demanding teacher and one who really cared about his
students. When grads came back from college and Rich would great them
with a smile. The scary teacher was gone. He asked how and what the
graduates were doing and he honestly cared. Gone was the in class
persona. That was business. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In some ways Rich was much like an earlier Stuyvesant math
legend. Phil Fisher, who terrorized us poor calc students in the
'80s. I got to know Phil when I came back as a teacher and once he
explained why he was so rigid and strict in class. Phil explained that
here he was, charged with teaching these amazing talented Stuy
students while at the same time, he felt he wasn't nearly as smart as
them. Phil needed 100% focus during every minute of every class to
give the kids what they deserved. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think Rich was something like that. Not exactly the same, he also
wanted the kids to learn to be responsible and respectful but I think
the core idea was the same.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a colleague and friend, Rich was the first guy to show appreciation
and the guy with enough character to tell you not what you wanted to
hear but what you needed to hear. I also learned to always be open and
honest with my team. Make sure everyone had all the information.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I learned a lot from both of these men. Stuyvesant misses them and I
miss them, but the there influence lives on through me, their
students, colleagues and friends.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>community</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-07-rich-rich.html/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2014 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>