<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about contests)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/contests.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 21:25:26 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Making contest problems and writing tests</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-2017-making-tests/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgccf0078" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgccf0078"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgccf0078"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'm now well behind in &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt;. Traveling up to Michigan to see
my son and my brother and his family will do that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was planning on working to catch up but got distracted earlier by
&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/comments/7idn6k/question_why_does_the_difficulty_vary_so_much/"&gt;this thread&lt;/a&gt; on the Advent of Code subreddit. Specifically &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/comments/7idn6k/question_why_does_the_difficulty_vary_so_much/dqy08tk/"&gt;this comment&lt;/a&gt;
by &lt;a href="http://was.tl/"&gt;Eric Wastl&lt;/a&gt;, the contest creator. The thread is about the level of
difficulty of the various problems and Eric's comment talks about some
of the factors that go into creating a good collection of problems for
a contest and the difficulties involved.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It made me think of a conversation I had twenty years ago with Rob
Kolstad. We were chatting at a programming competition while the
students were hacking away. We were discussing that there were only so
many questions that a typical high school or college competition can
ask:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Mathy question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recursion / divide and conquer etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graph stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dynamic Programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and I think one or two more. The actual questions were just window
dressing on these fundamental question types. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can see this in many competitions including Advent of Code -
particularly if you look over all three years. This is not a
criticism. I love Advent of Code and think that Eric and the people
he's working with are doing a great job . Read Eric's comment to get a
deeper dive into what he thinks about as a contest designer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also got to thinking how similar creating a competition is to
creating an exam. Maybe that's because I'm currently writing the final
my students will take in a couple of days. In class tests are
certainly not the best of assessments but they do have their place and
in any event, they're frequently  required by school or departmental
policy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are many similarities between what teachers consider when making
tests to what contest designers consider. What concepts and techniques
must the students use? Are the problems too similar? Do they ramp up
in difficulty? Are they all or nothing or can a student incrementally
work their way to a solution? Does one problem lead into another? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's no big reveal or surprise here today. Just something I've been
thinking about. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of busy days coming up but maybe over the weekend I can get
back to Advent of Code.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>assessment</category><category>contests</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-2017-making-tests/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2017 23:39:16 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>