<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about CS Education</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs-education.atom</id>
  <updated>2017-12-22T12:59:43Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs-education.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs-education/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>A Community Curated List of CS Education Resources</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awesome-cs/</id>
    <updated>2017-06-16T12:39:20-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-06-16T12:39:20-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awesome-cs/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
One of the things I mentioned in my post on the &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-educators-stackexchange/"&gt;CS Educators
StackExchange&lt;/a&gt; was the fragmentation of resources for CS Educators. My
friend and fellow CS teacher Ben pointed out that this is appropriate
as we're so young as a community. He's absolutely right but until we
mature, discover-ability can be a problem. We all have our resources
and I for one am frequently surprised when talking to a friend and
discovering that they don't know about a site or a mailing list that
I've known about for years. Likewise, I'm appreciative when others
share resources with me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are some collections of information, for instance, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred
Thompson&lt;/a&gt; has a list of CS Education bloggers but it's not so easy to
discover and it certainly shouldn't fall on Alfred to maintain such
a list making sure the links are all active and always being
responsible for adding new ones.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Recently I've noticed a proliferation of &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;awesome&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
lists. These are community curated lists hosted up on GitHub for a
variety of projects. I find myself using &lt;a href="https://github.com/emacs-tw/awesome-emacs"&gt;awesome-emacs&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/vinta/awesome-python"&gt;awesome-python&lt;/a&gt; more and more and there are tons of other such lists.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I thought we, as a community could benefit from such a list. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started one off. It's over at
&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education"&gt;https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education&lt;/a&gt; with instructions on
contributing at
&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education/blob/master/contributing.org"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education/blob/master/contributing.org"&gt;https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education/blob/master/contributing.org&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I seeded it with a few items but I'd love everyone to get involved. I
also started it with a few categories and a specific format but I'd
love to see that evolve into something most useful for the community
as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you agree that this could be something useful, please contribute to
it and help spread the word.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs-education" label="CS Education"/>
    <category term="resources" label="resources"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>CS Educators StackExchange</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-educators-stackexchange/</id>
    <updated>2017-06-15T07:57:02-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-06-15T07:57:02-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-educators-stackexchange/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;a href="https://cseducators.stackexchange.com/"&gt;CS Educators StackExchange&lt;/a&gt; is now in public beta. For those of you
who are not in tech, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stack_Exchange"&gt;StackExchange&lt;/a&gt; is a network of question answering
sites. &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com"&gt;StackOverflow&lt;/a&gt; is probably the most famous - many peoples go to
site for computer science and programming questions and answers. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
During this period of public beta the site will be working on defining
itself and also on developing a critical mass of users. I hope the
site succeeds and I encourage everyone to &lt;a href="https://cseducators.stackexchange.com/"&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;, ask questions,
answer some and let's all see where this goes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
An interesting difference between StackExchanges and most other
communities is that it's a question answering site not a discussion
board or shared resource collection. This works well for programming
questions where you can share a code snippet, algorithm, or derivation
which can be shown to be correct. We'll see how it works for something
more nebulous like education. The voting system should help but the CS
education community is already awash with anointed thought leaders
with little or no teaching or CS experience. It will also be
interesting to see how things develop given that, by and large, K12
educators know a whole lot more about teaching than those in higher ed
while the on the flip side, the professors are generally much
more knowledgeable about the subject matter and then you have the
education researcher which is another beast altogether. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Part of me thinks that discussion could be more valuable than answers
and in fact, I'm finding the comments which are more discussion like
to be more interesting, but that's just me. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A side thing I noticed was that the moderators have taken to asking
contributors not to link to other sites but to either write self
contained answers. I understand this desire to have everything under
your roof but it strikes me as wanting to use their silo instead of
someone else's silo. This happened to me on an answer because I had
already written a series of blog posts on the subject. Admittedly, I
just put up four links and could have (and will) provide more context
but I also had no desire to rewrite my content just to share info that
was already out there. Likewise there was a question that was posed on
A* which led to &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/a-star-is-born/"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;. I wanted to share my thoughts with "my"
community as well as on the stackexchange and didn't want to have to
do the same thing twice.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the moderators claims is that a link might not be
permanent. This is true. My blog might not be around in 5 years but
then the CS Educators StackExchange might not as well. I hope both are
around and thriving but time will tell.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This also got me thinking about the  mish mash of
CS Educator communities floating around. I'm familiar with and a
member of:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few Facebook groups (CS Education, CS Education Discussion, AP
Comp Sci, APCSP)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The CS Education subreddit
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A couple of mailing lists (the College Board AP Community, SIGCSE)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A few blogs are kind of communities in that there's a core group of
readers but discussion is pretty sparse.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Are there others I'm not aware of?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This has led to a lot of duplication and some fragmentation and there
is a concern about silos. The Facebook groups are very much a silo and
to a certain extent so are the mailing lists. I guess the SIGCSE list
is more community run than the College Board one, but still. Blogs are
our own personal islands so while I wish more people would both blog
and comment about CS Ed they're not necessarily open and permanent
either. At least with some blogs and with the subreddit and
stackexchange we can, if we want, download all of the data if we want
and preserve it for posterity.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know if there's a solution - maybe we should set up a &lt;a href="https://github.com/discourse/discourse"&gt;discourse&lt;/a&gt;
instance - something really open and accessible.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any event, please do check out the &lt;a href="https://cseducators.stackexchange.com/"&gt;CS Educators StackExchange&lt;/a&gt; and
let's all help it become the best question answering resource it can
be for our community.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="community" label="community"/>
    <category term="cs-education" label="CS Education"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
