<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about cs</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs.atom</id>
  <updated>2016-11-26T19:05:11Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Cornell Technion Project Studio</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cornell-tech-proj-studio/</id>
    <updated>2016-11-01T20:34:03-04:00</updated>
    <published>2016-11-01T20:34:03-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cornell-tech-proj-studio/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
I spent this evening as a crit advisor for this semesters &lt;a href="http://tech.cornell.edu/studio/curriculum/product-studio"&gt;Project
Studio&lt;/a&gt;. The class is basically a finishing class for their Masters
students. The class forms teams that work with a "company champion"
that acts an advisor to build a product.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a Crit Advisor, I, along with two other people from the tech
industry have a give and take with three groups and hopefully we can
provide useful feedback.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a "tech industry person" I feel a bit like an outsider since I'm
really the "teacher guy," but I think I had some worthwhile things to
share with the groups.  Besides,
I'd like to think I'm sufficiently in touch with the tech industry
through "the family" to be a reasonably sound advisor.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As it turns out, two of the groups I worked with had an education bent
so at least in terms of product they were in my wheelhouse.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't want to talk specifically about the student products since I
didn't ask permission but I did want to share a few thoughts.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The products reminded me very much of the projects my Stuy kids
produced in their senior SoftDev class. This is not to belittle the
Cornell Tech people but rather noting how advanced the work of the
Stuy kids is. Beyond that, I liked the composition of the groups I
talked to - nice combinations of skill sets and backgrounds. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I love the idea of the mentoring company which had an interesting effect on
the groups. In all cases, the mentoring company helped provide the
teams with an idea framework but in one case, I think the company's point of
view actually limited the groups vision a bit. This came up in our
discussions and I'm hoping that the students got something out of
that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also liked the crit review I was part of - bringing in outsiders to
show your work to and to get feedback from. It would probably hard
logistically at Stuy, but I'll talk to the guys there about the
concept. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I shared my contact info with the two groups that asked and if they
follow up, I'd love to be a resource for them. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm also looking forward to taking part in more events like this in
the future.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Computational Thinkers in Scotland</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/scotland/</id>
    <updated>2016-09-30T07:28:53-04:00</updated>
    <published>2016-09-30T07:28:53-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/scotland/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
I'm way behind on my &lt;a href="http://cacm.acm.org/"&gt;Communications of the ACM&lt;/a&gt;. I generally only read
them when I use my trainer in the mornings and with summer running and
outside riding, I'm still on the December 2015 issue.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This morning, I read a viewpoint by Jeremy Scott and Alan Bundy on &lt;a href="http://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2015/12/194638-creating-a-new-generation-of-computational-thinkers/abstract"&gt;a
program in Scotland&lt;/a&gt;. If you're an ACM member, and if you're a CS
practitioner, student, academic, or teacher you should be, you can read the piece for details.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
Me? I noticed a number of similarities between what Bundy and Scott
described and efforts here in the USA including some of the red flags.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not here to talk about the program described in detail or their
successes and failures. I don't have enough information to fairly
comment on that. I'm here in my usual role of curmudgeon to highlight
common red flags that if unheeded could cost all of us the opportunity
to get really great CS Ed to all of our students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One red flag right away were a number of references to the program
being curriculum and materials driven, not teacher driven. The
viewpoint states that materials "were designed to be used by even
non-specialist teachers." We see the same thing here in the USA and
not just in CS Ed. Teaching overall is being devalued with the elite
pushing programs that handcuff good teachers to a script (which leads
students towards "success" in passing a nonsense standardized exam)
all the while sending their own kids to elite private schools with
knowledgeable teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know i didn't want my kids to be taught chemistry history or any
other subject by a teacher that hasn't studied the content yet here we
go saying it's okay for CS. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The counter argument is that we have to do something now and we'll do
better later. We all go in with the best of intentions but more often
than not, once a politician has their sound bite and once a cheap
apparent solution is in place, it's good enough and we're done. I
ranted about that a while back both &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-04-expedient-vs-good.html/#.V-5UqN9vGAk"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-07-learning-takes-time.html/#.V-5Uot9vGAk"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. To their credit,
Bundy and Scott talk a bit about this concern in the piece.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The piece also said "It is also necessary to employ a pedagogy that is
informed by the latest research into the most effective ways to teach
computing." This sounds good but the truth is, education research
doesn't have the best reputation among educators. Last month, I
asked one of the best math teachers around what was being bandied
about as best practices in math education according to "the
research?" He basically said "the research says do &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;fad du jour&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
but that doesn't work for me so I just do &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;actually good technique&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the years, I've spoken to many teachers and by and large the best
ones discredit "the research." Of course, my comment will be
discredited by ed researchers saying that "you're just giving
anecdotes" but then, if I did the same thing while employed as a
researcher, did a couple of surveys and submitted it for publication,
then it would be "research." So much of teaching is a craft and the
truth is, practitioners know best.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Related to this is authentication by citing authority. Particularly
dangerous in our field because many people with little to no real
background in teaching CS are anointed as experts and thought leaders
(see this post: &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-26-self-appointed-experts.html/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). In this case, the viewpoint cites Cameron
Fadjo. I've only met Cameron once or twice and he seems like a sharp
guy but when he was given the post of Director of Software Engineering
for NYC, according to his linked in profile, he had neither taught k12
nor had any real CS background.  This is of course the profile of many
CS Education thought leaders. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My overall take. It sounds like just like here, Scotland has people
trying to make a difference and trying to do good. It also sounds like
they're falling into the same traps and pitfalls as we are on this
side of the Atlantic.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Can NYCIST become in leader in CS Education?</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/nycist/</id>
    <updated>2016-09-24T16:17:53-04:00</updated>
    <published>2016-09-24T16:17:53-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/nycist/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
I only learned about NYCIST last spring. They're the "New York
Consortium for Independent School Technologists." They had something
of an open house that I attended. I heard about them from friend
and fellow CS educator &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ed_saber"&gt;Saber Khan&lt;/a&gt;.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last Thursday I spent an afternoon and evening with NYCIST members for
a discussion of the state of K12 Computer Science Education in the
City.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most of my work has been with public schools and most of the teachers
I know, public school teachers so it was great to make new friends in
the Independent school community.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One thing I realized during the evening was that NYCIST has a real
opportunity to do something special. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In some ways, the public schools are leading the way in computer
science education as a result of this administrations CS4All
initiative but at the same time, public schools face some real
challenges. While some "early adopters" have developed their own take
on computer science education, by and large, CS4All is being defined
and driven by few for all and, at least right now, the model seems to
be the "a little PD and you're a CS teacher" model.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the same time, standardized testing and teacher evaluations are
pressuring schools, particularly schools of our most vulnerable
students to push resources towards test prep in tested subjects rather
than real education, including CS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In this particular instance, NYCIST and independent schools can be
what charter schools were supposed to be before they were corrupted.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Laboratories of innovation. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
NYCIST has already gathered together interested parties and the
independent schools aren't burdened by the weight of politically
driven testing and teacher evaluation. At the same time, small class
sizes and flexible models allow for innovation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If they wanted to, they could probably create curricular and
instructional frameworks for CS education and. dare I say it, share it
back to the public schools. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know I'm ignoring independent school politics and other issues that
would prevent this from happening, but I just feel that if there's a
desire to do so from a group like NYCIST, it could happen.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm looking forward to continuing to work with my new friends and if
any of you are interested in finding out more about NYCIST, just tweet
to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ed_saber"&gt;Saber&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know if my idea here will take root but if it does, I'd love
to work with NYCIST to make something happen.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="community" label="community"/>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
