<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (cs)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 15:24:52 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Quality Devs and Coding Contests</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/quality-devs-and-coding-contests/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I've been planning to put together a response to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt;'s
recent post - &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/02/software-developersquantity-vs-quality.html"&gt;Software Developers - Quantity vs Quality&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
TL;DR, although it isn't really long and I do encourage you to read
Alfred's post: a couple of articles talk about how the U.S. has the most
people entering CS competitions like HackerRank but Americans are not
at the top of the leaderboard. does this mean that there's less talent
in America? Does it even matter?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Before getting to "does it matter," I looked over at the Kaggle
leaderboards. Looking at their top 10, 2 were from the US - no other
country had more than 1. The 11th placing competitor was also from the
US and then 12 was from China, giving them 2 in the top 12.  I also
looked at recent &lt;a href="http://stats.ioinformatics.org/delegations/2016?sort=total_desc"&gt;IOI results&lt;/a&gt; and a quick glance seems to indicate that
the USA seems to do reasonably well. In short, if you buy into ranking
a country by these types of individual results on specific
competitions then we're doing fine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But, does filling the leaderboard mean a country's producing the best
tech talent? Probably not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Coding competitions focus on a specific skill set. There are problem
solving aspects but they also require speed, knowledge of data
structures and algorithms, and, yes, even accurate, fast typing
skills. They also require you work alone. They don't encourage well
designed, architected, or written code, working on existing code bases
or working with a team. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the years, I've known some very smart and talented individuals
who've excelled at these types of competitions. If you extend the pool
to math and science competitions, I've known quite a few. These
individuals have by and large done well for themselves but as a group,
you couldn't call them more successful than any other subset of my
former students. A number of them have gone on and are doing well as
professors or programmers but, by and large, they're not the ones
who've gone on to found companies and provide jobs for scores or even
hundreds of other people and they're not necessarily the ones who've
led teams that have developed major platforms and projects&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/quality-devs-and-coding-contests/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't argue that people who populate competition leaderboards are
talented and a necessary part of our tech ecosystem but they're only a
part. I probably want one of these programmers on my team, but not as
the entire team (see Fake Grimlock's laws of startups - &lt;a href="http://www.builtinchicago.org/blog/secret-laws-startups-part-2-build-right-team"&gt;law 9&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.builtinchicago.org/blog/secret-laws-startups-part-2-build-right-team"&gt;
&lt;img width="30%" src="http://media3.cdn.builtinchicago.org/sites/default/files/imagecache/Original/images/BATMAN-THEN-ROBIN.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Competitive programming is a piece of the puzzle as competitive
programmers are a part of the population. So are project based events
like &lt;a href="https://dreamitcodeitwinit.wordpress.com/"&gt;Dream it. Code it. Win it.&lt;/a&gt;, science fairs, and hackathons, which
can be either cooperative, competitive, or a combination.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What do we want? Balance. I think the Stuy program does it pretty
well. StuyCS graduates who wish to take part in coding competitions
can do so but if they want to excel at it, they have to work at it on
their own time. At the same time, the students learn how to work in
teams and take a project from idea to delivery all the while learning
some good academic CS and software engineering practices. They'll
learn more in college on the academic side and the rest on the
job. I'd love to see better balance in the colleges between CS
programs preparing kids for graduate programs and CS programs that
prepare kids for industry. I'd also love to see CS minors that were
more targeted towards CS+X rather than half of a CS major targeting
students going to grad schools. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also think there's a tremendous opportunity for community colleges
to fill the role currently occupied by code schools. They could more
easily strike a balance between academic depth and practical
preparation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm working on building Hunter College's honors CS program and while I
can't move the Hunter curriculum, I'm seeking that balance in my own
way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Will we get there? I don't know. Given the way education works, I
figure at some point people will decide that we have to have more of a
presence on the CS leaderboards and we'll see programs pop up with
that in mind. I have no doubt that when that happens, we'll see many
more Americans near the top. We have a large enough population that
talent shouldn't be in question. This will be great for students to
whom these competitions attract. It won't do much, however for the
rest of the students. I'm not really concerned one way or
another. Unlike math, where there's a natural progression through K12
math classes with math team and math competitions being a natural add
on, the driving forces in CS - be they from industry, government, or
academia don't seem to have partaken in any code competition Kool-Aid
so code competitions won't become a driving force in CS ed any time
soon. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/quality-devs-and-coding-contests/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some
are but probably a smaller percent from that group than from the
general pool.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/quality-devs-and-coding-contests/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2017 21:53:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Starting with scheme</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/starting-with-scheme/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Scheme is one of the languages used in Stuy's intro CS course. Like
any other language, there are pros and cons of using it to introduce
students to CS. Here are some of the reasons why I like Scheme as a
first language and why despite that,  I don't recommend it in many
cases.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Scheme certainly isn't mainstream. That's not the main reason why I
like it but it is a side benefit. It's less likely kids come into
class knowing it which creates a level playing field. The few times
I've had a student with a background in Scheme, they've been good,
helpful kids rather than ones that tried to show off and dominate the
class. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I like scheme because it's simple. It looks different than other
languages but is &lt;code&gt;(+ 3 4)&lt;/code&gt; really that different than &lt;code&gt;add(3,4)&lt;/code&gt; or
&lt;code&gt;3+4&lt;/code&gt;? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We can tell kids "everything's a function." While technically not
true, and I tell my students that it isn't, it's close enough for our
purposes. Everything's a function and the way we write a function is:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Apply function &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;f&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; on arguments &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;b c …&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;. So we have &lt;code&gt;(+ 2 3)&lt;/code&gt; to
add 2 and 3, &lt;code&gt;(and a b)&lt;/code&gt; for logical and &lt;code&gt;(= 3 4)&lt;/code&gt; to test to see if 3
is equal to 4, etc. We also have the same basic notation for things
like conditionals. In java, we might write:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In scheme, it would be:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even though we're fudging the rules, we can lay out a handful of rules
for the kids such as lambda and define follow a similar form to create and
name functions:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;define &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;add2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;+ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
where &lt;code&gt;(lambda (a b) (+ a b))&lt;/code&gt; returns a function that adds &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;a&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;b&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;code&gt;define&lt;/code&gt; associates it with the identifier &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;add2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;. Now we
can use the function: &lt;code&gt;(add2 5 10)&lt;/code&gt; which evaluates to 15.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With lambda, define, if, and a few more basics, it's off to the
races. The simple, consistent syntax makes things easy for the kids
and the constrained tool set lets us focus their way of thinking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course this wouldn't work had DrScheme (now &lt;a href="https://racket-lang.org/"&gt;Racket&lt;/a&gt;) not
existed. That gave us a nice learning IDE to work in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Using Scheme, we can not only cover the basics like conditionals,
abstraction and such but also deeper concepts like recursion, map,
filter, and reduce. When we move on from Scheme, the kids also have a
frame of reference for all the other languages and paradigms they use.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are downsides, however. Outside help is harder to come by and
there is some pushback from parents and it isn't as pretty and flashy
as some other tool-sets. Scheme worked at Stuy for a number of
reasons. When I created the class that used it, there were no good
pre-AP classes in the school and I had a pretty good reputation as a
teacher. The class also used multiple tools with &lt;a href="https://ccl.northwestern.edu/netlogo/"&gt;NetLogo&lt;/a&gt; being the
primary other one and tackled a variety of CS and non CS topics.
First time through, reputation and buzz filled the classes and after
that, the class developed a solid enough reputation to fill itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It also didn't hurt that our program developed from the inside
out. First, we had APCS-AB on the books as a junior year course, then
I added our post AP senior year electives. Since it was easy to show
what the kids were already graduating with, it was easy to diffuse any
pushback from not using mainstream tools in the first class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Scheme worked at Stuy and I feel that it still does. Would I use
Scheme for a first experience in a drop in program at an after-school
where kids might not come back if they don't get to a payoff
immediately? Probably not. Would I recommend it at a school where I
want to integrate CS with some of the other subjects quickly, again,
probably not (except for integration with algebra where &lt;a href="http://www.bootstrapworld.org/"&gt;Bootstrapworld&lt;/a&gt;
is a terrific program).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any event, if you're a high school CS teacher and  haven't played
with scheme  or some other functional language, I highly recommend
it - you might not actually ever teach it or use it but it can really
help develop you as a programmer and an educator.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>curriculum</category><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/starting-with-scheme/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2017 17:20:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Selecting a starting language - why not Javascript</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/starting-with-js/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was catching up with the team at Stuy the other day and they
mentioned that they were periodically getting pushback on their choice
of languages, particularly in the intro class. The pushback was mostly
in the form of "why don't you start them with Javascript?" 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back in the day, when I created our intro class where we use Scheme,
NetLogo and then later Python, I'd get similar pushback but then it
was "why not Java?", "why not C?", or "whu not C++?"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had a good discussion on this and I shared my thoughts as to why I
don't like Javascript as a first language and I thought I'd share some
of them here. I'll try to get around to the rationale behind Scheme
and NetLogo in a later post.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start, let me say that I &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Love&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; Javascript -
particularly when approaching it as a functional language. I also
think every school and situation is different so there are likely
times when Javascript is the right beginner language for the job.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's dive in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why are some of the pluses for Javascript as an intro language.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ubiquity and availability:

&lt;p&gt;
If you have a browser, you have Javascript - it's also available
through online IDEs and online lightweight sites like &lt;a href="https://jsfiddle.net/"&gt;JSFiddle&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;Interactivity:

&lt;p&gt;
You can tweak websites almost live, use the HTML5 canvas pretty
interactively and mode
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;It's mainstream
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;It's quick to get up and running
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is all true, but there are also downsides.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of my big problems with Javascript is the lack of simple solid
educational tooling. I love to use tools like &lt;a href="http://www.drjava.org/"&gt;DrJava&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://drpython.sourceforge.net/"&gt;DrPython&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href="https://racket-lang.org/"&gt;Racket&lt;/a&gt; (formerly DrScheme) with beginners. All simple learning
IDEs. True, you can use a simple online IDE but I haven't found them
to have as strong a learning interface. They also, generally, keep you
in an oversimplified programming sandbox. There's no clean transition
from the sandbox to the real deal - particularly given the non-trivial
state of js build tools and environments. These simple learning IDEs
set the stage and then we can transition to more powerful development environments.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also prefer, where possible, to have kids learn locally so that they
can learn something about the underlying operating system even if
only at a user level.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A problem relating to the lack of tooling is the fact that a JS
program can fail to run and not give you any meaningful feedback at
all - this is a problem for a beginner. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Javascript also has all sorts of wonkiness. We have &lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;==&lt;/code&gt;
which is pretty conventional, but then there's also &lt;code&gt;===&lt;/code&gt;. We have
potentially confusing scoping issues and also some other real
weirdness:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;53&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//  50&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;53&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'3'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// 50&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'53'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// 50 &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'53'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'3'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//50&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;53&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//  56&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;53&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'3'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// '533'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'53'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// '533&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'53'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'3'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// '533'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For more, check out the this &lt;a href="https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/wat"&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;. Start watching at about 1:20 -
it's a riot.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All of this weirdness actually makes sense - just not to a beginner. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Javascript also gives plenty of freedom - there are many ways to do
things. This can be great for the developer but not necessarily ideal
for the learner. Loops, recursion, mapping functions - you name it,
Javascript's got it. I like simpler languages for beginners because
it's easier to get them thinking and problem solving in certain ways
when there tool set is somewhat restricted (more on that when I write
about Scheme).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, the fact that Javascript's a mainstream language can be a
minus. Given its popularity, a beginner class could have at  least a
few kid who've at least played with the language. This can lead them
to think they know more than they do and more importantly, this can
be intimidating to the real newbies who develop the impression that
"everyone knows this but me." A less mainstream language puts everyone
on a level playing field.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let me say again that I love javascript as a language and before a
student graduates Stuy they can learn all about Javascript, front end
development, some functional programming, and more. It's just not the
right language to start with - at least not at Stuy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>curriculum</category><category>education</category><category>languages</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/starting-with-js/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 13:45:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Should CS Ed be in bed with the College Board</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'm guessing my views  on this aren't very popular -that's OK, every
community needs a curmudgeon.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A few years ago, I cautioned if we weren't careful, once the big
players got involved, CS Ed would go the way of other disciplines, and
not in a good way. It looks like indeed we're well on our way down
that road.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've ranted before about things like non-profits, drop in and summer
programs. &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-07-learning-takes-time.html/#.WJXSS99vHmE"&gt;STEM Oil Salesmen&lt;/a&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
selling easy fixes, exciting kids and parents, using the Think Method
just like Professor Harold Hill only to send the kids off where they
can blame a future teacher for failure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've also ranted about teacher preparation and how all the rage is
short term, &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/scotland/#.WJXT999vHmE"&gt;Superficial PD and scripted curricula&lt;/a&gt;  and my concern that   
once the politicians can say CS is in the schools, &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-04-expedient-vs-good.html/#.WJXT7d9vHmE"&gt;we'll be done&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've been working towards getting CS to all students for most of my
career and while it's wonderful to see us getting closer to the goal,
I'm seeing more and more signs that my caution is becoming
reality. and CS Ed is going the way of other Ed - aligned to testing
and more to the whims of the power players and politicians than to
teachers and students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other week I noticed, &lt;a href="http://teacherblog.code.org/post/156278055294/ap-cs-principles-could-make-history-how-can-we"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by Code.org trying to encourage
more students to take the APCSP exam - not encourage more students
take the class or some other class or to have more students be exposed
to CS but to actually sit for the APCSP exam. That post was followed
by &lt;a href="http://teacherblog.code.org/post/156689658029/ask-your-cs-principles-students-to-star-in-our"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; which also highlights actually taking the exam.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This didn't sit well with me. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What does the exam do for the kid? It doesn't drive instruction - by
that time, any good teacher knows their student and is better served
by using their own &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-we-dont-trust-teachers/#.WJXbA99vHmE"&gt;assessments&lt;/a&gt;. The college credit thing? I'm
skeptical. Fewer and fewer schools are giving credit for APCSA let
alone this new CS0 non major course. Blanket credit? Since full time
students pay for a range of credits, I'm still skeptical
here. Placement? It's a course for non-majors - what exactly are you
placing out of?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reasons not to take the exam?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it doesn't do anything for the kid, why take it
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stress of taking the exam
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are other ways of placing out of courses once in college
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the expense
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a general rule, I'm against forcing students to sit for
AP exams. At the extreme case, since we've been brainwashed to think
that a school that has lots of kids sitting for exams is good, I've
seen at least one case of a principal having all his kids sit for, and
just about all &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;fail&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; AP Calculus - that is, get a 1 or 2 on the exam. This
principal had all his students take the exam, and only 2 scores were 3
or higher. This principal then parlayed his success into a higher
profile gig - he's moved up in the world while setting up his students
to fail.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This follows last year's announcement that code.org was &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-19-code-org-college-board.html/#.WJXbm99vHmE"&gt;partnering with
the College Board&lt;/a&gt; - offering PD to teachers for free if the schools
signed up their students for the PSAT 8/9 - another meaningless
exam. So, we get teacher training light &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.2" name="fnr.2" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fn.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; as long as the school pays for
the PSAT8/9 for every kid so that the kid can take yet another test
with really no value&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.3" name="fnr.3" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fn.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why should students pay for an AP exam that doesn't do anything for
them? Why should Jane Q Taxpayer pay for exams that only server to
enrich the College Board.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
True, The College Board is a big player. They already have much more
influence of American High School education than they should. It's
easy to climb on board the AP train for entre into our schools. The
question is, should we use positions of influence to push efforts that
might help our end but leave collateral damage to students and the public.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't doubt code.org's sincerity in wanting good CS in all schools
nor the efforts or value as an advocate for CS Education. I'm
concerned that the desire to win big and win now is moving us in a
direction that we'll regret years from now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;Not my term, but I really like it&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.2" name="fn.2" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fnr.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;If you think that PD based
teacher training is OK, ask yourself if you want your own child's
chemistry teacher to be a history teacher with a few weeks summer
training in chemistry&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.3" name="fn.3" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fnr.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I'm guessing the exam will be offered
during the day so teachers will proctor for free rather than be
allowed to, you know, teach their students.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 11:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>BS? - BA</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ba-bs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I didn't know Hunter College had computer science.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I heard that refrain more than once during my fall visits to high
schools. Part of the reason for this is due to Hunter CS's low
profile and small size in spite of its high quality.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Part, though, was also because of some misconceptions about Computer
Science programs. I'd hear things like "but they only offer a BA not a
BS," or "but Hunter isn't an engineering school."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've come to realize that we have to do a better job educating kids as
to what can come next after high school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not entirely sure why many assume that CS has to be under
engineering. When I was applying to college, most of my choices were
Arts and Science schools offering BAs in CS. Maybe it's because people don't
disagregate STEM subjects. Even though it's not a computer science
program many schools seem to associate FIRST robotics with computer
science. Likewise any class with even a modicum of coding becomes
computer science and as makerspaces and robotics are a percieved as
easy entry STEM classes that appear to be CS (something I'll rant
about in a future post), CS becomes associated with engineering.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's easy enough to explain the difference between a BA in CS and a BS
in CS and it's equally easy to show that you can have tremendous
success either way. All you have to do to show the validity of a BA in
CS is look at succesful people from places like NYU, Courant, Columbia
College (as opposed to Columbia Engineering), Cornell school of Arts
and Sciences, etc to balance successful people from the engineering schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I'm sure you know, I'm pretty high on Hunter CS and it's certainly
one of the best value CS educations out there. Personally, I'm a big believer in a
liberal arts education but in any case, as a community we have to do a
better job educating the high schools so that graduating seniors are
best informed when deciding on their futures.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ba-bs/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2017 01:14:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>It gets easier (or advent of code 2016 day 19)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/it-gets-easier-advent19/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Today's &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/2016/day/19"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; problem was a variant on the &lt;a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/JosephusProblem.html"&gt;Josephus
problem&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I recalled that there was a formula to figure out the 
sole survivor but I decide to run a simulation rather than looking it
up. I also decided to write it up in C++, well, really C with cout
instead of printf.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Part 1 was the traditional problem. Part 2 was a variant where at each
iteration, you remove the elf opposite the elf being processed (see
the &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/2016/day/19"&gt;problem description&lt;/a&gt; for details).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For both solutions I coded up a circular doubly linked list:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;node&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;make_ring&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;node&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;node&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;current&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;first&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="n"&gt;first&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;node&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;sizeof&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;node&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;first&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;current&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;first&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;node&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;malloc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;sizeof&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;node&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;prev&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;current&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;current&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;next&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;current&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;current&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;next&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;first&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;first&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;prev&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;current&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;first&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can see my complete solutions &lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/advent2016/blob/master/day19.cpp"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was thinking about how I wrote the code – I just rolled it off the
top of my head. The same was true for the earlier AoC problems where I
had to implement a breadth first search or something similar. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not making a statement about my amazing coding abilities - linked
lists and graph searches are pretty basic, but rather than having done
the CS thing for so long, these fundamentals have become somewhat
routine. I haven't really written C code in years but other than a
couple of typos (and a stupid mistake in calculating steps) things
worked right off the bat. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I remember a time when I was in college or even a young professional
when I would use an array and an index as a stack or queue - not
because it made more sense but rather, because I wasn't fully
comfortable with memory manipulation and linked lists. The same could
be said for my first few years working with anything more than the
simplest recursion.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All of this is to say that it does get easier.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Things that seem trivial to us now seemed
insurmountable when we were beginners. Last year, I wrote about an overnight homework
assignment I gave to my class that would have been a final project a
year earlier (the post is &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-02-11-taking-stock-self-assess.html/#.WFiGl99iekA"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; but the homework links are no longer
active) and a few weeks ago I recall a fellow CS teacher talking about
how much longer it takes his students to write a chunk of code than it
takes the teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
New things are challenging and take time but with practice and
persistence techniques that were once daunting can become tools ready
at our disposal to use on a whim.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>coding</category><category>cs</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/it-gets-easier-advent19/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 00:56:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Advent of Code 2016 - Check your data</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016-check-data/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I'm spending the weekend up in Michigan. Visiting my brother and is
family. We're here to see the &lt;a href="http://umgass.org"&gt;UMGASS&lt;/a&gt; production of Gilbert and
Sullivan's &lt;a href="http://www.umgass.org/current-production"&gt;The Sorcerer&lt;/a&gt;. Batya also came up from Cornell to join us so
the two families are all togehter for the first time in about 10
years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This hasn't left much time for &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; but I did manage to
finish yesterday's challenge this morning.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What took me so long? Much like last year, it was &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-17-im-an-idiot.html/"&gt;because I'm an
idiot&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/2016/day/9"&gt;problem&lt;/a&gt; seemed pretty straighforward. I coded a solution and it
worked for all the test cases. I tried it on my data set but
the grader said the answer was wrong. I went through the problem a
number of times as well sa my code. I figured I either mis-interpreted
the question or had some bug. I found neither to be true.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After some frustration, I went over to the Advent of Code &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/"&gt;subreddit&lt;/a&gt;
grabbed a couple of posted solutions (trying not to look at them) and
ran both on my data - those solutions got the same answer on my data
set as I did. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This morning, I asked Batya to look over my code and the problem (it's
always good to have a daughter that's smarted than you are) but she
saw no problems.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, I emailed my buddy JonAlf since I know he completed the problem. He sent back his answer along
with his data set and I got the same answer as he did on his data.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What could be the problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
His data set was about 12k characters long, mine was 4k. Something had
to be wrong here. I went back to the Advent of Code site and grabbed
the data set again. This time, I went to the page and did a "save-as"
to save it - last time, I cut and pasted.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The cut and paste version was 4k, the save-as was 12k. This time it
worked and was accepted and I also finished part 2 in short order.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The moral of the story – make sure you check the integrity of your
data set - you'll never get the right answer if you're working with
the wrong data.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In case anyone's interested, you can find my AoC code &lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/advent2016"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>programming</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016-check-data/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2016 16:25:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Teacher looks at Advent of Code 2016 #2</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016-2/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Today we're looking at &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; 2016 &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/2016/day/2"&gt;number 2&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To change things up, I thought I'd do a video where I live code a solution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The solution I present is pretty straightforward - use a 2D array (or
technically, an array of strings) to represent the keypad, parse the
input, and follow the input instructions to build the code. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the things I really like about Advent of Code is that every
problem has two parts and depending on how you solved part 1, you may
or may not have extra work to do for part 2.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of years ago, I wrote about one of the coding techniques I
try to convey to my students. The idea of &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-26-change-the-data.md"&gt;changing the data&lt;/a&gt; to take
away edge and special cases. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Part two of this problem is a perfect time to use that technique.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's the video, I hope you enjoy it:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EC8gSrYQ11g" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>programming</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016-2/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2016 13:40:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Teacher looks at Advent of Code 2016 #1</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-code-2016-1/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I recently &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016/"&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; - a series of programming
problems relseased one a day. While they vary in terms of level of
difficulty, a number of them make nice problems for introductory to
mid level programming classes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I thought I'd share some of my thoughts on a few of them starting with
the first problem from this years competition.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/2016/day/1"&gt;Take a minute to read it over.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At first glance, it might seem to a young programmer that this problem
requires a two dimensional array - all about (x,y) coordinates but
then there's a problem - there are no limits on coordinates and we
can't make an unlimited size array.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After thinking a bit, hopefully the programmer realizes that all they
need to do is keep track of the how the &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;(x,y)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; location changes over
time. In the solution below, we start at &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;(0,0)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and count the steps as
we update two variables &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;x&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;y&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When we finish processing the moves, we have our current location in
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;(x,y)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and we have the number of steps taken to get there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The solution below hsa a couple of niceties that a beginning
programmer might not know or use (and I'm not arguing that what's written is
superior in any way, it's just what I ended up writing).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I make use of tuple destructuring:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
which assigns &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;x&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; to the first item in the tuple and &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;y&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; the
second. I used that a number of times 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also use a list  I call &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;dirs&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; to hold dx and dy values for the
four direcitons:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dirs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This made it easier to to update the location based on the 4
directions. I could also have just used if statements.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's all the code:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# assume our starting location is 0,0&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# we start with d=0 -&amp;gt; facing north&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# as we turn left or right, we can just increment or decrement d&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# and dirs[d] will give us the appropriate dx and dy to update&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# our locatoin for the next step&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;dirs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt;   
&lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# This is only needed for part 2  - We track visited locations&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# by adding them to the dictionary. If we try to add a location&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# that's already been visited we know that we've found our final &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# location&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# locs={}  # uncomment this line for part 2&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="n"&gt;totalsteps&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# the first char in i is the direction to turn in (L or R)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# the rest represents the number of steps.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;dir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;steps&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:])&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;dir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"L"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dirs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;steps&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;totalsteps&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;totalsteps&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Uncomment this block for part 2&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# each time we have a new location, see if it's already in&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# locs, if it isn't, add it.&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# if it is, we're visiting somewhere twice so we're done.&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#if ((x,y) not in locs):&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#    locs[(x,y)]=1&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#else:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#    print((x,y))&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#    print(abs(x)+abs(y)) # the answer&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#    sys.exit(0)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#    break&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;abs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;abs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# the answer&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Overall, a nice little problem for beginning and intermediate
students.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>programming</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-code-2016-1/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 15:46:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Advent of Code 2016</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Once again, it's time for &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; - a series of small
programming problems released once a day. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wrote a bit about it &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-15-advent.html/"&gt;last&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-17-im-an-idiot.html/#.WEMqBB9ieYQ"&gt;year&lt;/a&gt; and you can still find last years
problems &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/2015/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's only day three but so far, all of the problems look really nice
for students in APCS-A or any similar intro course. I'm thinking of
looking at a couple of the problems this week with my class at Hunter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I didn't think about this much last year but one thing I really like
about the competition is that each problem comes in two parts. You're
first presented with the problem and the input and once you put in the
correct answer, you're presented with part two.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This can be annoying at times, particularly when it requires a large
code rewrite but it also means that well designed, not too specific
solutions are rewarded. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not quite the same as changing the specs on a project mid way but
it does encourage thinking about more than just solving a super
specific problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Check out &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; and see if it's something you or your classes
might enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>apcs</category><category>cs</category><category>misc</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 20:25:26 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>