<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about cs4all</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs4all.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-01-31T13:04:56Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs4all.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cs4all/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>APCS-P -  Bigger Intake Or Leaky Pipe</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/apcsp-bigger-intake-or-leaky-pipe/</id>
    <updated>2018-01-01T19:28:37-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-01-01T19:28:37-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/apcsp-bigger-intake-or-leaky-pipe/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org45aa2c0" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org45aa2c0"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org45aa2c0"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Advanced Placement Computer Science got top billing on Alfred
Thompson's &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/01/computer-science-education-things-im.html"&gt;Things I'm Watching in 2017&lt;/a&gt; post. Alfred talks about how
APCS-P exploded onto the scene and wonders what will happen with APCS
this year. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have some questions as well but mine won't be answered for years to
come, if ever. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Like it or not, the College Board has an out sized influence on K12
education. As long as people are convinced that AP=good there will be
a push for more and more AP classes and APCS-P is a perfect class to
push. CS is the hot topic in K12, the topic is getting a big push
from both politicians and industry, the class has no pre-requisites
and in spite of being called a college course is somehow appropriate
for a typical tenth grader.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The concern here is that at the end of the day. APCS-P is an exam or
rather an exam plus two other assessments. The quality can vary
greatly. I've heard of APCS-P implementations that seem pretty
rigorous and I've seen implementations that are, quite frankly, a
joke. The question is this: is APCS-P both motivating kids to go on to
the next level and just as importantly preparing them to succeed at
that level? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We might never know.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A high school might only offer APCS-P. If APCS-A isn't offered, we
might not know if the student went on to take more CS and we won't
know if the student succeeded or not. I've seen this with some very
high profile, popular, after school/summer non-profits. The kids have
a great time and the non-profits rave about how much their kids learn
but then the kids take a real CS class in school and drop like
flies. Was it the teacher/professor or did the non-profit set the kids up to
fail by convincing them they knew a whole lot more than they did and
that CS was super easy all the time. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If credit is given for APCS-P, it looks like it will be blanket
credit. CS majors and minors will still have to take all the same classes in
college and CS so it will be very hard to tell if APCS-P is
responsible for any uptick in CS. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, the College Board is going to make a lot of
money but if APCS-P becomes the standard high school CS course will
this leave us with true, quality CS4All? I have my doubts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="ap" label="ap"/>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="cs4all" label="cs4all"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
