<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about csforall</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csforall.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-04-27T17:23:06Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csforall.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csforall/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Unfunded Mandates and CS For All</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/unfunded-mandates/</id>
    <updated>2018-04-27T08:43:09-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-04-27T08:43:09-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/unfunded-mandates/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orged323e8" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orged323e8"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orged323e8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This morning, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; write about &lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/2018/04/27/lack-of-funding-leads-to-lack-of-teachers-leads-to-lack-of-cs-classes-we-may-need-to-change-our-strategy/"&gt;unfunded mandates and CS for
All&lt;/a&gt;. Unfunded mandates frequently wreak havoc on schools in a number
of ways but in the long run, I don't think it should have a severe
effect on CS for All. Rather, it could have a big impact on the number
of CS courses we offer beyond that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark relay's a story from the Cambridge Rindge and Latin School where
at the time many students wanted more CS classes but the school wasn't
planning on hiring a new CS teacher. The money quote is:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
#+BEGIN&lt;sub&gt;QUOTE&lt;/sub&gt;
Over 50 percent of students signing up for Level 2 [computer science] courses next year identify as African Americans,
#+END&lt;sub&gt;SRC&lt;/sub&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No, I'm not talking about the diversity issue raised by the quote, I'm
talking about &lt;b&gt;Level 2 [computer science]&lt;/b&gt;. This implies that the
students already had &lt;b&gt;Level 1 computer science&lt;/b&gt;. Level 1 would cover
CS For All so now we're talking about CS vs other subjects. This is
something I had to deal with for most of my career even after we got a
CS requirement at Stuy. It was always a battle to hire enough CS
teachers to meet demand. The hard part was politics - there were
always older more entrenched subject areas who would rather force kids
into their electives rather than allow them to take my CS
electives. This is a whole other kettle of fish than CS for All. It's
an issue for some schools now and will become a &lt;b&gt;BIG&lt;/b&gt; issue in five to
fifteen years when a single CS required course is more the norm. Now
we have to deal with other entrenched classes, a discussion of the
relative value of CS electives vs other electives and also the ebb and
flow of interest - there might be demand for 5 more CS classes and 5
less something else this year but there might not be next year and
then we're in real trouble staffing wise.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Schools, public high schools in particular are zero sum endeavors. You
have a fixed number of periods a day, specific class requirements, and
certain mandates as to a the minimum and maximum number of classes a
student can take. In New York City, I believe students are required to
have a "full" schedule which basically means they can't come in for
English, Math, and History and then go home.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With CS for All, you're basically allocating reallocating some amount
of time to computer science. It might be hard to find a qualified
teacher. particularly in a small school where the population won't
support a full time CS teacher and it might ruffle the feathers of the
teachers that will be losing the time but it shouldn't make much of a
dent or really any dent on the budget.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark also raises the possibility of embedding CS into other subject
classes. &lt;a href="http://www.bootstrapworld.org/"&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; is a program that I'm rather fond of that does
just this in Algebra classes (although more recently they're working
to branch out into other subject areas). Even though I'm a big
Bootstrap fan I don't think that's the answer to CS for All or CS in
the high schools in general. I think that one of the reasons why
Bootstrap works so well is the alignment between the CS tool they use
and the way Algebra is or can be taught so that. Another is the fact
that while Algebra is the lowest level of the traditional high school
classes, it's frequently the one for which the most time is
allocated. Students in low performing schools might take Algebra over
two years or have a double period. This won't be the case for other
subject areas. What this means is that there more likely extra time
to embed another subject into the Algebra class. Long term, embedding CS into
another subject area requires:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a teacher that really knows both subjects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;enough time so you can add all the cool CS content while still
preparing the students for both the next level of whatever subject
you're embedded in  as well as for whatever standardized
assessments come at the end of the year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="csforall" label="csforall"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
