<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about csforall)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csforall.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 21:25:31 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Is Cs for All Worth Doing</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-cs4all-worth-doing/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org906e238" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org906e238"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org906e238"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last time I mentioned the pushback on CS for All. While many people
are all in for CS for All, resistance is coming from many
areas. There's resistance from teachers of other subject areas, people
who think it's merely job training for the tech industry (which it can be if done poorly),
people who feel it will be implemented at the expense of other
important subjects already on the chopping block like music and art,
and others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I started the intro course at Stuy I tried to design something
that would be of value to all Stuy students and also inspire some to
continue on to more advanced CS classes. The class has been a
requirement for well over a decade at this point. I know that not
everyone loved the course but as they say, the proof is in the
pudding. It clearly got more people into the pool as gender numbers
for our more advanced CS courses got and remained much better since
the intro class became a requirement. I can't tell you how many people
now in tech have told me that they never considered CS and only got
into it from our intro course.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, we had CS for All at Stuy before there was a CS for All and if
exposing more kids to CS was the only benefit it would have been worth
it but there's more. In addition to getting more people and more
underrepresented people into tech, I've had scores of kids in a huge
range of fields come back to exclaim the value of having been forced
to take our intro course. These kids became authors, lawyers,
entrepreneurs, (non CS) teachers, journalists, venture capitalists,
Wall Street people, (non CS) professors and researchers, and more.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The benefit of being in the latter stages of a career is that you can
look back at years of results and see the good and the bad.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's no doubt in my mind that the battle to get a good CS course to
every Stuy student was one worth fighting and winning.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>csforall</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-cs4all-worth-doing/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 26 May 2018 20:18:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Should CS for All be implemented at the college level?</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csforall-in-college/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org035321e" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org035321e"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org035321e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There's been a lively discussion on pushback to CS for All at the K12
level over on Facebook. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; started a sub thread asking if CS
for All should first be implemented at the undergrad level rather than K12. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's an interesting question and as good as anything to get me out of
my month long non-blogging rut.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark was right when he said that if Colleges implement CS for All, K12 will 
likely do so to follow - just look at AP. Colleges have been saying
that students should take more AP classes (while giving less credit)
and we all know where that's led. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, can colleges really do CS for All, what does it
mean and what would it look like.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Much like there is no single K12 - it's 50 states and who knows how
many independent school districts, there won't be a single CS for All
at the college level but let's think about how things could play out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Many colleges have distribution requirements. Students must take one
course from bucket A, two from bucket B etc. Many schools that I've
looked at already  count CS courses in one of their distribution
buckets. This doesn't mean every student will take CS but in theory
means they can. Colleges could in theory create a required CS bucket
or even a required CS course but I don't think it's as easy as
that. It might be at a private institution but while I don't know all
the ins and outs of Hunter's governance rules I do know that adding a
universal student requirement is a HUGE undertaking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So my take is that while it might be easy for a private college
to add a CS requirement I'm guessing other public institutions are
more similar to Hunter and it's not going to be an easy task.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Regardless, let's say we have a required class on the books. Will we
have the capacity to teach it? It seems that schools are struggling to deal
with their existing CS majors and running sufficient electives and
courses for them. Just a month or so ago there was an article about a
college ending its CS minor due to lack of resources. It doesn't sound
like a radically different problem then that faced in K12. Maybe it's
harder given that at least in NY, there is &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall"&gt;room for a required CS
course&lt;/a&gt; if you can find the teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even so, assuming we have the capacity to enroll every undergrad in a
CS course what would that be? I think most people would be in
agreement that it shouldn't be CS 101. Maybe existing pre-major
courses but even there I don't know if that's always the best
path. There could be a great pre-major course to give students the
basics and lead some into the major but what about a CS course for
students in majors that need some deeper but focussed programming
skills. The appropriate course for them isn't the same as a
general/pre-major course. Using Statistics as an example, at Hunter,
many majors require a statistics course which is off loaded to the
Stats department. Each major has slightly different requirements. Over
years, the end result is a course that it seems that nobody is happy
with - a least common denominator course. CS for All at the college level
could give us a least common denominator course that doesn't serve
anyone.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, if you have the resources, none of these are issues. A well
heeled private institution can run tons of sections of specialized
classes no problem but this means just like on the K12 level we'll
get the CS for All tale of two cities that I see coming in NY where
the rich schools have good programs and the poor get a substandard
experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With all of this said, I'm finally getting to the big red flag with
college CS for All and it's an issue that everyone conveniently
ignores. I'm talking about teacher quality. One of my big takeaways
from SIGCSE is that college faculty are well behind K12 teachers in
terms of pedagogy and I don't see this changing anytime soon. This is
to be expected given that professor's career advancement is really
based on research. Having a good teacher is always important but it's
even more important for non-major students since a student in the
professor's major will at least be passionate about the subject
area. To me, this is not a recipe for success.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One can certainly make the claim that we aren't any better off right
now at the K12 level because we don't have teachers who know either
the subject nor how to teach it and at least at the college level they
know the subject matter. This is very true and it's why pre-service CS
teacher preparation is so critical to getting this right even though
it will take time. That's something that both Mark and I have been
vocal about but more on that subject next time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>csed</category><category>csforall</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csforall-in-college/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2018 20:23:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Is there room for CS for All</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgfc53ac3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgfc53ac3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgfc53ac3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A fear revolving around CS For All concerns where will the money
come from and how will we fit in the new classes. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One suggested solution is to integrate CS into other subjects. I
thought I'd write today about why I don't think the fear is valid and
while integrating CS into other classes can have value, it probably
isn't a long term solution for CS education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's start with the integration solution. The idea is to bring CS
into an existing class. &lt;a href="http://www.bootstrapworld.org/"&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;, a program I've written about before
and one of the programs I like does this, primarily in Algebra. The
idea is that this supports the student's learning Algebra while
exposing them to CS. It's a nice program but a math teacher using
Bootstrap shouldn't be confused with a computer science
teacher. They're bringing some CS to their student and engaging the
students in a different way mathematically and that's all great but in
general you can't take two classes worth of material and concepts and
fit them into one class and the number of teachers who are truly
knowledgable in any two academic subject areas both in content and
pedagogical content knowledge is few. I'm guessing that one of the
reasons that Bootstrap works in Algebra is the alignment of the
toolset and Algebra and how you can teach it. The other is that
Algebra is frequently given more time for fewer topics. In some
struggling schools, students might have two years of algebra or a
double period so there's time to add in some CS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm all for cross curricular work. You can look at applications of
science in math classes, do mathy work in a CS class, run stats and
data analysis in math and CS classes on materials from History classes
and all of this is great. You can even create great combined curricula
where you do indeed teach multiple subjects in an integrated way but
to think that you can take what is typically taught in two different
classes and you can combine both so that they're taught in one class
with one teacher sounds fishy to me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, at the end of the day, if you go the integration approach you're
either going to have to dedicate a similar set of resources both in
time and personel to having independent courses. The alternative is
that CS will be the second class subject.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, let's look at actually bringing in CS For All as a separate
course. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here are the New York State Graduation Requirements &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Subject&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Number of semesters&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;English&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Soc Studies&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Science&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Math&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;LOTE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Arts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Phys Ed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Health&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Electives&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It can be difficult to fit Phys Ed in since it has to be offered every
semester so let's double the Phys Ed requirement to 8 semesters. What
is actually normally done is to have 7.5 periods of science a week and
2.5 periods of Gym.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This means that the basic student program uses 48 class slots and
includes 7 elective slots.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In terms of exit exams, students have to pass the following Regents:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any single math (Algebra, Geometery, Alg 2 / Trig)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any single Social Studies (US History or Global History&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any single Science (Living Env (bio), Chem, Phys, Earth Science)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any additional Regents exam&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The requirement of passing a single Math regents is what leads to the
extra time allocated to Algebra that I mentioned when discussing
integrating CS into Algebra above.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To get an Advanced Regents diploma you have to pass additional exams -
both history, all three math, three science and maybe more.  
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Using a Typical 7 period plus lunch day, we have room for 56 single
semeter classes in a high school career. This means that assuming
students aren't failing too many classes, even with the extra Phys Ed
allocation I mentioned above  we can easily fit computer
science into our day. In fact, we can technically fit in four full
years assuming a student doesn't have to repeat any class. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So in New York state we certainly have the time but what about the
budget? That's not an issue either. The state also requires that
students recieve 5.5 hours of instruction a day exclusive of
lunch. At 47 minute periods, that translates to students being
assigned 7 instructional classes a day which means we can't just give
the kids the required 44. We have to fill all 56 available class slots
over those four years. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course it's not really that simple. Students fail classes and have
to repeat them and some classes might be assigned more time than
others but it looks to me like we should be able to fit
computer science in without any big budgetary or scheduling
changes. The challenge will be finding the teacher and working the
internal politics and policies since as computer science comes in it
will mean removing some electives even if those electives are additional years
of science, math, or English.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Programs like &lt;a href="https://www.tealsk12.org/"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; and Bootstrap are important transitional programs
and even when we do have qualified CS teachers they will play an
important role - TEALS in providing industry support and resources and
Bootstrap by integrating curricular areas and over time as preservice
programs start to appear the rest will work itself out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;The state
lists by credits which are a year, I doubled the numbers to map to semesters&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>csforall</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2018 20:29:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Unfunded Mandates and CS For All</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/unfunded-mandates/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org62780da" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org62780da"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org62780da"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This morning, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; wrote about &lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/2018/04/27/lack-of-funding-leads-to-lack-of-teachers-leads-to-lack-of-cs-classes-we-may-need-to-change-our-strategy/"&gt;unfunded mandates and CS for
All&lt;/a&gt;. Unfunded mandates frequently wreak havoc on schools in a number
of ways but in the long run, I don't think it should have a severe
effect on CS for All. Rather, it could have a big impact on the number
of CS courses we offer beyond that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark relay's a story from the Cambridge Rindge and Latin School where
at the time many students wanted more CS classes but the school wasn't
planning on hiring a new CS teacher. The money quote is:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over 50 percent of students signing up for Level 2 [computer science] courses next year identify as African Americans,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No, I'm not talking about the diversity issue raised by the quote, I'm
talking about &lt;b&gt;Level 2 [computer science]&lt;/b&gt;. This implies that the
students already had &lt;b&gt;Level 1 computer science&lt;/b&gt;. Level 1 would cover
CS For All so now we're talking about CS electives vs other
electives. This is something I had to deal with for most of my career
even after we got a CS requirement at Stuy. It was always a battle to
hire enough CS teachers to meet demand. The hard part was politics -
there were always older more entrenched subject areas who would rather
force kids into their electives rather than allow them to take my CS
electives. This is a whole other kettle of fish than CS for All. It's
an issue for some schools now and will become a &lt;b&gt;BIG&lt;/b&gt; issue in five to
fifteen years when a single CS required course is more the norm. The
issue raised here is a new CS elective vs entrenched teachers and
classes which shuld lead to a discussion of the relative value of CS
electives vs other electives. That said, the reality is that it
usually comes down to school and local power and politics. Also to be
considered is the potential ebb and flow of interest - there might be
demand for 5 more CS classes and 5 less something else this year but
there might not be next year and then we're in real trouble staffing
wise.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Schools, public high schools in particular are zero sum endeavors. You
have a fixed number of periods a day, specific class requirements, and
certain mandates as to a the minimum and maximum number of classes a
student can take. In New York City, I believe students are required to
have a "full" schedule which basically means they can't come in for
English, Math, and History and then go home.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With CS for All, you're basically allocating reallocating some amount
of time to computer science. It might be hard to find a qualified
teacher. particularly in a small school where the population won't
support a full time CS teacher and it might ruffle the feathers of the
teachers that will be losing the time but it shouldn't make much of a
dent or really any dent on the budget.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark also raises the possibility of embedding CS into other subject
classes. &lt;a href="http://www.bootstrapworld.org/"&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; is a program that I'm rather fond of that does
just this in Algebra classes (although more recently they're working
to branch out into other subject areas). Even though I'm a big
Bootstrap fan I don't think that's the answer to CS for All or CS in
the high schools in general. I think that one of the reasons why
Bootstrap works so well is the alignment between the CS tool they use
and the way Algebra is or can be taught. Another reason is the fact
that while Algebra is the lowest level of the traditional high school
classes, it's frequently the one for which the most time is
allocated. Students in low performing schools might take Algebra over
two years or have a double period. This won't be the case for other
subject areas. What this means is that there's more likely extra time
to embed another subject, cs, into the Algebra class. Long term,
embedding CS into another subject area requires:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a teacher that really knows both subjects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;enough time so you can add all the cool CS content while still
preparing the students for both the next level of whatever subject
you're embedded in  as well as for whatever standardized
assessments come at the end of the year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I said, I'm a Bootstrap fan but I don't think that's the answer for
CS in K12.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back to the original topic there are certainly issues with
implementing CS for All but I don't think school funding is the
biggest hurdle. For me there are other big challenges. One is having a
supply of qualified teachers. In the long run as states outline CS
requirements and pre-service programs crop up this will work itself
out. Until then, yes, we will have an issue and yes it will take some
funding for stop gap and transitional teacher preperation. A second issue is
working the internal politics. Adding CS does mean removing something
else or more likely a piece of something else. The third one is what
I'm noticing in NY where CS for all seems to at times forget about
the CS. If we have knowledgeable teachers we can work around that one
but I still think that might be my biggest concern.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>csforall</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/unfunded-mandates/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 12:43:09 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>