<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about csta</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csta.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-09-18T12:59:17Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csta.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/csta/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>CSTA 2018 - Funding and Direction</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csta-2018-future/</id>
    <updated>2018-07-12T17:24:07-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-07-12T17:24:07-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csta-2018-future/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgfe1cfca" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgfe1cfca"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgfe1cfca"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In addition to everything I wrote about last time there were a couple
of other big announcements at this year's CSTA conference. Both
announcements deal with funding.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, there is a new class of CSTA membership. The free tier remains
but now for $50 you can join &lt;a href="https://www.csteachers.org/page/cstaplus"&gt;CSTA+&lt;/a&gt;. This new level of membership comes
with a bunch of extras that are probably good for K12 teachers but I
doubt I'll use any of them. I did, however, get a snazzy CSTA+ water
bottle by joining at the conference. For me the interesting part is
that 50% of CSTA+ dues will go to support local chapters.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't exactly know what that means but it's what got me to
join. Ultimately, local teaching communities are important and CSTA+
supports that, I'm all in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That said, what do chapters do? I know what goes on in NY but not
elsewhere. I bet the same is true for people all over the country. One
question that came up repeatedly at the conference, at least in my
circles was "what would the chapters use the money for?" I think it
would be wonderful if on the CSTA web site there was a page where
chapters could easily list activities funded by the central
organization. I'm not looking for a big write up - who has time to
read or write that. I'm looking for a line or two. What the chapter
did and maybe a few comments on details. Over time this could be  a
great way for chapters to steal ideas from each other.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other piece of big news was &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/new-partnership-support-computer-science-teachers-mary-snapp-1c/?published="&gt;Microsoft pledging a big chunk of
change to the CSTA&lt;/a&gt;. I've often lamented that so many CS Education (and
education decisions in general) are decided by everyone except the
teachers. The CSTA is our teacher's professional organization and our
best bet for teacher representation when policy is made and
implemented. Once again it appears that some of these funds will help
support local chapters. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Microsoft funding though got me thinking. The linked piece talks
about advocacy, professional development and curriculum. All important but
there's an even greater need right around the corner. We need quality,
qualified CS teachers and we need them now. Taking a teacher with no
CS background and giving them some PD can be a stop gap but it isn't a
solution. Long term we need pre and in service teacher preparation
programs similar to what we're rolling out at Hunter. Programs that
include both pedagogy and content. As states begin to require these
programs, as they do in all other subject areas, teachers both new and
in service will have to take a number of graduate credits. In our
case, 18 for a certificate for an already licensed teacher and our MA
program is somewhere in the 30s. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'd love to see money allocated to pay for CS teacher certification
through our public colleges as they (we) roll out programs. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This said, the Microsoft commitment is great news for the CSTA and
CSTA is a great option for teachers that can afford it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here in NY, our CSTA chapter is fairly young. I'm excited to see what
this year brings both on the local and national level.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="csed" label="csed"/>
    <category term="csta" label="csta"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
