<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about cstuy</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cstuy.atom</id>
  <updated>2017-09-23T13:00:39Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cstuy.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/cstuy/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>NYC DOE - Doing what it can to keep opportunities away from kids</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cstuy-coi/</id>
    <updated>2016-04-28T17:18:06-04:00</updated>
    <published>2016-04-28T17:18:06-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cstuy-coi/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org797072e" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org797072e"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org797072e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The difficulties I've had with the city and DOE are pretty well
documented by now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today I'm going to tell you about my latest dealings with DOE and how
they prevented my team from bringing free quality CS education to city
students. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
CSTUY's not running SHIP, its summer program this year.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's not something I'm happy about but part of me knew it might
happen. What did surprise me, although it shouldn't have, was the role that
the NYC DOE played in preventing it from happening.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The bottom line initial reason for us not running SHIP this summer
was my time. Moving over to my new position at Hunter has
been terrific but I haven't had the time needed for adequate
fundraising and outreach.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I recently talked a bit about the difficulties we've had with
fundraising as compared to the "chosen programs" in 
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-04-10-thought-leaders/#.VyKAnh9vH0o"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've also written a bit about related issues in these posts:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-03-teachers-suck.html/#.VyKA9R9vH0o"&gt;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-03-teachers-suck.html/#.VyKA9R9vH0o&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-26-self-appointed-experts.html/#.VyKA-x9vH0o"&gt;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-26-self-appointed-experts.html/#.VyKA-x9vH0o&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-07-learning-takes-time.html/#.VyKBHB9vH0o"&gt;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-07-learning-takes-time.html/#.VyKBHB9vH0o&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
In any event, we weren't going to be able to run this summer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I spoke to the team, Sam asked, "if we can keep the budget down
and figure out how to not be dependent on fundraising and outreach, can
we do something?" I told him, I'd love to.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He came up with a plan. Instead of a full day program, we'd run half
day - this means fewer staff hours and no lunch. If we could run it at
Stuyvesant, in the computer labs (which already run Linux), we
wouldn't have to worry about equipment. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Under this plan, additional fundraising wasn't needed, in fact, kids
could attend free of charge.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In terms of outreach, since we already had sufficient funds, even if
we only got returning shipmates and a few from word of mouth we'd be
ok and if we could cast a wider net, so much the better.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Oh, and the plan was for me to take the summer off. I'd help with
initial organization but I wouldn't actually work the summer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, to summarize:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free for the kids&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm not involved and receive no compensation for the summer (this is
important for later)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My teachers would be paid for teaching in the program and CSTUY
would supply the funds to pay them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We floated the idea to Stuyvesant's principal figuring that since
the teaching staff is from there and some of the kids tat would
benefit are Stuy students it wouldn't be a problem. She said she loved
the idea but had to send it off to the conflict of interests people.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You see, it's very important that teachers and former teachers don't
actually benefit from working extra – it's critical that teachers be
kept down.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Long story short - the teachers could work the program but aren't
allowed to run it. They can come in and teach but can't talk to the
principal about organizing it. For some reason, running a &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;free&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
program for kids instead of relaxing over the summer means that the
teachers are getting this &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;huge&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; benefit. Sure they'd be paid for
their time, but that seems fair. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As to me, I'm not allowed any dealings with the DOE for a year. Forget
the fact that I wanted to set this up while taking &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;no&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; pay so that
the kids wouldn't be left without a program. Nope, that's no good -
can't have us bringing quality CS education to the kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I dealt with these folks once before so I wasn't really surprised.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A few years ago, a friend connected me with people at Amplify
to see about creating their APCS MOOC. We met a couple of times but
then the DOE people said I couldn't work with them even though I was
just going to be working on the MOOC and not dealing directly with the
DOE in any way. I wasn't negotiating contracts, making sales pitches,
or anything. I was just going to work on MOOC content.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It wasn't like a certain NYC School's Chancellor who had just left the DOE and
took the leadership position at Amplify. That wasn't a conflict - I
guess it's just important to keep the teachers in line - the rules
aren't meant for the higher ups.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Funny side note – when I shared the fact that I couldn't work for
Amplify with my friend, his first reaction was "because of the union?"
That seems to be the knee-jerk reaction from people in the business
world. Nope - the union was fine with it - it was the administration /
city. The city has done &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;far&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; more harm to the public schools than
the union ever could. Pretty much all the union does is make sure the
city follows the jointly negotiated contract.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back to the story.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, we're not allowed to use school space to bring free CS education
to kids this summer. Plenty of other organizations non-profit and
for-profit alike seem to have no problem bringing their programs into
the schools. I'm sure many are getting money for this, grant based or
otherwise. In all cases, I'd take my team and their program over what
the DOE is actually rolling out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is the type of thing makes me want to say to hell with DOE but,
unfortunately, they aren't affected, it's the kids that lose out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Announcing def hacks("Winter",2015)</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-09-def-hacks-winter-2015.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-11-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2015-11-09T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-09-def-hacks-winter-2015.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last March, we (CSTUY) hosted our first hackathon - def hacks():
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was a tremendous success. Fifty students of all experience levels,
a bunch of great mentors and judges - added all together and it was a
terrific day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wrote about it &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2015/03/29/defhacks.html#.VkFAN5_0-Ak"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We're doing it again. We love last years hosts &lt;a href="http://sumall.com/"&gt;SumAll&lt;/a&gt; and are grateful
that they continue to host our Saturday &lt;a href="http://cstuy.org/programs/hacking_sessions"&gt;Hacking Sessions&lt;/a&gt; but we are
also grateful to Facebook NY for allowing us to use their larger space for
this edition of def hacks(). Larger space = more hackers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, if you're a high school student who wants to spend a fun day
building something cool or if you know one, more information and
registration can be found here:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://defhacks.com/"&gt;http://defhacks.com/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hacking Sessions - iterating until it's right</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-26-hacking-sessions.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-09-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2015-09-26T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-26-hacking-sessions.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hacking-sessions-2015/hs.jpg" alt="hs.jpg" width="480px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today we kicked off Hacking Sessions 2015. Saturday morning with sixty kids in a room
brainstorming ideas.  Soon they'll settle on teams and projects and
we'll be off for a semester of exploring CS and tech.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The next couple of weeks will be a little chaotic with groups
shifting, mentors figuring out which groups to work with and us, the
instructors launching each team on its way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is our third year running Hacking Sessions. We're setting things
up to have student teams exploring a project, technology, or
tool. Each team will have more experienced students mentoring them. In
some cases the mentors will also be new to the topic. Supporting both
the hackers and mentors are our instructors.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm pretty happy with our model but it took us a couple of iterations
to get here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Our first go round was Fall 2013. We had just started CSTUY and wanted
to get something started prior to launching a summer program. &lt;i&gt;SumAll&lt;/i&gt;
provided us with space and we were able to attract a small cadre of
kids. We had a few of our older students as teaching assistants and
ran the program with a mix of instruction and projects. Over the year
we saw that a Saturday program presents a number of challenges:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students have other obligations on Saturdays such as athletic
teams. This can lead to inconsistent attendance.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SATs also kill attendance
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can't count on the participants to work between the sessions.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lateness can be an issue early on a Saturday morning.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once a week makes building a community a challenge.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kids have enough classroom learning during the week. Saturday should
be a change of pace.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We learned a lot that year and ran V2.0 the following fall. Second
time around we had the advantage of bringing in kids from our summer
program to seed the culture. We also knew we wanted to move to more of
a project / mentor based model but due to space restrictions couldn't
really get to where we wanted to be.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That changed halfway through when SumAll moved to larger offices. By
the end of the year, I think we worked out most of the kinks. We
figured out how to get the kids into teams and pointing in the right
direction as well as  how to find the right mentors and provide them
with support. The only thing we weren't happy with was that the mentors
didn't have enough time to work on their own projects. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now we're in V3.0. Thanks to our &lt;a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/262929085/saturday-hacking-sessions"&gt;kickstarter&lt;/a&gt;, we're fully funded and
somehow word seems to have gotten out. Numbers are way up and I think
we've finally gotten the model down.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As with anything new, it takes time and revisions to get things right
but as long as one leaves the kids with a net positive and as long as
one can look at oneself with a critical eye, you eventually get there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looking forward to a great year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Help us create a Saturday Hacking Space for kids</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-08-12-kickstarter.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2015-08-12T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-08-12-kickstarter.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/kickstarter/pairing.jpg" alt="pairing.jpg" width="480px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
As many of you know, I'm part of the team behind &lt;a href="http://cstuy.org/about"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;, a non-profit
dedicated to bringing the best CS education to kids who wouldn't
otherwise have the opportunity.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the past two summers we've hosted our highly succesful immersion
program SHIP. We were also able to run a small Saturday program thanks
to the generosity of &lt;a href="http://sumall.com"&gt;SumAll&lt;/a&gt; who provided space, and other members of
the StuyCS family who provided laptops and the funds we needed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We're trying to do it again, this time through a kickstarter. What
would be really awesome is if we could not only fund the Saturday
program but also the summer program so we can focus on getting to the
kids and not on raising money.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, we need you to head over to:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/262929085/saturday-hacking-sessions"&gt;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/262929085/saturday-hacking-sessions&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Watch the video, read the project, and kick in for the cause.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Just as importantly, spread the word - your friends, co-workers,
managers, funders - anyone who can help.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Wouldn't it be asweome if we could blow the roof off this kickstarter
and be able to focus all year on teaching kids!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thanks.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What makes a great manager? - Open praise for my team</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-07-30-ship-teachers.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-07-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2015-07-30T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-07-30-ship-teachers.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today was the last day of SHIP 2015, CSTUY's summer immersion
program. I was blown away by the projects. The shipmates and the
stewards all did tremendous work.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All through the reception parents would come up to me and rave about
the job I did with the program. They'd thank me, tell me how exited
their child was every day, how proud they were of what they were
learning and on and on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I of course nodded and told them that "yep, I'm that good."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No. Seriously.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First I thanked them and then told them the secret. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I forget who said this but some coach or manager was one asked "what
makes a great manager?" His answer: "Great players."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I explained to the parents that I've been fortunate enough to be
surround by amazing teachers and that's what makes our program
special. We've got the best program because we've got the best
teachers. The best thing I can do is point them in the direction of
the kids and get out of the way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So this post is an open thank you and congratulations to JonAlf, Sam,
Topher, and Yulia on yet another job well done. Four amazing CS
teachers. There's been a lot of discussion in the online CS communities
about CS teachers being isolated and not having resources but I am
fortunate in being surrounded by you four. I can't think of another
team that I'd rather "go to war" with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, I don't want to leave out the other amazing players that made
SHIP a success. Chris, Marlena, Stanley, and Valeriy. Chris, Marlena,
and Stanley - you allowed us to give the individual attention we
needed for this program and students and parents sang your praises and
Valeriy, you were able to show the stewards stuff far beyond what I
could have.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And to all our Stewards - your impact on the shipmates was also so
critical to the programs success and that doesn't even mention your
projects which blew me away.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So to everyone, congratulations, job well done. 
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>"def hack(2015)</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-29-defhacks.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2015-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-29-defhacks.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
.center {text-align:center;}
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;

&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/dh2015/dh-logo.png" alt="dh-logo.png" width="300px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
This past Saturday, 50 high school students, 10 high school mentors, and 10
more post high school mentors headed down to &lt;i&gt;SumAll&lt;/i&gt; to participate in
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;def hacks(2015):&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;CSTUY&lt;/i&gt;'s first hackathon.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The fifty participants, came from all over the city, Long Island, and
New Jersey. They ranged from having never programmed to three or four
years experience. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Projects ranged from web sites to full stack applications. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After workshops run by CSTUY teachers and mentors and also by
&lt;a href="http://codesters.com"&gt;Codesters.com&lt;/a&gt; the hackers spread out all over SumAll's offices, working in small
groups with the support of our amazing mentors.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p style="float:left"&gt;
&lt;figure style="float:left;padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/dh2015/dh-hacking.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/dh2015/dh-hacking-2.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="clear:both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Four nourishment, we had sandwiches from &lt;a href="http://amishintribeca.com/"&gt;Amish Market&lt;/a&gt;, pizza from
Wanted Pizza, snacks and those amazing doughnuts from &lt;a href="http://doughbrooklyn.com"&gt;Dough Flatiron&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p style="float:left"&gt;
&lt;figure style="float:left;padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/dh2015/dh-food1.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/dh2015/dh-dough.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="clear:both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, the hackers demoed and the judges judged
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="float:left"&gt;
&lt;figure style="float:left;padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/dh2015/dh-winner-demo.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/dh2015/dh-demo-1.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="clear:both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure style="float:center;padding:20px;width:100%"&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/dh2015/dh-judging.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p style="clear:both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the end everyone made something terrific and walked away having
built new skills, met new people, and gotten a little swag.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/dh2015/dh-certificate.jpg" alt="dh-certificate.jpg" width="300px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The judges singled out two groups for special
recognition. One was a team of four experienced programmers who put
together a full stack app to help schedule parent/teacher meetings.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/dh2015/dh-winner-group.jpg" alt="dh-winner-group.jpg" width="300px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other was a solo project from a young man who had never programmed
prior to the event. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/dh2015/dh-winner-demo-2.jpg" alt="dh-winner-demo-2.jpg" width="300px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That one really blew me away. We were able to give these groups
Raspberry Pis thanks to a last minute donation from &lt;a href="http://www.fullstackacademy.com/"&gt;Fullstack Academy&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
None of this would have been possible without the help of:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Our organizers - Caitlin and Lise
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Our Mentors - both the Stuy students and the older mentors
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Our judges:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ben Fried (Google)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Noah Weiss (Foursqurae)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Benny Wong (TimeHop)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gerry Seidman (Too many to list)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Davin Chew (SumAll)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and our Sponsors:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://timehop.com"&gt;TimeHop&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://sumall.com"&gt;SumAll&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://digitalocean.com"&gt;DigitalOcean&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.generalcatalyst.com/"&gt;General Catalyst Partners&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://codesters.com"&gt;Codesters.com&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Building a High School Summer CS Program - SHIP</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-09-05-SHIP-index.html/</id>
    <updated>2014-09-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2014-09-05T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-09-05-SHIP-index.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wanted to do a couple more posts on the &lt;a href="http://cstuy.org"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt; summer program SHIP,
particularly about getting funding and reflections but I think I'll
just wrap things up with the school year starting. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Overall it was an amazing success and I'm amazingly proud of the
entire team (in no particular order):
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Devorah, JonAlf, Sam, Yulia, Topher, Ethan, 
Leslie, Brian, Andreas, Natan, Miranda, Nadia, Fawn, Lise, Jessica,
Angela, Benedict, Elise, Fish, and Derek.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and also proud of all the shipmates. Looking at where they started and
where they ended up – they were really terrific.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The only downside is knowing what we can accomplish when we have the
freedom, it reminds me about how badly we're
handcuffed by our school and the department of education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here are links to all the posts in case anyone's interested: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/07/03/launching-ship.html#.VAuVjB_GyzU"&gt;Preparing to launch&lt;/a&gt; - Some overall stats that we started with.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/07/10/ship-tas.html#.VAsC7h_fTZ8"&gt;The Stewards&lt;/a&gt; - How older students mentored younger ones.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/07/17/ship-guests.html#.VAsC7R_fTZ8"&gt;The Guests Stars&lt;/a&gt; - Guest speakers to inspire the kids.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/07/20/ship-outreach.html#.VAsC6x_fTZ8"&gt;Outreach&lt;/a&gt; - Some of the challenges in finding the kids.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/07/28/ship-toolset.html#.VAsC6h_fTZ8"&gt;Toolset&lt;/a&gt; - What language should we use?
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/07/30/ship-demo-day-tomorrow.html#.VAsC6B_fTZ8"&gt;Demo Day&lt;/a&gt; - What the TA's built.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/08/05/ship-outcomes.html#.VAsC5h_fTZ8"&gt;Outcomes&lt;/a&gt; - And the overall results.
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/08/08/ship-partners.html#.VAsC5B_fTZ8"&gt;Partners&lt;/a&gt; - We couldn't have done this without St. Josephs
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/08/16/ship-crew.html#.VAsC4x_fTZ8"&gt;The Crew&lt;/a&gt; - And the best teaching crew in the business.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Building a SHIP - The Crew</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-08-16-ship-crew.html/</id>
    <updated>2014-08-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2014-08-16T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-08-16-ship-crew.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;div class="center"&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship-crew/crew.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;The Crew&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the most important, possibly the most important part of SHIP's
success was the crew and that's what sets us apart.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've seen CS Ed organizations run by business people, lawyers,
investors and more.The people developing curriculum are EdTech people,
entrepreneurs and anything but seasoned educators. I've seen programs
developed, curriculum created and then the search for teachers
commence. Ofttimes real educators aren't involved at all.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We're teachers all the way down.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've said it before and I'll say it again - it's not about the
curriculum, it's about the teachers. Take, for example, math. Math curricula
have been well defined for years but we still have major problems with
math education. The bottom line is that it's the teacher in the room
that can bring a topic to life or kill it. A great teacher can make
a lousy curriculum decent. A great curriculum won't do anything for a
lousy teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's where we will succeed - we've got the best teachers and
that's our crew.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, onto the crew.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'm fortunate enough to have worked with some terrific teachers. If
they'd allow it, I'd like to think of three of them as my
proteges. Sam and JonAlf were actually students of mine when they were
at Stuy but I include Topher in the mix. Our fourth teacher, Yulia,
was JonAlf's student teacher this past year.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Coaching trees have become popular in recent history. It's kind of cool
that we have one for CS teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="center"&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
 &lt;img height="400px" width="600px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship-crew/tree1.png"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Coaching tree&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, it extends up as well, although my mentors, excepting Robert, didn't teach
CS. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="center"&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
 &lt;img height="400px" width="600px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship-crew/tree2.png"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Extended coaching tree&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And of course the rest of the team have other influences as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So let's talk about the crew.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4-0-1" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="sec-4-0-1"&gt;JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-4-0-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I like to describe JonAlf as a younger, hipper version of me. Of
course, I set the hip bar pretty low. I tell my kids that I used to be
the young teacher but I was never the hip teacher. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
JonAlf and I are probably the most similar in style. Of course, this
means that if you put us in a room together, all productivity
ceases. We've come up with such great ideas as our mascot, Clyde
"Thluffy" Sinclair," the Stuy CS semi-formal and more (or is that
less).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He's been my partner in crime since he came on board. Back in the day
I was the only teacher of our post AP classes and I was delighted to
offload some of that burden to JonAlf.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4-0-2" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="sec-4-0-2"&gt;Topher Brown&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-4-0-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JonAlf was the hip one (with the bar, admittedly set pretty low) until
Topher came aboard. Topher didn't go to Stuy so he can never be a made
man, but he's pretty awesome, nonetheless. He came in as a math
teacher who just coincidentally had a bit of a CS background. He fit
into our insanity from day one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4-0-3" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="sec-4-0-3"&gt;Sam Konstantinovich&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-4-0-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sam was also my student. He's the mature one (again, the bar was set
pretty low). I joke that he has the reputation for being the mean one
because his first day at Stuy he said something that scared some of
his students. Definitely more together and organized than the rest of
us I tried to convince him to join our team for three or four years
before he finally came over.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Just to be sure no one misreads my comments on Sam. I've trusted him
with my son's CS education. I think that should tell you how much I
think of him.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4-0-4" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="sec-4-0-4"&gt;Yulia Genkina&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-4-0-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yulia's the new kid on the block. We all went in feeling very positive
about having her on the team. At least until she tried to off all of
us on Pirate Day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="center"&gt;
&lt;p style="float:left"&gt;
&lt;figure style="float:left;padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="150px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship-crew/dw.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Yulia trying to off JonAlf&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="150px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship-crew/sam.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Sam&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="clear:both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="float:left"&gt;
&lt;figure style="float:left;padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="150px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship-crew/topher.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Topher&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="150px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship-crew/z.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;and me&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="clear:both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Seriously though, she fits right in and is also a real talent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-5" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-5"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That's the crew. I'm amazingly proud of all of them and one of the
things I was most happy about my role in SHIP was that I was able to
empower them to be themselves and just do their thing. When you have
a great crew that's how you do it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Building a SHIP - Our partner - St. Joseph's College</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-08-08-ship-partners.html/</id>
    <updated>2014-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2014-08-08T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-08-08-ship-partners.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From the day we filed the paperwork to create CSTUY, we knew we wanted
to run a summer program. In fact, we started looking for a space
during the 2012/2013 school year. We were hoping to run SHIP for the
first time in the summer of 2013 but we all knew it wasn't really a
realistic goal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our original plans required at least one classroom sized space, and up
to three for full days for a month. We figured this would be a hard
sell for a tech company, after all, what company is going to take a
room, let alone three, off line for half the summer. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, we turned to institutions of higher learning. I started talking to friends at a CS
program in one of our city's colleges. They loved the idea of hosting
a CSTUY program. Problem was that once the plans went up through the
college channels, the administrative side wasn't as hot to host
us. While the CS people really wanted us, the administrative side was
perfectly willing to give us space as long as we paid an amount that
really was much more than we could afford. To be honest, this really
irritated me. Here we have a supposedly non-profit college that's
supposed to support the community and the public good nickle and
diming another non profit that really is trying to do some good.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We ended up speaking to a number of educational institutions across
the city and the situation was the same. Sure you can have space. Here
are our rates…..
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-5" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-5"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, you might wonder, why not just use high school space? Because it
was important to be hosted at what should be the "next level" for the
participants.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-6" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-6"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the mean time, I met &lt;a href="http://www.sjcny.edu/FacultyExperts/124"&gt;Bill McAllister&lt;/a&gt;, CS Professor at St. Joseph's
College on Long Island. He hosts a terrific annual high school
&lt;a href="http://faculty.sjcny.edu/~ProgrammingCompetition/"&gt;programming competition&lt;/a&gt;. Bill referred me to David Seppala-Holtzman
the Math and CS Chair at the Brooklyn Campus. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
David and I clicked and one thing led to another and in the end,
having overlapping visions and goals, St. Joseph's College in Brooklyn
decided to host us.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I couldn't ask for a better partner. They provided us with all the
facilities we needed from rooms for the classes, to lounge space, to
access to the cafeteria (and got us a great rate on food to boot).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The whole St. Joseph's family made everything so easy for us. At one
point one of our instructors commented "wow, this is such a friendly
campus."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Without the help and support of St. Joseph's college, SHIP doesn't
happen. It was a great partnership and we're looking forward to
working together on SHIP 2.0 next year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Building a SHIP - Outcomes</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-08-05-ship-outcomes.html/</id>
    <updated>2014-08-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2014-08-05T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-08-05-ship-outcomes.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
SHIP ended last week. So, how did we do? Time to look at outcomes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Outcomes can be tricky. There are lots of programs out there and they
all claim amazing results. Unfortunately, it seems to me, that
everyone's so concerned with good PR that, well, you know, lies,
damned lies, statistics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First you've got claims like "learn how to make a mobile app in under
n weeks." I always chuckle at this. If it was that easy, why do we
have a tech talent shortage? I'm immediately skeptical of any program
that claims that kids go from nothing to making full featured web
apps or some amazing professional quality game in just a few
weeks. Learning takes time. The only way you get these miracle results
is by using frameworks, simplified tools, or scaffolding of some
kind. True learning, retention, and the ability to transfer knowledge
is minimal. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Then we have assorted stats. Here's one of my favorites.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Our students outperform other students who take APCS. We see this from
screened programs. Now, I have no problem with screening – we do this
at CSTUY, just don't imply that you're just taking everyone who
applies. If you have an application or an interview, you're screening
and starting ahead of the game. Since kids have to elect to come to
our programs they certainly have a good deal of interest. So, what
this claim is really saying is that a kid who likes CS enough to spend
their summers and or after school time doing it is likely to do better
than a kid who isn't going to spend this time doing CS. Big surprise.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, how do we measure our outcomes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-5" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-5"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We can start with the work the
shipmates did. We use processing and the shipmates learned from the
ground up. That is, they wrote everything from scratch. Some of the
groups taught themselves how to use processing libraries if they
needed facilities like a web API or accessing a camera, but since they
built everything up from simple statements, if they successfully
completed good projects, we could be pretty sure they've moved from
neophytes to programmers. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The projects were terrific
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="float:left"&gt;
&lt;figure style="float:left;padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship-outcomes/pacinvaders.png"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;PacInvaders by Sam, Margaret, and Ryan&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship-outcomes/iphone.png"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;IPhone simulator by Aminata, Sabrina, and Soraya&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="clear:both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The screen shots are just two samples but all the shipmates put
together great projects and since we used real tools, the shipmates
are well prepared for their next courses be they with us, in school,
or elsewhere.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Stewards also completed projects. I talked a bit about them in my
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/07/30/ship-demo-day-tomorrow.html#.U-Frpx_GyzU"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-6" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-6"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We also looked at surveys. We did ask some of the soft questions that
I alluded to above. Are you more likely to explore CS after SHIP?
How has SHIP influenced your opinion of CS and Tech? The answer to
the first was an overwhelming yes and the second was also
overwhelmingly positive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The money questions though, were did they want to come back for a
Saturday program and one next summer. Other than the shipmates that
lived too far away, again, the vast majority want to return.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-7" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-7"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Combine the programs they made and the fact that they want to come
back with great unsolicited feedback from parents and the shipmates
themselves and I think we can say that SHIP was a tremendous success.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-8" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-8"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we have to figure out how to raise the funds for the Saturday
program and next summer.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Can't wait for CSTUY SHIP Demo day tomorrow</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-30-ship-demo-day-tomorrow.html/</id>
    <updated>2014-07-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2014-07-30T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-30-ship-demo-day-tomorrow.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship-demo-day-tomorrow/mirandia.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Miranda and Nadia showing off their project&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Tomorrow is the last day of SHIP and we'll be capping the whole thing
off with a day of demos, science fair style.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Both the shipmates and the stewards will be showing off their work and
I can't wait. I've intentionally stayed away from the shipmates
because I want to be surprised but I've seen what the stewards have
been doing and I can't tell you how proud I am of their work. I was
going to say amazed, but actually, I'm not amazed at all – I know
they're all awesome.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'll put up pictures, descriptions and hopefully video after the event
but here's a quick summary of what they've done:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;3d network augmented reality pong&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - 
A 3d depth perception networked pong that you play using your hand as
*the paddle. The program uses the camera and blob recognition to
control the game.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Augmented Reality Board Game&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - 
It started with the stewards taking a picture of a maze and then
having their program solve it but it evolved into a game. The computer
continually takes a picture of the board and plays against a human
opponent who makes moves on the physical board.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Painting identifier&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; (pictured above) - 
Take a picture of a painting and the program will try to identify it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Seam Carving Image editor&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - 
Look it up on youtube - it's really neat.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Photo Booth&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - 
A little more cut and dry than the above but one of the instructors
has a wedding coming up and so we needed to build the photo booth.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All these projects are awesome and what's more they're all done from
scratch. Early on Gerry was visiting and commented on an early version
of the pong game. He said "they're writing their own blob detection,
right?" Of course. They can use libraries later. Now it's about
learning neat things.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I can't wait to see the stewards show these off tomorrow and also to
see the shipmates projects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On a side note, I've started to go through the comments the shipmates
have been writing down about the program - they just confirm what I
already knew - I'm lucky to be working with the best group of
educators out there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Building a SHIP - Toolset</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-28-ship-toolset.html/</id>
    <updated>2014-07-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2014-07-28T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-28-ship-toolset.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We're almost at the end of CSTUY SHIP's first journey. The Shipmates
and stewards will be showing off their work in another day or so and
I'm excited to see their finished projects. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But what toolset are they using. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With knew we would be working with two rooms of relative beginners. We
needed something that allowed us to develop the shipmates CS skills
while also having a low cost of entry. At the same time, we had to
use an environment that our Stewards would be comfortable with as they
would be both supporting the shipmates and developing their own projects.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Those of you that know me know that I'm &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;not&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; a fan of drag and drop
languages. I've looked at them time and again. I even made a concerted
effort while exploring a version of the new proposed AP course earlier
this year &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-28-ship-toolset.html/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Languages such as scratch require almost no ramp up
but for kids that are old enough for a traditional text based language
I've found the following:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After a short time, my students find DnD languages restrictive and
slow. They can get more done more quickly by typing.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many kids work on laptops with small screens. Small screens and DnD
languages are not a good match.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's much easier to look things up in a text based language.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm not convinced that starting with a DnD is in any way better
prepares a student for a text based language. 
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Bottom line, I've had to rescue a number of kids who were turned off
by the "toy" factor of languages like scratch and appinventor.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
DnD languages are probably fine for younger kids who are experimenting
and playing around but for my kids, I want something more real.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;The contenders:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4-1" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-4-1"&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-4-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Python&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - I'm a big python fan. It's one of my go to languages. Low
  cost of entry and very flexible.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4-2" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-4-2"&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-4-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Scheme&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - I love functional. It's simple, but it's a harder sell
  for parents and while in school, it's ok to take a few days to ramp
  up to get to the fun stuff, in a summer program, a delay in fun can
  be deadly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4-3" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-4-3"&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-4-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Javascript / web based&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - I also really like Javascript but the
  development environments are pretty lousy and it's almost "C like" in
  the number of hidden problems for newbies.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4-4" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-4-4"&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-4-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Java&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; - I'm not really a fan of the language but it is pretty
straightforward and it is the language of the AP exam. I'm not a fan
of AP but as we're trying to build a program from the ground up, it
doesn't hurt to be able to say "this will prepare you for APCS."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-5" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-5"&gt;The winner:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So what did we use? &lt;a href="http://processing.org"&gt;Processing&lt;/a&gt;. Processing is a wrapper and IDE around
Java. It's really simple to get started with and it makes all sorts of
graphics work very easy. Here's a simple processing program that
creates a circle wherever you click the mouse:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="org-src-container"&gt;

&lt;pre class="src src-java"&gt;&lt;span style="color: #228b22;"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="color: #0000ff;"&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;() {
  size(400,400);
}

&lt;span style="color: #228b22;"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="color: #0000ff;"&gt;mouseClicked&lt;/span&gt;() {
    fill(color(random(255),random(255),random(255)));
    ellipse(mouseX,mouseY,20,20);
}

&lt;span style="color: #228b22;"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="color: #0000ff;"&gt;draw&lt;/span&gt;() {

}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's it. No &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;public static void main…&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; or anything like that, but
it's legit Java, has types and classes plus:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;great online documentation.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it's used to interface with arduino.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it has libraries for web cams, music, internet APIs, and more.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
By using something like processing, the shipmates learn a real
language with sufficient depth to do something real and there's also
enough of an online community so that they can continue to work on
their own if they can't avail themselves of our future programs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While we were convinced that processing was the right choice for the
shipmates. I wasn't 100% sold on it as the best choice for the
stewards. Python would probably have been better for them but most of
them will be doing advanced Python (as well as Javascript) in their
classes in the fall and I didn't want to teach them something now and
reteach it to them in another month. On the other hand, they all
already knew Java and there was still plenty of neat things for them
to explore with processing. In the end, I think we made the right choice.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-28-ship-toolset.html/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
After going through the curriculum and scratch in depth, I
concluded that the intro course I designed and my team has evolved
over the past ten years is a stronger and more appropriate course for
our students.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Building a SHIP - Outreach</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-20-ship-outreach.html/</id>
    <updated>2014-07-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2014-07-20T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-20-ship-outreach.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;



&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We've got a few more topics to cover in the &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Building a SHIP&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
series. We still have to cover:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Crew
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Curricular Choices
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The long term plan
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Site and funding
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But for today, we'll talk outreach.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Outreach proved to be particular challenge for SHIP. Our entire crew
is made up of teachers. That meant that we couldn't communicate with
schools during business hours. That made things particularly tough.  I
could send emails after hours or set up emails to be sent at specific
times during the day, but we couldn't call while at our day jobs. As a
result, this led to a vary long communication loop and we could never
be sure that information about SHIP was getting to the right people.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We did have a small number of non-teacher volunteers and they were
invaluable but they had limited knowledge from the teaching side.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, we had the volunteers try to call schools during the day and we
followed up by emailing a flyer and link to a web site. We tried to
emphasize that we needed help from the schools in finding the right
students – that is students who might not have even considered
something like SHIP but where we could potentially turn them on to
something new.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In spite of this, we did get over 200 applicants for our 48 slots. I
have no idea how this compares to similar programs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There were many terrific applications, but there were some head
scratching situations. There were some incomplete applications which I
attribute to students who weren't really interested in the program,
but I was surprised by two things on the student side.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, sme times we needed a little more information from a student so we
sent an email to the addresses (primary and backup) that they listed
in the application. Some times students got right back to us. Other
times it took days or even weeks. In one case, we weren't able to
accept the student because he didn't get back to us until after the
selection process was over. I know that not everyone reads or responds
to emails promptly but I was surprised since these were cases of
students who wanted to partake in our program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another thing that surprised me is that we almost lost a couple of
students because they thought the program would cost too much. We
tried to make it as clear as possible that we offered financial
assistance and in many cases could cover all fees but apparently we
weren't as clear as I had hoped.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-5" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-5"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The one &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;really big&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; shock to me involved
recommendations. We required our applicants provide one email
address for someone that agreed to write a recommendation letter and
allowed for a second, optional one. We then contacted these
recomenders. If we didn't hear back, we sent reminder emails and asked
the applicants to prod the recommenders as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had a return rate of about 10%. This cut across type of school
(public, private, parochial, and charter) and grade (rising 9 through
12). As a teacher myself, I know of some colleagues who don't actually
write recs they agree to write but I was shocked that we only heard
back from 10%. The end result was that we could use a recommendation
to help an applicant but we didn't feel that it was fair to penalize a
student just because a teacher didn't send in a rec.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-6" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-6"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a final though on outreach, it should get easier for us over
time. SHIP is going great and next year, we'll be a known quantity to
schools. We should also have our cadre of shipmates helping spread the
word and of course, we want them back for another summer of more
advanced work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
    <category term="pedagogy" label="pedagogy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Building a SHIP - Guest Stars</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-17-ship-guests.html/</id>
    <updated>2014-07-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2014-07-17T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-17-ship-guests.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship_guests/cynthia.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Cynthia Koo talking about UX&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Much like the Love Boat had every week, at CSTUY SHIP, we too have our
guest stars.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the one hand, it's important to have a focused program that leaves
the shipmates empowered to continue their CS studies on their
own. That means the shipmates have to explore something with
sufficient depth so that the learning sticks. It also means there has
to be sufficient depth for the shipmates to continue their voyages
after our month together has ended.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, we want to present the big picture as well. There
are a lot of interesting things in computer science and technology
that we really can't get to in just a few weeks. Certainly not if we
want to do justice to those topics.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Having one off lectures helps. This way, our shipmates are exposed to
a wide array of voices and ideas. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, scheduling the right speakers at the right time can be a challenge.
Too technical too early can be a turn off. So can too simple.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We're lucky enough to have some amazing guest stars on our ship. We
started with a great talk on UX by &lt;a href="http://www.cynthiakoo.com/blog/"&gt;Cynthia Koo&lt;/a&gt;. UX is something I wish
kids were more exposed to and I think it was great that Cynthia was
able to talk to the shipmates about it before they embark on their own
projects. If we set the seeds early and have user experience in the
back of the shipmates heads before they start building things, I
suspect that the end results will show it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Cynthia talked about user needs and business needs and used looked at
Instagram and Snapchat as case studies. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The talk got the shipmates thinking about apps in a way they had never
considered before. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship_guests/edgar.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Edgar talking about all sorts of opportunities in tech&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today we had our second guest star. Edgar Troudt. Edgar talked about
innovation, disruption, crowd consumption and more.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Later on, we'll drill down with more technical talks.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For now, though, these talks were meant to give a broader view and to
inspire. I think they did.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Building a SHIP - the Stewards</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-10-ship-tas.html/</id>
    <updated>2014-07-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2014-07-10T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-10-ship-tas.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
div.left {text-align:left; padding:20px;}
div.right {text-align:right;padding:20px;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Stewards:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="float:left"&gt;
&lt;figure style="float:left;padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship-tas/bb.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;In size order.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure style="padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship-tas/fawn.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;And from the other side&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="clear:both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure style="float:left;padding:20px;width:100%"&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship-tas/stewards.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Ok, seriously - here they are.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p style="clear:both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I thought I'd share some thoughts on how we designed SHIP. I'll try to
talk about curriculum choices, tools and more in the coming week but
first, let's talk about our stewards.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When we first designed SHIP, we knew we wanted to run two rooms each
with around 24 shipmates and two teachers. We also figured that we'd want a
few of student teaching assistants, which I decided to name
Stewards - Natan wanted to call them Tars in tribute to the British
Navy, but he was outvoted.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had some questions:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what do we do with them when they're not working with the shipmates
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how old should they be
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what should they know
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We knew that we'd be using &lt;a href="http://processing.org"&gt;Processing&lt;/a&gt; as our development environment
for the shipmates &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-10-ship-tas.html/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; so we wanted the Stewards to know Java. We
also knew that when the shipmates worked on their group projects we'd
want to have one Steward mentor each group. That meant at least 12
Stewards. We went with 14. We also decided that we'd take kids that just
finished our AP CS classes at Stuyvesant since they were already well
versed in our lunacy and would help seed the culture we're looking to
grow.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What to do with them when they weren't working with the shipmates?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most of the stewards will be in my SoftDev class come the fall so I
didn't want to just teach them that material
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How about shepherding them through some advanced projects using the
tools that the shipmates would be using.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, we had a plan. We'd have the stewards work in small groups on
interesting projects when they  weren't working with the shipmates.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How has it gone so far? Pretty well I think. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I first asked them to figure out how to work with the webcam and
images in processing – at this point they can figure things out like
that on their own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We then talked about edge detection and they coded it up. This also
proved to be a nice demo for the shipmates.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure style="float:left;padding:20px"&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/ship-tas/leslie.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Leslie demoing for the shipmates&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p style="clear:both"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After that I asked them to come up with their own algorithms for blob
detection. They came up with some interesting solutions after which I
let them look up techniques on line. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why the image processing work? Many of the projects they want to work on are going to need to do image processing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now they're hammering out project proposals and getting to work. So
far I'm happy with what they're doing and delighted with the support
their giving the shipmates.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know if other programs have teaching assistants and how they
use them but I'm pretty happy with our arrangement.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-10-ship-tas.html/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
Subject of a later post.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Preparing to launch SHIP</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-03-launching-ship.html/</id>
    <updated>2014-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2014-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-07-03-launching-ship.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class="center"&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
 &lt;img height="300px" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/launch_ship/tas.jpg"&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Some of our Ship Stewards (TAs) planning day one. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What's been happening since the close of the school year? We've been
getting ready to start &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/04/07/ship-announce.html"&gt;SHIP&lt;/a&gt; - CSTUY's first summer program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
SHIP will be running starting this Monday through the end of July and
should be a great adventure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-0-1" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-0-1"&gt;Fast facts:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-0-1"&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have 47 students and 14 student teaching assistants (stewards)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have 4 amazing teachers, 1 mentor for the TAs, me, and one official
program mom.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most of the shipmates claim little or no programming experience.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our students come from 30 different schools. Mostly NYC but a few from beyond.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;36% of our shipmates are girls
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday the team spent the morning at St. Joseph's College setting
up the rooms. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now all we have to do is wait for Monday morning to roll around.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Announcing SHIP</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-04-07-ship-announce.html/</id>
    <updated>2014-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2014-04-07T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-04-07-ship-announce.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
It's been a while since my last post.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's mostly since I've getting things ready for this announcement.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've talked about our non-profit &lt;a href="http://cstuy.org"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt; before. Well, we've been hard
at work getting things together for our first summer program:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;SHIP - Summer Hackers Immersion Program&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We're really excited about this - taking our years of experience
teaching kids at our schools and taking it to a wider audience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;SHIP&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; is being hosted at St. Joseph's College in Brooklyn and runs from July 7th through July 31.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, if you know a rising 9th through 12th grader in or around New York City let them know about this great opportuity. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Information can be found at &lt;a href="http://programs.cstuy.org/ship"&gt;http://programs.cstuy.org/ship&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And the application is here: &lt;a href="http://programs.cstuy.org/ship-apply"&gt;http://programs.cstuy.org/ship-apply&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Information on our overall plan is here: &lt;a href="http://programs.cstuy.org/ship-outreach"&gt;http://programs.cstuy.org/ship-outreach&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We're also still raising funds for the program, so if you or someone you know can help, they can contact me or donate directly &lt;a href="http://cstuy.org/webform/donate"&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Summing up at SumAll</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-01-sumall.md/</id>
    <updated>2014-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2014-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-01-sumall.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our hackers have been coming down to &lt;a href="http://sumall.com"&gt;SumAll&lt;/a&gt; every
Saturday for a while now. It's a great space and we've been given run
of the office. That said, the hackers really had no idea what SumAll
is all about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, we had our first guest speaker. Davin Chew, founder and CTO of
SumAll. Davin's also a member of the StuyCS family, he was my student back in the nineties. When Davin heard
we needed space for our Saturday program, he and the SumAll team
graciously offered to host.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Davin spoke to the hackers about what SumAll does, how it's trying to, in Davin's words "Democratize data." How they're building a platform that lets a small business or even an individual really study their data. They've got some great visualizations and tools and you all should &lt;a href="http://sumall.com"&gt;check them out&lt;/a&gt; (and yes, according to their web site, there is and always will be a free tier).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Davin talked a little about how he and his co-founder sat in the room
we were all in and how they came up with SumAll. He talked about
passions, starting out a new compnay and a variety of other topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's always great to connect young hackers with people doing great
work in the real world so they can get a glimpse of the awesome things
they will be able to accomplish in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Some Links:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://smallbiztrends.com/2014/01/dane-atkinson-big-data-strategy.html"&gt;Dane Atkinson of SumAll: A Big Data Strategy That Goes Beyond Cutting and Pasting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.meangeme.com/1/post/2014/01/my-top-5-social-media-analytics-platforms.html"&gt;My Top 5 Social Media Analytics Platforms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hacking Sessions Resume</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-05-hacking-sessions-7.md/</id>
    <updated>2014-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2014-01-05T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-05-hacking-sessions-7.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2014-01-05-hacking-sessions-7/hackers.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to school last Thursday after almost two week off. Twenty four
hours later - Snow Day. I know this sounds a bit hokey, but I really
would have rather had school. I love a good snow day as much as the
next guy, but after a big vacation, I was really ready to get back to
work with the kids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday, hacking sessions were set to resume. Being in Manhattan,
getting around was pretty easy but we've got hackers from all over the
city from Staten Island to the Bronx. Needless to say, some boroughs
were easier to get around in than others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we were a small group - we were down two instructors and a TA but
Batya and Zach were in from college and helping out so instructors
actually outnumbered students!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did we do? Since the hackers are just starting on their projects,
this was a great opportunity to work one on one with them. Two of us
went over Javascript and SVG as an alternative to the HTML Canvas,
Zach worked with a couple of people on a Markov chain text generator
and so on. Even though the turn out was low, I'm really glad we got
back to business. Weather permitting, we should be back at full
capacity this coming Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's finally time to start talking to them about git.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hacking Sessions - putting it all together</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-16-hacking-sessions-5.md/</id>
    <updated>2013-11-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2013-11-16T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-16-hacking-sessions-5.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/pairprog.jpg" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/pairprog.jpg" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Week 5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, I lamented over the difficulties with only meeting once a
week. We went over a log of new material last week and I was happy
when today rolled around and the hackers would be able to start
putting things together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When writing a web app, you've got to know about all sorts of things -
for us it's HTML, CSS, Python, and the microframework,
&lt;a href="http://flask.pocoo.org"&gt;flask&lt;/a&gt;. That's quite a bit, particularly when
working with a group with a wide range of experience coming in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what did we do? We put together two partial web sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One had all the Python code, but was missing the HTML and CSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other had the HTML and CSS, but the Python logic was all missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was our hacker's mission to fill in the missing pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We liked the setup for a few reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each Hacker came in with different strengths and weaknesses. With this project, they could start with something they knew (picking the part with the "hard part" filled in) and then moving to a more challenging piece.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By looking at the other half of the project, they could find sample code for the pieces they were working on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hackers also had last weeks code as a reference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also introduced the hackers to pair programming - something I love
from a pedagogical point of view - but more on that in another post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I think the day went very well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also gave out our first assignment -- over the weeks, the hackers
will finish up their projects - next week we'll demo and give prizes
for the best.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hacking Sessions Week 4 - The challenges of once a week</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-11-hacking-sessions-4.md/</id>
    <updated>2013-11-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2013-11-11T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-11-11-hacking-sessions-4.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hacking-sessions-4/week4-tri.jpg" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hacking-sessions-4/week4-tri.jpg" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We just finished week 4 of CSTUY's Hacking Sessions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm really happy with how our hackers are doing - they're a great
bunch and even if they don't realize it yet, are making great progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, as an instructor and program designer I'm noticing the
differences between a once a week program and having a class every day
(note - I'm not the sole designer or instructor. I have a great team -
JonAlf, Sam, and Topher are three of the best teachers I've had the
privilege of working with - this post, however, is based on my
observations).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Once a week vs every day&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a big adjustment. In class, we only have 40 minutes but we get
it 5 days a week. Here we have 3 hours, but only on a single
morning. This means we can spend time on a large activity but once
noon rolls around, it's over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a student is confused, that confusion can fester for a week and by
the time we get to the next session we might not remember to clear
things up until the problem arises again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;They can run away&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In class, I know I have my students for a full term. We can bore them
or even annoy them a bit as long as we win them back. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of what we teach is boring. Other things are difficult and can be frustrating for students until we dedicate enough time for things to click. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you know you have the kids all term, you don't have to worry
about a bad day on your part or on the students. They'll be back
tomorrow. Meeting with people every day makes it much easier to
develop connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a once a week voluntary program you have to be more careful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;We can't count on work over the week&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm hoping that once we get a little further along the hackers will
want to work on projects over the week. That said, we know that
Hacking Sessions is extra curricular so when the hackers have big
assignments, SAT exams and the like, we have to take a back seat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the default for a Saturday program is that it's a partial restart
every week. That's a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Communication is tough&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the one that's vexed me most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we're only meeting once a week, it would be really great if we
can generate some online dialog in between. So far, it's been tough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in class, over the years, I've had mixed levels of success with
online communication. Some classes, some years, I've gotten great buy
in to an online class community. The dialog is consistent, varied, and
great. Other times, it's just the bare minimum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my classes I usually use a Google group but I'm becoming less and
less happy with that as a solution. For Hacking Sessions we've been
using &lt;a href="http://www.piazza.com"&gt;Piazza&lt;/a&gt; so far but in spite of its
popularity at colleges, I'm not feeling it. I find it both cluttered
and limiting. I think we're going to try Vanilla forums next. It's
pretty easy to host and fairly flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm hoping that in a few weeks we'll get past the basic tools and onto
some neat project and it'll be easier to encourage talk throughout the
week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Overall&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this is a new challenge but a fun one - designing and implementing
a once a week program. Bottom lining it - I think the hackers are
doing great and we're off to a really strong start. We'll make some
mistakes along the way but as long as we keep looking at what we're
doing we can adjust as we move along we'll continue to build a great program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hacking-sessions-4/week4-chris.jpg" rel="lightbox"&gt;
  &lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hacking-sessions-4/week4-chris.jpg" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hacking Sessions - Week 2</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-28-hacking-sessions-2.md/</id>
    <updated>2013-10-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2013-10-28T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-28-hacking-sessions-2.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-28-hacking-sessions-2/hackers2.jpg" rel="lightbox"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-28-hacking-sessions-2/hackers2.jpg" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday was the second day of CSTUY's Hacking Sessions. We started out
wit a minor panic - none of the laptops could connect to the
wireless!!! After a brief scramble, we finally gave up and gave our
host a call (sorry Davin) and the problem was swiftly addressed. From
there it was off to the races.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week we spent most of the session with mixers and setting up the
laptops. Not today. Sam started us off with a brief survey of Python -
some of the Hackers had never seen it before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there we divided up the hackers - making sure to spread out the
Pythonistas and they were off on a project. We did a little pig-latin
converter. It's a fun project to start a class with since it can be
attacked in a few different ways and you can illustrate a lot of
interesting coding techniques. For instance, checking for vowels or
consenants can be done with conditionals but testing set membership: &lt;strong&gt;if letter in "aeiou": &lt;/strong&gt; is a touch more elegant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was really nice to watch things develop. At first groups were four
individual hackers working on four laptops. Soon, with the
encouragement of our awesome TAs, it was two groups of two talking to
each other and then finally, groups of four all working together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;22 students from 9 schools all hacking together - that's what we're
trying to build. I think we're off to a great start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We finished the day sharing the projects and learning a little bit
about the Flask microframework for Python.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hacking Sessions Begin</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-20-Hacking-Sessions-Begin.md/</id>
    <updated>2013-10-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <published>2013-10-20T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-20-Hacking-Sessions-Begin.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yesterday was my 46th birthday. How did I spend it?  Well, 20
"Hackers" from 9 schools, 4 student TAs and a few of us teachers
gathered at &lt;a href="http://sumall.com"&gt;SumAll&lt;/a&gt; to kick off CSTUY's first
weekly program - Hacking Sessions (sometimes called Hackers Sessions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-20-hacking-sessions/hackingsessions-2.jpg" rel="lightbox"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-10-20-hacking-sessions/hackingsessions-2.jpg" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the first week so it was mostly mixers, setting up machines
(installing Linux on 24 laptops takes time) and going over how we'll
be communicating but I'm really excited about the weeks to come. We
all expect to hit the ground running this coming Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's easy for a Stuyvesant student to become part of the Stuy CS
family. Most students at other schools aren't lucky enough to have
that type of critical mass. Typically they're one of a few techie
students and if they're lucky there will be maybe one teacher who's
really knowledgeable and passionate about CS and tech in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're hoping that this is going to change that. These 20 hackers
represent the start of a community for student hackers -- taking what
we've developed at Stuy outside the confines of the school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Davin and everyone at &lt;a href="http://sumall.com"&gt;SumAll&lt;/a&gt;
for providing not only space but an amazingly welcoming and friendly
environment and also Fanming for coming up with the laptops.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cstuy" label="cstuy"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
