<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>C'est la Z (curriculum)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/curriculum.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 22:16:46 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Essential topics for an intro course (not)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/essentials-for-an-intro-course/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
What essential topics should we teach in our intro courses? This seems
to be a recurring topic recently. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It can be an important topic but, unfortunately, too often, it seems
that people have too myopic a view
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I remember thinking about this years ago when APCS moved from C++ to
Java. Both languages have good and bad points both for practical and
educational use. A big loss in the move to Java was memory management
and the topics you could cover when memory issues arose. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course one might say that memory management shouldn't be in the
first year of CS. That's fine, as long as you put it back in somewhere
later on - something that didn't seem to happen universally. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's the myopic view - far too few look at the overall picture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
C++ to Java ended up in removing a topic. I've also seen the reverse. 
I was talking to a friend about intro topics. He told me that it was
critical to cover (insert topic here) in an intro course. Why, I
asked? Because the kids absolutely needed to know that material in the
third year course he was teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I pressed a bit – "how many kids actually remember (insert topic
here) and do you have to reteach anything." The answer - pretty much
no one remembered and he always retaught the subject.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Did this mean that no one taught the topic in the earlier class?
Unlikely. More likely is that the topic was taught without purpose or
context, just because it was supposed to be taught and thus the
knowledge wasn't retained. Sounds to me like the topic wasn't in the
right place to begin with. Maybe it should have just been taught in
that 300 level course to begin with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo?ref_src=twsrc%255Etfw"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt; wrote a post earlier today asking about &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/01/how-important-are-number-bases-for-pre.html"&gt;teaching
number bases&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Is it important? Maybe. Is it essential for an intro course? Probably
not. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Binary makes sense when you start talking about low level stuff. If
your intro course never gets close to the machine then why muddy the water
with a topic that's out of place. The topic probably won't be
appreciated and retention and understanding will be low. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If your intro course gets close to the machine or if you decide to
talk about compiled code or similar topics, you have an entre to talk
binary which leads to the convenience of hexadecimal. At Stuyvesant,
it was much more sensible to talk about number bases in our systems
course when we looked at C code in a debugger rather than in our intro
our AP course. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You also might work on some application where bitmaps or similar as
useful. That might be another good time to talk about number bases.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Is it important for a CS person to understand binary and it's relation
to digital computers? Certainly. Does it have to be studied day one?
Certainly not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We need to keep an eye on the big picture. You can't get everything
into a single class or a single yea. The question to ask is - do our students know what they have to by the time they
leave our charge?
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>curriculum</category><category>teaching cs</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/essentials-for-an-intro-course/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 20:56:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Lesson plans - scripts to springboards</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/lesson-plans/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent last Saturday up at the Microsoft offices in Times Square
observing a &lt;a href="https://www.tealsk12.org/"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; training session. My fried &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nathanielgranor"&gt;Nathaniel Granor&lt;/a&gt;, Teals
Regional Manager in the east has invited me a number of times and this
time I was able to make it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you don't know, TEALS is a program that takes volunteers in the
tech industry and places them in classrooms. Unlike other programs,
the TEALS volunteers work with the teachers while the kids learn some
CS. The idea is that the teacher will learn about CS from the
volunteer and the volunteer will learn something about teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not the same as having a strong, knowledgeable CS teacher in the
classroom but until we get there, TEALS is doing great work giving
kids something that they need and otherwise wouldn't get.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At one point, Nathaniel started to talk to the volunteers about lesson
plans emphasizing the fact that TEALS would provide all the lesson materials and
the plans so these new to teaching tech volunteers wouldn't have to
make curricular decisions. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The lesson plan form was pretty traditional and pretty formulaic:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;warm up
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hook
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;instruction 
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;practice
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assessment
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Very similar to what I was shown back in the day during my two day
"teaching boot camp" that kicked off my career &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/lesson-plans/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and very
appropriate as an effective and efficient way to prepare these
volunteers for their first days. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking about my lesson planning over the years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I started, I was teaching math but I wasn't really a math
guy - I was CS all the way. I had to remember the math from high
school, learn the new topics, and figure out how to teach it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had a very supportive department but they were busy with their own
classes and this was pre internet. Fortunately, the NYC DOE published
lesson plan books. They were basically bound volumes of xerox copies
of hand written and typed lesson plans provided by experienced
teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I spent many hours copying them, studying  them, and then later
tweaking them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They were a life saver back then. How was the teaching? OK. Not
great. I got the material to the kids but I was nothing special. This
is where I started to form my bias against the scripted teaching
that's being pushed down today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I developed my chops, I started to design my own experiences for my
classes and things improved. By the time I was done teaching math -
maybe 4 years in, I was just scratching the surface of being a math
teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One year in, I started teaching CS along with math at Seward
Park. When I was bumped to Stuy, I went back to math for  a year and a
half and then it was all CS all the time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For CS, we didn't have lesson plan books so I had to craft everything
from scratch. It was a lot of work but the results were much better.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At first, I would actually write out lesson plans a la math lesson
plans. A "do now," "instructional objectives," "applications,"
"Homework," etc. The only thing I never formally wrote out was a
"medial summary."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over time, my lessons got better but my lesson plans looked worse and
worse. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were times a lesson plan might look something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/lesson-plans/plan.jpg" alt="plan.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
OK, not exactly but as I developed at my craft, I didn't need a laid
out script to follow line for line  rather, just a set of little
reminders and maybe some printed out code. If we were going to develop
a complicated algorithm or derivation, though, I would still write out
all the steps.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This doesn't mean that as my career progressed I planned any less. It
might appear that I'm winging it but even if little to nothing is
written down, there is a plan and there's always a lot of pre work
before class begins.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, to bring this back to TEALS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's interesting how what's good in one context is not so much in
another.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What TEALS is doing is great - they've got to get a lot of
technologists in to classrooms quickly but once there, they'll be with
real, hopefully experienced teachers. What they're doing gets them
ready to go. It's a starting point, not an end.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, when I see scripted curriculum being sold as the
special sauce, be it in CS teacher "training," Teach for America
summer prep or in the name of charter school uniformity, I run the
other way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's prepare curricular  materials for important programs like TEALS
and for beginning teachers just starting out but let's not confuse a
scripted lesson that can be delivered by one and all to be anything
close to the work of a master educator and craftsman.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/lesson-plans/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;full disclosure: I
came in to teaching with zero education credentials and took the
minimum number of ed classes for my license after I started.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>curriculum</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>teals</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/lesson-plans/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2016 23:31:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Navajo Math Circles</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, I saw the New York Premiere of &lt;a href="http://www.zalafilms.com/navajo/"&gt;Navajo Math Circles&lt;/a&gt;, a
documentary on a &lt;a href="http://www.mathcircles.org/"&gt;Math Circle&lt;/a&gt; put in place to support and enrich the
currently under-served community in the Navajo educational system.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At their core, Math Circles are math outreach and enrichment
programs. I'm most familiar with the &lt;a href="https://www.nymathcircle.org/"&gt;New York Math Circle&lt;/a&gt;. I'm friends
with many of their teachers and organizers and my son took part in
their summer program for a couple of years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over in the southwest, these Math Circles have been bringing together
students, frequently across great distances each day to explore
problem solving and creativity through mathematics.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As someone who's worked hard to bring educational opportunities to the
have nots, I love the program. Some of the highlights include the kids
working on open ended problems, focusing on process and techniques
more than specific results, working both collaboratively but also
developing self sufficiency, and more. I also love the fact that
they've started teacher math circles to help to bring some of that
math circle magic to the everyday classroom.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I enjoyed the film and recommend you check it out to see what's
possible and I want to share my two big takeaways.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, early on in the film, one of the people running the program
talked about developing a math enrichment program through and with
Navajo traditions and culture. This is HUGE and I feel it's something
we're losing. America is so diverse from coast to coast and here in
New York City you can see radically different ways of life living
right across the street from each other. Everyone pays lip service to
"making the work interesting and relevant to the student" but few
people walk the walk. These folk do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Second, I left the documentary with a sour taste in my mouth. Not
because of the program but because the Navajo Math Circle project and
projects like it are scraping together what little resources they can
to try to do what the school systems should be doing to begin with.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
As we move to scripted lessons, national standards, curricula dictated
or at least influenced by large private concerns and standardized
tests, our schools are moving further and further away from community
and local culture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the documentary, one student pointed out that in math class, they
have to use the textbook. They learn the process and then have to
solve the problems. In Math Circle, there are no textbooks. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Afterwards, the students in from the Math Circle did some Q&amp;amp;A. I asked
them to elaborate - what's the difference between there Math Circle
experiences and their in school ones. I got:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Math Circle is fun!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think that says it all.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know many great teachers who try to bring culture and community to
their classes. One of my son's best teachers, &lt;a href="http://www.heinemann.com/authors/828.aspx"&gt;Paula Rogovin&lt;/a&gt; did it all
the time. Many of my friends and colleagues try to do so as well but
the powers that be make it harder and harder. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Until we win back public education it's important to support programs
like Math Circles (and, if I do say so myself, programs like our own
&lt;a href="http://cstuy.org"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;) and it's also critical that we work to try to bring community
and culture to our regular classes.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>curriculum</category><category>education</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 11:03:55 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>