<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about currulum</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/currulum.atom</id>
  <updated>2017-09-23T13:00:39Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/currulum.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/currulum/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Theseus's Curriculum</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/theseus%27s-curriculum/</id>
    <updated>2017-09-05T18:41:14-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-09-05T18:41:14-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/theseus%27s-curriculum/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orga37d266" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orga37d266"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orga37d266"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With the school year starting I was originally planning on writing
about my class rules. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Instead I think I'll riff on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt;'s post today titled
&lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/09/curriculum-is-hard.html"&gt;Curriculum is Hard&lt;/a&gt;. I'm guessing I found curriculum design and
development daunting decades ago but at this point in my career it's
something I enjoy. In any event, Alfred got me to thinking - when is a
curriculum your own?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you grab a curriculum complete with lesson plans, assignments; the
whole kit and caboodle and you use it verbatim it's clearly not your
curriculum. It probably also isn't really teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What about the more common case. Math curricula has basically been set
for years. Algebra, Geometry &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/theseus%27s-curriculum/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and then Algebra 2
and Trigonometry. Most books seem to be sequenced in a similar way
and at least in the schools I know about, the math department has some
document listing a day by day list of topics. This makes sense since
you probably have more than one class of each type and you want some
cross class consistency. Particularly during the first weeks of the
semester when kids can transfer and then also at the end of term or
year. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When a teacher uses that departmental document are they using someone
elses curriculum?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What if they create their own homeworks and assigments?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most teachers I know use the department's curriculum but make their
own unit and day to day lesson plans. Most revise them each
semester. Typically these teachers do a little more here or a little
less there depending on a number of factors.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Are they creating their own curriculum?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What if they re-sequence the topics?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How about adding an enrichment topic?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back when I taught math I used the departmental syllabus, as many
texts as I could find, colleagues lesson plans and whatever I could
find but I always pulled it together to something I could call my
own. If I didn't, I wouldn't have been comfortable going in front of
my class. Was it my curriculum? They were certainly my lessons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, when designing a course I start from the end outcomes and work
backwards but when teaching a course, I still look at as many
resources as I can find. I'll pull a little from here, a little from
there and combine that with whatever I can come up with myself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, when is it your curriculum and when is it not? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're just delivering scripted lessons it's certainly not yours.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you know your stuff and you  take someone elses material, make it
your own and add it to your bag of tricks, I think it's now yours as
well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/theseus%27s-curriculum/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;which is really logic and deductive
reasoning using Euclidean Geometry as platform&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="currulum" label="currulum"/>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
