<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about curriculum</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/curriculum.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-09-05T21:31:48Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/curriculum.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/curriculum/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Time To Create An Ethics Course</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/time-to-create-an-ethics-course/</id>
    <updated>2018-07-21T16:52:21-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-07-21T16:52:21-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/time-to-create-an-ethics-course/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc45bbe2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc45bbe2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc45bbe2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think it's time for me to start developing a CS Ethics class. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
An ethics course isn't a replacement for having teachers that live and
model good behavior and weave ethical issues throughout the curriculum
but still, adding a separate course on top of that has its merits.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not in a rush to create this course. I might be done in a month or
it might take a couple of years. When I'm done, I'll add it as an
option in my CS Teacher education programs but hopefully it will be an
attractive course for undergrad CS majors as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While it's easy enough to come up with possible topics - privacy,
moral responsibilities, biased algorithms, net neutrality and on and
on I'm looking for this course to have a serious coding component. I
want the students to build things to really understand the
implications of what they're studying.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One topic I definitely want to cover is &lt;a href="https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2011/10/youre-not-so-anonymous/"&gt;anonimity&lt;/a&gt;. I'd love to find
the right combination of data sets and have the class discover that
some hidden information in the sets isn't nearly as hidden as it seems
to be. When I was at Stuy, I was thinking about
having the kids give me permission to use their class schedules since
even with names removed we could probably identify many kids by
electives and overlapping classes. I have no idea what I'll be able to
do at Hunter. If I can come up with something good I think this will
form the basis of a pretty amazing part of the class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another project I'd love to put together is something dealing with a
biased algorithm. Again, I don't know where this will go, maybe
something where I can seed the class so that different groups
implement some project differently and we can then analyze each groups
biases, hidden or otherwise. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Beyond these two, I'm not sure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How about you? Anyone out there have any good ideas for programming
projects for an ethical CS course? If so, please share. It might be a
while but when I do finish putting this together I'll be sure to
publish whatever the end result is.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="csed" label="csed"/>
    <category term="curriculum" label="curriculum"/>
    <category term="ethicalcs" label="ethicalCS"/>
    <category term="ethics" label="ethics"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NYC CS4All - This Is Not The CS We're Looking For</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/this-is-not-the-cs-were-looking-for/</id>
    <updated>2017-09-29T10:40:24-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-09-29T10:40:24-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/this-is-not-the-cs-were-looking-for/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org18df527" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org18df527"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org18df527"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It's no secret that I'm something of an old curmudgeon in the K12 CS
Education world and I've been critical of a number of initiatives and
organizations over the years but I've been pretty quiet on the CS4All
movement in NYC Department of Education. I've had and any number of
concerns though.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This past week at the inaugural meeting of New York City's CSTA
chapter we got a taste of the &lt;a href="http://blueprint.cs4all.nyc/"&gt;NYC CS4All Blueprint&lt;/a&gt;. A highlight was
this video:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/224494221" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Along with the &lt;a href="http://blueprint.cs4all.nyc/resources/3/%0A"&gt;supporting web page&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
TL;DR - in a elementary school CS class, the students kept tapping out
drumbeats on the desk because they had drumming class the period
prior. Now the drumming teacher is teaching rhythms that match
segments of HTML so the students can tap and chant the line as a
memory aid. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sure, it's nice when teachers can work together to support each other
but at the end of the day this is a mnemonic aid to memorize
HTML. Nothing particularly innovative here. Mnemonics like this are
great until there are too many to keep track of or ones that are too
similar. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The part that saddened me was that this  was the video that was
chosen  as a highlight, an exemplar. It was OK but there was
nothing new or innovative. What was worse was that there was no
computer science.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The kids were memorizing HTML. As we watched the video, my neighbor
nudged me and asked "why are they memorizing HTML?" I would ask the
same question. Now, I do think that HTML or some other mechanism to
create content that can be shared with the world is important. Having
students get there work out in the word can be tremendously rewarding
and motivating. Also, although I'm not sold on it, some say that HTML
is a good stepping stone to CS but still. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's try an experiment.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Imagine that lesson but instead of HTML the kids were learning
Microsoft word so instead of a chant for &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a href=""&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; you have a
chant for putting a link into a word document or instead of a chant
for &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;somethingbold&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; you have a chant like
&lt;code&gt;control-b-typestuff-then-control-b&lt;/code&gt;. Same lesson, same technique,
still no CS. You could also say that this was just one video and maybe
most of the year is about real CS. Maybe, but then why highlight this
on the CS4All web site as a featured resource.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was disappointing but not surprising. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some will say that kids aren't ready for hardcore CS at that
age. That's fine. We can have that discussion but if CS is appropriate
for whatever grade was in the video then it should be real CS. We can
also have endless discussing about what that is but memorizing HTML is
not it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wondered if the video was representative so I looked at &lt;a href="http://blueprint.cs4all.nyc/resources/5/"&gt;another&lt;/a&gt;. It
turned out this was also a lesson on HTML and again the video could of
been about any number of subject areas. I will give this one credit
for highlighting that you can do "unplugged" activities but it wasn't
really a CS activity.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then there was &lt;a href="http://blueprint.cs4all.nyc/resources/15/"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. No video here but how we structure a CS
lesson. We have this outline:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Warm-up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mini lesson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Independent work time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share session&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Or, as we used to say back in the stone age:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do Now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instructional activity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;summary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Nothing new and nothing CS here. I used that model when I taught math
but deviated from it more and more as I developed my CS teaching
chops.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally I looked at &lt;a href="http://blueprint.cs4all.nyc/resources/24/%0A"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. For full disclosure I have to say that
Eric, the teacher, is a friend of mine and I &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;know&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; he's a dynamite
teacher and I know he knows his stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This video, however was all about differentiation. Just like the other
resources, there's nothing wrong with them per se but there's not
really about CS. You could reskin them for any subject. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also agree with a lot of what Eric says in the video but as CS
Standards take hold and standardized exams become the norm we'll find
that individualized instruction and meeting students where they are
is in direct conflict with the testing that comes with standards. I'll
talk more about that in my standards rant that I keep putting off
writing.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Sure, the resources site has  a page with concepts like algorithms and
many schools, for better or worse, in the upper grades just fall back
on AP offerings but the more I dig the more it's apparent to me that
CS4All in NY will be more about getting something into every classroom
rather than something appropriate and good.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="csed" label="csed"/>
    <category term="curriculum" label="curriculum"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ethics, Cybersecurity, ethics, curricula  and standards</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-cybersecurity-curricula-standards/</id>
    <updated>2017-08-02T07:43:24-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-08-02T07:43:24-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-cybersecurity-curricula-standards/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgfa87da2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgfa87da2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgfa87da2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This morning, I read &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt;'s post on &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/08/cybersecuritythis-summers-computer.html"&gt;teaching
cybersecurity&lt;/a&gt;. as Alfred says, it's something of a CS Ed buzzword this
summer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another hot topic in K12 CS Ed this summer is the inclusion of ethics
in our CS courses courtesy of efforts like the #ethicalCS twitter chat every
Wednesday at 8:00 Eastern time  hosted by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ed_saber"&gt;Saber Khan&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Discussions about both topics include "where should we be doing this?"
"What should we be doing?" and of course "How?" 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking about designing curriculum from the top down -
that is, as dictated by outside forces: principals, superintendents,
states, industry or bottom up: a teacher sees a need and designs
something for their students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The best classes I've seen are those designed by a passionate teacher
from the ground up. I met  &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dougbergmanUSA"&gt;Doug Bergman&lt;/a&gt; at this past year's CSTA conference. He's terrific. I
think he came to the conference wanting to find out more about what
cybersecurity really meant. By the second day, he was raving about all
the amazing possibilities. I'd love to be in the class he develops.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, when topics or standards are forced down from
above, I've seen something entirely different.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've observed and been involved in cybersecurity discussions  with CS
teachers. The discussion goes something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Well, we do memory allocation in course XYZ so we can give a
homework assignment there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can rewrite the story (theme) for the assignment in our data
structures class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We already do a crypto assignment in algorithms so we're already
doing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've seen the same with groups of math teachers discussing
implementing common core. They talk about resequencing topics,
rewriting a few word problems or homework assignments but at the core,
the feeling is "we already know how to teach math."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It gets worse when there's a standardized or high stakes test at the
end of the tunnel and you get the "you need this for the test" type
units.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This might not be as big of a problem in K12 CS right now because so many
teachers are just learning their craft but in established fields such
as math or college CS, when an edict comes from above telling a
teacher how to teach, unless the teacher really believes in it, the
teacher will only pay lip service to it. If it isn't an issue in CS Ed
right now, it will eventually become one as our field develops legs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is arguably a bigger issue with Ethical CS than cybersecurity. If
the teacher doesn't really believe it's an important topic, we'll get
lip service at best and in the case of ethics, unless the teacher
really believes it and models it, the students will be able to tell
that it's a show.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't have an answer other than what my friend and mentor Herb
Greenhut told me many years ago "Solving the education problem is
easy. Hire good teachers and get the f*ck out of the way."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="curriculum" label="curriculum"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Designing a course with constraints</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/design-course-with-constraints/</id>
    <updated>2017-05-19T11:38:20-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-05-19T11:38:20-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/design-course-with-constraints/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org74e3a53" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org74e3a53"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org74e3a53"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the hats I wear at Hunter is to build a new &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs.html"&gt;CS Honors program&lt;/a&gt;
and to bring my particular brand of insanity to &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-important"&gt;Hunter College CS&lt;/a&gt; as a
whole.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday was my last class for the semester so I thought I'd write a
bit about the course.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For the Fall semester, I taught an intro programming course to the
entire cohort. For some in the cohort, this was their first exposure
to CS. Others had one or more classes under their belt. It was a
Python based programming class and a big part of it was to start
building the cohort into a community. I'm going to work on tweaking
what I taught for next time around but the constraints of designing
such a course are pretty common – an intro course where the students
all want to be there the level of previous experience varies to some degree.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Second semester was more of a challenge. The "next" course was CSCI
135, CS 100 - like APCS but in C++. I could teach that but since some
of my students had APCS credit, they didn't need 135. This would break
up the group. There was also the issue of the students getting credit
for the course without showing any proficiency in C++.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, Hunter requires students in 135 to take CSCI 136. A 1
credit programming lab. It meets once a week in a computer lab and the
students complete a weekly programming assignment. The lab meets for 2
hours. The instructor goes over anything that's needed for the lab
that hasn't been covered yet and then the students work independently
(with the instructors support) on the lab. Overall it works well. It
makes sure the students are spending at least a couple of hours a week
coding in a supported environment.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
How did 136 help me? I taught a 3 credit course where 1 day was
basically the lab component (what the students were to do in 136) and
one day was enrichment - the stuff I was going to do with them. This
enabled us keeping the cohort together and it also made sure that by
taking the class, the honors cohort members with AP credit would
indeed get up to speed in C++.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was happy with the basic structure. I was able to cover some topics
in project development, testing, debugging, and software engineering but the
designing and teaching the class proved to be challenging for a number
of reasons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One was timing. The lab class meets 1 day a week for 1 hour. My class,
2 days a week for 1 hour 15. This meant that if we were to keep the
lab to one day either the students would have less time or I'd have to
impose on them to stay late or come early. I wasn't happy with that
but given the inconsistency in the way the other sections handled lab
timings, I think it worked out OK.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some of the other difficulties included:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org62d835c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org62d835c"&gt;The language was C++:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org62d835c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since the labs were to be done in C++, I had to use that as the
language for the class. That meant no "fun" libraries or frameworks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd6b3be8" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd6b3be8"&gt;The labs were solo assignments:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd6b3be8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since the labs were solo projects and there was one per week it made
it very difficult to structure group experiences. I wanted to cover
things like group development, code review, working off of other
peoples code bases but this proved difficult with an outside separate
lab being handed down each week.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgef3ff7c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgef3ff7c"&gt;Someone else dictated the language sequence:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgef3ff7c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The labs were designed to support what the students were learning in
135 and were only distributed a day or two before the week was to
start. This meant that I couldn't plan too far ahead and had to adjust
frequently. This should be easier next year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd9fa44f" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd9fa44f"&gt;Labs didn't match the supplemental material:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd9fa44f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The best example of this was when we were talking about testing. We
ended up using &lt;a href="https://github.com/philsquared/Catch"&gt;Catch&lt;/a&gt; as a testing framework. The problem was that
right afterwards the lab (and also 135 project) didn't lend themselves
to using a testing framework like catch. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were more challenges but overall I think the class went fairly
well. I'll know more when I get feedback from the students and when we
all look back next year with some perspective.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's been an interesting experience designing a class that had to
interleave with another, existing class. I've designed many classes
over the years and I know that whatever you plan, it probably changes
once you're actually in the classroom and working with the kids, or as
Mike Tyson said: "Everyone has a plan until they get punched in the
mouth." This has been a little more of a challenge but I think the
first go through went well and that the course will get better and be
better defined as we go through a couple more iterations. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="curriculum" label="curriculum"/>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Starting with scheme</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/starting-with-scheme/</id>
    <updated>2017-02-15T12:20:25-05:00</updated>
    <published>2017-02-15T12:20:25-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/starting-with-scheme/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
Scheme is one of the languages used in Stuy's intro CS course. Like
any other language, there are pros and cons of using it to introduce
students to CS. Here are some of the reasons why I like Scheme as a
first language and why despite that,  I don't recommend it in many
cases.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Scheme certainly isn't mainstream. That's not the main reason why I
like it but it is a side benefit. It's less likely kids come into
class knowing it which creates a level playing field. The few times
I've had a student with a background in Scheme, they've been good,
helpful kids rather than ones that tried to show off and dominate the
class. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I like scheme because it's simple. It looks different than other
languages but is &lt;code&gt;(+ 3 4)&lt;/code&gt; really that different than &lt;code&gt;add(3,4)&lt;/code&gt; or
&lt;code&gt;3+4&lt;/code&gt;? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We can tell kids "everything's a function." While technically not
true, and I tell my students that it isn't, it's close enough for our
purposes. Everything's a function and the way we write a function is:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Apply function &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;f&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; on arguments &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;b c …&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;. So we have &lt;code&gt;(+ 2 3)&lt;/code&gt; to
add 2 and 3, &lt;code&gt;(and a b)&lt;/code&gt; for logical and &lt;code&gt;(= 3 4)&lt;/code&gt; to test to see if 3
is equal to 4, etc. We also have the same basic notation for things
like conditionals. In java, we might write:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In scheme, it would be:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even though we're fudging the rules, we can lay out a handful of rules
for the kids such as lambda and define follow a similar form to create and
name functions:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;define &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;add2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;lambda &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;+ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
where &lt;code&gt;(lambda (a b) (+ a b))&lt;/code&gt; returns a function that adds &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;a&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;b&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;code&gt;define&lt;/code&gt; associates it with the identifier &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;add2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;. Now we
can use the function: &lt;code&gt;(add2 5 10)&lt;/code&gt; which evaluates to 15.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With lambda, define, if, and a few more basics, it's off to the
races. The simple, consistent syntax makes things easy for the kids
and the constrained tool set lets us focus their way of thinking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course this wouldn't work had DrScheme (now &lt;a href="https://racket-lang.org/"&gt;Racket&lt;/a&gt;) not
existed. That gave us a nice learning IDE to work in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Using Scheme, we can not only cover the basics like conditionals,
abstraction and such but also deeper concepts like recursion, map,
filter, and reduce. When we move on from Scheme, the kids also have a
frame of reference for all the other languages and paradigms they use.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are downsides, however. Outside help is harder to come by and
there is some pushback from parents and it isn't as pretty and flashy
as some other tool-sets. Scheme worked at Stuy for a number of
reasons. When I created the class that used it, there were no good
pre-AP classes in the school and I had a pretty good reputation as a
teacher. The class also used multiple tools with &lt;a href="https://ccl.northwestern.edu/netlogo/"&gt;NetLogo&lt;/a&gt; being the
primary other one and tackled a variety of CS and non CS topics.
First time through, reputation and buzz filled the classes and after
that, the class developed a solid enough reputation to fill itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It also didn't hurt that our program developed from the inside
out. First, we had APCS-AB on the books as a junior year course, then
I added our post AP senior year electives. Since it was easy to show
what the kids were already graduating with, it was easy to diffuse any
pushback from not using mainstream tools in the first class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Scheme worked at Stuy and I feel that it still does. Would I use
Scheme for a first experience in a drop in program at an after-school
where kids might not come back if they don't get to a payoff
immediately? Probably not. Would I recommend it at a school where I
want to integrate CS with some of the other subjects quickly, again,
probably not (except for integration with algebra where &lt;a href="http://www.bootstrapworld.org/"&gt;Bootstrapworld&lt;/a&gt;
is a terrific program).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any event, if you're a high school CS teacher and  haven't played
with scheme  or some other functional language, I highly recommend
it - you might not actually ever teach it or use it but it can really
help develop you as a programmer and an educator.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="curriculum" label="curriculum"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Selecting a starting language - why not Javascript</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/starting-with-js/</id>
    <updated>2017-02-13T08:45:48-05:00</updated>
    <published>2017-02-13T08:45:48-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/starting-with-js/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org8db41aa" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org8db41aa"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org8db41aa"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was catching up with the team at Stuy the other day and they
mentioned that they were periodically getting pushback on their choice
of languages, particularly in the intro class. The pushback was mostly
in the form of "why don't you start them with Javascript?" 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back in the day, when I created our intro class where we use Scheme,
NetLogo and then later Python, I'd get similar pushback but then it
was "why not Java?", "why not C?", or "whu not C++?"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had a good discussion on this and I shared my thoughts as to why I
don't like Javascript as a first language and I thought I'd share some
of them here. I'll try to get around to the rationale behind Scheme
and NetLogo in a later post.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start, let me say that I &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Love&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; Javascript -
particularly when approaching it as a functional language. I also
think every school and situation is different so there are likely
times when Javascript is the right beginner language for the job.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's dive in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why are some of the pluses for Javascript as an intro language.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Ubiquity and availability:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you have a browser, you have Javascript - it's also available
through online IDEs and online lightweight sites like &lt;a href="https://jsfiddle.net/"&gt;JSFiddle&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Interactivity:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can tweak websites almost live, use the HTML5 canvas pretty
interactively and mode
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;It's mainstream&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;It's quick to get up and running&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is all true, but there are also downsides.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of my big problems with Javascript is the lack of simple solid
educational tooling. I love to use tools like &lt;a href="http://www.drjava.org/"&gt;DrJava&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://drpython.sourceforge.net/"&gt;DrPython&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href="https://racket-lang.org/"&gt;Racket&lt;/a&gt; (formerly DrScheme) with beginners. All simple learning
IDEs. True, you can use a simple online IDE but I haven't found them
to have as strong a learning interface. They also, generally, keep you
in an oversimplified programming sandbox. There's no clean transition
from the sandbox to the real deal - particularly given the non-trivial
state of js build tools and environments. These simple learning IDEs
set the stage and then we can transition to more powerful development environments.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also prefer, where possible, to have kids learn locally so that they
can learn something about the underlying operating system even if
only at a user level.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A problem relating to the lack of tooling is the fact that a JS
program can fail to run and not give you any meaningful feedback at
all - this is a problem for a beginner. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Javascript also has all sorts of wonkiness. We have &lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;==&lt;/code&gt;
which is pretty conventional, but then there's also &lt;code&gt;===&lt;/code&gt;. We have
potentially confusing scoping issues and also some other real
weirdness:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;53&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//  50&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;53&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'3'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// 50&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'53'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// 50 &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'53'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'3'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//50&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;53&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//  56&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;53&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'3'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// '533'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'53'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// '533&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nx"&gt;console&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'53'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'3'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// '533'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For more, check out the this &lt;a href="https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/wat"&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;. Start watching at about 1:20 -
it's a riot.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All of this weirdness actually makes sense - just not to a beginner. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Javascript also gives plenty of freedom - there are many ways to do
things. This can be great for the developer but not necessarily ideal
for the learner. Loops, recursion, mapping functions - you name it,
Javascript's got it. I like simpler languages for beginners because
it's easier to get them thinking and problem solving in certain ways
when there tool set is somewhat restricted (more on that when I write
about Scheme).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, the fact that Javascript's a mainstream language can be a
minus. Given its popularity, a beginner class could have at  least a
few kid who've at least played with the language. This can lead them
to think they know more than they do and more importantly, this can
be intimidating to the real newbies who develop the impression that
"everyone knows this but me." A less mainstream language puts everyone
on a level playing field.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let me say again that I love javascript as a language and before a
student graduates Stuy they can learn all about Javascript, front end
development, some functional programming, and more. It's just not the
right language to start with - at least not at Stuy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="curriculum" label="curriculum"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="languages" label="languages"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Essential topics for an intro course (not)</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/essentials-for-an-intro-course/</id>
    <updated>2017-01-09T15:56:08-05:00</updated>
    <published>2017-01-09T15:56:08-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/essentials-for-an-intro-course/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
What essential topics should we teach in our intro courses? This seems
to be a recurring topic recently. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It can be an important topic but, unfortunately, too often, it seems
that people have too myopic a view
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I remember thinking about this years ago when APCS moved from C++ to
Java. Both languages have good and bad points both for practical and
educational use. A big loss in the move to Java was memory management
and the topics you could cover when memory issues arose. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course one might say that memory management shouldn't be in the
first year of CS. That's fine, as long as you put it back in somewhere
later on - something that didn't seem to happen universally. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's the myopic view - far too few look at the overall picture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
C++ to Java ended up in removing a topic. I've also seen the reverse. 
I was talking to a friend about intro topics. He told me that it was
critical to cover (insert topic here) in an intro course. Why, I
asked? Because the kids absolutely needed to know that material in the
third year course he was teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I pressed a bit – "how many kids actually remember (insert topic
here) and do you have to reteach anything." The answer - pretty much
no one remembered and he always retaught the subject.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Did this mean that no one taught the topic in the earlier class?
Unlikely. More likely is that the topic was taught without purpose or
context, just because it was supposed to be taught and thus the
knowledge wasn't retained. Sounds to me like the topic wasn't in the
right place to begin with. Maybe it should have just been taught in
that 300 level course to begin with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt; wrote a post earlier today asking about &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/01/how-important-are-number-bases-for-pre.html"&gt;teaching
number bases&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Is it important? Maybe. Is it essential for an intro course? Probably
not. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Binary makes sense when you start talking about low level stuff. If
your intro course never gets close to the machine then why muddy the water
with a topic that's out of place. The topic probably won't be
appreciated and retention and understanding will be low. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If your intro course gets close to the machine or if you decide to
talk about compiled code or similar topics, you have an entre to talk
binary which leads to the convenience of hexadecimal. At Stuyvesant,
it was much more sensible to talk about number bases in our systems
course when we looked at C code in a debugger rather than in our intro
our AP course. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You also might work on some application where bitmaps or similar as
useful. That might be another good time to talk about number bases.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Is it important for a CS person to understand binary and it's relation
to digital computers? Certainly. Does it have to be studied day one?
Certainly not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We need to keep an eye on the big picture. You can't get everything
into a single class or a single yea. The question to ask is - do our students know what they have to by the time they
leave our charge?
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="curriculum" label="curriculum"/>
    <category term="teaching-cs" label="teaching cs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lesson plans - scripts to springboards</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/lesson-plans/</id>
    <updated>2016-06-23T19:31:11-04:00</updated>
    <published>2016-06-23T19:31:11-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/lesson-plans/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org337d3ec" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org337d3ec"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org337d3ec"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent last Saturday up at the Microsoft offices in Times Square
observing a &lt;a href="https://www.tealsk12.org/"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; training session. My fried &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nathanielgranor"&gt;Nathaniel Granor&lt;/a&gt;, Teals
Regional Manager in the east has invited me a number of times and this
time I was able to make it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you don't know, TEALS is a program that takes volunteers in the
tech industry and places them in classrooms. Unlike other programs,
the TEALS volunteers work with the teachers while the kids learn some
CS. The idea is that the teacher will learn about CS from the
volunteer and the volunteer will learn something about teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not the same as having a strong, knowledgeable CS teacher in the
classroom but until we get there, TEALS is doing great work giving
kids something that they need and otherwise wouldn't get.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At one point, Nathaniel started to talk to the volunteers about lesson
plans emphasizing the fact that TEALS would provide all the lesson materials and
the plans so these new to teaching tech volunteers wouldn't have to
make curricular decisions. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The lesson plan form was pretty traditional and pretty formulaic:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;warm up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;instruction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assessment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Very similar to what I was shown back in the day during my two day
"teaching boot camp" that kicked off my career &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/lesson-plans/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and very
appropriate as an effective and efficient way to prepare these
volunteers for their first days. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking about my lesson planning over the years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I started, I was teaching math but I wasn't really a math
guy - I was CS all the way. I had to remember the math from high
school, learn the new topics, and figure out how to teach it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had a very supportive department but they were busy with their own
classes and this was pre internet. Fortunately, the NYC DOE published
lesson plan books. They were basically bound volumes of xerox copies
of hand written and typed lesson plans provided by experienced
teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I spent many hours copying them, studying  them, and then later
tweaking them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They were a life saver back then. How was the teaching? OK. Not
great. I got the material to the kids but I was nothing special. This
is where I started to form my bias against the scripted teaching
that's being pushed down today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I developed my chops, I started to design my own experiences for my
classes and things improved. By the time I was done teaching math -
maybe 4 years in, I was just scratching the surface of being a math
teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One year in, I started teaching CS along with math at Seward
Park. When I was bumped to Stuy, I went back to math for  a year and a
half and then it was all CS all the time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For CS, we didn't have lesson plan books so I had to craft everything
from scratch. It was a lot of work but the results were much better.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At first, I would actually write out lesson plans a la math lesson
plans. A "do now," "instructional objectives," "applications,"
"Homework," etc. The only thing I never formally wrote out was a
"medial summary."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over time, my lessons got better but my lesson plans looked worse and
worse. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were times a lesson plan might look something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/lesson-plans/plan.jpg" alt="plan.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
OK, not exactly but as I developed at my craft, I didn't need a laid
out script to follow line for line  rather, just a set of little
reminders and maybe some printed out code. If we were going to develop
a complicated algorithm or derivation, though, I would still write out
all the steps.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This doesn't mean that as my career progressed I planned any less. It
might appear that I'm winging it but even if little to nothing is
written down, there is a plan and there's always a lot of pre work
before class begins.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, to bring this back to TEALS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's interesting how what's good in one context is not so much in
another.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What TEALS is doing is great - they've got to get a lot of
technologists in to classrooms quickly but once there, they'll be with
real, hopefully experienced teachers. What they're doing gets them
ready to go. It's a starting point, not an end.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, when I see scripted curriculum being sold as the
special sauce, be it in CS teacher "training," Teach for America
summer prep or in the name of charter school uniformity, I run the
other way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's prepare curricular  materials for important programs like TEALS
and for beginning teachers just starting out but let's not confuse a
scripted lesson that can be delivered by one and all to be anything
close to the work of a master educator and craftsman.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/lesson-plans/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;full disclosure: I
came in to teaching with zero education credentials and took the
minimum number of ed classes for my license after I started.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="curriculum" label="curriculum"/>
    <category term="pedagogy" label="pedagogy"/>
    <category term="teals" label="teals"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Navajo Math Circles</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</id>
    <updated>2016-06-08T07:03:55-04:00</updated>
    <published>2016-06-08T07:03:55-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, I saw the New York Premiere of &lt;a href="http://www.zalafilms.com/navajo/"&gt;Navajo Math Circles&lt;/a&gt;, a
documentary on a &lt;a href="http://www.mathcircles.org/"&gt;Math Circle&lt;/a&gt; put in place to support and enrich the
currently under-served community in the Navajo educational system.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At their core, Math Circles are math outreach and enrichment
programs. I'm most familiar with the &lt;a href="https://www.nymathcircle.org/"&gt;New York Math Circle&lt;/a&gt;. I'm friends
with many of their teachers and organizers and my son took part in
their summer program for a couple of years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over in the southwest, these Math Circles have been bringing together
students, frequently across great distances each day to explore
problem solving and creativity through mathematics.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As someone who's worked hard to bring educational opportunities to the
have nots, I love the program. Some of the highlights include the kids
working on open ended problems, focusing on process and techniques
more than specific results, working both collaboratively but also
developing self sufficiency, and more. I also love the fact that
they've started teacher math circles to help to bring some of that
math circle magic to the everyday classroom.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I enjoyed the film and recommend you check it out to see what's
possible and I want to share my two big takeaways.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, early on in the film, one of the people running the program
talked about developing a math enrichment program through and with
Navajo traditions and culture. This is HUGE and I feel it's something
we're losing. America is so diverse from coast to coast and here in
New York City you can see radically different ways of life living
right across the street from each other. Everyone pays lip service to
"making the work interesting and relevant to the student" but few
people walk the walk. These folk do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Second, I left the documentary with a sour taste in my mouth. Not
because of the program but because the Navajo Math Circle project and
projects like it are scraping together what little resources they can
to try to do what the school systems should be doing to begin with.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
As we move to scripted lessons, national standards, curricula dictated
or at least influenced by large private concerns and standardized
tests, our schools are moving further and further away from community
and local culture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the documentary, one student pointed out that in math class, they
have to use the textbook. They learn the process and then have to
solve the problems. In Math Circle, there are no textbooks. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Afterwards, the students in from the Math Circle did some Q&amp;amp;A. I asked
them to elaborate - what's the difference between there Math Circle
experiences and their in school ones. I got:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Math Circle is fun!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think that says it all.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know many great teachers who try to bring culture and community to
their classes. One of my son's best teachers, &lt;a href="http://www.heinemann.com/authors/828.aspx"&gt;Paula Rogovin&lt;/a&gt; did it all
the time. Many of my friends and colleagues try to do so as well but
the powers that be make it harder and harder. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Until we win back public education it's important to support programs
like Math Circles (and, if I do say so myself, programs like our own
&lt;a href="http://cstuy.org"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;) and it's also critical that we work to try to bring community
and culture to our regular classes.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="curriculum" label="curriculum"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="pedagogy" label="pedagogy"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
