<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about disruption</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/disruption.atom</id>
  <updated>2016-08-23T00:48:23Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/disruption.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/disruption/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Ed Disruption - why it's different</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ed-disrupt-why-diff/</id>
    <updated>2016-07-25T19:32:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2016-07-25T19:32:01-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ed-disrupt-why-diff/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Earlier today I read &lt;a href="http://www.eliothorowitz.com/blog/2016/07/25/innovate-vs-appropriate/"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/eliothorowitz"&gt;Eliot Horowitz&lt;/a&gt;, founder and CTO of MongoDB.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Eliot titled the post "Innovate vs Appropriate" and talks about the
importance of knowing when to come up with something new vs when to
use the accepted tool, technique, or method. Eliot, of course is
discussing this as it applies to MongoDB and it's well worth a read
but it got me thinking about the ever popular need to "disrupt"
education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've witnessed this disruption or Ed Reform for the last decade
plus. The basic notion that public education isn't working so we need
to disrupt things. We've suffered through:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vouchers
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charters
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Online "learning" replacing teachers
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teach for America and other temp type efforts
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merit pay
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VAM for teacher evaluation
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and more
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These disruptions are brought to you by your friendly neighborhood
billionaire "philanthropist" or your politicians.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
By and large, they haven't worked.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Bill Gates got us to close down community schools and create small
ones. While we did need more small schools, overall it didn't work
(&lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/marc-epstein/small-schools-miracle-or_b_2641400.html?utm_hp_ref=new-york"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/answer-sheet/wp/2014/06/09/how-much-bill-gatess-disappointing-small-schools-effort-really-cost/%0A"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;). VAM teacher evaluation is &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/answer-sheet/wp/2014/06/09/how-much-bill-gatess-disappointing-small-schools-effort-really-cost/%0A"&gt;arbitrary and capricious&lt;/a&gt;,
merit pay has &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/answer-sheet/post/ravitch-why-merit-pay-for-teachers-doesnt-work/2011/03/29/AFn5w9yB_blog.html"&gt;never worked&lt;/a&gt;, nor does the &lt;a href="http://educationnext.org/online-charters-mostly-dont-work-forum-virtual-schools-greg-richmond/"&gt;online thing&lt;/a&gt;. Meanwhile, charter
schools by and large &lt;a href="http://www.nea.org/home/32999.htm"&gt;don't do better&lt;/a&gt; than public schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Rather than saving our schools, these efforts have lowered teacher
morale and done little for our most vulnerable children.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what's the difference between ed disruption and the tech world?
Well, for starters, those disrupting education totally ignore the very
advice that Eliot posted about today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Disruption to and of our public schools hasn't been a matter
appropriating what works and innovating what needs to be innovated but rather
a playground for pet projects of politicians and well meaning rich
folk.  Rather than looking at something simple that works, like, say,
smaller class sizes, we get computerized testing. Instead of
experienced teachers, we get inexperienced newbies that leave after
their commitment is up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why the difference? It hit me while reading Eliot's post. When a
founder is "disrupting" he has skin in the game - it's his company -
sink or swim. Not so for education reformers. Politicians merely need
to be re-elected.Sso as long as something looks good short term, it is
good. Those who disrupt schools are never held accountable. We got
small schools and VAM from among other places, Bill Gates. He admitted
his reforms didn't work but was there any penalty for disrupting so
many lives? Nope. For politicians, it's the same story. As Mayor Mike
Bloomberg once said "If they don't like my education policy, they can
boo me at parades."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Can we fix this? Sure, but not unless those forcing the changes have
real skin in the game. Will it happen? I'm not holding my breath.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="disruption" label="disruption"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
