<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>C'est la Z (education)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/education.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 11:33:28 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Hillary and Student Loans</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I read over Hillary's briefing on her initiative on
&lt;a href="https://www.hillaryclinton.com/briefing/factsheets/2016/06/27/hillary-clintons-initiative-on-technology-innovation/"&gt;Technology and Innovation&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A lot of it sounds good but, at least for the education piece, I have
my doubts. My feeling is that she's pretty much aligned with the
current administration education wise and the current administration
has been as bad if not worse than the previous with respect to public
education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While I have issues with some of the education pieces and very much
like some of the others, I don't want to get into that today. I want
to focus on one specific part of her plan. The part that defers
college debt for up to 3 years for founders and entrepreneurs. This
sounds great but is this really a good thing?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some initial responses from the education community is "what about
young teachers, don't they deserve some help on college debt? What
about nurses?…" and of course they're right. On the other hand, I
don't want people to go into teaching for 2 or 3 years just to get
some debt relief benefit and then jump ship. That's the Teach for
America model that I feel has become so harmful.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But again, that's not where I'm going with this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's start with "who are these founders?" I don't have any hard data
but I have read a couple of recent pieces that indicate that founders
right out of college are typically from well to do backgrounds. This
of course makes sense. A kid up to his or her eyes in debt from a poor
background. No savings, no property, likely a family, that is siblings
and parents who are also treading water can ill afford to take a big
financial risk. A kid from a monied family? Much more so. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This alone makes Hillary's plan a boon for the wealthy but not so
much for the people we need to give a hand up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Next, this plan talks about the founders and only says it will
"explore similar incentives"  for early employees, citing "10 to 20."
This doesn't seem right to me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now let's look further into the benefits. I don't know what the
success and failure rates are for startups. I've seen a bunch of
figures including:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;90% of startups fail within the first three years
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three out of four startups fail 
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Of 10 startups, 3 or 4 totally fail, 3 or 4 break even and the
others turn a profit.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know where the truth lies but I'd imagine that the success
rate for startup by a recent college graduate, wet behind the ears is
probably higher than for a more season professionals.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hillary's plan defers debt for up to three years. If any of the
failure numbers cited above are near correct it means that these kids
will have burned through up to three years with the experience of a
failed startup to show for it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've always advised my students, all things being equal, start at a
big or mid size company, develop your chops, learn how they do it,
further build out your network, and then go out and do your
thing. Most kids are better served not going directly from college to
their first startup.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So there it is. A plan that makes for great "press release" but is it
really addressing the issues?
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><category>tech</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 21:38:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Navajo Math Circles</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, I saw the New York Premiere of &lt;a href="http://www.zalafilms.com/navajo/"&gt;Navajo Math Circles&lt;/a&gt;, a
documentary on a &lt;a href="http://www.mathcircles.org/"&gt;Math Circle&lt;/a&gt; put in place to support and enrich the
currently under-served community in the Navajo educational system.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At their core, Math Circles are math outreach and enrichment
programs. I'm most familiar with the &lt;a href="https://www.nymathcircle.org/"&gt;New York Math Circle&lt;/a&gt;. I'm friends
with many of their teachers and organizers and my son took part in
their summer program for a couple of years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over in the southwest, these Math Circles have been bringing together
students, frequently across great distances each day to explore
problem solving and creativity through mathematics.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As someone who's worked hard to bring educational opportunities to the
have nots, I love the program. Some of the highlights include the kids
working on open ended problems, focusing on process and techniques
more than specific results, working both collaboratively but also
developing self sufficiency, and more. I also love the fact that
they've started teacher math circles to help to bring some of that
math circle magic to the everyday classroom.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I enjoyed the film and recommend you check it out to see what's
possible and I want to share my two big takeaways.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, early on in the film, one of the people running the program
talked about developing a math enrichment program through and with
Navajo traditions and culture. This is HUGE and I feel it's something
we're losing. America is so diverse from coast to coast and here in
New York City you can see radically different ways of life living
right across the street from each other. Everyone pays lip service to
"making the work interesting and relevant to the student" but few
people walk the walk. These folk do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Second, I left the documentary with a sour taste in my mouth. Not
because of the program but because the Navajo Math Circle project and
projects like it are scraping together what little resources they can
to try to do what the school systems should be doing to begin with.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
As we move to scripted lessons, national standards, curricula dictated
or at least influenced by large private concerns and standardized
tests, our schools are moving further and further away from community
and local culture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the documentary, one student pointed out that in math class, they
have to use the textbook. They learn the process and then have to
solve the problems. In Math Circle, there are no textbooks. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Afterwards, the students in from the Math Circle did some Q&amp;amp;A. I asked
them to elaborate - what's the difference between there Math Circle
experiences and their in school ones. I got:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Math Circle is fun!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think that says it all.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know many great teachers who try to bring culture and community to
their classes. One of my son's best teachers, &lt;a href="http://www.heinemann.com/authors/828.aspx"&gt;Paula Rogovin&lt;/a&gt; did it all
the time. Many of my friends and colleagues try to do so as well but
the powers that be make it harder and harder. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Until we win back public education it's important to support programs
like Math Circles (and, if I do say so myself, programs like our own
&lt;a href="http://cstuy.org"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;) and it's also critical that we work to try to bring community
and culture to our regular classes.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>curriculum</category><category>education</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 11:03:55 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>