<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about education)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/education.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Apr 2018 20:02:00 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Tools and Complexity</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tools-and-complexity/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org45c1165" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org45c1165"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org45c1165"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt; wrote about &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/04/thoughts-on-where-cs-education-tools.html"&gt;CS education tools&lt;/a&gt; earlier today. I've
also been meaning to write on the topic but from a different point of
view.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I do my best to keep up with the latest and greatest in the CS world
both on the academic side as well as the professional one. That's not
really possible, but I do my best. When I have a small project to work
on I'll some times use it as an excuse to play with some recent
technology. Over December, I wanted to write an application viewer to
use for company / student internship matching. I started by looking at
&lt;a href="https://reactjs.org/"&gt;React&lt;/a&gt; but ended up using &lt;a href="https://vuejs.org/"&gt;Vue.js&lt;/a&gt; which I liked much more for a variety
of reasons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The viewer served it's purpose but I think it can be turned into a
much more comprehensive student / employer internship platform. I
tried to steal a few minutes over this past week's spring break to
start a rewrite using another toolset, Clojure, Clojurescript and
Reagent. I'm really liking the Clojure stack and using
Emacs and Cider for the IDE is really blowing me away. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I've noticed is that for every new language of framework you also
have to learn a whole set of ancillary tools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It didn't used to be that way. Back in the day, things were much
simpler. I remembering doing work at Goldman Sachs, it was as simple
as typing something on the command line like &lt;code&gt;cc file1.c file2.c
file3.c&lt;/code&gt;. I of course had to be cutting edge and use fancy modern
tools like &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/make/"&gt;Make&lt;/a&gt;. What's more, the tools I used in industry were very
similar to what I used in college. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We now live in very different times.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you go to the getting started guides for React or Vue it's pretty easy to
get hello world up and running but beyond that you start to fall in to
the Javascript tooling hole. To start you need either &lt;b&gt;npm&lt;/b&gt; or &lt;b&gt;yarn&lt;/b&gt;
just to manage packages and dependencies. Then you need a build system
or bundler like &lt;b&gt;webpack&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;browserify&lt;/b&gt;, or &lt;b&gt;parcel&lt;/b&gt; and that's not even
considering older options like &lt;b&gt;gulp&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;grunt&lt;/b&gt; and ancillary tools
like &lt;b&gt;babel&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A typical React or Vue project is going to need a &lt;a href="https://github.com/krasimir/react-webpack-starter/blob/master/package.json"&gt;project.json&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/krasimir/react-webpack-starter/blob/master/webpack.config.js"&gt;webpack.config.js&lt;/a&gt; file and sometimes some other files as well. Check
out the links. They're from a simple project template I found
online. Far from simple.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I was playing with Vue.js a couple of months ago, I ended up
using Webpack to convert the source code into the final JS, take care
of live-reloading, and in general manage the project. I still have no
idea how most of it works. I don't know if it's just me but I'm very
uncomfortable relying on tools that I really don't fully understand to
build my systems. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Clojure world is little better with Leiningen and Boot. If you
don't believe me, try to make heads or tails of &lt;a href="https://github.com/bhauman/figwheel-template/blob/master/src/leiningen/new/figwheel/project.clj"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While it's true that as a professional you'll likely use one set of
tools on a day to day basis and you'll eventually get to know them
that doesn't mean it's not a good idea to prepare kids for what's to
come.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
On the K12 side we have drag and drop languages, specialized learning
IDEs like BlueJ, simple cut down IDEs like Dr Racket and completely
online environments like repl.it. All great starter tools that
insulate beginners from the complexities to come. College's
might get closer to the "real world" but just a tad. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Don't get me wrong, I like many of the tools used in K12
classes and there's far too much complexity in the professional world to
throw at beginners. If we look at a student's entire school
career, classes are already so packed with material it would be hard to
really prepare kids for the real world within their classes. You could
take that tried and true teacher / professor technique of just
requiring it and having the kids figure it out on their own but that's
really just downright abusive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't have an answer for this one. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have my kids use tools like Git and GitHub early along with using
testing frameworks and external libraries. I also try to move my
students to a general purpose programmable platform like Emacs or
Vim. I think these are sound practices but students will still have a
big learning curve when they finally get to industry. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I really would love it to see the tooling become simpler and
documentation better. &lt;a href="https://github.com/parcel-bundler/parcel"&gt;Parcel&lt;/a&gt;, a Javascript bundler is one of the newer
kids on the block and is much simpler and cleaner than alternatives
like Webpack. The new version of Clojure has it's own command line
tool which is also simpler than the alternatives. Maybe we are already
moving in the right direction and this entire rant will become moot in a couple of years.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>csed</category><category>education</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tools-and-complexity/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2018 22:55:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ethics In CS Education</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-in-cs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org13c9eaa" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org13c9eaa"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org13c9eaa"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've been meaning to write about ethics in CS education for a
while. Probably since I saw &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/02/12/business/computer-science-ethics-courses.html?smid=fb-share"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; in the NY Times but got sidetracked.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was reminded when I saw this tweet by Hadi the other day:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;This message is bigger than Facebook. Computer science faces an ethics crisis. That’s why &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/codeorg?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@codeorg&lt;/a&gt; covers ethics and digital citizenship in our computer science courses. (And we’re thankful that most of the largest tech companies support us) &lt;a href="https://t.co/roSkAzANQM"&gt;https://t.co/roSkAzANQM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Hadi Partovi (@hadip) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hadip/status/977673429485731840?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;March 24, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think we can all agree that bringing ethics and digital citizenship
and, frankly, citizenship in general to our students is important. What I wonder is
what approaches will lead to meaningful results and what methods will
lead us to checking off the "covered that" box.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm skeptical of throwing an ethics course into the curriculum as some
places seem to be doing. A class might be required, might fulfill an
elective requirement or it might just be an extra course. If it's
required, what does it replace or are you just going to add more to
the student load. If it fulfills an elective credit, will it be
perceived as "the easy course" as opposed to say, theory and if it's
just an extra course, who's going to take it? Will it just become
preaching to the choir. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Better is what Hadi mentioned in his tweet - embed ethics throughout
all of your courses and while I think this type of embedding is
important and I'd argue necessary, I'm still betting it won't be
enough to make a difference.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When teaching a course, teachers cover the curriculum but when you
drill down to where they focus their time, it comes down to:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what they think is important for the kids to know.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what they think the kids will need for that high stakes exam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If a teacher feels embedding ethical concerns is important they'll
spend time on it, if not, it will be lip service. Even if it's on the
high stakes exam, unless the teacher really believes that this is
important it will just be teaching to the test.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'd argue that it has to go even further since teachers can only do so
much. How many schools have honor codes and how many of us know
graduates from those schools who exhibit less than ethical behaviour.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So what do we do?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, of course we do have to embed ethical concerns across the
curriculum. Teachers should be armed with both the materials and time
needed to address ethical concerns but beyond that, we need teachers
for which ethical CS is important.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My friend &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ed_saber"&gt;Saber Khan&lt;/a&gt; has been facilitating a monthly #ethicalCS
twitter chat for close to a year now. I don't take part in too many
twitter chats but do recognize that they're important in raising both
awareness and community. I've also seen ethical CS issues more
frequently appear as conference sessions and professional development.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The next big step is to start at the beginning - pre service teacher
training and in my opinion, not with a course but rather embedding
ethical issues throughout teacher preparation. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If we want to crack this nut it can't just be from curriculum and from
the choir. Pre service CS teacher training is in it's infancy and has
not yet really found its form.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Much to my chagrin, a lot of CS Ed has gone the way of other Ed: Math
Ed, Science Ed, etc. and not in a good way. Let's see if we can make
sure that pre service CS teacher preparation develops to attract and
create great teachers for which ethical CS is part of their core. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>ethicalCS</category><category>preservicexs</category><category>teachers</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-in-cs/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Mar 2018 20:59:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>On Prestigious Competitons And High Schools</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-prestigious-competitons-and-high-schools/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org8b98398" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org8b98398"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org8b98398"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The ACM recently announced this year's winners of the Cutler-Bell
Prize in High School Computing. Over on his blog, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt;
noted that the winners were either from independent or magnet public
schools. Alfred also noted that most of the winners of prestigious
science competitions like the Regeneron Science Talent Search (nee
Intel, nee Westinghouse) were from public magnet schools. In &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/03/impressive-high-school-computer-science.html%0A"&gt;his post&lt;/a&gt;,
Alfred ruminates on this and wonders "how to we add the flexibility
and support to more students at more schools?"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As someone who spent over 25 years at Stuyvesant, arguably the
granddaddy of these public magnet schools, I wanted to share some
thoughts. I can only share my experiences from Stuy along with what I
know from a few other schools but I still hope this is worth a read.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Regeneron competitions under it's various names is the oldest and
most established of these competition so it's pretty easy to get some
data. Stuy is at or near the top of the list in terms of Regeneron
finalists and semi finalists. The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regeneron_Science_Talent_Search"&gt;Wikipediapage&lt;/a&gt; lists Stuy as second
to Montgomery Blair with 22 finalists to 40 but the data only goes
back to 1999. I personally know of at least 7 more finalists from my
early years at Stuy, 4 more from the early 90s, 8 more listed under
the page's "notable" entries and who kows how many from the 80s and
earlier. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Stuy had a strong run of finalists in the early 90's and the early
2000's but there has been a fall off in recent years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's look at what makes Stuy "special" and then at the fall off.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
In terms of money, Stuy gets a basic budget similar to other NYC
public schools plus some extra due to the extra graduation
requirements (other schools get extra money for an assortment of
reasons). I seem to recall that the Parents Association raises
somewhere in the low to mid six figures and the Alumni Association has
been historically dysfunctional as a fundraising body.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, it's not money.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Flexible scheduling? That's something that Alfred mentioned. Stuy kids
have super packed programs. Some kids take 10 classes a day with no
lunch so that's not it either.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teachers? Stuy gets its teachers the same way as other public
schools and just like other public schools they have some terrific
teachers and some absolute disasters. Stuy also gets a slice of a
particular class of teacher that starts their career at Stuy, never
learns to teach because the kids figure it out but thinks they're gods
gift to teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, no, it's not the teachers, at least not on the whole.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what does Stuy do?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It collects talent and this is the same thing that the other magnet
schools and the elite private schools do as well. Get a bunch of
bright, hard working, motivated kids together and good things
happen. It gets high achieving students from a combination of entrance
exam, reputation, and location &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-prestigious-competitons-and-high-schools/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not arguing against this – I think there is a need for public
magnet schools like Stuy but I think it's important to recognize that
this is a major contributor to competition results and doesn't
necessarily say anything about the school in terms of leadership or
instruction.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's similar to a college coach who gets the best recruits. Are they
really a great coach? Can they develop talent or are they just getting
the best talent and getting out of the way. Who's the better coach?
The one who gets all the 5 star recruits every years and frequently
wins it all or the coach who gets 3 star recruits, doesn't win as much
but develops those 3 stars to a point where they can compete against the 5 star
programs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's the starting point but then there's the targeting of the top
prospects. Stuy had a run of finalists during the early 2000s. At the
time, a friend of mine ran the math research program. His strategy? He
would scour the school for the kids most likely to win the
competition, get those kids into his class, and hook them  up with
professors with the most promising project potential. It worked
more often than not. Contrast that to what I did when I ran our CS
research program. I didn't take the program seriously for a variety of
reasons but my job was to give EVERY kid in my class the opportunity
to explore some aspect of CS. I had a few semi-finalists which is
neither here nor there but never the stream of winners that my friend
had.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looking back to Stuy's earlier success, we had a Bio Chair who ran a
similar program. I knew people in that program from when I was a
student. The top talent was recruited and nurtured, the rest, pretty
much ignored. Makes a school look good but not really the hallmark of
a great school
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Other schools had a similar strategy. Back in the '80s Cardozo - a
neighborhood high school in Bayside Queens had a great run of
Westinghouse results but that's because the science chair at the time
had a similar program - rope in the top talent early (sophomore year)
and nurture them. After a while the school got a reputation and would
then attract more "science talent."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Stuy's had a falloff in finalists in recent years and I believe that's
due to not having anyone focusing on recruiting kids specifically for
results. Personally, I think this is a good thing but others
disagree. A school with one finalist is perceived to be better than a
school that gives a great research experience to every student but
produces no finalists. In recent years, there's been talk of "what
can we do to get more winners again." I think that's a shame, the
conversation should always be "what can we do to improve the
educational experience we offer all of our students."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
None of this is to take away from any of the winners of  any of these
competitions. All the finalists and winners I've known have been
exceptional intellects and top people in their fields. This is just a
commentary on what role a school does, should, and shouldn't play.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my early years at Stuy, I worked with our top kids on CS
competitions, The kids would place very well in the USACO competitions
throughout the year. One year we entered the ACSL and I realized that
I had a choice - focus on the top handful of kids to make a winning
team that could compete for the title or focus on all the kids but not
expect that great single result. I realized that the top kids
would probably be alright without that extra attention. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I still think I did right by those kids but that realization also led
me to design my intro class, hack required CS into Stuy and probably
end up positively affecting far more students than if I just focused
on the top percent of a percent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-prestigious-competitons-and-high-schools/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;That said, students have also been
drawn to Stuy for the CS program which is fairly unique and also for a
couple of specific math teachers.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>competitions</category><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-prestigious-competitons-and-high-schools/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Mar 2018 19:49:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sigcse2018 Making theory more acccesible</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-theory/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf2eb3b3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgf2eb3b3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgf2eb3b3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up from SIGCSE 2018 is John MacCormick's session on
&lt;a href="https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3159557"&gt;Strategies for Baing the CS Theory Course on Non-decision Problems&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
MacCormicks's stance is that CS theory  is tough the first time around
and using non-decision problems is a viable approach to make theory
more accessible to beginners. As MacCormick said in his paper:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
… a decision problem may ask the yes/no question, "Does this graph
have a Hamilton cycle?" The corresponding non-decision problem is,
"Please give me a Hamilton cycle of this graph if it has one."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This leads to writing programs to explore concepts in CS theory rather
than just living in the world of proof. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
MacCormick goes on to say that:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For this audience, the key advantage of non-decision problems
is that they are more realistic: they match the previous programming
and algorithms experience of undergraduates more closely.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I love the idea. Writing a program can make an abstract problem more
concrete and can lead to better understanding for those of us who are
less math inclined.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My next thought was that this shouldn't just be a change implemented
in theory courses. Some of these ideas should move down to more
introductory CS classes. Not the hardcore stuff but light
introductions to the topics so that we can layer the learning. If we
introduce some of these concepts in CS 1 classes then when they get to
the theory class it won't be the students first rodeo.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've had success with this when teaching recursion early. I've also
done it with other concepts. When we teach the Towers of Hanoi, yes,
it's a nice recursion problem but really it's to get the students
thinking about run time and a bit of proof. likewise, when we do a
maze solver in NetLogo we're alluding to dynamic programming, search,
and path finding.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't have too much more to say on this topic right now. I'm not
enough of a theory guy to sensibly design these experiences. The good
news is that MacCormick has written an soon to be released &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/What-Can-Computed-Practical-Computation/dp/0691170665/ref=asap_bc?ie=UTF8"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; on the subject. I
signed up for a reviewer copy at SIGCSE and look forward to receiving
a copy. Once I do I hope to be able to find some gems that I can work
into CS 1 experiences.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>theory</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-theory/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2018 23:21:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How my views on education research were shaped</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/practitioners-and-researchers/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb4aede6" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgb4aede6"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgb4aede6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After reading a couple of comments on my &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-code-tracing/"&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; where I talked a
bit about practitioners vs researchers I thought I'd expand and
expound a bit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While there are education researchers that I very much respect,
overall, I'm skeptical of education research. Note
that I'm not talking specifically about CS Ed research but rather
education research in general.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's go back to the beginning. I entered teaching from
industry. Goldman Sachs to be specific. I started in a shortage area -
math and barely had the credentials to do so. The transcript evaluator
at the DOE counted my Algorithms and Numerical Methods courses as Math
courses to get me over the credit hump.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had zero ed courses under my belt and was thrown into the
fire. Fortunately, I landed in a school, Seward Park High School, with
a very supportive faculty. I wouldn't have survived my first year
without Mike G, Bruce B, Jonathan G, and many others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then, I had to start taking education credits to make my license
permanent. Some classes were taught by professors some by
adjuncts. The adjuncts were invariably experienced teachers and the
professors were research faculty. In many classes, I had to read the
latest research. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I found that what "the research" told us to do was contrary to what
some of the best teachers did in practice. I kept hearing about the
"right" way to teach but it frequently didn't jive with reality. When
the true way worked, circumstances were right and the technique
aligned with the teacher's natural tendencies. When it didn't, why
not? Many reasons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lack of prep time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;too many students (per class, per day, per term)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;different populations than the one researched&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;factors the researcher didn't include (and there are tons of them)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teachers with different personalities and skill sets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and each of the above points opens up to scores of specifics. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
This theme continued throughout my career. I'd ask teachers in other
subject areas about the current state of the art research. What was
the current trends in their fields. Generally the best teachers would
summarize what was going on and then either say that it didn't work
for them or that if it did, they didn't take it seriously because in
five or ten years "the research" would tell them to do something
different and then they would all of a sudden be bad teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was another point. The right way to do it has changed over and
over during my career.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then there's the reproducibility problem. Apparently it's pretty bad
in education research. I mentioned in my &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-code-tracing"&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt; that when a
researched does it once on a small group it's research but when a
teacher did it over and over it's an anecdote.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I was young I would listen to a master teacher tell me about how
he set up some experience - the one I'm remembering now is an
experiential / discovery lesson on triangle geometry. He'd talk about
all the hard work that went into prepping his class for this type of
lesson as well as the prep time for the lesson itself. He told me how
he did it four years ago and it was great but then the year after it
fell flat and how he changed it for the next year. How it worked in
third period but not seventh and why he thought it played out the way
it did. That's a lot more reproduction than most 'research' actually
gets and this is what a master teacher does all the time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, I got tired of hearing how to do it by people who don't
actually have to. If you're going to talk the talk, you should walk
the walk. As a side, this problem is really bad with "thought leaders."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All this sounds like I'm really down on education research or at least
the overarching system. I probably am but there are many education
researchers doing great work and I respect them immensely.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They know they don't have a magic bullet:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is what I tried with this population at this time and this is
what happened. You might want to try it or a variation on it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's a far cry from "here's how to teach"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The researchers who acknowledge that their experience as college
researchers or even teaching faculty are different from a k12 teacher
and that no matter how hard they try to work out all the variables
they can only ever account for a tiny fraction of them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The key is that they're adding another drop into the bucket of
knowledge. Over time it adds up. I have great respect for everyone
doing this. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These researchers have to keep prodding us teachers to re-evaluate our
practice and then either take or incorporate the research or reject it
after determining if it would be good or not for our population. At
the same time, it's up to practitioners to keep pushing back against
magic bullet research and the one true way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We all have a role to play in this game.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>research</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/practitioners-and-researchers/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2018 23:41:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fixing the Absent Teacher Reserve (ATR) situation</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/atrs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd1a1cac" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd1a1cac"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd1a1cac"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the New York City department of education a recurring hot topic is
the Absent Teacher Reserve or ATR pool. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A teacher or administrator in the ATR pool is a licensed, most likely
tenured teacher not assigned permanently to a school. Each year these
educators get shuttled from school to school and denied a chance to
actually settle in a position.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The ATR pool was created under the Bloomberg administration. Prior to
that, when there was an opening school transfers were basically
seniority based and when school had too many teachers the least senior
was excessed or basically out of a job until a school with an opening
could be found. The Bloomberg plan allowed teachers to use criteria
other than seniority for transfers but so as not to violate the
contract agreed to by both parties, teachers who were excessed, as
they might not be least senior, were kept on as employees and put in
the pool.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
ATR's would rotate from school to school. Sometimes for a couple of
week but more recently for a year at a time. When at a school for only
a couple of weeks they could only be used as subs or for grunt work
but even when there for a year they're treated like second class
citizens.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The ATR pool grew in size when the Bloomberg/Klein DOE went on the war
path, set schools up to fail and closed them left and right. If you
had the bad luck being at a close out school when it closed then, hello
ATR pool.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the years, the press, ed reformers and politicians have unfairly
bashed this group of educators. They've falsely claimed that these are
criminal teachers or unsatisfactory teachers. That's a blatant
lie. Teachers up on charges are removed from schools and await a
hearing in another draconian process set up to violate teacher's
rights. If a teacher is ultimately found guilty, they are disciplined
or fired. If exonerated, they're returned to their schools. In any
case they're not ATRs. Teachers that are repeatedly found to be
unsatisfactory are likewise removed (although the process here is
ridiculous and unfair as well).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
ATRs like any pool of teachers run the gamut. Some are great, some are
poor, many will fall in between. All are stigmatized and treated like
damaged goods.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
People ask, how can a good teacher get into the ATR pool? As I said,
be at a closeout school. In the year before I was able to bring my friend
and former colleague JonAlf over to Stuy, he was at Brandeis High
School - a
closeout school. I tried to bring him over that year but his principal
wouldn't release him. Had I not been successful in bringing him over
the following year he might very well have ended up in the ATR pool
and he's one of the best teachers I know. What about the teacher that
doesn't want to abandon those kids that the DOE abandoned when they
decided to close the school. That martyr teacher surely ends up in the
ATR pool but that's the type of dedicated teacher every principal
should want.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So now we have a bunch of stigmatized teachers looking for work in a
system that won't give them a chance. Not only due to them being
considered "damaged goods" but also because they're expensive to
hire. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When a school gets an ATR to them, it's free - the cost isn't added to
their budget - they keep them as extra manpower for the year and then
throw them out with the trash. At times, they get some credit for
keeping them a second year and even beyond they can get rid of them
whenever they want. Great way to bust the contract.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A clear example of this is Stuy's  current math chair. He's an ATR
Assistant Principal. They got him for free for the first year and I
believe at a 50% discount for the second and even now they can dump
him whenever they want. This is rubbish – he's either good enough for
the position or he's not. If he is, he should be given the job for
real and if he isn't then what is he still doing there. I'm not making
any value judgment on him or the department but it's either one or the
other.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, a big reason for this ATR mess is about budgets and money. The
problem is that it's a big lie. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The DOE pretends the we have a situation like this:
&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/atr1.png" alt="atr1.png" align="center" height="250"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The DOE has money and schools have money. The schools pay for their
teachers, supplies, and everything else but the ATRS are paid for by
the DOE. Of course this isn't the case. The truth is that the DOE pays
for everything:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/atr2.png" alt="atr2.png" align="center" height="250"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
ALL the money comes from the DOE.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the past the DOE has come up with poorly conceived and poorly
received plans on how to deal with the ATR situation but it's really
quite simple.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Start by recognizing that ALL the money comes from the DOE. Once you
do that you can address the problem:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assign the ATR to a school&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the school likes the ATR and the ATR likes the school, they keep
them and the DOE picks up the tab or rather adjusts the schools
budget to compensate. The DOE will continue to do so until a real
opening occurs at the school in the ATR's area at which point the
ATR fills the position officially and the budget is readjusted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the school or ATR don't like each other the ATR gets rotated,
however you create a 3 strikes (or maybe 2 or 4 or some number)
rule.
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the school keeps sending away ATRs semester after semester hit
them with a penalty or force an ATR placement when they have an
opening (assuming the ATR is amenable).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the ATR keeps declining positions after a set number of
schools force the placement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's it. Simple and solves the problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/atrs/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 13:01:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New York State moving forward with CS Teacher Certification</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/NY-CS-Certificate/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd92872d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd92872d"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd92872d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last April I woke up early and trekked up to Albany along with a few
of my Hunter College colleagues to share our thoughts on K12 Computer
Science teacher certification with the Board of Regents. We gave a
presentation to the Regents Higher Education Committee and afterwards
had a chance to talk with some of the Regents as well as other members
of the New York State Department of Education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I left feeling that our proposals were well received and I think
everyone present - both the Hunter and NYSED contingents hoped that
things would move forward on this important issue.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward to today, December 8, 2017. I was up at the crack
of dawn. Driving in the dark in the snow from NYC to Albany to once
again attend a Board of Regents Higher Education Committee
meeting. This time, the agenda item was:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Proposed Amendments to Part 30 of the Regents Rules and Section 52.21
and Part 80 the Regulations of the Commissioner of Education Relating
to a New Certification Area and Tenure Area for Computer Science 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No discussion or debate this time around just the proposal. If I
understand the process correctly, this should come up again at the
March meeting at which point it will be voted on. If approved, it
looks like we'll have a pathway towards certification for CS teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I haven't had a chance to dive into the details but at the meeting a
few key points came up:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As the proposal indicates this will be a subject area in which a
teacher can be certified and be awarded tenure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be a traditional pathway for new teachers - Bachelors /
Masters degree&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an alternative pathway for people entering from the
workforce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an extension for teachers with another license so they
won't have to give up tenure in their current license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an "individual evaluation" pathway which sounds to me
like it could catch people who fall through the cracks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There looks to be a sensible ramp up period - until September 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's a grandfathering provision that looks to last 10 years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This sounds like a smart sensible plan. Multiple pathways, shallow
ramp up and provisions to protect existing teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, the devil is in the details. What's an approved program?
Can a grandfathered teacher teach all CS classes or just intro ones?
etc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I said, I haven't had a chance to dive into the details yet but
this is very exciting.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Prior to the meeting I was chatting with a few other people
attending. One, a &lt;a href="http://www.uft.org/"&gt;UFT&lt;/a&gt; representative was very excited about the
prospect. Another contingent, a group from &lt;a href="https://www.nysut.org/"&gt;NYSUT&lt;/a&gt; was very much against
a new certification area. Their position was that this would create a
teacher shortage because no one would have a CS license and no one
would get one due to the difference in salary between teaching and the
tech industry. I've already written on how I feel that this is a &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry"&gt;red
herring&lt;/a&gt;. What shocked me though was their feeling that "we already
have many non-CS teachers effectively teaching CS across the
state. They're doing a great job and don't need any additional content
or pedagogical knowledge." I think they're wrong and I also think that
when we as a community talk about how our summer professional
development is all that's needed, we undercut CS education and
the teaching profession as a whole.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any event this was a big step for New York. I tried to individually
thank as many of the participants as I could for helping shepherd this
along but could only speak to a few so I'll just give a blanket thank
you here to the NY State Board of Regents, Board of Education and
State Education department.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>certification</category><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/NY-CS-Certificate/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 23:57:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Professional Development beyond Scratch</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/election-day-pd-2017/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org69fe332" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org69fe332"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org69fe332"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today was Election Day. One of the few days each year when students
stay home and teachers spend all day attending what is generously
known as professional development.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Years ago I was in a room with a few colleagues when my friend Dave -
one of the best math teachers I know said "you know, every time we
have a PD day in NJ and my wife and I have to scramble to take care of
the kids I get a little annoyed but then think I shouldn't get annoyed
since they're spending the day doing all sorts of valuable PD." He
then said "but then I realize that their PD is probably about as
useful as our PD and I get really angry."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There you have it. This is not to say that there is no good PD but it
seems that the professional development opportunities provided by our
schools have over the years ranged from useless to insulting with
maybe a small bright spot here and there. Historically it's been worse
for CS teachers because we get lumped in with math teachers and have
to spend the day learning about tools and techniques we'll never use
or discussing curricula we never teach.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, when I spoke to JonAlf about rescuing the Stuy teachers for the
day and hosting them at Hunter, he and the other CS teachers were
pretty excited. It wasn't as though I had the magic PD answer but I
was going to provide a space and we'd figure out together what would
be productive and valuable for them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As it turns out, I've been spending a good amount of time these past
few weeks visiting high schools to talk about Hunter CS and when I was
at Bronx Science the topic of Election Day PD came up and I thought
that it would be nice to get the Bronx Science and Stuy teachers
together. After thinking about it more, I recalled that there were few
good PD opportunities for CS teachers who taught advanced classes as
opposed to all the CS PD floating around these days at more of a
beginner level.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I thought that we could change this. In the end, I hosted PD today and
had teachers from Stuyvesant, Bronx Science, Brooklyn Tech, and the
Manhattan Hunter Science High School in attendance. I invited teachers
from a few more schools but in the end we had those four schools and
seventeen teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The original agenda was:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;09:00 - 10:00 : Each school describes it's program and courses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:00 - 11:00 : An intro to Git and GitHub for the classroom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:00 - 11:45 : Sharing neat lessons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:45 - 12:00 : Presentation by &lt;a href="http://chicktech.org"&gt;ChickTech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12:00 - 01:00 : Lunch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;01:00 - End   : Small group lesson and curriculum work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Oh boy did I mess up on the timing. The description and
discussion of school programs took all morning. It was interesting to
hear how each school's program evolved and how they fit into the
school's culture. Brooklyn Tech, for instance is a school where
students declare majors. This has a big impact on what classes kids
have to take and are able to take. This is very different from Stuy or
Science where kids programs are more open ended or MHSHS which is a
much smaller school and has restrictions related to size. It was also
interesting to note Brooklyn Tech's decision to have every student
take APCS-P. Interesting because Brooklyn Tech is one of the country's
largest high schools and most of them should have done well on the
exam. That gave NYC around 1,400 passing AP scores in one shot. On
the other hand none of the other schools present today offered APCS-P
but did have their own intro CS class that students took prior to
APCS-A.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We finished the morning with a visit by Heather from
&lt;a href="http://chicktech.org"&gt;ChickTech&lt;/a&gt;. ChickTech is a non-profit dedicated to retaining women in
Tech. It works with both girls in K12 and also those in industry. My
hope was to get a conversation started and see if there were some
potential avenues of partnership between the organization and the
schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After lunch, the group decided that we should do the Git/GitHub
workshop and JonAlf obliged.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Overall I think the day was a success. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My hope is that today's attendees can form a core group of CS teachers
who teach more advanced courses and we can form something of a support
group for each other. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I plan to try to facilitate future meetings and hopefully we'll be
able to attract more teachers to our group.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All in all I'm very happy with how the day went.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>pd</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/election-day-pd-2017/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 23:08:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>There's always something to learn (from your students)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/when-they-change-the-script/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org2ab85af" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org2ab85af"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org2ab85af"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One thing I've learned from teaching is that there's always something
new to learn. For the kids, yes, but I'm talking about for the
teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other day, I taught a lesson I've taught many times. Find the mode
of a data set. That's the problem that they solve but the lesson is
really about run time complexity, hidden complexity and using data
structures in alternate ways.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I blogged about this &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-03-23-Who_won_the_election-Quadratic_to_Linear_Time.md"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; so you can get an earlier take there
although the code isn't formatted correctly due to blog conversions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As with the last time, the students  had already written code to find
the largest value in a list and also to find the frequency of an item
in a list.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;build_list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;low&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;high&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;randrange&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;low&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;high&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;get_max_value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;max_index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;max_val&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;enumerate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;max_val&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class="n"&gt;max_index&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class="n"&gt;max_val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;max_val&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;get_freq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;requested_val&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;requested_val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class="n"&gt;count&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;count&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They had to write mode prior to the class. In the past, students would
generally come up with something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;get_mode_1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;mode_val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;mode_freq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;get_freq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;mode_val&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;enumerate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;get_freq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mode_freq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class="n"&gt;mode_freq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class="n"&gt;mode_val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mode_val&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;build_list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;m&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;get_mode_1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They'd use their existing knowledge and the 'find the largest' idiom
to find the mode by:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;find the frequency of the first item and assume it's the mode so far&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for each item in the list
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;find the frequency of that idem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if it occurs more than the mode so far then it becomes the new
mode so far&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's a lot of good in this solution. The kids incrementally develop
a solution, they use and exctend code and concepts they already know
and understand and it's clear and understandable.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We would then run the code on larger and larger data sets and notice
that it gets slow pretty quickly. This leads to an informal discussion
of run time and the fact that there's hidden complexity – the call to
&lt;code&gt;freq&lt;/code&gt; in the main loop introduces a linear component so we have a
loop within a loop and an N&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; routine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The big takeaway is get a feel for run time and to be aware of hidden
complexity. We then move to a linear solution by using a list as
buckets. You can read more about that in the &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-03-23-Who_won_the_election-Quadratic_to_Linear_Time.md"&gt;original post&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What was interesting this time around was that most of the kids came
up with a solution more like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;get_mode_2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;freqs&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;item&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;get_freq&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class="n"&gt;freqs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;mode_count&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;freqs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;mode_value&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;enumerate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;freqs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
       &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mode_count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	   &lt;span class="n"&gt;mode_count&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;
	   &lt;span class="n"&gt;mode_value&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mode_value&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;build_list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;m&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;get_mode_2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;m&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Instead of calculating the frequency inside the loop they made a list
of frequencies. &lt;code&gt;freq[0]&lt;/code&gt; had the frequency of &lt;code&gt;l[0]&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;freq[1]&lt;/code&gt; the
frequency of &lt;code&gt;l[1]&lt;/code&gt; etc. They then loop through that &lt;code&gt;freq&lt;/code&gt; list to
find the largest element and that's the index of the mode value in the
original list.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's functionally the same as the first solution but in some ways it's
very different. They built the data set they needed ahead of time
instead of calculating the data on the fly and they used the concept
of parallel lists.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I like the solution and it didn't prevent us from getting to the run
time stuff but this did give me something to think about. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why did this class led them largely to a different solution than the
classes I've taught in the class. There are a lot of things to ponder
since it's a college class that meets twice a week with kids from a
range of backgrounds (CS and otherwise) vs a high school class that
meets 5 days a week and the kids all had the same in class experience
prior to this lesson. Did I do something differently before hand? Some
assignments? Something I modeled?  I'm not sure but it's something I'm
going to ponder.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It will interesting to see if this was a one shot deal and my current
class will solve problems as I predict moving forward or if I'm going
to get to see a lot of new things.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>lessons</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/when-they-change-the-script/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 15:41:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A test result is just a test result</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org49bb251" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org49bb251"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org49bb251"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This past weekend was &lt;a href="http://catskillsconf.com"&gt;Catskillsconf&lt;/a&gt; - my favorite event of the
year. I spent the weekend up in Ulster County with a bunch of my
students. some great friends old and new, and Devorah. It was a great
weekend but I was mostly offline.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a result I missed a rather heated discussion in the CS Ed Facebook
groups. The debate was over whether or not Strong AP CSP exam results
are indicative of a good curriculum or good professional development (PD).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc62d62f" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc62d62f"&gt;TL;DR - NO!!!!!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc62d62f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Further, anyone who thinks that a set of exam results can tell you
that a particular PD sequence or curriculum is good shouldn't be
allowed to call themselves a teacher and I don't want them anywhere
near my kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I guess that language is strong, even for me but it's true.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tests are designed to assess students and many tests don't even do
that well. They shouldn't be used to measure something further
removed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The last time this idea made its rounds was using student test results
for teacher evaluation. They do that in NY. A judge called the
practice "capricious" and "arbitrary." My friend and former
colleague Gary Rubinstein showed a year or so ago that standardized
test scores varied enough from year to year so as to make the ratings
useless &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Using test scores to say a PD sequence is good? What if that PD
focused on test prep? What if it did nothing in particular? When I was
at Stuy and when I was at Seward Park the Calc teachers' students had
great AP results. I can tell you that none of those teachers had any
quality PD specific to AP Calc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Curriculum? My mentor and friend Danny Jaye told me many times - "A
great teacher can save a class from a  horrible curriculum but a great
curriculum will do nothing for a class with a horrible teacher." He
was right. Again, what if the curriculum encourages test prep. What if
pressure on the teacher encourages them to focus on test prep
regardless of curriculum or PD (see my recent &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/standards-who-for"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
An AP test measures one thing - how well the student did on the AP
test. There are so many variables that go into a class:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it first period at 8:00am?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it the last class of the day?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it before lunch or right afterwards?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What about right after Gym.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's the mix of students - every class is different&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the teacher teaching the subject once a day? Two times? Five
times?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How large is the class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many other classes are the kids taking?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The list goes on and on. There are so many contributing factors that
you just can't say "Good test results = good curriculum" or "good test
results = good PD."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Want to know if a curriculum is good - have experienced teachers who
know their subject run it a few times through and ask them. Same for
PD.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teachers know education a lot better than test makers, curriculum
developers and PD providers. How about listening to them for a change?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;sorry, I just got back from the weekend trip and am too tired
to find the link. You can go to his site and search and while you're
there, there's lots of good stuff to read.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>assessment</category><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 00:17:21 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>