<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about education)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/education.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2018 09:35:03 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Giving control of NYC's specialized schools to a political appointee</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat-part2/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org0e4b023" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0e4b023"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0e4b023"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I shared my thoughts on Bill de Blasio's plans to "fix" the
selection criteria for New York City's specialized high schools. If
you haven't read the post, you can find it &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was going to get back to CS and CS Ed related blogging today but
there's more to the story.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In spite of what BdB stated, it's not enough for him to switch to another
measure - the middle school state exam along with some modifiers. This
is about ending the exam altogether and not replacing it with anything
better. Here's a link to information on the proposed legislation for
&lt;a href="https://legiscan.com/NY/bill/A10427/2017"&gt;New York Assembly Bill 10427&lt;/a&gt; including links to the actual text.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's a lot of beurobabble but the end game is to basically allow
the chancellor (not sure if this means city or state) to do whatever
they want.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here are some of the key points:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seats would ultimately go to the top 5 to 7 percent of each middle school's
class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These students would have to also be classified in the top 25% city wide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top is defined by a composite score of multiple measures as
determined by the chancellor which means anything goes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remaining seats will be filled by
lottery of all students with a 3.7 GPA or greater.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's not clear how the students would be allocated to each of the
specialized schools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what does this all mean? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Multiple measures could mean the state test + average. It could mean
average + recommendation. It could be shoe size + favorite color. The
chancellor also decides how to weight these multiple measures. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This means that the politicians can do whatever they want to paint any
picture they want regardless of how their ideological and political
games hurt kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Any teacher, in fact, any rational adult  will tell you that middle
schools are not interchangeable. The top students at one middle school
are typically not at the same level as top students at another
one. I'm sure you can cluster middle schools in terms of the students
they graduate, what the students know and can do and the clusters will
likely fall on economic lines. This is the problem that BdB should be
addressing not how to rig the specialized school admissions stats. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even if this is done right, you're assuming an even distribution of
top gifted students across all the middle schools. If one school has
higher concentration of gifted students, they're out of luck. The end
result is that if you attend an SP or other gifted program for eighth
grade you'll likely be locked out of the specialized schools. What if
a particular middle school is attractive to all of our top math team
talent? Only a couple will get in to the specialized schools under the
new system since each school is allocated a fixed number of slots. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I guess this does make sense if you don't believe in gifted students
or gifted education but then why not just get rid of the specialized
schools to begin with rather than playing these games. This "solution"
will result in parents having to decide - do I send my kids to the
gifted middle school program and hurt their chances to get into a
specialized high school or do I try to find the lowest performing
school I can find and have my kid stand out. This is pretty messed up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, though, you have to remember that any change to
the process can help one group and hurt another. Stuy, for example has
46% of it's students on free or reduced lunch and is about 70%
Asian. If in the new system you're increasing the percent population
of an under represented group, you're likely reducing the percentage
of Asian students. So, you're creating opportunities for a number of as of yet
undetermined students (who might not be properly prepared for the
experience) at the expense of economically disadvantaged Asian
students who have proven to be prepared for the experience. Wouldn't
a better solution be to fix the opportunities presented at the middle
schools rather than rig the system of high school acceptance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Going further, a response on another blog noted that BdB probably
refused to do anything with the admissions criteria of the non big
three because they all had numbers that he would consider more
diverse. The commenter provided the Black / Latino percentages, I added the
free and reduced lunch numbers:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="border" border-spacing="10px"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;School&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Percent Black / Latino&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Free / Reduced Lunch&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Brooklyn Latin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;28%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;61%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSMSE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;26%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;46%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSAS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;17%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;25%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Queens Sci&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;12%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;64%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All the more reason to run some tests or analysis there. Of course, if
you look further you'll note that HSAS only has 25% of its students on
free or reduced lunch so is it really doing better than Stuy or Sci
with ~45% low income students  each  or Brooklyn Tech which supports
62% or are we to say that there's low income and then there's the
right low income?
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Certainly the education system needs work but the proposed legislation
is not a solution. It's taking a flawed but objective measure and
replacing it with essentially chancellor's discretion. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If the legislation passes, by the year 2022 we will have admissions to
what used to be some of the nations finest high schools determined by
a political appointee rather than an objective test.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a shame. It was very important to my wife and me to have our kids
go to public schools and I was very happy to have been able to
navigate the system with them from first grade through high school
graduation with only a few bumps along the way. With this nonsense
from the political left and the privatization push from the political
right (or actually both sides) pretty soon there will be nothing left.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>gifted</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat-part2/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 12:00:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Changing Admissions to the NYC Specialized High Schools</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org5647c3a" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org5647c3a"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org5647c3a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, Bill de Blasio, the current Mayor of New York City outlined
how he would "fix" our specialized schools. The schools he was
referring to were the "big three" of Stuyvesant, Bronx Science, and
Brooklyn Tech and then five additional schools - The High School  for
Math Science and Engineering at CCNY, The High School for American
Studies at Lehman, Brooklyn Latin, The Queens Arts and Science High
School at
York College, and Staten Island Tech.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All use a single SAT style test, the SHSAT, for admission. The Big Three are
locked into that system unless there are changes made by the state
legislature. The Mayor can make changes to the admissions criteria of
the other five on his own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem, as stated by Chalkbeat writers Alex Zimmerman and  Monica
Disare is that: 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The city’s specialized high schools — considered some of the crown
jewels of New York City’s education system — accept students based on
a single test score. Over the last decade, they have come under fire
for offering admissions to few students of color: While two-thirds of
city students are black or Hispanic, only about 10 percent of
admissions offers to those schools go to black or Hispanic students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I normally don't write about things like this but given my history at
and with Stuyvesant I thought I should.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Before getting started, my biases - I believe in public schools, not
charters, I also believe that a system should have gifted programs and
magnet schools and also a mix of large comprehensive schools and
smaller niche ones. Additionally, while I do believe in gifted
programs I'm not sure at what point it makes sense to start offering
them. When we were looking at elementary schools for our own kids we
opted for a neighborhood public school rather than applying to the
district gifted program as we felt it offered a better overall
education. On the other hand, had our kids not made Stuyvesant, I'm
not sure what we would have done. Part of that was due to the fact
that the Bloomberg administration destroyed just about all the large
comprehensive schools so, other than that large test schools and
LaGuardia, good luck finding a school that was strong in the
humanities, sciences and offered a robust music program. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org7a9b65e" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org7a9b65e"&gt;The overall picture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org7a9b65e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For reference, here are &lt;a href="http://www.theschoolboards.com/showthread.php/4324-Specialized-High-School-SHSAT-Cutoff-Scores-for-2018"&gt;unofficial cutoff scores&lt;/a&gt; for the specialized
schools from 2018 along with the NY State data on free and reduced
lunch for 2017. Note that there's overlap between the schools. I
separated out SI Tech since geography probably affects it's numbers
more than the other schools and I separated the big three from the
remaining four because I think the three are all substantially larger. The
free and reduced lunch percent is important because I believe an
entire school qualifies for Title I funding if the number's
over 40 so while these schools are not populated entirely by low
income students, all but HSAS has a substantial number and there's a
chance, some say a good one that at best BdB's plans will merely
shuffle which low income kids get in rather than actually solving the
root problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="border" border-spacing="10px"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;School&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Lowest Score admitted&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;High Score&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Pct free or reduced lunch&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Stuyvesant&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;559&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;698&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;46&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Bronx Science&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;518&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;637&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;45&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Brooklyn Tech&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;493&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;668&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;62&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSMSE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;516&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;616&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;46&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSAS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;516&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;633&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Brooklyn Latin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;482&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;555&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;61&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Queens Sci&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;538&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;542&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;64&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;SI Tech&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;519&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;660&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf0f6f49" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgf0f6f49"&gt;The plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgf0f6f49"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf35161e" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgf35161e"&gt;Part 1 - test prep&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgf35161e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There's idea here is that test prep is rampant for SHSAT and that the
test can be gamed. This may or may not be true but if it is then it's
safe to assume that a lot of low income kids are doing test
prep either by prioritizing test prep programs in family budgets,
working off of an SHSAT test prep book or by attending a middle school
that has some form of prep. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There has long been a program on the books called "The Discovery
Program" which has a free city run test prep component and also a
summer component. The summer component is for low income students who
score within "a few points" of the school in question's cutoff
score. At the end of the summer, I believe the students retest and in
general make the school in question.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;This program is a good thing and should be reinstated&lt;/b&gt; but I don't
know if it will result in the changes that BdB is looking for. More
likely Stuy will get its discovery kids from Science and Science from
Tech. As there are already many low income students at all of the
schools there's no indication that this would increase the number of
under represented groups which is BdB's goal. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's also worth noting that there's a sizable chunk of Brooklyn Tech
students that don't perform particularly well on regents exams.
Everyone knows I'm not a fan of standardized tests and I don't
believe that students that score a "few points" lower on the SHSAT are
any less qualified to be in a specialized school but at the lowest
performing end of these schools, one has to ask how specialized is it
really?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb920711" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgb920711"&gt;Part 2 - use state test scores instead of the SHSAT&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgb920711"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This &lt;b&gt;could be&lt;/b&gt; a &lt;b&gt;very&lt;/b&gt; good thing with one major caveat. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Twenty one middle schools produce over half the students that
ultimately are accepted to the specialized schools. For the rest,
there are a few reasons
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many students don't take the SHSAT.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There have been stories of schools steering kids away from the
specialized schools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's no culture in those schools of striving for specialized
school acceptance or attendance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The academic programs at those schools don't prepare students for
the SHSAT exam for reasons that we're not going to delve into here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All students already take the NY State middle school Math and English
exams. Yes, it would further raise the stakes for those exams but it
would ensure that the specialized schools are on the map for everyone, 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The big question here is "do the current state exams cover enough
material in enough depth to select and differentiate for gifted
programs." I don't know the answer to this question. If they don't
then using state test scores will be a disaster. If they do, then they
could be a suitable alternative.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org0607368" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org0607368"&gt;Part 3 - admissions from every middle school&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0607368"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is the third part of BdB's proposal - guarantee admissions to the
top 10% of students at every middle school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This could be a real disaster either for the students or for the
schools. There's no question that students coming out of different
middle schools are at different levels of preparedness for the
specialized schools. Arguably the most obvious difference is that some
middle schools offer algebra and others don't. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For better or worse, the specialized school's curricula, classes, and
overall programs have evolved hand in hand with the exam. If you all
of a sudden end up placing a large number of students with a
different and arguable weaker academic profile into these schools one
of two things will happen. Either the students will struggle immensely
or the school will have to lower its standards. There's no two ways
about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you set standards for academic preparedness for the specialized
schools either by making a hard cutoff on an exam score be it state or
SHSAT and then spread those acceptances across all the schools maybe
it could work. If not, you're setting up students with high grades at
schools with weak programs up for failure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another problem is what to do with non-public school students -
private schools, charters which take public money but act as private
schools, parochial, and home school students. Where do they fall in to
this equation?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org33995ae" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org33995ae"&gt;Is one measure bad?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org33995ae"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So there you have my thoughts on BdB's specific proposals but I also
want to address his contention that a single measure is bad and makes
the comparison to colleges where they by and large use multiple
measures. This is a ridiculous comparison. Yes, colleges look at
multiple measures but after watching decades of Stuy students go off
to college, it's clear to me that the process is by no means fair or
consistent. Elite schools can easily game their acceptances and
they still can have 100% of their applicants with off the charts SAT
scores. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A single test might not be ideal but it can only be gamed by test prep
and test prep can be as cheap as buying a test prep book.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As to other measures that come up from time to time - interviews,
portfolios, essays - who does that help? The low income kid or the
well to do one?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're going to add another measure for admission it has to be
something that can't be gamed or politically influenced,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd4640da" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd4640da"&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd4640da"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Should the city address the fact that there are groups that are under
represented at the specialized schools? Certainly, or rather, the city
should address deficiencies in opportunities that are like the causes
of this under representation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Should the city be doing things differently? Also yes. Here are some
thoughts on what the city can and should be doing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org9ac1e5e" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org9ac1e5e"&gt;Do the experiments in the non-big three.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org9ac1e5e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are five specialized schools that aren't covered by state
legislation. Why not run your experiments there. You've got  the big
three as a control group and what's more if you look at the
"acceptance score windows" in the table above, you'll see that there's
enough overlap that you can probably get some real data out of these
experiments.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why not change the admissions criteria for one or two of them and see
how it goes before jumping in whole hog. Figure out if anything works first.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbb91a4a" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgbb91a4a"&gt;Check existing data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgbb91a4a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We've got SHSAT results and State Test score results along with
student grades for years. Why not study correlations between
them. Rather than making a specious claim about middle school grades
in NYC Public Schools vs state tests vs the SHSAT, run the
numbers. Take a look at student high school performance based on these
predictions. This shouldn't be guess work and city should have the
data to do better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org6b83d00" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org6b83d00"&gt;Fix the middle schools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org6b83d00"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This one is more pie in the sky because no politician really wants to
take this one but you've got to look at what's going on in the middle
schools and why. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I tweeted this the other day:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;would love to see this experiment - take the entire staff / faculty / admin of one of the 20 or so middle schools that are the primary feeders to the spec schls and swap them with another middle school and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;— Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/1003074760786501632?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;June 3, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The truth is that if you did this, the high performing school would
probably continue to be high performing and the low performing one
would still struggle. There's only so much a teacher can do. A school
with a disadvantaged population needs the resources to succeed - lower
class sizes for a start. Add wraparound services, extensive after
school and weekend opportunities - make the schools a part of the
community and maybe we can get somewhere.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another question relating to our schools in general is to look at
attrition rates to private schools - how many students in our under
represented groups are being siphoned off to private schools on
scholarship. I don't have any data for this. It could be an
insignificant amount or it could go a long way in explaining the
downturn in the numbers over the decades. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org0ad1cca" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0ad1cca"&gt;So where are we&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0ad1cca"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are a lot of changes I'd love to see in our public schools and I
do believe BdB's heart is in the right place. I'm concerned that some
of the solutions that he and other politicians come up with will hurt
the current low income students at the specialized schools and
unintentionally advantage the well to do while not helping those that
at least BdB may honestly want to help.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He should enact Discovery and research the State Tests but proceed
with caution. The test schools have always been and continue to be a
gateway for poor and immigrant students and any changes that are
proposed should be weighed carefully and &lt;b&gt;tested&lt;/b&gt; before taking steps
that could real harm when good is intended.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>gifted</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 11:01:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Do the students finish the tests or does the test finish the students</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tests-finish-students/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc102b10" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc102b10"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc102b10"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I tweeted this the other day:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Why don't so many  teachers and professors understand that the test or assignment you can do in 15 minutes will take your beginning students at least an hour and probably a lot more to complete.&lt;/p&gt;— Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/986609723557404673?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;April 18, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What led to the tweet was a discussion I was having with some students
about not having enough time on tests which led to a discussion of
having to drop everything to spend every waking hour on a project.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org1e99658" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org1e99658"&gt;Let's talk about tests.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org1e99658"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'm not saying that tests are the best forms of assessment - most of
the time I'd much rather have students work on projects. There are,
however, times when tests make sense or are otherwise appropriate.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any event, writing a test is hard. Rather, writing good test is
hard. It's certianly easy enough to put a bunch of multiple choice or
short answer questions on paper and it's easy enough to give a hard
equation to solve or some code to write but creating a good test is a
task and half. You first have to figure out what you're trying to
assess - memory, thought process, synthesizing concepts? Then you want
to construct questions that give you insights into your students
knowledge and thought process.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some things that I consider when putting together a test:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does it ramp up in difficulty - that is, are there some "gimme
questions" and some challenges.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are questions all or nothing - if a kid doesn't see things my way
are they dead in the water.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the test repeatedly penalize or reward the same concept over
and over again on the test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I cover all the concepts I want to assess.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you make kids waste time with boilerplate code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do the questions take so long to read and digest that there's little
time to form and write down answers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do the answers convey anything about the students thought process or
just correctness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it easy or impossible to grade and grade fairly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What about length? To me a well crafted test should be completed by
the average student with a few minutes to spare - enough time to check
a couple of answers. This is not to say that they'll ace the exam,
just finish it. Far too many teachers make tests an assessment of
speed and accuracy at speed rather than understanding. That might
actually be important in certain contexts - preparing for the APCS-A
multiple choice section as an example but in general, it's not a good
way of assessing what a student really knows. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's also important that the the average student can achieve a score
that you expect from an average student. That's probably in the 80s on
a 0-100 scale or a B. Yes, I know, C is supposed to be average but
with grade inflation being what it is…
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You should &lt;b&gt;NOT&lt;/b&gt; give an assessment where the average score is
something like 17 out of 100 with the top student earning a 37. Sure,
you can curve it but it also places a lot of stress on the
students. You might do this from time to time - you might misjudge the
difficulty of a test or your class but it shouldn't be a regular
occurence. Teachers sometimes forget about the psychological affect
that a unfair test can have on a student even if the teacher "fixes" it
after the fact.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org474b075" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org474b075"&gt;Don't be afraid to experiment or have some fun.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org474b075"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It's also ok to try different things. One year, having just completed
a unit on Cellualar Automata I decided to give a quiz. I figured it
would take the kids 10 to 15 minutes so I gave them 30. The quiz was
something like the following:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You have 30 minutes to compose something on a sheet of paper that when
I review it convinces me that you know something about the Cellular
Automata Unit we just completed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some kids loved the quiz, some hated it. The ones that hated it had
been trained for years as expert standardized test takers and this
level of freedom really freaked the out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another time, I gave a multi page test of serious questions mixed with
crazy shenanigans. Question one would be some CS problem followed by
some instructions like "stand up, do 5 jumping jacks and sit down" or
"shout out your favorite olde timey exclamation" or even "stand up, if
or when you see another student standing, switch seats with the and
continue the test." The test started with explicit instructions not to
read ahead but to read and do each question in order. The last page
was the answer key and I asked the kids to self-grade. Interestingly
enough the grading was pretty honest. After that one, I received a few
apology emails from kids who read to the end first encouraging me to
give them failing grades for cheating. Wow, I wasn't expecting
that. The test was something of an end of year goof. The CS questions
were really easy - I wanted to reward them with something silly and
easy - a guaranteed A after a year of hard work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org85c64d7" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org85c64d7"&gt;Tests to drive instruction and future practice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org85c64d7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a final point to ponder, tests shouldn't only be about grades. A
well crafted test should drive instruction. Kids will get answers
wrong - will your questions be crafted so that you can gain insights
into why the got them wrong.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In an early class you might notice things like:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kids printing rather than returning answers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kids not understanding scope&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kids having difficulty with idioms like &lt;code&gt;i=i+1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;kids needing more scaffolding to approach a problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This can drive instruction moving forward.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over time you'll also learn how to fine tune your tests and other
assessments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org80d8bc3" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org80d8bc3"&gt;Next time, we'll talk about projects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org80d8bc3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Unless of course I get distracted by another blog topic or shiny
object.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>assessments</category><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tests-finish-students/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 19:53:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tools and Complexity</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tools-and-complexity/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org45c1165" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org45c1165"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org45c1165"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt; wrote about &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/04/thoughts-on-where-cs-education-tools.html"&gt;CS education tools&lt;/a&gt; earlier today. I've
also been meaning to write on the topic but from a different point of
view.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I do my best to keep up with the latest and greatest in the CS world
both on the academic side as well as the professional one. That's not
really possible, but I do my best. When I have a small project to work
on I'll some times use it as an excuse to play with some recent
technology. Over December, I wanted to write an application viewer to
use for company / student internship matching. I started by looking at
&lt;a href="https://reactjs.org/"&gt;React&lt;/a&gt; but ended up using &lt;a href="https://vuejs.org/"&gt;Vue.js&lt;/a&gt; which I liked much more for a variety
of reasons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The viewer served it's purpose but I think it can be turned into a
much more comprehensive student / employer internship platform. I
tried to steal a few minutes over this past week's spring break to
start a rewrite using another toolset, Clojure, Clojurescript and
Reagent. I'm really liking the Clojure stack and using
Emacs and Cider for the IDE is really blowing me away. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I've noticed is that for every new language of framework you also
have to learn a whole set of ancillary tools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It didn't used to be that way. Back in the day, things were much
simpler. I remembering doing work at Goldman Sachs, it was as simple
as typing something on the command line like &lt;code&gt;cc file1.c file2.c
file3.c&lt;/code&gt;. I of course had to be cutting edge and use fancy modern
tools like &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/make/"&gt;Make&lt;/a&gt;. What's more, the tools I used in industry were very
similar to what I used in college. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We now live in very different times.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you go to the getting started guides for React or Vue it's pretty easy to
get hello world up and running but beyond that you start to fall in to
the Javascript tooling hole. To start you need either &lt;b&gt;npm&lt;/b&gt; or &lt;b&gt;yarn&lt;/b&gt;
just to manage packages and dependencies. Then you need a build system
or bundler like &lt;b&gt;webpack&lt;/b&gt;, &lt;b&gt;browserify&lt;/b&gt;, or &lt;b&gt;parcel&lt;/b&gt; and that's not even
considering older options like &lt;b&gt;gulp&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;grunt&lt;/b&gt; and ancillary tools
like &lt;b&gt;babel&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A typical React or Vue project is going to need a &lt;a href="https://github.com/krasimir/react-webpack-starter/blob/master/package.json"&gt;project.json&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/krasimir/react-webpack-starter/blob/master/webpack.config.js"&gt;webpack.config.js&lt;/a&gt; file and sometimes some other files as well. Check
out the links. They're from a simple project template I found
online. Far from simple.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I was playing with Vue.js a couple of months ago, I ended up
using Webpack to convert the source code into the final JS, take care
of live-reloading, and in general manage the project. I still have no
idea how most of it works. I don't know if it's just me but I'm very
uncomfortable relying on tools that I really don't fully understand to
build my systems. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Clojure world is little better with Leiningen and Boot. If you
don't believe me, try to make heads or tails of &lt;a href="https://github.com/bhauman/figwheel-template/blob/master/src/leiningen/new/figwheel/project.clj"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While it's true that as a professional you'll likely use one set of
tools on a day to day basis and you'll eventually get to know them
that doesn't mean it's not a good idea to prepare kids for what's to
come.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
On the K12 side we have drag and drop languages, specialized learning
IDEs like BlueJ, simple cut down IDEs like Dr Racket and completely
online environments like repl.it. All great starter tools that
insulate beginners from the complexities to come. College's
might get closer to the "real world" but just a tad. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Don't get me wrong, I like many of the tools used in K12
classes and there's far too much complexity in the professional world to
throw at beginners. If we look at a student's entire school
career, classes are already so packed with material it would be hard to
really prepare kids for the real world within their classes. You could
take that tried and true teacher / professor technique of just
requiring it and having the kids figure it out on their own but that's
really just downright abusive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't have an answer for this one. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have my kids use tools like Git and GitHub early along with using
testing frameworks and external libraries. I also try to move my
students to a general purpose programmable platform like Emacs or
Vim. I think these are sound practices but students will still have a
big learning curve when they finally get to industry. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I really would love it to see the tooling become simpler and
documentation better. &lt;a href="https://github.com/parcel-bundler/parcel"&gt;Parcel&lt;/a&gt;, a Javascript bundler is one of the newer
kids on the block and is much simpler and cleaner than alternatives
like Webpack. The new version of Clojure has it's own command line
tool which is also simpler than the alternatives. Maybe we are already
moving in the right direction and this entire rant will become moot in a couple of years.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>csed</category><category>education</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tools-and-complexity/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2018 22:55:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ethics In CS Education</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-in-cs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org13c9eaa" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org13c9eaa"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org13c9eaa"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've been meaning to write about ethics in CS education for a
while. Probably since I saw &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/02/12/business/computer-science-ethics-courses.html?smid=fb-share"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; in the NY Times but got sidetracked.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was reminded when I saw this tweet by Hadi the other day:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;This message is bigger than Facebook. Computer science faces an ethics crisis. That’s why &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/codeorg?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@codeorg&lt;/a&gt; covers ethics and digital citizenship in our computer science courses. (And we’re thankful that most of the largest tech companies support us) &lt;a href="https://t.co/roSkAzANQM"&gt;https://t.co/roSkAzANQM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Hadi Partovi (@hadip) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hadip/status/977673429485731840?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;March 24, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think we can all agree that bringing ethics and digital citizenship
and, frankly, citizenship in general to our students is important. What I wonder is
what approaches will lead to meaningful results and what methods will
lead us to checking off the "covered that" box.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm skeptical of throwing an ethics course into the curriculum as some
places seem to be doing. A class might be required, might fulfill an
elective requirement or it might just be an extra course. If it's
required, what does it replace or are you just going to add more to
the student load. If it fulfills an elective credit, will it be
perceived as "the easy course" as opposed to say, theory and if it's
just an extra course, who's going to take it? Will it just become
preaching to the choir. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Better is what Hadi mentioned in his tweet - embed ethics throughout
all of your courses and while I think this type of embedding is
important and I'd argue necessary, I'm still betting it won't be
enough to make a difference.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When teaching a course, teachers cover the curriculum but when you
drill down to where they focus their time, it comes down to:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what they think is important for the kids to know.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what they think the kids will need for that high stakes exam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If a teacher feels embedding ethical concerns is important they'll
spend time on it, if not, it will be lip service. Even if it's on the
high stakes exam, unless the teacher really believes that this is
important it will just be teaching to the test.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'd argue that it has to go even further since teachers can only do so
much. How many schools have honor codes and how many of us know
graduates from those schools who exhibit less than ethical behaviour.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So what do we do?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, of course we do have to embed ethical concerns across the
curriculum. Teachers should be armed with both the materials and time
needed to address ethical concerns but beyond that, we need teachers
for which ethical CS is important.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My friend &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ed_saber"&gt;Saber Khan&lt;/a&gt; has been facilitating a monthly #ethicalCS
twitter chat for close to a year now. I don't take part in too many
twitter chats but do recognize that they're important in raising both
awareness and community. I've also seen ethical CS issues more
frequently appear as conference sessions and professional development.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The next big step is to start at the beginning - pre service teacher
training and in my opinion, not with a course but rather embedding
ethical issues throughout teacher preparation. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If we want to crack this nut it can't just be from curriculum and from
the choir. Pre service CS teacher training is in it's infancy and has
not yet really found its form.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Much to my chagrin, a lot of CS Ed has gone the way of other Ed: Math
Ed, Science Ed, etc. and not in a good way. Let's see if we can make
sure that pre service CS teacher preparation develops to attract and
create great teachers for which ethical CS is part of their core. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>ethicalCS</category><category>preservicexs</category><category>teachers</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-in-cs/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Mar 2018 20:59:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>On Prestigious Competitons And High Schools</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-prestigious-competitons-and-high-schools/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org8b98398" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org8b98398"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org8b98398"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The ACM recently announced this year's winners of the Cutler-Bell
Prize in High School Computing. Over on his blog, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt;
noted that the winners were either from independent or magnet public
schools. Alfred also noted that most of the winners of prestigious
science competitions like the Regeneron Science Talent Search (nee
Intel, nee Westinghouse) were from public magnet schools. In &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2018/03/impressive-high-school-computer-science.html%0A"&gt;his post&lt;/a&gt;,
Alfred ruminates on this and wonders "how to we add the flexibility
and support to more students at more schools?"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As someone who spent over 25 years at Stuyvesant, arguably the
granddaddy of these public magnet schools, I wanted to share some
thoughts. I can only share my experiences from Stuy along with what I
know from a few other schools but I still hope this is worth a read.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Regeneron competitions under it's various names is the oldest and
most established of these competition so it's pretty easy to get some
data. Stuy is at or near the top of the list in terms of Regeneron
finalists and semi finalists. The &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regeneron_Science_Talent_Search"&gt;Wikipediapage&lt;/a&gt; lists Stuy as second
to Montgomery Blair with 22 finalists to 40 but the data only goes
back to 1999. I personally know of at least 7 more finalists from my
early years at Stuy, 4 more from the early 90s, 8 more listed under
the page's "notable" entries and who kows how many from the 80s and
earlier. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Stuy had a strong run of finalists in the early 90's and the early
2000's but there has been a fall off in recent years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's look at what makes Stuy "special" and then at the fall off.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
In terms of money, Stuy gets a basic budget similar to other NYC
public schools plus some extra due to the extra graduation
requirements (other schools get extra money for an assortment of
reasons). I seem to recall that the Parents Association raises
somewhere in the low to mid six figures and the Alumni Association has
been historically dysfunctional as a fundraising body.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, it's not money.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Flexible scheduling? That's something that Alfred mentioned. Stuy kids
have super packed programs. Some kids take 10 classes a day with no
lunch so that's not it either.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teachers? Stuy gets its teachers the same way as other public
schools and just like other public schools they have some terrific
teachers and some absolute disasters. Stuy also gets a slice of a
particular class of teacher that starts their career at Stuy, never
learns to teach because the kids figure it out but thinks they're gods
gift to teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, no, it's not the teachers, at least not on the whole.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what does Stuy do?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It collects talent and this is the same thing that the other magnet
schools and the elite private schools do as well. Get a bunch of
bright, hard working, motivated kids together and good things
happen. It gets high achieving students from a combination of entrance
exam, reputation, and location &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-prestigious-competitons-and-high-schools/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not arguing against this – I think there is a need for public
magnet schools like Stuy but I think it's important to recognize that
this is a major contributor to competition results and doesn't
necessarily say anything about the school in terms of leadership or
instruction.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's similar to a college coach who gets the best recruits. Are they
really a great coach? Can they develop talent or are they just getting
the best talent and getting out of the way. Who's the better coach?
The one who gets all the 5 star recruits every years and frequently
wins it all or the coach who gets 3 star recruits, doesn't win as much
but develops those 3 stars to a point where they can compete against the 5 star
programs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's the starting point but then there's the targeting of the top
prospects. Stuy had a run of finalists during the early 2000s. At the
time, a friend of mine ran the math research program. His strategy? He
would scour the school for the kids most likely to win the
competition, get those kids into his class, and hook them  up with
professors with the most promising project potential. It worked
more often than not. Contrast that to what I did when I ran our CS
research program. I didn't take the program seriously for a variety of
reasons but my job was to give EVERY kid in my class the opportunity
to explore some aspect of CS. I had a few semi-finalists which is
neither here nor there but never the stream of winners that my friend
had.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looking back to Stuy's earlier success, we had a Bio Chair who ran a
similar program. I knew people in that program from when I was a
student. The top talent was recruited and nurtured, the rest, pretty
much ignored. Makes a school look good but not really the hallmark of
a great school
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Other schools had a similar strategy. Back in the '80s Cardozo - a
neighborhood high school in Bayside Queens had a great run of
Westinghouse results but that's because the science chair at the time
had a similar program - rope in the top talent early (sophomore year)
and nurture them. After a while the school got a reputation and would
then attract more "science talent."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Stuy's had a falloff in finalists in recent years and I believe that's
due to not having anyone focusing on recruiting kids specifically for
results. Personally, I think this is a good thing but others
disagree. A school with one finalist is perceived to be better than a
school that gives a great research experience to every student but
produces no finalists. In recent years, there's been talk of "what
can we do to get more winners again." I think that's a shame, the
conversation should always be "what can we do to improve the
educational experience we offer all of our students."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
None of this is to take away from any of the winners of  any of these
competitions. All the finalists and winners I've known have been
exceptional intellects and top people in their fields. This is just a
commentary on what role a school does, should, and shouldn't play.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my early years at Stuy, I worked with our top kids on CS
competitions, The kids would place very well in the USACO competitions
throughout the year. One year we entered the ACSL and I realized that
I had a choice - focus on the top handful of kids to make a winning
team that could compete for the title or focus on all the kids but not
expect that great single result. I realized that the top kids
would probably be alright without that extra attention. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I still think I did right by those kids but that realization also led
me to design my intro class, hack required CS into Stuy and probably
end up positively affecting far more students than if I just focused
on the top percent of a percent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-prestigious-competitons-and-high-schools/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;That said, students have also been
drawn to Stuy for the CS program which is fairly unique and also for a
couple of specific math teachers.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>competitions</category><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-prestigious-competitons-and-high-schools/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Mar 2018 19:49:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sigcse2018 Making theory more acccesible</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-theory/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf2eb3b3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgf2eb3b3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgf2eb3b3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up from SIGCSE 2018 is John MacCormick's session on
&lt;a href="https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3159557"&gt;Strategies for Baing the CS Theory Course on Non-decision Problems&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
MacCormicks's stance is that CS theory  is tough the first time around
and using non-decision problems is a viable approach to make theory
more accessible to beginners. As MacCormick said in his paper:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
… a decision problem may ask the yes/no question, "Does this graph
have a Hamilton cycle?" The corresponding non-decision problem is,
"Please give me a Hamilton cycle of this graph if it has one."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This leads to writing programs to explore concepts in CS theory rather
than just living in the world of proof. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
MacCormick goes on to say that:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For this audience, the key advantage of non-decision problems
is that they are more realistic: they match the previous programming
and algorithms experience of undergraduates more closely.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I love the idea. Writing a program can make an abstract problem more
concrete and can lead to better understanding for those of us who are
less math inclined.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My next thought was that this shouldn't just be a change implemented
in theory courses. Some of these ideas should move down to more
introductory CS classes. Not the hardcore stuff but light
introductions to the topics so that we can layer the learning. If we
introduce some of these concepts in CS 1 classes then when they get to
the theory class it won't be the students first rodeo.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've had success with this when teaching recursion early. I've also
done it with other concepts. When we teach the Towers of Hanoi, yes,
it's a nice recursion problem but really it's to get the students
thinking about run time and a bit of proof. likewise, when we do a
maze solver in NetLogo we're alluding to dynamic programming, search,
and path finding.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't have too much more to say on this topic right now. I'm not
enough of a theory guy to sensibly design these experiences. The good
news is that MacCormick has written an soon to be released &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/What-Can-Computed-Practical-Computation/dp/0691170665/ref=asap_bc?ie=UTF8"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; on the subject. I
signed up for a reviewer copy at SIGCSE and look forward to receiving
a copy. Once I do I hope to be able to find some gems that I can work
into CS 1 experiences.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>theory</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-theory/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2018 23:21:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How my views on education research were shaped</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/practitioners-and-researchers/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb4aede6" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgb4aede6"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgb4aede6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After reading a couple of comments on my &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-code-tracing/"&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; where I talked a
bit about practitioners vs researchers I thought I'd expand and
expound a bit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While there are education researchers that I very much respect,
overall, I'm skeptical of education research. Note
that I'm not talking specifically about CS Ed research but rather
education research in general.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's go back to the beginning. I entered teaching from
industry. Goldman Sachs to be specific. I started in a shortage area -
math and barely had the credentials to do so. The transcript evaluator
at the DOE counted my Algorithms and Numerical Methods courses as Math
courses to get me over the credit hump.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had zero ed courses under my belt and was thrown into the
fire. Fortunately, I landed in a school, Seward Park High School, with
a very supportive faculty. I wouldn't have survived my first year
without Mike G, Bruce B, Jonathan G, and many others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then, I had to start taking education credits to make my license
permanent. Some classes were taught by professors some by
adjuncts. The adjuncts were invariably experienced teachers and the
professors were research faculty. In many classes, I had to read the
latest research. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I found that what "the research" told us to do was contrary to what
some of the best teachers did in practice. I kept hearing about the
"right" way to teach but it frequently didn't jive with reality. When
the true way worked, circumstances were right and the technique
aligned with the teacher's natural tendencies. When it didn't, why
not? Many reasons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lack of prep time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;too many students (per class, per day, per term)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;different populations than the one researched&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;factors the researcher didn't include (and there are tons of them)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teachers with different personalities and skill sets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and each of the above points opens up to scores of specifics. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
This theme continued throughout my career. I'd ask teachers in other
subject areas about the current state of the art research. What was
the current trends in their fields. Generally the best teachers would
summarize what was going on and then either say that it didn't work
for them or that if it did, they didn't take it seriously because in
five or ten years "the research" would tell them to do something
different and then they would all of a sudden be bad teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was another point. The right way to do it has changed over and
over during my career.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then there's the reproducibility problem. Apparently it's pretty bad
in education research. I mentioned in my &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-code-tracing"&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt; that when a
researched does it once on a small group it's research but when a
teacher did it over and over it's an anecdote.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I was young I would listen to a master teacher tell me about how
he set up some experience - the one I'm remembering now is an
experiential / discovery lesson on triangle geometry. He'd talk about
all the hard work that went into prepping his class for this type of
lesson as well as the prep time for the lesson itself. He told me how
he did it four years ago and it was great but then the year after it
fell flat and how he changed it for the next year. How it worked in
third period but not seventh and why he thought it played out the way
it did. That's a lot more reproduction than most 'research' actually
gets and this is what a master teacher does all the time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, I got tired of hearing how to do it by people who don't
actually have to. If you're going to talk the talk, you should walk
the walk. As a side, this problem is really bad with "thought leaders."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All this sounds like I'm really down on education research or at least
the overarching system. I probably am but there are many education
researchers doing great work and I respect them immensely.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They know they don't have a magic bullet:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is what I tried with this population at this time and this is
what happened. You might want to try it or a variation on it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's a far cry from "here's how to teach"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The researchers who acknowledge that their experience as college
researchers or even teaching faculty are different from a k12 teacher
and that no matter how hard they try to work out all the variables
they can only ever account for a tiny fraction of them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The key is that they're adding another drop into the bucket of
knowledge. Over time it adds up. I have great respect for everyone
doing this. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These researchers have to keep prodding us teachers to re-evaluate our
practice and then either take or incorporate the research or reject it
after determining if it would be good or not for our population. At
the same time, it's up to practitioners to keep pushing back against
magic bullet research and the one true way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We all have a role to play in this game.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>research</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/practitioners-and-researchers/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2018 23:41:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fixing the Absent Teacher Reserve (ATR) situation</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/atrs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd1a1cac" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd1a1cac"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd1a1cac"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the New York City department of education a recurring hot topic is
the Absent Teacher Reserve or ATR pool. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A teacher or administrator in the ATR pool is a licensed, most likely
tenured teacher not assigned permanently to a school. Each year these
educators get shuttled from school to school and denied a chance to
actually settle in a position.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The ATR pool was created under the Bloomberg administration. Prior to
that, when there was an opening school transfers were basically
seniority based and when school had too many teachers the least senior
was excessed or basically out of a job until a school with an opening
could be found. The Bloomberg plan allowed teachers to use criteria
other than seniority for transfers but so as not to violate the
contract agreed to by both parties, teachers who were excessed, as
they might not be least senior, were kept on as employees and put in
the pool.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
ATR's would rotate from school to school. Sometimes for a couple of
week but more recently for a year at a time. When at a school for only
a couple of weeks they could only be used as subs or for grunt work
but even when there for a year they're treated like second class
citizens.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The ATR pool grew in size when the Bloomberg/Klein DOE went on the war
path, set schools up to fail and closed them left and right. If you
had the bad luck being at a close out school when it closed then, hello
ATR pool.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the years, the press, ed reformers and politicians have unfairly
bashed this group of educators. They've falsely claimed that these are
criminal teachers or unsatisfactory teachers. That's a blatant
lie. Teachers up on charges are removed from schools and await a
hearing in another draconian process set up to violate teacher's
rights. If a teacher is ultimately found guilty, they are disciplined
or fired. If exonerated, they're returned to their schools. In any
case they're not ATRs. Teachers that are repeatedly found to be
unsatisfactory are likewise removed (although the process here is
ridiculous and unfair as well).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
ATRs like any pool of teachers run the gamut. Some are great, some are
poor, many will fall in between. All are stigmatized and treated like
damaged goods.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
People ask, how can a good teacher get into the ATR pool? As I said,
be at a closeout school. In the year before I was able to bring my friend
and former colleague JonAlf over to Stuy, he was at Brandeis High
School - a
closeout school. I tried to bring him over that year but his principal
wouldn't release him. Had I not been successful in bringing him over
the following year he might very well have ended up in the ATR pool
and he's one of the best teachers I know. What about the teacher that
doesn't want to abandon those kids that the DOE abandoned when they
decided to close the school. That martyr teacher surely ends up in the
ATR pool but that's the type of dedicated teacher every principal
should want.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So now we have a bunch of stigmatized teachers looking for work in a
system that won't give them a chance. Not only due to them being
considered "damaged goods" but also because they're expensive to
hire. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When a school gets an ATR to them, it's free - the cost isn't added to
their budget - they keep them as extra manpower for the year and then
throw them out with the trash. At times, they get some credit for
keeping them a second year and even beyond they can get rid of them
whenever they want. Great way to bust the contract.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A clear example of this is Stuy's  current math chair. He's an ATR
Assistant Principal. They got him for free for the first year and I
believe at a 50% discount for the second and even now they can dump
him whenever they want. This is rubbish – he's either good enough for
the position or he's not. If he is, he should be given the job for
real and if he isn't then what is he still doing there. I'm not making
any value judgment on him or the department but it's either one or the
other.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, a big reason for this ATR mess is about budgets and money. The
problem is that it's a big lie. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The DOE pretends the we have a situation like this:
&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/atr1.png" alt="atr1.png" align="center" height="250"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The DOE has money and schools have money. The schools pay for their
teachers, supplies, and everything else but the ATRS are paid for by
the DOE. Of course this isn't the case. The truth is that the DOE pays
for everything:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/atr2.png" alt="atr2.png" align="center" height="250"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
ALL the money comes from the DOE.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the past the DOE has come up with poorly conceived and poorly
received plans on how to deal with the ATR situation but it's really
quite simple.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Start by recognizing that ALL the money comes from the DOE. Once you
do that you can address the problem:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assign the ATR to a school&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the school likes the ATR and the ATR likes the school, they keep
them and the DOE picks up the tab or rather adjusts the schools
budget to compensate. The DOE will continue to do so until a real
opening occurs at the school in the ATR's area at which point the
ATR fills the position officially and the budget is readjusted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the school or ATR don't like each other the ATR gets rotated,
however you create a 3 strikes (or maybe 2 or 4 or some number)
rule.
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the school keeps sending away ATRs semester after semester hit
them with a penalty or force an ATR placement when they have an
opening (assuming the ATR is amenable).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the ATR keeps declining positions after a set number of
schools force the placement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's it. Simple and solves the problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/atrs/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 13:01:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New York State moving forward with CS Teacher Certification</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/NY-CS-Certificate/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd92872d" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd92872d"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd92872d"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last April I woke up early and trekked up to Albany along with a few
of my Hunter College colleagues to share our thoughts on K12 Computer
Science teacher certification with the Board of Regents. We gave a
presentation to the Regents Higher Education Committee and afterwards
had a chance to talk with some of the Regents as well as other members
of the New York State Department of Education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I left feeling that our proposals were well received and I think
everyone present - both the Hunter and NYSED contingents hoped that
things would move forward on this important issue.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward to today, December 8, 2017. I was up at the crack
of dawn. Driving in the dark in the snow from NYC to Albany to once
again attend a Board of Regents Higher Education Committee
meeting. This time, the agenda item was:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Proposed Amendments to Part 30 of the Regents Rules and Section 52.21
and Part 80 the Regulations of the Commissioner of Education Relating
to a New Certification Area and Tenure Area for Computer Science 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No discussion or debate this time around just the proposal. If I
understand the process correctly, this should come up again at the
March meeting at which point it will be voted on. If approved, it
looks like we'll have a pathway towards certification for CS teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I haven't had a chance to dive into the details but at the meeting a
few key points came up:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As the proposal indicates this will be a subject area in which a
teacher can be certified and be awarded tenure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be a traditional pathway for new teachers - Bachelors /
Masters degree&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an alternative pathway for people entering from the
workforce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an extension for teachers with another license so they
won't have to give up tenure in their current license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an "individual evaluation" pathway which sounds to me
like it could catch people who fall through the cracks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There looks to be a sensible ramp up period - until September 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's a grandfathering provision that looks to last 10 years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This sounds like a smart sensible plan. Multiple pathways, shallow
ramp up and provisions to protect existing teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, the devil is in the details. What's an approved program?
Can a grandfathered teacher teach all CS classes or just intro ones?
etc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I said, I haven't had a chance to dive into the details yet but
this is very exciting.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Prior to the meeting I was chatting with a few other people
attending. One, a &lt;a href="http://www.uft.org/"&gt;UFT&lt;/a&gt; representative was very excited about the
prospect. Another contingent, a group from &lt;a href="https://www.nysut.org/"&gt;NYSUT&lt;/a&gt; was very much against
a new certification area. Their position was that this would create a
teacher shortage because no one would have a CS license and no one
would get one due to the difference in salary between teaching and the
tech industry. I've already written on how I feel that this is a &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry"&gt;red
herring&lt;/a&gt;. What shocked me though was their feeling that "we already
have many non-CS teachers effectively teaching CS across the
state. They're doing a great job and don't need any additional content
or pedagogical knowledge." I think they're wrong and I also think that
when we as a community talk about how our summer professional
development is all that's needed, we undercut CS education and
the teaching profession as a whole.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any event this was a big step for New York. I tried to individually
thank as many of the participants as I could for helping shepherd this
along but could only speak to a few so I'll just give a blanket thank
you here to the NY State Board of Regents, Board of Education and
State Education department.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>certification</category><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/NY-CS-Certificate/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 23:57:37 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>