<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about education)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/education.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Sep 2017 16:59:45 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>I Believe CS Teachers are Smart and Capable</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orga7bb940" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orga7bb940"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orga7bb940"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
People sometimes accuse me of being an elitist CS snob that I feel that CS
teachers have to have advanced CS degrees. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not that at all. Rather, I feel that CS teachers are smart and
capable. Circumstances frequently result in a teacher in front of a CS
class with limited content and pedagogical content knowledge. It's not
ideal but it's reality. Of course I feel that we should do everything
to support and encourage these teachers but we should also insist that
after a reasonable period of time, they know their stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is why I hate it when I hear people in the CS Ed community say
something is too hard. Git's too hard. The command line is too
hard. Functional programming's too hard &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. That's all nonsense. At last
year's SIGCSE conference people from a state, I forget which, was
considering not using the Praxis exam for CS teacher certification
even though the state uses the Praxis exam for other subject
areas. They claimed that the praxis was too hard for CS teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/praxis.jpg" alt="praxis.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I haven't taken the Praxis exam but some friends have. It doesn't
appear to be unreasonable at all&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.2" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fn.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While I can certainly understand a teacher not knowing much when they
start - thrown in due to necessity I think it's ridiculous not to
insist that they ultimately get to real mastery.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A math teacher generally has to know math beyond calculus. Science
teachers have to have gotten through Orgo. English teachers have to
understand Joyce. &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;THIS IS HARD STUFF!!!!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.3" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fn.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think it's insulting to say that CS teachers aren't capable of doing
the same in their subject area.
'
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;whether or not any of
these topics are appropriate for a particular course is discussion for
another time&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.2" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fnr.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;although I'm not a big believer
in standardized exams for certification or in general.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.3" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/#fnr.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;There are plenty of
lousy teacher prep programs that don't ensure teachers learn the
subject matter they should but the good ones do.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teachers-smart/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 22:17:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Is the new Secret Sauce ever better?</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-the-new-secret-sauce-ever-better/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org3ba1fa0" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org3ba1fa0"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org3ba1fa0"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I read &lt;a href="http://nancyebailey.com/2017/09/05/xq-super-schools-business-working-to-end-public-high-schools/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; piece earlier today on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/NancyEBailey1"&gt;Nancy Bailey&lt;/a&gt;'s blog. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
TL;DR (although it really isn't too long so you should read it) - it's
on Laurene Powell Jobs, her efforts to "reform" education and why
she's misguided as are most of the well to do non-educators working
hard to change and in many cases privatize public education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Laura posts a nice list of simple, common sense ways to improve
education. I'll repost them here:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For years, research has shown that high school students need more sleep. They should have later start times. .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smaller class sizes would help.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure teachers don’t have so many preparation plans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;End advanced placement classes (IMHO).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve career-technical classes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide rich extra-curricular activities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bring back life skill classes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include a social justice curriculum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include students on the disciplinary board.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide civics education.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure students get opportunities to participate in the arts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work to include the community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure students have access to counselors, and school support staff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every high school should have a great library, a real librarian, and technology and books.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looks very much like what those elite private schools that those rich
non-educators send their kids to.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other day I also overheard a conversation between two
professors. One noted that they had just taught a course totally
online for the first time and that the professor really had fun doing
it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These got me thinking more about all the secret sauce and magic
bullets coming from tech to save education - things like MOOCS or  "personalized"
learning system.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started to wonder - have these &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;ever&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; been pushed on public
schools because they're better or rather because they cut costs (or in
the slightly better case to reach a student that otherwise wouldn't
have any opportunity which, in a way is generally cost related).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I couldn't come up with a single instance. They're always a way to
replace what I consider personalized instruction – you know, when a
teacher has a small class and can personally deal with, learn about,
interact with, and teach the child. Kids spend hours in front of a
screen instead of working with others. Kids do a MOOC (or maybe drop
out of a MOOC) so that you can have your student/teacher ratio reach
ridiculous levels. I've never seen any tech solution rolled out to
public schools because it's better. Only to cut costs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How do I know that it's not better? Well, we have Nancy's list
above. It's what those rich people pay all that money to the elite
private schools for.  If all these solutions the Jobs and Gates of the
world were so much better, wouldn't they insist upon them  for their
own children? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Just some Friday food for thought.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><category>STEM</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/is-the-new-secret-sauce-ever-better/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 16:32:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Teaching APCS-A for the first time</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teaching-ap-first-time/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org6338bcd" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6338bcd"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6338bcd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I got  an email from a friend the other day. Among other things, he
mentioned that he would be teaching APCS-A for the first time this
year. He's a little trepidatious. He knows his stuff but he hasn't
really done much using Java.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was going to respond in an email but thought I might share here
instead.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
TL;DR - for all you APCS teachers who are new or new to Java - learn
your core CS, lean on your resources and support and it's OK to tell
your kids "I don't know, I'll get back to you.". Don't worry, you'll be great.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first time I taught APCS was some time around 1991 or 1992. It was at
&lt;a href="http://www.sewardparkhs.com/Famous-Alumni/"&gt;Seward Park&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.sewardparkhs.com/History/"&gt;High School&lt;/a&gt;. It was the AB curriculum - that is one
semester of programming in Pascal and one semester of Data Structures
and Algorithms.  Being a computer science major the core material was
never a concern. I had taken APCS the first time it was offered in May
1984 in Pascal and while most of my college and pre-teaching professional work
was in C, my college started it's CS sequence with Pascal. I was more
concerned with the actual teaching part. I had taught math for a year
and a half at that point but never CS and by any measure I was still
wet behind the ears. I never finished that first experience because I
was excessed to Stuy mid semester. I wasn't particularly happy with my
performance but looking back, I think I did a pretty good job given
the situation and my experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After teaching math for a year and a half I was back in APCS at
Stuy. Still in Pascal. I spent the next few years figuring out how to
teach CS and APCS in particular along with starting a couple of new
classes. When the College Board decided to move the AP class to C++ I
was happy, sad and a little worried. Pascal had a bunch of limitations
but I had never used C++. True, I was a C programmer at heart but I
had never really done the OOP thing. I did, as it turned out, design a
number of my C systems in an Object Typed design: I would use a single
file per "class" where local variables were de facto instance
variables and functions in the file were methods and each file was a
singleton class. I read &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Object-Oriented-Analysis-Design-Applications-3rd/dp/020189551X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1503519770&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=Grady+Booch"&gt;Booch&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Object-Oriented-Software-Construction-Book-CD-ROM/dp/0136291554/ref=asap_bc?ie=UTF8"&gt;Meyer&lt;/a&gt; on my own but I had no
schooling in OOP and no professional experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As it turned out, I didn't have to worry. I knew my CS and while it
took me a while to become comfortable with OOP, the class, and of
course I knew this from the get go, started from nothing and built
up complexity a step at a time. The worst that might have happened is
that some of my solutions might have been more C-esque than C++.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The move to Java was a little more jarring. Now we had a totally new
language. I couldn't fall back on C. It removed memory management and
explicit pointers and it had to be used in an Object Oriented
manner. I remember asking Mike Schidlowsky, a former student turned
friend who was the Java consultant on the Java edition of Sedgewick's
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Robert-Sedgewick-Algorithms-Fundamentals-Structures/dp/B008VR3ZH4/ref=sr_1_4?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1503520269&amp;amp;sr=8-4&amp;amp;keywords=schidlowsky"&gt;Algorithms&lt;/a&gt; book how to do something. It had to do with passing and
modifying arrays. In C there were a number of ways to accomplish what
I wanted to do. In Java, I couldn't figure out how to do it the way I
wanted. My friend Mike told me "you just don't do it that way in
Java." Again, it turned out that I didn't have to worry. The basic
coding was still the same as were the data structures and
algorithms. The only challenge was that I had to get into a Java OOP
mindset which it turned out wasn't that hard. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While I never really warmed up to OOP - I find other paradigms more
natural for me, I knew my CS and got more and more comfortable with
the Java (or C++) way of doing things as time wore on. Sometimes I
would say "I don't know" or "let's figure it out" but that's OK.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Nowadays, there are many more resources available for CS teachers. If
you're new, lean on them. Use the mailing lists, stackexchange,
facebook groups. Online resources like repl.it, codehs.com etc. Yes,
it's true that you'll be better next time around and even better years
down the road but right now, you're probably better than you think.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A number of my former students volunteer for &lt;a href="https://www.tealsk12.org/"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; - a really great
program that brings software engineers into the classroom to work with
non-CS teachers to deliver instruction. A number of my kids have
shared the following sentiment: 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know if I'm really helping
the teacher to become self sufficient or if I'm a great teacher but I
do know one thing - while I'm there, the kids are getting a hell of a
lot more than if I wasn't there." 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
– Remember that as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ap</category><category>apcs</category><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teaching-ap-first-time/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 19:56:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Cost of AP Exams</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cost-of-ap-exams/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org86800f2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org86800f2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org86800f2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that I'm back from vacation and summer's winding down I thought
I'd start getting back to more classroom related posts. I still have a
few summer topics I want to write about – standards and side projects
in particular but I'm also looking forward to talking more about the
classroom since, after all, at my core, I'm a teacher. When I saw &lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/future_tense/2017/08/how_online_textbooks_could_help_more_students_take_ap_exams.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;
article in my inbox this morning I thought I'd talk about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the piece, Lindsey Tepe since more kids are taking AP classes and
they're very expensive, schools should look to lower other costs
related to AP classes so as to provide financial support so that
students can take that oh so important end of year exam:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While the College Board continues to reimburse about one-third of the
test cost for eligible low-income students, only about half of states
are now offering any further financial assistance for students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Ms. Tepe's solution? Lower text book costs. As a way of lowering
school costs, I'm all for it. I've used free online resources in lieu
of textbooks for years but the savings should go somewhere where it
can make a difference. Perhaps lowering class sizes. The fatal flaw in
Ms. Teps's piece is that it continues spinning the misplaced narrative
that AP Exams are a very important part of a child's education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's be reminded of something: The AP Exam is one thing - an exam - a
single test at the end of the year. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The narrative is that students should take more and more AP classes,
that they're somehow better for kids. Part of this is due to the
potential college credit and part is because the public has been
bamboozled by the ridiculous school ratings that give credit for AP
classes taken. Back in "the day," AP classes were basically early
college. You could then argue that they were the most rigorous classes
offered in a school. AP Calc was basically college Calc. Same for
APCS-AB, AP-Bio and the rest. Now, with classes like APCS-P aimed to
be accessible to typical high school students in the lower grades,
they can't (but still will) make that claim. In fact, at Stuy, my
former school, there are plenty of non AP classes that are more
rigorous than AP classes and the best AP teachers don't always cover
the whole syllabus because they're more concerned with their students
actually learning rather than scoring 5 on an exam.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the college credit front, if a student has a high probability of
saving money through AP credit then I'm all for it but otherwise, it's
just money going to the college board.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It seems ridiculous for me to have to write this but the important
part of a class is, you know, the class. Not the single exam given by
an outside agency at the end and graded after the semester concludes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My suggestion? Offer college level work to students that are ready for
it but don't push the AP exam. This would save a ton of money. What value
does the college board actually bring to the table? Remember, they're
making a pretty penny on all of this testing. A math teacher should be
able to teach calculus with or without AP. A good text being used by
that teacher in class - be it free or paid for is actually much more
important to a student learning calculus than a single exam taken at
the end of the year. I'd go further and say that I'd trust the
teacher's exam more than the college board's. If a teacher knows the
math but needs to see some sample syllabi, they're a web search
way. The same is true for most other college courses that have AP
equivalents and maybe even more so for computer science.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day it should be about students learning not about
students taking high stakes exams.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ap</category><category>csed</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cost-of-ap-exams/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 11:07:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ethics, Cybersecurity, ethics, curricula  and standards</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-cybersecurity-curricula-standards/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org3b85648" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org3b85648"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org3b85648"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This morning, I read &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt;'s post on &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/08/cybersecuritythis-summers-computer.html"&gt;teaching
cybersecurity&lt;/a&gt;. as Alfred says, it's something of a CS Ed buzzword this
summer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another hot topic in K12 CS Ed this summer is the inclusion of ethics
in our CS courses courtesy of efforts like the #ethicalCS twitter chat every
Wednesday at 8:00 Eastern time  hosted by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ed_saber"&gt;Saber Khan&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Discussions about both topics include "where should we be doing this?"
"What should we be doing?" and of course "How?" 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking about designing curriculum from the top down -
that is, as dictated by outside forces: principals, superintendents,
states, industry or bottom up: a teacher sees a need and designs
something for their students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The best classes I've seen are those designed by a passionate teacher
from the ground up. I met  &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dougbergmanUSA"&gt;Doug Bergman&lt;/a&gt; at this past year's CSTA conference. He's terrific. I
think he came to the conference wanting to find out more about what
cybersecurity really meant. By the second day, he was raving about all
the amazing possibilities. I'd love to be in the class he develops.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, when topics or standards are forced down from
above, I've seen something entirely different.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've observed and been involved in cybersecurity discussions  with CS
teachers. The discussion goes something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Well, we do memory allocation in course XYZ so we can give a
homework assignment there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can rewrite the story (theme) for the assignment in our data
structures class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We already do a crypto assignment in algorithms so we're already
doing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've seen the same with groups of math teachers discussing
implementing common core. They talk about resequencing topics,
rewriting a few word problems or homework assignments but at the core,
the feeling is "we already know how to teach math."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It gets worse when there's a standardized or high stakes test at the
end of the tunnel and you get the "you need this for the test" type
units.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This might not be as big of a problem in K12 CS right now because so many
teachers are just learning their craft but in established fields such
as math or college CS, when an edict comes from above telling a
teacher how to teach, unless the teacher really believes in it, the
teacher will only pay lip service to it. If it isn't an issue in CS Ed
right now, it will eventually become one as our field develops legs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is arguably a bigger issue with Ethical CS than cybersecurity. If
the teacher doesn't really believe it's an important topic, we'll get
lip service at best and in the case of ethics, unless the teacher
really believes it and models it, the students will be able to tell
that it's a show.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't have an answer other than what my friend and mentor Herb
Greenhut told me many years ago "Solving the education problem is
easy. Hire good teachers and get the f*ck out of the way."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>curriculum</category><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-cybersecurity-curricula-standards/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2017 11:43:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Grit: A Kind Word and a Gun</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/grit-kind-word-gun/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org01c30ed" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org01c30ed"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org01c30ed"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back in May, I read this &lt;a href="http://avc.com/2017/05/grit/"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; about Angela Duckworth and &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Grit-Passion-Perseverance-Angela-Duckworth-ebook/dp/B010MH9V3W/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1501543669&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=Grit"&gt;Grit&lt;/a&gt;. Grit
has become an education buzzword in the past few years so I figured I
should read Duckworth's book. It took this long because there was a
long waiting list at the New York Public Library to get the ebook. I'm
still not quite finished with the book but I thought I'd share some of
my thoughts on the book and the buzz.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first big takeaway is "you can get much further with a kind word
and a gun than with a kind word alone." Or in grit terms Duckworth
says a number of times that Grit is important but that other factors
such as talent do indeed come into play and towards the end of the
book she lists other character qualities that are arguably more
important than grit. I'll get back to grit + other qualities towards
the end of this post.  On the buzz side, all of that's forgotten - in
the ed reform world it's all grit all the time. We must teach it at
our low income schools and we should include grit in our evaluation of
teachers and schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Duckworth recently has come out to say grit shouldn't be used in
evaluating schools and teachers but as I mentioned &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/outside-influences-on-cs-ed/"&gt;a few days ago&lt;/a&gt;,
ed reformers have ways of taking arguably good ideas and using them towards
awful ends.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So we have a basic premise that hard work and sticktoitiveness is
important but so is talent. Talent alone won't get you as far as
talent and grit. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So in spite of the "ed reformers" take on grit, given Duckworth's
balanced perspective, I was hooked.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Where Duckworth started to lose me, however is when she dove into the
education landscape for examples.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First up is Teach for America. Certainly the founder, Wendy Kopp is
full of grit and Duckworth talks about teachers needing to be gritty
but when you talk about TFA, you're talking about a group that:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has a 5 week training program - not nearly enough to learn to teach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has a 2 year commitment before moving to "better things"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;encourages practices like scripted lessons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
None of this sounds particularly gritty to me. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Duckworth also highlights the KIPP charter chain as an terrific
example of grit and the success that follows. She touts KIPP's
graduation rate neglecting to mention that like most other charters
claiming miracles, KIPP's stats should be eyed with scrutiny (&lt;a href="http://garyrubinstein.teachforus.org/2011/07/08/kipp-on-trickin-looking-at-the-raw-data/"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://garyrubinstein.wordpress.com/2016/01/22/whatever-happened-to-kipp/%0A"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://garyrubinstein.wordpress.com/2017/04/28/4th-best-high-school-in-new-york-is-a-kipp-school-that-doesnt-exist/"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;). I would have expected a researcher to dig a little deeper.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My friend, former colleague, and TFA alum Gary Rubinstein visited a
KIPP school in NY a few years ago. His take:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So what I saw there was not very impressive.  I didn’t see any classes
where teachers were getting that mythical period and half of growth in
one period.  I saw some good teaching, mostly average teaching, and
even some very bad teaching.  I saw a novice teacher struggle to
control a class of nine students.  They were walking all over him and
accomplished very little that period.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And in terms of KIPP's grit training:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also saw the ‘grit’ training program which amounted to the students
getting the teacher to define very clearly how little homework they
would have to do to still get their candy bar rewards.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, Duckworth holds up Geoffrey Canada's as another shiny example
failing to notice that again, the &lt;a href="http://garyrubinstein.teachforus.org/2013/05/12/canadas-legend-ary-ted-talk-lie/"&gt;Emperor has no clothes&lt;/a&gt; and if you
look at attrition, the results are far from stellar.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All of this left me thinking that if Duckworth was so off base with
these three example where I have some details of the behind the scenes
going on, how much can I trust the rest of the book?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In spite of this, I still agreed with Duckworth's basic premise so I
read on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Later in the book, Duckworth talks about developing grit. This quote struck me:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Like a lot of parents I had a strong intuition that grit is enahnced
by doing activities like ballet… or piano … or football…
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It struck me because it seemed funny coming from a researcher. It
reminded me of Christopher Alexander's "A Timeless Way of Building," a
book on architecture that is sometimes credit as the root source for
Object Oriented Programming. Alexander talks about how societies
throughout history and throughout the world "knew" how to build
certain structures – barns, homes with certain features, even
towns. Back in the day we didn't have engineering and architecture
schools but we figured out how to do these things and we figured it
out pretty much universally. Duckworth is basically saying "parents
know." It reminded me of my belief - "teachers know." This applies to
teaching content and teaching skills like grit. You can't script a
grit lesson. A good teacher knows when a student needs encouragement,
when a student needs to be coddled and when a student needs to be
redirected. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This post has been something of a ramble but I want to get back to 
grit and other qualities and how people are talking about grit as the
be all and end all and not just a component.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over on &lt;a href="http://avc.com"&gt;AVC&lt;/a&gt;, in the post that got me to read Grit, Fred closed with:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
If you hire and manage people, if you run start and run companies, if
you invest in people and their projects, then Grit is a book you
should read.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He's absolutely right but remember the whole person and what you've
prescreened for before you consider grit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Way back when discussions were ongoing about the design for &lt;a href="https://www.afsenyc.org/"&gt;AFSE&lt;/a&gt; -
before the DOE stopped returning my emails and froze me out of the
process I was at am meeting. A bunch of tech industry heavy hitters
were there. We were arguing over admission screening - did the school
need one. My position was that if you wanted to produce "Google ready"
engineers after high school you needed one. If that wasn't the goal
you didn't. One of the DOE representatives posed a question to the
tech people: "what qualities do you look for in a hire?" This elicited
responses like hard working, able to work with others, able to
communicate. The DOE person was proud to have made his point that
these tech companies weren't looking for talent, advanced skills
anything similar - grit was all you needed. I followed up - "and from
what schools do you look for the kids with these qualities?" - MIT,
Harvard, Cornell… and the tech people got it - they were already
screening for the academic stuff so all that was left to look for were
the other skills. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Should we look at grit? Certainly. Just remember that it's a piece of
the puzzle just like everything else.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>soft skills</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/grit-kind-word-gun/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2017 11:19:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Thoughts on non educator  influences on CS Education</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/outside-influences-on-cs-ed/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org66d4ddc" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org66d4ddc"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org66d4ddc"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; blogged about a NY Times piece discussing
&lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/2017/07/28/silicon-valley-pushing-coding-into-american-classrooms-through-code-org-nytimes/"&gt;Silicon Valleys influence on education through Code.org&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark questioned the validity of the piece. If you don't read Mark's
blog and you're in CS Ed you probably should. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I tried to leave a comment on Mark's blog - not about the NY Times
article but rather my thoughts on why I think it's important that we
remain wary and vigilant to industry and outsiders influence and
impact on CS education and on education in general.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know if my comment is sitting waiting for Mark to moderate or
if I'm experiencing WordPress weirdness but since it hasn't shown up
there, I thought I'd share it here:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While the article might not make a strong case it's important to be wary of outside influences on education policies. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm a fan of a lot of what code.org does but speaking about outsiders in general…
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Bill Gates and Co. directly or indirecty gave us such delights like stack ranking teachers, improving, I mean evaluating, I mean firing teachers based on test scores of students they don't teach, more and more high stakes nonsense testing for kids, and  at least in NY the destruction of neighborhood schools. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They've also pushed the current charter movement that, aided by misleading stats appear successful but in truth are no better and frequently worse than public schools while not sharing back a single "best practice."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then we have private companies like the College Board and Pearson both of whom have an outsized influence on US Ed policy and curriculum.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't doubt the good intentions of code.org - as I said, I'm a fan. I am concerned when they and others take actions that can affect ed policy. I'm concerned when code.org representative pushes students to take an AP exam - not a great CS course with a great CS teacher but the actual exam. I'm even more concerned when code.org offers free PD when a school signs up for the PSAT8/9 - another high stakes meaningless test at taxpayer expense. For code.org it's a means to  get more CS ed out there. To me it's setting up a new cash cow for the college board at my expense and at students expense.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've seen many Ed Tech people, armed with the best intentions, enter the lions den – a school, district, or municipality only to see their best intentions corrupted in the name of cost cutting, profits, or politics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/outside-influences-on-cs-ed/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 15:40:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Three strikes and you're out or third time's a charm</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/three-times/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org9a1925b" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org9a1925b"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org9a1925b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CompSci4All/with_replies?lang=en"&gt;Brenda Wilkerson&lt;/a&gt;, Director of CS and IT education for Chicago public
schools was one of the keynote speakers at this year's CSTA
conference.  During her talk, she made a comment about it taking three
times through to get it right so if you're working hard and struggling
in your first year of teaching CS, it's not the time to give
up. Learning to teach takes time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
She's absolutely correct. I saw this in myself and I've seen this in
many other young teachers. First year through, your job is to
survive. This is when you rely on colleagues lesson plans, it you can
you shadow another teacher and in general do your best to give what
you can to your students while making it through the semester. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then, I often see something interesting. Year two is frequently a step
back. It was for me and I've seen this in many young teachers in many
subject areas. I'm guessing this happens because we feel we have a
year under our belt and then we overreach while trying to be
innovative and more effective.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In year three things start to improve again and then, if the teacher
continues to work at their craft, there's steady progress for years to
come. At the point, the teachers seem to better understand how to
experiment and grow as a teacher in a safer way while also
understanding that it's OK to have a bad day or even a bad unit -
there's usually time to recover.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's also interesting that while this progression is most obvious in
new teachers it also seems to take place with experienced teachers
teaching new courses. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All this means that teaching CS or any new subject takes time, effort,
and patience. It means young teachers shouldn't beat themselves up and
that supervisors need to be supportive and give the time and resources
to allow teachers to succeed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It also means that schools with high teacher churn - notably charter
chains create environments that are anything but conducive to allowing
society to build a cadre of expert teachers. It works for these
charter chains because they're exploiting the fact that they require a
small number of teachers as compared to large urban public schools so
can burn through teachers like gasoline and the fact that they're
judged only by standardized tests. The model is not sustainable if
privatizers get their wish and charters become the national norm.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, it's another reason for people to wise up to "leadership"
programs like Teach for America where candidates come in for a couple
years before moving on to "better" opportunities.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, if the third time's a charm, how about the flip side? After how long
a period of time should we expect CS teachers to really know their
subject area? I'd say three years is also probably right. Year one,
the teacher is just surviving but after that, I'd expect a teacher to
want to master their subject. When I taught math early on in my
career, I felt overmatched. Particularly at Stuyvesant. I was a CS
major, not a math major. What did I do? I sat in on colleagues
classes and did self study over the summer. Of course by the time I
got up to speed, at least to my standards, I was teaching compute
science.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, if you're a new CS teacher, why not take CS101 and data structures
over the summer instead of doing another scripted PD? Between local
and community colleges, at least in urban areas, this shouldn't be
a problem. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, is third time a charm? Three strikes and you're out? A bit of
both? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We have to give our new CS teachers the time and support to learn to
teach and to learn the subject area but at the same time, I think it's
reasonable to require that they do so given the resources.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/three-times/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2017 21:38:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>CS Ed advocates should pay attention to greater ed issues</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cd-ed-and-all-ed/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orga67b0d8" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orga67b0d8"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orga67b0d8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For anyone involved in K12 CS education, the past few years have been
a wild ride. When I first tried to make inroads in the DOE decades ago
I couldn't get through the door. Now, CS Education is everyone's
darling. It's really amazing. It's been a combination of grass roots
efforts by teachers, non profit education efforts such as &lt;a href="http://teals12k.org"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt;, advocacy of
groups like &lt;a href="http://code.org"&gt;Code.org&lt;/a&gt; and amazing individuals like &lt;a href="http://avc.com/2017/06/bearing-witness/"&gt;Fred Wilson&lt;/a&gt; who has
probably done more to move the needle of CS Ed in NY than any other 10
people combined.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While everyone agrees that to do CS education right at the K12 level
we need great teachers and lots of them, everyone also knows that
teachers voices are often unheard. The voices with the greatest weight
belong to the large non-profits, principals, superintendents and
local politicians. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today's post is a plea to those with voices to think about the effects
of their advocacy for CS Ed to the greater education landscape.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started thinking about this recently as I've been developing the
CS teacher certification programs for Hunter College. As I spoke to
people across the nation I found that many of the efforts to
developing teacher certification are what I call the "you take it you
teach it" model. You take an abbreviated version of APCS-A and APCS-P
and you're a certified CS teacher. Just about every real educator feels
that this is ludicrous. Some feel that this can be a first step - get
these credentials to get in the door and then you have three to five
years to really learn your subject and craft. I'm good with that but I
have a problem with anyone who says "you take it you teach it" is good
enough and I've heard of a number of regions that are seriously
considering it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why is this so bad and, I'd argue, dangerous? Not merely because we'll
end up with substandard CS teachers for the foreseeable future but
also because it undermines the teaching profession as a whole.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's no secret that public education is under attack. A number of
states including Wisconsin, Arizona, Oklahoma, New York and Michigan
have considered relaxing the standards to become a teacher to address
a teacher shortage. In their twisted logic, the politicians and
"reformers" say that we can't find enough qualified teachers because
we've made it an untenable career so let's lower standards. You can
argue that any current state's requirements are overly cumbersome but
that's another conversation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When CS Educators say that all that's needed to teach CS is to sit in
on a two week APCS institute is saying that to teach any subject you
don't need content expertise. This is dangerous to education as a
whole and when power players in the CS Ed movement don't speak up
otherwise or even worse that the stance that "you take it you teach
it" is OK, we're undermining teaching as a profession. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We need our heavy hitters to publicly and privately say that we need a
short term entry into the profession but we absolutely need plans and
pathways so that at the end of the day we have the best prepared
teachers in our schools for CS and for all subjects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another issue is when as CS Educators we don't pay attention to the
whole child. I was at a meeting of CSTA people  from about thirty
states a few years ago. Someone asked "how can we advocate for CS when
the school might use it as an excuse to get rid of music?" Cameron
Wilson, at the time a lobbyist for the ACM said something to the
effect of "I'm not concerned with other subjects, my concern is
getting CS into the schools." I get it, he was employed to stump CS
but we have to remember that we're only a piece of the puzzle. We want
a seat at the table but we have to make sure that the table is
populated with everyone needed to provide a great education for our
kids. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A final issue I'll mention here is how so many CS educators are so
close to the College Board. It was very disturbing that so many CS Ed
players were pushing for more students to take the APCS exam. Not the
class, not some other CS class but the APCS exam. AP is an extremely
controversial subject among teachers and many of us feel that too many
kids take too many AP classes and certainly too many exams. Remember,
the College Board is the organization that pushes things like the
PSAT8/9 another meaningless but high stakes exam inflicted upon our
kids at taxpayer expense. I understand that AP makes things easy -
they have courses, curricula, etc. but we've given the college board
an outsized influence on CS education and we're not paying attention
to their outsized influence on education in general. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm just a small time teacher. I don't have a national voice. I'm
urging those that do:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look into what's going on in greater education. Look at the way
public education has been under attack and why.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look at the side affects of our choices - who we partner with and
what policies we push.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We might not agree on the right path but everyone with a voice in CS
Education should be having hard conversations about this and then
strongly advocating for the positions they feel correct.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cd-ed-and-all-ed/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 23:51:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A friendly reminder to use the right language when describing CS</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/languages-or-cs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orga2f76fd" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orga2f76fd"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orga2f76fd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was part of this conversation the other day:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;When science teachers asked me if I taught AP Java I'd always respond by asking them if they taught AP Microscope.&lt;/p&gt;— Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/883327927831711745"&gt;July 7, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I always use that line to emphasize that I teach CS - a way of
thinking and problem solving and looking at the world. The languages
we use in our classes are tools to help us communicate ideas not the
ends but rather a means.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've spent the past couple of days at the CSTA conference. It's been a
lot of fun. I've been spending the time with old friends and meeting
new ones and as everyone who knows me knows - I love talking shop. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I overheard a conversation today. One CS teacher describing what they
did to a few others. I overheard:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We teach Scratch then Swift and C++ and also teach Python
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I heard statements like this describing programs more than a couple of
times. I know we're at a conference of CS Educators but even in this
community we have everything from beginners getting their feet wet to
hardcore computer scientists to everything in between.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We shouldn't be teaching languages as an ends unto themselves and the
majority of us don't.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What many of us do, though, is take the easy path and use the name of
a programming language to describe what we do rather than really
define what we do. This is why we hear "I teach Java" or "I teach a
class in Swift" even when the teacher teaching Java might really be
teaching Object Oriented program design and development or data
structures or something similar just using Java as the language or
tool.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I too fall into this trap but I try to catch myself. I try not to say
"I teach Scheme" but rather I'll say "I teach Scheme. Actually, we're
studying functional programming using Scheme as the language but for
convenience, I'll just say Scheme for the rest of this talk…."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The words we use to describe our field set the tone. If we're sloppy
and say "we teach Java," it's just like biology teacher saying "I
teach microscope." 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As we try to define our field in the K12 space and seek equal footing
with established subject areas it's important that we use the right
language so that other educators and policy makers don't get the wrong
idea.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>csed</category><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/languages-or-cs/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2017 01:17:47 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>