<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about education)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/education.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Feb 2017 13:38:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Should CS Ed be in bed with the College Board</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'm guessing my views  on this aren't very popular -that's OK, every
community needs a curmudgeon.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A few years ago, I cautioned if we weren't careful, once the big
players got involved, CS Ed would go the way of other disciplines, and
not in a good way. It looks like indeed we're well on our way down
that road.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've ranted before about things like non-profits, drop in and summer
programs. &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-07-learning-takes-time.html/#.WJXSS99vHmE"&gt;STEM Oil Salesmen&lt;/a&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
selling easy fixes, exciting kids and parents, using the Think Method
just like Professor Harold Hill only to send the kids off where they
can blame a future teacher for failure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've also ranted about teacher preparation and how all the rage is
short term, &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/scotland/#.WJXT999vHmE"&gt;Superficial PD and scripted curricula&lt;/a&gt;  and my concern that   
once the politicians can say CS is in the schools, &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-04-expedient-vs-good.html/#.WJXT7d9vHmE"&gt;we'll be done&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've been working towards getting CS to all students for most of my
career and while it's wonderful to see us getting closer to the goal,
I'm seeing more and more signs that my caution is becoming
reality. and CS Ed is going the way of other Ed - aligned to testing
and more to the whims of the power players and politicians than to
teachers and students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other week I noticed, &lt;a href="http://teacherblog.code.org/post/156278055294/ap-cs-principles-could-make-history-how-can-we"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by Code.org trying to encourage
more students to take the APCSP exam - not encourage more students
take the class or some other class or to have more students be exposed
to CS but to actually sit for the APCSP exam. That post was followed
by &lt;a href="http://teacherblog.code.org/post/156689658029/ask-your-cs-principles-students-to-star-in-our"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; which also highlights actually taking the exam.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This didn't sit well with me. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What does the exam do for the kid? It doesn't drive instruction - by
that time, any good teacher knows their student and is better served
by using their own &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-we-dont-trust-teachers/#.WJXbA99vHmE"&gt;assessments&lt;/a&gt;. The college credit thing? I'm
skeptical. Fewer and fewer schools are giving credit for APCSA let
alone this new CS0 non major course. Blanket credit? Since full time
students pay for a range of credits, I'm still skeptical
here. Placement? It's a course for non-majors - what exactly are you
placing out of?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reasons not to take the exam?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it doesn't do anything for the kid, why take it
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stress of taking the exam
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are other ways of placing out of courses once in college
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the expense
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a general rule, I'm against forcing students to sit for
AP exams. At the extreme case, since we've been brainwashed to think
that a school that has lots of kids sitting for exams is good, I've
seen at least one case of a principal having all his kids sit for, and
just about all &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;fail&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; AP Calculus - that is, get a 1 or 2 on the exam. This
principal had all his students take the exam, and only 2 scores were 3
or higher. This principal then parlayed his success into a higher
profile gig - he's moved up in the world while setting up his students
to fail.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This follows last year's announcement that code.org was &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-19-code-org-college-board.html/#.WJXbm99vHmE"&gt;partnering with
the College Board&lt;/a&gt; - offering PD to teachers for free if the schools
signed up their students for the PSAT 8/9 - another meaningless
exam. So, we get teacher training light &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.2" name="fnr.2" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fn.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; as long as the school pays for
the PSAT8/9 for every kid so that the kid can take yet another test
with really no value&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.3" name="fnr.3" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fn.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why should students pay for an AP exam that doesn't do anything for
them? Why should Jane Q Taxpayer pay for exams that only server to
enrich the College Board.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
True, The College Board is a big player. They already have much more
influence of American High School education than they should. It's
easy to climb on board the AP train for entre into our schools. The
question is, should we use positions of influence to push efforts that
might help our end but leave collateral damage to students and the public.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't doubt code.org's sincerity in wanting good CS in all schools
nor the efforts or value as an advocate for CS Education. I'm
concerned that the desire to win big and win now is moving us in a
direction that we'll regret years from now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;Not my term, but I really like it&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.2" name="fn.2" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fnr.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;If you think that PD based
teacher training is OK, ask yourself if you want your own child's
chemistry teacher to be a history teacher with a few weeks summer
training in chemistry&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.3" name="fn.3" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fnr.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I'm guessing the exam will be offered
during the day so teachers will proctor for free rather than be
allowed to, you know, teach their students.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 11:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>BS? - BA</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ba-bs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I didn't know Hunter College had computer science.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I heard that refrain more than once during my fall visits to high
schools. Part of the reason for this is due to Hunter CS's low
profile and small size in spite of its high quality.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Part, though, was also because of some misconceptions about Computer
Science programs. I'd hear things like "but they only offer a BA not a
BS," or "but Hunter isn't an engineering school."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've come to realize that we have to do a better job educating kids as
to what can come next after high school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not entirely sure why many assume that CS has to be under
engineering. When I was applying to college, most of my choices were
Arts and Science schools offering BAs in CS. Maybe it's because people don't
disagregate STEM subjects. Even though it's not a computer science
program many schools seem to associate FIRST robotics with computer
science. Likewise any class with even a modicum of coding becomes
computer science and as makerspaces and robotics are a percieved as
easy entry STEM classes that appear to be CS (something I'll rant
about in a future post), CS becomes associated with engineering.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's easy enough to explain the difference between a BA in CS and a BS
in CS and it's equally easy to show that you can have tremendous
success either way. All you have to do to show the validity of a BA in
CS is look at succesful people from places like NYU, Courant, Columbia
College (as opposed to Columbia Engineering), Cornell school of Arts
and Sciences, etc to balance successful people from the engineering schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I'm sure you know, I'm pretty high on Hunter CS and it's certainly
one of the best value CS educations out there. Personally, I'm a big believer in a
liberal arts education but in any case, as a community we have to do a
better job educating the high schools so that graduating seniors are
best informed when deciding on their futures.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ba-bs/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2017 01:14:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Selling out or getting a seat at the table</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/selling-out-or-a-seat-at-the-table/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
The other day, a friend posited a question on Facebook (paraphrased):
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If called upon, would you take a job in an administration who's policies you strongly
disagreed with?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Would you go work for an administration that you reviled in order to
get a seat at the table? To try to affect change from the inside or
would you consider yourself a sellout or worse, publicly promote
positions you disagree with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tough question.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The original question implied national level positions. I've never and
will never breath such rarefied air but I have had such experiences
closer to ground level, both with DOE projects and also in
conversations with some charter chains.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My take?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Anyone that knows me knows that I've had various dealings with the NYC
DOE and also knows that those dealings never resulted in outcomes I
was happy with. Over my time at Stuy, I had many philosophical
differences with Tweed (a common nickname for the NYC DOE as they're
housed in the old Tweed courthouse) and these were times where I tried
to play nice to have a seat at the table.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once I was at a meeting that also included a number of tech industry
heavy hitters. After the meeting, one came over to me. He knew me
by having worked with my former students. I knew him by reputation. He
asked "do they really want our thoughts on this or are we just here so
that they can do what they wanted in the first place and then parade us out 
to say that they consulted experts in the tech industry?" I honestly
didn't know at the time but I had my doubts as to the DOE's sincerity
in being open to either my views or this CTO's As it turned out, they
just did want to parade us. Later in the process, I was told in a back
room that it would be wise of me not to publicly voice my thoughts
about the direction of one particular project.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So there you have it. I was given a seat at the table but only as long
as my views mirrored the views of those in power. Not really much of a
seat. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've also sat down with some charter chains - chains that I've been
more than happy to denounce publicly. Why did I take the meetings?
Mostly to find out if I was mistaken in my position and if so, maybe
I could help them. Every time I've had such a meeting, however, I've
left the table with my feelings unchanged and knowing that I would
never willingly help them as I felt their practices were harmful to
kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In one case, I took the seat but failed to affect change. In the other
I refused the seat. I'll always take a meeting and I'll always work
with someone who wants to help kids and who has an open mind but I've
found that the more powerful the player, at least in education, the
more likely they are to just want confirmation of their own bias.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You might get a seat at the table but you also might end up lending
your reputation to a cause you don't believe in.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/selling-out-or-a-seat-at-the-table/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 00:47:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Evaluate teachers like they do in the real world</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/evaluating-teachers/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
This old article has been reposted a few times in my circles over the
past few weeks &lt;a href="http://educationnext.org/facadeofexcellence/"&gt;http://educationnext.org/facadeofexcellence/&lt;/a&gt;. It's from
2003 and complains about the lack of flexibility schools had back then
with regard to hiring and salary. The article is old and out of date
and the seniority system no longer holds for hiring but it does for
lay offs. The salary scale from back then, though, is still in place. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My friend Alex  asked my thought about how we might deal with evaluating
teacher quality. I thought I'd share them here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Alex listed a number of commonly tried and suggested options on
teacher evaluation and why they're all flawed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I haven't asked Alex's permission so I won't post his list and
comments here. Instead let's start with the boogeyman those that attack public
education always trot out – tenure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's get a couple of things straight - tenure is not a job for
life. For K12 teachers, it's the right to due process. That means you
can't be fired without cause. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I hear the free market capitalists out there already – "in the real
world, you're an at will employee, why do teachers need this due
process?" - I'll get to that down below. For now, let's look at a few
points on tenure:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First - you can fire a tenured teacher, you just have to document your
case. This means that the supervisor has to actually do their job.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Next - people can complain about rubber rooms and the time it takes to
fire one of these tenured teachers. That's because the DOE won't hire
sufficient hearing officers. In a recently resolved case, a friend of
mine - a terrific AP was finally returned to her post after she was
railroaded on false charges. She was in the rubber room for years. The
DOE kept delaying the process – all she wanted was to go to "trial"
since everyone knew she'd be exonerated - the fact that she was up on
charges at all speaks to why teachers need tenure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Next - teachers don't grant tenure, the administration does. Why are
all these horrible teachers being granted tenure? Stories abound of
administrators granting tenure to bad teachers so long as they
transfer to another school - who's to blame here? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, the contract that establishes tenure is jointly negotiated
by the teachers union and the city - no one ever seems to complain
about the city.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Next, let's talk about bonuses and competition. People in the business
world take the false assumption that everyone thinks, acts, and feels like
they do. Here's a surprising fact – teachers aren't in it for the
money. Sure, we'd like to make a little more - perhaps enough to
actually  live in a decent apartment and not need a second job to make
ends meet -  but no one went into teaching to get rich. Teachers are in
it to uplift ALL their students and their school as a whole. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now let's look at the model currently in vogue - value added
measures. Besides the fact that they're arbitrary and don't work (see
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-09-06-why_i_might_no_longer_be_an_effective_teacher.md/"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-25-effective-teacher-2.md/"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;) they're nothing like how people are evaluated
in the real world.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How are people evaluated in regular jobs? As far as I know, they're
evaluated by their managers and bosses - possibly also by their peers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Funny thing - that's how teachers used to be evaluated before all this
nonsense brought about by the "reformers." Of course, no one will
admit to this. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Did this system work? For the most part, but not entirely. Why were
there problems? Because, unlike a business, principals are not
necessarily incentivized to have the best teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Schools and principals are evaluated on ridiculous metrics - the same
standardized tests they use to evaluate teachers. To look at a small
piece – to graduate high school, kids need to pass at least one math
regents and pass three years of math classes. To be "college ready" a
student still only needs to pass one math regents and take at least
one year of geometry or trig.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This means that as far as math is concerned, a principal is
incentivized to have a math department that can get their kids through
the algebra regents. Here's how this frequently plays out. The kids
take algebra over two years and then passes the exam. The kids take
geometry as their third year. They don't have to pass the regents, but
it appears that in order to increase a student's chances of passing
that exam, classes don't teach proof - the most important and hardest
part of the class. Why not? Because it's easier to pass the exam by
learning most of the other stuff.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here we have a school where the incentive is to hire teachers that can
teach to the algebra regents and that's about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's at a school with a low performing population. In a higher
performing school, the kids will do well on the standardized tests
regardless of teacher quality so there's no incentive to hire the
best. Even if that's what they want to do, there's no way to know if
they're actually doing it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back to why teachers need due process. Since principals aren't held
accountable in any reasonable way, teachers can't be. The end result
is that teachers are subject to abuses by principals. I myself was
once brought up on bogus charges raised by a principal (not a Stuy
one) who wanted to make trouble. Without due process, I would be out
of a job. So would many others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The answer? To me it's figure out how to hold principals
accountable. In Alex's Facebook post he  mentions evaluation by
college and workforce success but that has a slow feedback loop. The
truth is, education does have a slow feedback loop. Schools, however,
exist for along time and principals should have tenure periods of more than
just a couple of years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My feelings? Why not look at graduates succeeding in college or on the
tax rolls? This wouldn't be perfect but it would be a start. While NY
can't count on private universities sharing accurate information in a
timely manner there should be a way of tracking if a high school
graduate is enrolled in a SUNY or CUNY one, two, three, or four
semesters after graduation. Create a baseline for a school and start
from there. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If principals were actually accountable in a reasonable
way they'd have incentive to have the best teachers. Then we can get
back to the old system which was indeed the way the "real world"
works.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/evaluating-teachers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 21:47:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Science Talent Search winners do not a great school make</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/dont-focus-on-sts/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over on Facebook, my Alma Mater and long time employer, Stuyvesant
High School seems to be making a big push to up it's Regeneron Science
Talent Search game. For those of you who aren't familiar, that's the
latest incarnation of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regeneron_Science_Talent_Search"&gt;the Westinghouse Science Talent Search&lt;/a&gt; from
back in my day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It seems that Stuyvesant hasn't had that many semi finalists,
finalists, and winners over the past few years and isn't happy about
it. The result is a bunch of social media reminding us of old winners
and trying to raise funds to get us back to the glory days.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'd rather they spent there time, energy, and money elsewhere.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I was a young teacher, I was enamored with those types of
results. When my kids did well on a USACO competition, for example, I
felt pretty good about myself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then one day, I had an epiphany. I was looking over the results of a
big USACO competition. My kids came in 4th, 5th, and I think
fifteenth. I was feeling pretty good about myself but then I realized
that Dan, Evan, and Jon - my three top scorers would probably have
done just fine without me. Sure, I do believe that I was able to help
them in their growth as both computer scientists and as people but
they were already off the charts smart. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The same is true about the Science Talent Search (STS) winners. A
friend of mine ran Stuyvesant's math research class for a number of
years. He had a pretty impressive string of finalists and winners. How
did he do it? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify Stuyvesant's top talent - the ones already most likely to
succeed in the STS.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pawn them off on a lab or professor.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Stuy class, by and large, did little or nothing for these kids yet
we would hold them up as shining examples of how wonderful we were.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I had my epiphany, I started designing my intro class and
focusing my efforts on the whole school population. The results?
Scores of people succeeding in tech who never would have considered it
otherwise.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While my super high achievers have indeed gone  on to successful lives
and careers, some of my most successful graduates, by any number of
measures have been the students who would otherwise have gotten lost
in the crowd at Stuy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The truth is, many of Stuyvesant's STS winners would have been STS
winners regardless of where they went. We may or may not have helped
them along the way but STS results are not the measure of a great
school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Improving a school, any school, for all its students might not help in
those bogus national ratings but that really should be what we're
about.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/dont-focus-on-sts/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2016 20:22:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Hunter CS is so important to NYC</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-important/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
If you know me you know that my morning reads include a visit over to
&lt;a href="http://avc.com"&gt;avc.com&lt;/a&gt;, Today, &lt;a href="http://avc.com/2016/10/cranes/"&gt;Fred's post&lt;/a&gt; talked about development and progress,
evolution, if you would, in the city. Although not directly related,
it got me thinking about gentrification. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To me, gentrification all too often seems to result in pushing out
people and business that were there during the hard times.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We don't need to force out long time residents that can no longer make
rent - we need to uplift communities with pathways to towards greater
economic opportunity.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Those of us in CS Education, each in our own way, are trying to help
build those pathways.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Return readers know that I've ranted about some of the popular magic
bullets. I've periodically talked about my concerns over code schools
but even at their best they represent a workforce program for the well
to do. I've also talked about efforts like P-Tech which sound good,
but besides the fact that &lt;a href="https://garyrubinstein.wordpress.com/2016/10/06/p-tech-principal-responds/"&gt;the emperor has no clothes&lt;/a&gt;, is the school
really preparing kids for opportunities in their own neighborhoods or
in data centers far from home?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are some workforce programs like &lt;a href="https://perscholas.org/"&gt;Per Scholas&lt;/a&gt; that I really like
and respect but they're limited in what they can do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What does that leave us with? The traditional path – college.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In terms of tech, New York City has some amazing colleges. You ask
most people, they'll come back with NYU, Columbia. Great institutions
but &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;very&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; expensive.  Not everyone can afford $75,000 a year and
not everyone can afford to go into hundreds of thousands of debt.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is why Hunter CS is so important. Actually CUNY but I can only
affect my little corner of the world. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hunter College has a really nice CS program and department. It's small
and has flown under the radar but it's one of the reasons I came over
to Hunter. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of my responsibilities at Hunter is to develop our new honors CS
program and to connect all of  Hunter CS to the tech sector in NY. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I haven't written much about what's been going on but that will change
int the months to come. Suffice it to say that to uplift our
communities we need real, affordable educational opportunities and in
terms of tech, education that leads to real opportunities in
our city's tech sector.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm convinced that Hunter College can be a game changer for the wealth
of young talent we have in New York and for our tech sector.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-important/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 23:13:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Computational Thinkers in Scotland</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/scotland/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I'm way behind on my &lt;a href="http://cacm.acm.org/"&gt;Communications of the ACM&lt;/a&gt;. I generally only read
them when I use my trainer in the mornings and with summer running and
outside riding, I'm still on the December 2015 issue.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This morning, I read a viewpoint by Jeremy Scott and Alan Bundy on &lt;a href="http://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2015/12/194638-creating-a-new-generation-of-computational-thinkers/abstract"&gt;a
program in Scotland&lt;/a&gt;. If you're an ACM member, and if you're a CS
practitioner, student, academic, or teacher you should be, you can read the piece for details.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
Me? I noticed a number of similarities between what Bundy and Scott
described and efforts here in the USA including some of the red flags.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not here to talk about the program described in detail or their
successes and failures. I don't have enough information to fairly
comment on that. I'm here in my usual role of curmudgeon to highlight
common red flags that if unheeded could cost all of us the opportunity
to get really great CS Ed to all of our students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One red flag right away were a number of references to the program
being curriculum and materials driven, not teacher driven. The
viewpoint states that materials "were designed to be used by even
non-specialist teachers." We see the same thing here in the USA and
not just in CS Ed. Teaching overall is being devalued with the elite
pushing programs that handcuff good teachers to a script (which leads
students towards "success" in passing a nonsense standardized exam)
all the while sending their own kids to elite private schools with
knowledgeable teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know i didn't want my kids to be taught chemistry history or any
other subject by a teacher that hasn't studied the content yet here we
go saying it's okay for CS. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The counter argument is that we have to do something now and we'll do
better later. We all go in with the best of intentions but more often
than not, once a politician has their sound bite and once a cheap
apparent solution is in place, it's good enough and we're done. I
ranted about that a while back both &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-04-expedient-vs-good.html/#.V-5UqN9vGAk"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-07-learning-takes-time.html/#.V-5Uot9vGAk"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. To their credit,
Bundy and Scott talk a bit about this concern in the piece.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The piece also said "It is also necessary to employ a pedagogy that is
informed by the latest research into the most effective ways to teach
computing." This sounds good but the truth is, education research
doesn't have the best reputation among educators. Last month, I
asked one of the best math teachers around what was being bandied
about as best practices in math education according to "the
research?" He basically said "the research says do &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;fad du jour&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
but that doesn't work for me so I just do &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;actually good technique&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the years, I've spoken to many teachers and by and large the best
ones discredit "the research." Of course, my comment will be
discredited by ed researchers saying that "you're just giving
anecdotes" but then, if I did the same thing while employed as a
researcher, did a couple of surveys and submitted it for publication,
then it would be "research." So much of teaching is a craft and the
truth is, practitioners know best.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Related to this is authentication by citing authority. Particularly
dangerous in our field because many people with little to no real
background in teaching CS are anointed as experts and thought leaders
(see this post: &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-26-self-appointed-experts.html/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). In this case, the viewpoint cites Cameron
Fadjo. I've only met Cameron once or twice and he seems like a sharp
guy but when he was given the post of Director of Software Engineering
for NYC, according to his linked in profile, he had neither taught k12
nor had any real CS background.  This is of course the profile of many
CS Education thought leaders. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My overall take. It sounds like just like here, Scotland has people
trying to make a difference and trying to do good. It also sounds like
they're falling into the same traps and pitfalls as we are on this
side of the Atlantic.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/scotland/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2016 11:28:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Impostor Syndrome - I'm not good enough</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/imposters/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I've been meaning to comment on these tweets for a while:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;I went to high school with some scary smart people. Never made math team. Didn't get into honors math. Thought I wasn't good at it.&lt;/p&gt;— Stanislav Nikolov (@snikolov) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/snikolov/status/748660381392871424"&gt;June 30, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zamansky"&gt;@zamansky&lt;/a&gt; :D&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;that's the thing though you can get such an inferiority complex by always comparing yourself to others &lt;a href="https://t.co/LvaMjp1WVf"&gt;https://t.co/LvaMjp1WVf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Stanislav Nikolov (@snikolov) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/snikolov/status/748918417667727360"&gt;July 1, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Stan, of course, is one of the most talented people I know. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It reminded me of a conversation I had with my colleague and friend
Jim last year. I had just recieved an email from a former student
turned friend. We were trying to find some time to catch up.  I told
Jim I had just heard from this young lady and Jim replied "I remember
her, she's awesome. Really smart." I mention this because the
individual we were talking about, while to us, extremely talented in
addition to being just a terrific person spent much of her career
living in self doubt.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Meantime, I was having a conversation with another friend and the
topic turned to impostor syndrome and the desire to make it a thing of
the past.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Problem is, I don't know if that will ever be the case. I'm
approaching 50 and have a career of good work behind me but I still
find myself questioning my credentials, work, and ability. Then I realized I wasn't alone
when I read &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/RobertTalbert"&gt;Robert Talbert's&lt;/a&gt; recent &lt;a href="http://rtalbert.org/blog/2016/tenure-second-time"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; about his going through
the tenure process for a second time and "learning through this process
that I have not outrun impostor syndrome and probably never will."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Stan's tweets tell part of the story. When we surround ourselves with
smart, accomplished people, we sometimes feel we don't measure
up. I've found that for the most part, the extremely accomplished
people I've worked with are very unassuming and low key. They seem to
operate assuming that  everyone else is at least as capable and quick as
they. I recall &lt;a href="http://paulgraham.com/articles.html"&gt;Paul Graham&lt;/a&gt; talking about this in an essay but
I don't remember which one. The problem is, if you don't understand
their sincerity, you end up feeling even more inadequate. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It gets worse when we start comparing ourselves to some unreal
composite. I remember feeling pretty stupid back when I was younger
comparing myself with others. The problem was that I clearly didn't
measure up to the best math kid, or the best computer kid, the best
fencer, the best violinist, etc. Now, the best math kid might have
been a lousy athlete and the best fencer, a so so mathematician, but
to me, I was comparing myself with this composite super human. No
wonder I never measured up. Eventually, though, I realized three
things. First, there's always someone better at something and always
someone worse. Second, that's not the true value of ones worth as a
person, and three, I bring some good stuff to the table and I should
be (and am) content with that
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, I still struggle with impostor syndrome but at the end of the day,
it just serves as a reminder to look back on what I've done and what
I've learned in the process.  I start out in question but in the end,
leave confident. Maybe the trick isn't to eliminate impostor syndrome
but rather to understand and contain it. We don't want to live in fear
and anxiety but both are useful emotions when we control them and not
the reverse.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's probably good when we question ourselves and re-evaluate our
positions - we just have to make sure as we're bringing new people
into the tech fold that we foster acceptance and confidence  and when
impostor syndrome sets in that it can be channeled into a positive
and not scare people away.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>community</category><category>education</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/imposters/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 17:53:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Federal Aid for Code Schools - is this a good thing?</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/fed-aid-for-code-schools/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I saw this headline earlier today: &lt;a href="http://www.inc.com/salvador-rodriguez/coding-bootcamps-just-got-a-big-boost.html"&gt;The U.S. Just Made a Bold Move to Improve Diversity in Tech&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The article talks about a program by which a number of code schools
will be able to accept federal student aid. I don't know if we're
talking student loans or  grants but I'm not sure it matters.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The headline sounds great. I'm not so sure that this is a good thing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My thinking's evolved over the years but right now, everything tells
me that public funds and for profit education don't mix.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What we, more often than not, end up with is a cash cow for a private concern. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Example one: The edTPA - a required exam for teacher licensing, at
least in NY. Prospective teachers pay hundreds of dollars to pass this
gatekeeper. Pearson, a private company (and not even an American one)
is essentially in charge of teacher licensing. They make the
assessments, they grade them, they decide who passes. A foreign
company is deciding who teaches our kids and at great expense to those
prospective teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We'd be much better off going back to the old days. To become a
teacher, you had to pass through "The board of examiners." Basically,
to get your permanent license you had to do an oral defense. Teachers
would be placed in a room of principals, supervisors, and master
teachers for an open grilling. It was cheaper and MUCH more
effective. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Example two: The PSAT 8/9, PSAT, and SAT. These are exams that tell us
one thing: how kids will do on future PSAT and SAT tests. They're not
good predictors of college success but the college board (a non-profit
in name only) has convinced us, or at least "convinced" our
politicians of the exams importance. So, rather than having
individuals make a choice as to whether or not to take these exams, NY
forks over who knows how much money per year so that our kids can take
a test with the belief that the exam will mystically make them college
ready. To make matters worse, students lose a day of instruction and
teachers have to proctor the exam instead of teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Example three: Common core tests. Made in secret, graded in secret
with cut off scores designed after the fact. Absolutely no educational
value but once again, public funds flow freely into testing companies.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem is that these private concerns never really have to show
results and they're never held accountable and since the money we pay
them is hidden in city and state budgets, the taxpayer is none the wiser.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what about code schools?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In a similar vein, money will flow from the government to the code
schools. The question is, do they really have the secret sauce.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have lots of friends who run and work in code schools and have met
many more. Some code schools are trying to really educate and some
not so much. In any case, let's take a look.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You frequently hear about the success stories but for every one of
those, you can also find a manager talking about the fact that the
code school graduate can't do anything other than ape the narrow tool
that they were exposed to in the three or so months at the code
school. So, the truth is that results are probably a mixed bag.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Is this good? Well, when you consider the typical code school MO it
really isn't.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To attend a for profit code school you have to not only afford the
tuition but also be able to sustain yourself for the duration of the
program. That makes most code schools options for the well to do -
those already well positioned for success.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then they make the candidates go through pre-work – frequently online
course work. So, before you even step into a code school, they know
you're likely going to succeed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once in, they train the candidates in a narrow slice of tech. I've
talked to a number of code school leaders about that. I've asked how
well the kids would be able to adapt given the constraints of their 3
month or so training. The typical answer was that the candidate could
just re-up and pay again to learn the next limited time only skill.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Should taxpayer dollars go to this? Probably not. There's no
indication that code schools can provide meaningful long lasting
education to even those who are best prepared to learn on their
own. Whats' more, we haven't seen evidence that they have the answers
for the under-served. Combine that with government's history of not
keeping an eye on and not holding accountable private education
providers, I think we're just setting up a new line of corporate
welfare that will, on the surface help some but it is in no way the
answer. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Too often public/private means that the private entity gets the money
and the public gets stuck holding the bag. Better would be to have
tech companies foot the bill. Some coding schools already do
this. Tech companies that are happy with coding school graduates can
finance the program. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What we should be doing is focusing on things like community
colleges. Organizations that are supposed to be real, long term,
community centers. With moderate tweaking, there's no reason why a
community college, not to mention 4 year schools, couldn't provide far
superior preparation than even the best code school.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/fed-aid-for-code-schools/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 19:42:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ed Disruption - why it's different</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ed-disrupt-why-diff/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Earlier today I read &lt;a href="http://www.eliothorowitz.com/blog/2016/07/25/innovate-vs-appropriate/"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/eliothorowitz"&gt;Eliot Horowitz&lt;/a&gt;, founder and CTO of MongoDB.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Eliot titled the post "Innovate vs Appropriate" and talks about the
importance of knowing when to come up with something new vs when to
use the accepted tool, technique, or method. Eliot, of course is
discussing this as it applies to MongoDB and it's well worth a read
but it got me thinking about the ever popular need to "disrupt"
education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've witnessed this disruption or Ed Reform for the last decade
plus. The basic notion that public education isn't working so we need
to disrupt things. We've suffered through:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vouchers
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charters
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Online "learning" replacing teachers
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teach for America and other temp type efforts
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merit pay
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VAM for teacher evaluation
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and more
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These disruptions are brought to you by your friendly neighborhood
billionaire "philanthropist" or your politicians.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
By and large, they haven't worked.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Bill Gates got us to close down community schools and create small
ones. While we did need more small schools, overall it didn't work
(&lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/marc-epstein/small-schools-miracle-or_b_2641400.html?utm_hp_ref=new-york"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/answer-sheet/wp/2014/06/09/how-much-bill-gatess-disappointing-small-schools-effort-really-cost/%0A"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;). VAM teacher evaluation is &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/answer-sheet/wp/2014/06/09/how-much-bill-gatess-disappointing-small-schools-effort-really-cost/%0A"&gt;arbitrary and capricious&lt;/a&gt;,
merit pay has &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/answer-sheet/post/ravitch-why-merit-pay-for-teachers-doesnt-work/2011/03/29/AFn5w9yB_blog.html"&gt;never worked&lt;/a&gt;, nor does the &lt;a href="http://educationnext.org/online-charters-mostly-dont-work-forum-virtual-schools-greg-richmond/"&gt;online thing&lt;/a&gt;. Meanwhile, charter
schools by and large &lt;a href="http://www.nea.org/home/32999.htm"&gt;don't do better&lt;/a&gt; than public schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Rather than saving our schools, these efforts have lowered teacher
morale and done little for our most vulnerable children.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what's the difference between ed disruption and the tech world?
Well, for starters, those disrupting education totally ignore the very
advice that Eliot posted about today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Disruption to and of our public schools hasn't been a matter
appropriating what works and innovating what needs to be innovated but rather
a playground for pet projects of politicians and well meaning rich
folk.  Rather than looking at something simple that works, like, say,
smaller class sizes, we get computerized testing. Instead of
experienced teachers, we get inexperienced newbies that leave after
their commitment is up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why the difference? It hit me while reading Eliot's post. When a
founder is "disrupting" he has skin in the game - it's his company -
sink or swim. Not so for education reformers. Politicians merely need
to be re-elected.Sso as long as something looks good short term, it is
good. Those who disrupt schools are never held accountable. We got
small schools and VAM from among other places, Bill Gates. He admitted
his reforms didn't work but was there any penalty for disrupting so
many lives? Nope. For politicians, it's the same story. As Mayor Mike
Bloomberg once said "If they don't like my education policy, they can
boo me at parades."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Can we fix this? Sure, but not unless those forcing the changes have
real skin in the game. Will it happen? I'm not holding my breath.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>disruption</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ed-disrupt-why-diff/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2016 23:32:01 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>