<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about events</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/events.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-04-18T21:34:41Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/events.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/events/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Competitions and Hackathons</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hs-competitions/</id>
    <updated>2018-04-06T17:22:15-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-04-06T17:22:15-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hs-competitions/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org36b3fdf" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org36b3fdf"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org36b3fdf"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Today's the last day of spring break. After the weekend it's back to
the grind. It really hasn't been much of a spring break. The rain and
the snow made for very little spring and between working on the Hunter
/ CUNY2X Internship program and reviewing applications for my Hunter
Daedalus CS Honors program there has been very little break.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today was no exception - I spent much of the day working but I did
take a few hours to head over to Cornell Tech on Roosevelt
Island. Why? To check out the &lt;a href="https://www.cs.cornell.edu/events/cornell-high-school-programming-contest"&gt;Cornell High School Progrmaming
Contest&lt;/a&gt; - first time in NYC.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was invited by my friend and organizer &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/diane_levitt"&gt;Diane Levitt&lt;/a&gt;. I only stayed
for an hour or so but it was shaping up to be a great event. It looked
like around a hundred kids from maybe a dozen or so schools and it was
run simultaneously with high schoolers on the Ithaca campus where the
competition has been running for a few years. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The format was similar to other high school programming competitions
I've been to. Teams of two or three sharing a single computer to solve
a number of programming problems that varied in difficulty. You can
check out a few "warm up" problems on the competition &lt;a href="https://www.cs.cornell.edu/events/cornell-high-school-programming-contest"&gt;site&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The competition reminded me of the &lt;a href="https://www.sjcny.edu/long-island/academics/programs-departments/mathematics-and-computer-science/programming-competition"&gt;St. Joseph's High School
Programming Competition&lt;/a&gt; held every spring but in NYC so more
convenient for city dwellers. I went to the St. Joseph's competition a
few times and I'm a big fan. I particularly like the awards luncheon
after the competition. If I were to make one suggestion to the
organizers there it would be to mix the seating at the luncheon so
that kids get to sit with and spend time with kids from different
schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These competitions contrast nicely with hackathons like &lt;a href="http://stuyhacks.com/%0A"&gt;StuyHacks&lt;/a&gt;
for which I acted as a judge a couple of months ago. Competitions are, well,
competitive. Hackathons can be but don't have to be. Competitions are
about solving problems, hackathons, building things. Each can speak to
a different kind of student. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Both competitions and hackathons have problems as well. On the competition
side we have:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schools with more developed CS programs dominate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A single strong student can carry a team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some kids don't like or do well in the competitive environment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And on the hackathon side:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;24 hours of straight work is just a bad idea and a bad thing to
encourage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big advantage to teams that bring prefab code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big advantage to kids with experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Both types of events are great opportunities for young
programmers. They're celebrate academic work, bring tech kids together
as a community and when done right are
something of a CS party. Neither type of event speaks to all kids so
it's great to have both competitions and hackathons to go along with
other types of events available for our kids. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another thing I love abut the Cornell and St, Joseph's competitions
along with StuyHacks is that they're open to all schools and hence all
students. There's room for the novice and also the expert and you
don't have to be in a particular school or program to participate.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are other events beyond these three. There are online
competitions like &lt;a href="http://www.usaco.org/"&gt;the USACO&lt;/a&gt;, competitions on HackerRank and Topcoder,
&lt;a href="http://halite.io"&gt;Halite&lt;/a&gt; along with it's hackathon which is great but specialized and in
person ones that are farther away like the &lt;a href="http://pclassic.org/%0A"&gt;PClassic&lt;/a&gt; in Philidelphia
and Rowan's &lt;a href="http://elvis.rowan.edu/rupc/%0A"&gt;HS programming competition&lt;/a&gt; in New Jersey but it's great to
see great local opportunities like these emerging and hopefully
running for years to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="competitions" label="competitions"/>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="events" label="events"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
