<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about hunter)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/hunter.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 17:15:19 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>2017 in review - Hunter Undergraduate CS</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2017-review-hunter-cs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org80491be" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org80491be"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org80491be"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I usually don't do year in review posts. At Stuy, not much changed
year after year so I never felt it worth summarizing the past and
projecting the future. At Hunter, now that I'm a couple of years in,
projects are really picking up steam so I think it's worth talking
about them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of my two major missions at Hunter was to build a CS Honors
program and raise the profile of Hunter's undergraduate CS program in
general. Hunter had a strong CS program before I joined the team it's
just that few people knew about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My goal is to see Hunter become the "go to" institution for
undergraduate CS in New York City before my time is done.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is an extremely important mission. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are other strong CS options besides Hunter but compare the costs:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Institution&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Annual Tuition&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;NYU&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;$50,464&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;NYY Tandon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;$48,750&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Columbia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;$54,504&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Hunter&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;$6,530&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org579e945" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org579e945"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org579e945"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hunter is about one tenth the cost.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
True, if you're wealthy this isn't a problem and if you're at the
bottom of the economic ladder you might get a full ride but if you
fall into that category where you earn more than the financial aid
people think is "poor" but are clearly not rich you're left in a bad place. This seems
particularly true for New Yorkers as our income seems higher than that
of people from other parts of the country but our cost of living is
higher as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My wife and I are both career public educators. No one would confuse a
family of two working teachers as upper class but we were granted no
financial aid for our kids. The alternatives without a great public
option are to have saved for our entire lives and now liquidate those
savings or go into tremendous debt.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This alone makes the mission critical. Add to that the accessibility
issue - elite private institutions only have to concern themselves
with whatever slice of the population they choose to accept. We are
charged with providing a top flight education to all - be they the
high achievers, the late bloomers, the struggling students or anyone 
else.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what's happened in the past year?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, the Daedalus honors program is developing nicely. In our first
year we had a cohort of 12. This past year 27. I haven't seen the
applicant pool yet - Hunter applications are open until the end of
January, but I'm hoping to bring in an even larger cohort this year. I
spent a good amount of time this fall visiting high schools to talk
about Hunter CS and CS options in general. Not as many as I'd like but
more than during year one. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had classes, trips, and special events but more important was that
the cohort is starting to form a community and the students want it to
be a community that includes ALL of Hunter CS, not just the honors
students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They've started a once a week Dojo where students can work on projects
and interact and we're starting an evening speaker series in
the Spring. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Overall there's a vibe of excitement and an energy around Hunter CS
that I've been told hasn't been there before.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my class, I've been introducing a number of real world practices
that are usually not covered in undergraduate CS and we're starting to
talk about bringing those practices into the non-honors sections.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, we've started to partner with the New York Tech
community. We're bringing together the Hunter students and the tech
professionals to raise awareness outside of Hunter of what our
students can do and to best prepare our students for their next
steps. These partnerships, in addition to internship possibilities
have led to us planning some great things this coming semester
incuding:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;workshops such as how to work on an open source project or how to do
a code review.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having industry mentors at our local Dojo sessions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mixer events to educate our students as to the variety of pathways
they can follow when they graduate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This past year set the stage but there will be some challenges moving
forward.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The biggest one is continued outreach to high schools. Getting to the
students and their parents to let them know that we have a great
program. It's also about convincing them to come to Hunter. Back in
the day CUNY was "the poor man's Harvard" but open enrollment in the
1970s killed that reputation. CUNY has been making it's way back and
Hunter has many excellent programs but reputations are decades in the
making and at Hunter CS we're just starting to get the word out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other big challenge will be with time. Right now, for the most
part, I'm a team of one. I have tremendous support from my colleagues
but they all have their own full time obligations and the overall
growth in Hunter CS has already put a strain on personnel and
resources.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In spite of the challenges, I'm not complaining. This has been an
exciting year for Hunter CS and an exciting year for me to be a part
of it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>hunter</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2017-review-hunter-cs/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 15:05:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hunter College - Honors CS</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's been a while since my last post and a while since I started at
Hunter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Time to share a bit about what I've been up to.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the better kept secrets in New York City is Hunter College's
computer science program. It's been around for years and it's been
that way for years. In fact, when I was looking to get my masters
degree back in the mid nineties I carefully researched all of the
area's MS in CS programs. It came down to Hunter College and Courant
Institute at NYU. I was going to go with Hunter since the programs
seemed comparable and Hunter was far more affordable but I had to go
with NYU due to class schedules. Too many of the Hunter offerings were
to early in the day and I had my full time teaching job to consider.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hunter isn't currently offering their Masters program but their
Bachelor of Arts program is alive and well, it's just that people
don't know about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Part of my job is to change that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, not really, part of my job is to add my piece to the puzzle. The
rest will take care of itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My piece? It's all about creating a tech culture, tying into the NY
Tech ecosystem, and filling in the gaps that are shared by just about
every college computer science program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How do we do it? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The long term plan is that we're starting a new CS Honors program. In
the fall, I'll be teaching and mentoring a group of entering
undergrads. We'll have workshops, trips, activities. You name it. I'll
also be teaching them modified versions of our courses with the hope
of bringing some of my modifications back to the rest of the student
body. Things like integrating real tools and professional techniques
into what is already a solid academic program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the mean time, I'm getting to know Hunter's current CS students and
working to energize the existing community. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We already had an amazing event hosted at &lt;a href="http://yext.com"&gt;Yext&lt;/a&gt;. We had a panel and
mixer with representatives from about a dozen companies talking to the
kids about the possibilities ahead of them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We've also set up a couple of workshops in house.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm also starting to talk to friends at companies across the city to
plan out both curriculum and programs to set up our kids to
succeed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My goal is that within five years, I want people to realize that
Hunter CS is the place to be for CS Education in NYC. Not everyone can
afford the 40K and up private college tuition and there's no reason to
when you can get a great CS education with ties to the tech community
at CUNY prices.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you want to help, drop me a note. We're looking to start something
very special and you have a chance to be a part of it.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>hunter</category><category>misc</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs.html/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>