<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about misc)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/misc.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jun 2017 00:04:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Advent of Code 2016</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Once again, it's time for &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; - a series of small
programming problems released once a day. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wrote a bit about it &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-15-advent.html/"&gt;last&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-17-im-an-idiot.html/#.WEMqBB9ieYQ"&gt;year&lt;/a&gt; and you can still find last years
problems &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/2015/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's only day three but so far, all of the problems look really nice
for students in APCS-A or any similar intro course. I'm thinking of
looking at a couple of the problems this week with my class at Hunter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I didn't think about this much last year but one thing I really like
about the competition is that each problem comes in two parts. You're
first presented with the problem and the input and once you put in the
correct answer, you're presented with part two.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This can be annoying at times, particularly when it requires a large
code rewrite but it also means that well designed, not too specific
solutions are rewarded. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not quite the same as changing the specs on a project mid way but
it does encourage thinking about more than just solving a super
specific problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Check out &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; and see if it's something you or your classes
might enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>apcs</category><category>cs</category><category>misc</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 20:25:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hunter College - Honors CS</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's been a while since my last post and a while since I started at
Hunter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Time to share a bit about what I've been up to.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the better kept secrets in New York City is Hunter College's
computer science program. It's been around for years and it's been
that way for years. In fact, when I was looking to get my masters
degree back in the mid nineties I carefully researched all of the
area's MS in CS programs. It came down to Hunter College and Courant
Institute at NYU. I was going to go with Hunter since the programs
seemed comparable and Hunter was far more affordable but I had to go
with NYU due to class schedules. Too many of the Hunter offerings were
to early in the day and I had my full time teaching job to consider.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hunter isn't currently offering their Masters program but their
Bachelor of Arts program is alive and well, it's just that people
don't know about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Part of my job is to change that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, not really, part of my job is to add my piece to the puzzle. The
rest will take care of itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My piece? It's all about creating a tech culture, tying into the NY
Tech ecosystem, and filling in the gaps that are shared by just about
every college computer science program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How do we do it? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The long term plan is that we're starting a new CS Honors program. In
the fall, I'll be teaching and mentoring a group of entering
undergrads. We'll have workshops, trips, activities. You name it. I'll
also be teaching them modified versions of our courses with the hope
of bringing some of my modifications back to the rest of the student
body. Things like integrating real tools and professional techniques
into what is already a solid academic program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the mean time, I'm getting to know Hunter's current CS students and
working to energize the existing community. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We already had an amazing event hosted at &lt;a href="http://yext.com"&gt;Yext&lt;/a&gt;. We had a panel and
mixer with representatives from about a dozen companies talking to the
kids about the possibilities ahead of them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We've also set up a couple of workshops in house.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm also starting to talk to friends at companies across the city to
plan out both curriculum and programs to set up our kids to
succeed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My goal is that within five years, I want people to realize that
Hunter CS is the place to be for CS Education in NYC. Not everyone can
afford the 40K and up private college tuition and there's no reason to
when you can get a great CS education with ties to the tech community
at CUNY prices.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you want to help, drop me a note. We're looking to start something
very special and you have a chance to be a part of it.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>hunter</category><category>misc</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs.html/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2016 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Leaving Stuyvesant</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-23-leaving-stuy.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Almost twenty six years. That's how long I've been a NYC public school
teacher. Most of that time at my alma mater, Stuyvesant. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of years ago, the school paper wrote up an overview of my
career. I re-posted it &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/09/17/stuycs-spectator.html#.Vnqfxh8Sr0o"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I'm somtimes amazed at where we are now
and how we got here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Regulars here also know my frustrations. To Stuy, I'm an
interchangeable, generic math teacher and the DOE has shown no
interested in supporting what we've built. I've also written about my
concerns with the direction the city's going with respect to K12 CS
education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was time for me to start the next phase of my career.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm happy to say that I will be joining Hunter College in late
		January. I'll be developing their CS Teacher Ed program and also
		working with their computer science undergrads. I'll also have the
		opportunity to work with the Manhattan/Hunter Science High School and
		Hunter College High School.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		I also look forward to the opportunity to work more closely with my
		friends in the K12 Ed space.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		I'm very excited about this opportunity but it feels a bit weird after
		being in the same place for so long. I don't feel any special
		attachment to the institution that is Stuyvesant, my allegiance is to
		my current and former students and that community isn't going
		anywhere. Next year I'll still be working with terrific young people,
		just in a different location under a different name.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		I will miss the team that we've put together but even then, we get to
		continue our work with CSTUY.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		With the new year comes new opportunity and I can't wait.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>misc</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-23-leaving-stuy.html/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2015 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Advent of Code</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-15-advent.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/advent/advent.png" alt="advent.png" width="480px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Has everyone seen &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt;?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a site with a series of programming problems that are being
revealed one a day, a la an advent calendar. You can read more about
it &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/about"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I came to the party a little late so I'm only up to day 6.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Each problem comes in two parts. The second is revealed after you
complete the first. Both students and teachers are enjoying the
problems.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I like about the Advent of code, besides the one a day release,
is the fact that at least so far, the problems aren't super crazy
hard. They require a little thought but they seem very doable.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For me, that makes them a perfect platform on which to play with a new
language. I'm working through these in Clojure. I've been putting my
solutions up &lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/adventofcodeclojure"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I have no idea if my code is "good" Clojure but
it's been fun nonetheless.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, if you're looking for a nice set of small programming problems
and want to explore something new, check it out.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>misc</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-15-advent.html/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Finding the Bell Tower</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-06-bell-tower.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
No Edu-Rant today nor a clever lesson plan.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I just thought I'd share an email exchange that cracked me up. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
We're out in Ann Arbor visiting our son Natan who is in his first year at Michigan.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Devorah sent an email asking where we should meet.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It turns out that Natan's last class of the day is Music Composition. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's what followed:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Natan:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Composition is in the bell tower on Central. It's hard to miss. It's a
bell tower. It's right by Hill Auditorium, and looks like a bell
tower. It also sounds like a bell tower at certain points in the day,
but I don't think I've heard it sound like a bell tower around the end
of class, so you're probably better off looking for the thing that
looks like a bell tower rather than listening for the thing that
sounds like a bell tower. I would assume it also smells and tastes
like a bell tower, but if you're in close enough proximity to smell or
taste the bell tower, I think you've probably found the bell tower. It
looks like a huggable building, but please, dad, do not hug the bell
tower. I have class there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Devorah:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We can meet you at the bell tower as long as we can figure out what it
looks like.  Can you please give us a detailed description? Maybe
you should taste it just in case.  Does the bell tower on Central
smell like the bell tower on North?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Natan:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The bell tower is around the size and shape of a bell tower. It's ten
stories high, with the first nine stories being a little less than
one-tenth of a bell tower tall, and the tenth being rather more than
one-tenth of a bell tower tall (the tenth story being where the bells
are). The width is about equal to that of a bell tower. It has two
doors, one on one side of the bell tower, and the other on the other
side of the bell tower. It has clock faces on top, which should, at
the point you see it, resemble a clock face indicating the time which
it is. (The appearance of the clock faces should update in near-real
time.) If you stick around long enough, it should start to sound like
a bell tower, or perhaps like a monster descending the stairs singing
Gilbert and Sullivan. I don't know what the bell tower on North smells
like because the bell tower on North is currently blocked off. But it
also resembles a bell tower, being approximately the same size and
shape of a bell tower. It is much less likely to sound like a bell
tower, though.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>misc</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-06-bell-tower.html/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2015 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Something growing in the Hudson Valley</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description><category>community</category><category>misc</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015.html/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Coding schools - or why I chose NYCDA</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-12-nycda.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of you might have noticed that a few months ago, I decided to
affiliate myself with &lt;a href="http://nycda.com/"&gt;The New York Code and Design Academy&lt;/a&gt; or NYCDA. I
took on the role of "Academic Director, Youth Programs." It's a part
time gig, at least for now and I'm helping them develop their programs
for middle and high school students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why did I choose them?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are a number of coding schools with varying levels of hype
around them. At their core, all are workforce programs. They take
people with little or no programming background and after a few months
of intensive training, they ship them off as web devs or the like.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have friends at many of these coding schools and related programs so
what was different about NYCDA that made me decide to work with them?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They know who they are, they know what they do, they know where they
want to go, and we all feel I can help them get there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let me explain.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most coding schools follow the same mold.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For one reason or another, a founder decides to start teaching a
class. This works pretty well so it starts to grow into a
business. For many of these coding schools, the teaching staff comes
from the program's own graduates.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The key point here is that most coding schools have little to no
interaction with real, experienced educators.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, why do they work? Well, to start, there's plenty of low hanging
fruit. Right now, as these programs are in high demand,  programs can
cream top applicants. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Many programs also have applicants complete
pre-work - that is a program of self study before starting the coding
school. This pretty much ensures that your classes are going to be
composed of hard working, intelligent self starters - that's a recipe
for a successful student body.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Given the student population and the fact that the skill set for an
entry level programmer can be taught fairly formulaicaly, it's a recipe
for success.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, I don't mean to imply that these schools are bad or doing bad
things - all of them are taking people and giving them a chance at a
new career. It's good and it's important. Even more so for
organizations that provide a step up for the have nots.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teaching kids is another matter. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For adults you're teaching a specific skill set for a specific job
market. For kids, you're setting a foundation and opening doors. You
can't just take your adult model and apply it to kids. Well, you can,
and it will even look good, but it won't have real substance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's what impressed me about NYCDA - when &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jeremysnepar"&gt;Jeremy&lt;/a&gt; came to me it was
clear - they knew what they did and what they did well. He also knew
that as they ramp up their youth offerings, it was important to
involve real, experienced educators - that it was about having true
expert teachers even more than it was curriculum. He understood that
while NYCDA is doing a great job, how much better could it be to
include CS educators who have been sending kids into industry
successfully for years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was even more delighted when my partner in crime JonAlf
Dyrland-Weaver - one of the best teachers I know, CS or otherwise,
agreed to teach one of our NYCDA youth courses this semester.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
NYCDA is the only coding school working to bring the best teachers out
there to their youth programs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's why I joined on and that's why I'm really excited for the
programs we're going to roll out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>misc</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-12-nycda.html/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How it all began</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-09-be-a-cs-teacher.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This past week, Garth Flint wrote a couple of posts on how he
got to be a CS teacher and on being a CS teacher. You can find them here:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gflint.wordpress.com/2015/10/07/so-you-want-to-be-a-cs-teacher-part-1/"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gflint.wordpress.com/2015/10/08/so-you-want-to-be-a-cs-teacher-part-2/"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They're both well worth a read.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It got me thinking about how I got my start.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I never planned on being a teacher. I figured I'd just work in
tech. After working my way through college, fresh CS degree in hand, I
landed at Goldman Sachs. I had other opportunities but the tech scene
was very different. You could (basically):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work for a financial house or insurance company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do niche consulting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;travel out of the city to Bellcore, AT&amp;amp;T or IBM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, I didn't drive and wasn't going to do consulting so I ended up
on Wall Street. I worked there for a bit but it didn't do it for me,
then tried a consulting gig. No better. Wall street never appealed to
me and at the time, more programming type jobs involved you working
alone on a computer in an office or a cube all day. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, for no particular reason, I decided to give teaching a go.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I always wonder, if I had come along a few years later if I would have
stayed in pure tech.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had zero teaching credentials but there was a math teacher shortage
at the time. By taking a couple of CS classes as math classes
(numerical methods, algorithms) they justified giving me temporary
license. I would have to take a handful of Ed credits within a couple
of years and later get a masters (which I knew would be in CS, no way
was I getting an Education degree).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I started at Seward Park High School as a math teacher. Best thing
that could have happened to me. I was working with an incredibly
diverse population - high achieving kids, low achieving kids,
immigrants, multi-generational Americans, delightful kids and kids on
parole. That's where I developed my chops.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Knowing that I was a CS guy the math chairman started having me teach
the basic programming course and later APCS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of years later, I was bumped to Stuy. Taught math and the
rest of my history can be seen &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/09/17/stuycs-spectator.html#.VhfhBt8qcbw"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Garth talks about requirements and Alfred Thompson, in his &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2015/10/an-inside-look-at-being-computer.html"&gt;link to
Garth's posts&lt;/a&gt; talks about the problems of CS teacher isolation. It
took a long time and it was hard work, but I started in a school with
no CS to speak and no CS teachers and now we have a required course,
between six and 10 CS teachers depending on the year, and a thoroughly
oversubscribed program. Of course, if you're at a small school, you
can't really do that. I remember in the early years, when it came to
course signup time, I'd have to visit every math class in the building
on one day to hock my courses. I'm glad those days are gone.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Garth also makes a great point about all there is to learn as a real
CS teacher. The best math teachers I know love doing math and love
solving problems but by and large, they're not learning new subfields
every year. Over my time as a teacher I've learned, either by choice
or necessity:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new fields such as
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relearning AI, which is radically different then when I was in
college&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data mining&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OOP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UX&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HCI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new languages
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Java&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C++&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Javascript&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Haskell (a bit)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perl&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And tons of technologies
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unix as a toolset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;system administration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;network administration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Git
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and many more.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, since I do work with many other CS teachers, I
might be a little bit of an outlier. Some of my colleagues also work
to keep current and learn new things while others are content with
their knowledge base and are happy to teach what they're currently
teaching. That's not to say that they don't work on their craft, but
rather, they're in a comfort zone of knowledge.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So what's next? As initiatives like CS4All progress, CS education will
become more formalized. You all know my fear about the current
efforts - CS Ed will go the way of Math Ed and we'll be left with Meh
CS education for all. If that's the case, and I hope I'm wrong, many
of Garth's issues will disappear. CS across the nation will become
more generic but more accessible and CS teachers will hopefully know
how to teach their courses but maybe not too much more. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even if that is the case, there will hopefully still be places for us
old time gluttons for punishment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>misc</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-09-be-a-cs-teacher.html/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2015 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>I guess some people like the blues</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-01-fans.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Funny story from yesterday.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Devorah, my better half, is an assistant principal at another high
school. Yesterday evening, she was at work late for "curriculum
night." Parents came to the school after hours to hear a variety of
presentations.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
During her presentation, Devorah mentioned her name, that she had two
former public school kids in college, and that's about it for the
personal info.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After the session, two parents approached Devorah to say "we're big
fans of your husband!"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since when do teachers have fans?????????
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I mean, I understand "my daughter/son was in your husbands class and
really enjoyed it," but "I'm a big fan?" She wasn't sure how to take
it. Obviously we both took it as an honor and compliment but we also
both got a chuckle out of the turn of phrase.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've already said that teachers aren't &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/12/14/rockstar-godfather.html#.Vg264t8Sr0o"&gt;rock stars, we're blues men&lt;/a&gt; so
I guess this shows that some folks still like the blues.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>misc</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-01-fans.html/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Suspension if disbelief and the Mikado</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-21-mikado.html/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was brought up on Gilberg and Sullvan. My father, who always wanted
to be an opera singer sang with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Light_Opera_of_Manhattan"&gt;LOOM&lt;/a&gt; back in the day and there was
always classical music playing. Either from the Hi Fi or my father
singing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Recently, there's been a kerfufle over what was to be &lt;a href="http://nygasp.org"&gt;NYGASP's&lt;/a&gt;
production of Mikado.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	My son, Natan wrote a terrific blog post on it and the suspension of
	belief in opera. It's long but well worth a read.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you like G&amp;amp;S or opera in general, take a look.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It can be found &lt;a href="http://seccorecit.blogspot.com/2015/09/imagine-if-you-will.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy. 
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>misc</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-21-mikado.html/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2015 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>