<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about misc</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/misc.atom</id>
  <updated>2016-09-30T12:12:21Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/misc.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/misc/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Hunter College - Honors CS</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs.html/</id>
    <updated>2016-03-29T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2016-03-29T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's been a while since my last post and a while since I started at
Hunter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Time to share a bit about what I've been up to.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the better kept secrets in New York City is Hunter College's
computer science program. It's been around for years and it's been
that way for years. In fact, when I was looking to get my masters
degree back in the mid nineties I carefully researched all of the
area's MS in CS programs. It came down to Hunter College and Courant
Institute at NYU. I was going to go with Hunter since the programs
seemed comparable and Hunter was far more affordable but I had to go
with NYU due to class schedules. Too many of the Hunter offerings were
to early in the day and I had my full time teaching job to consider.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hunter isn't currently offering their Masters program but their
Bachelor of Arts program is alive and well, it's just that people
don't know about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Part of my job is to change that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, not really, part of my job is to add my piece to the puzzle. The
rest will take care of itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My piece? It's all about creating a tech culture, tying into the NY
Tech ecosystem, and filling in the gaps that are shared by just about
every college computer science program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How do we do it? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The long term plan is that we're starting a new CS Honors program. In
the fall, I'll be teaching and mentoring a group of entering
undergrads. We'll have workshops, trips, activities. You name it. I'll
also be teaching them modified versions of our courses with the hope
of bringing some of my modifications back to the rest of the student
body. Things like integrating real tools and professional techniques
into what is already a solid academic program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the mean time, I'm getting to know Hunter's current CS students and
working to energize the existing community. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We already had an amazing event hosted at &lt;a href="http://yext.com"&gt;Yext&lt;/a&gt;. We had a panel and
mixer with representatives from about a dozen companies talking to the
kids about the possibilities ahead of them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We've also set up a couple of workshops in house.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm also starting to talk to friends at companies across the city to
plan out both curriculum and programs to set up our kids to
succeed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My goal is that within five years, I want people to realize that
Hunter CS is the place to be for CS Education in NYC. Not everyone can
afford the 40K and up private college tuition and there's no reason to
when you can get a great CS education with ties to the tech community
at CUNY prices.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you want to help, drop me a note. We're looking to start something
very special and you have a chance to be a part of it.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="hunter" label="hunter"/>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Leaving Stuyvesant</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-23-leaving-stuy.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-12-23T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-12-23T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-23-leaving-stuy.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Almost twenty six years. That's how long I've been a NYC public school
teacher. Most of that time at my alma mater, Stuyvesant. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of years ago, the school paper wrote up an overview of my
career. I re-posted it &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/09/17/stuycs-spectator.html#.Vnqfxh8Sr0o"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I'm somtimes amazed at where we are now
and how we got here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Regulars here also know my frustrations. To Stuy, I'm an
interchangeable, generic math teacher and the DOE has shown no
interested in supporting what we've built. I've also written about my
concerns with the direction the city's going with respect to K12 CS
education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was time for me to start the next phase of my career.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm happy to say that I will be joining Hunter College in late
		January. I'll be developing their CS Teacher Ed program and also
		working with their computer science undergrads. I'll also have the
		opportunity to work with the Manhattan/Hunter Science High School and
		Hunter College High School.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		I also look forward to the opportunity to work more closely with my
		friends in the K12 Ed space.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		I'm very excited about this opportunity but it feels a bit weird after
		being in the same place for so long. I don't feel any special
		attachment to the institution that is Stuyvesant, my allegiance is to
		my current and former students and that community isn't going
		anywhere. Next year I'll still be working with terrific young people,
		just in a different location under a different name.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		I will miss the team that we've put together but even then, we get to
		continue our work with CSTUY.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
		With the new year comes new opportunity and I can't wait.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Advent of Code</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-15-advent.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-12-15T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-12-15T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-12-15-advent.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/advent/advent.png" alt="advent.png" width="480px" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Has everyone seen &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt;?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a site with a series of programming problems that are being
revealed one a day, a la an advent calendar. You can read more about
it &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/about"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I came to the party a little late so I'm only up to day 6.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Each problem comes in two parts. The second is revealed after you
complete the first. Both students and teachers are enjoying the
problems.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I like about the Advent of code, besides the one a day release,
is the fact that at least so far, the problems aren't super crazy
hard. They require a little thought but they seem very doable.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For me, that makes them a perfect platform on which to play with a new
language. I'm working through these in Clojure. I've been putting my
solutions up &lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/adventofcodeclojure"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I have no idea if my code is "good" Clojure but
it's been fun nonetheless.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, if you're looking for a nice set of small programming problems
and want to explore something new, check it out.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Finding the Bell Tower</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-06-bell-tower.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-11-06T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-11-06-bell-tower.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
No Edu-Rant today nor a clever lesson plan.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I just thought I'd share an email exchange that cracked me up. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
We're out in Ann Arbor visiting our son Natan who is in his first year at Michigan.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Devorah sent an email asking where we should meet.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It turns out that Natan's last class of the day is Music Composition. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's what followed:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Natan:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Composition is in the bell tower on Central. It's hard to miss. It's a
bell tower. It's right by Hill Auditorium, and looks like a bell
tower. It also sounds like a bell tower at certain points in the day,
but I don't think I've heard it sound like a bell tower around the end
of class, so you're probably better off looking for the thing that
looks like a bell tower rather than listening for the thing that
sounds like a bell tower. I would assume it also smells and tastes
like a bell tower, but if you're in close enough proximity to smell or
taste the bell tower, I think you've probably found the bell tower. It
looks like a huggable building, but please, dad, do not hug the bell
tower. I have class there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Devorah:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We can meet you at the bell tower as long as we can figure out what it
looks like.  Can you please give us a detailed description? Maybe
you should taste it just in case.  Does the bell tower on Central
smell like the bell tower on North?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Natan:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The bell tower is around the size and shape of a bell tower. It's ten
stories high, with the first nine stories being a little less than
one-tenth of a bell tower tall, and the tenth being rather more than
one-tenth of a bell tower tall (the tenth story being where the bells
are). The width is about equal to that of a bell tower. It has two
doors, one on one side of the bell tower, and the other on the other
side of the bell tower. It has clock faces on top, which should, at
the point you see it, resemble a clock face indicating the time which
it is. (The appearance of the clock faces should update in near-real
time.) If you stick around long enough, it should start to sound like
a bell tower, or perhaps like a monster descending the stairs singing
Gilbert and Sullivan. I don't know what the bell tower on North smells
like because the bell tower on North is currently blocked off. But it
also resembles a bell tower, being approximately the same size and
shape of a bell tower. It is much less likely to sound like a bell
tower, though.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Something growing in the Hudson Valley</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-10-29T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-10-29T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-29-catskills-2015.html/"/>
    <summary type="html"></summary>
    <category term="community" label="community"/>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Coding schools - or why I chose NYCDA</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-12-nycda.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-10-12T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-10-12T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-12-nycda.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of you might have noticed that a few months ago, I decided to
affiliate myself with &lt;a href="http://nycda.com/"&gt;The New York Code and Design Academy&lt;/a&gt; or NYCDA. I
took on the role of "Academic Director, Youth Programs." It's a part
time gig, at least for now and I'm helping them develop their programs
for middle and high school students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why did I choose them?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are a number of coding schools with varying levels of hype
around them. At their core, all are workforce programs. They take
people with little or no programming background and after a few months
of intensive training, they ship them off as web devs or the like.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I have friends at many of these coding schools and related programs so
what was different about NYCDA that made me decide to work with them?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They know who they are, they know what they do, they know where they
want to go, and we all feel I can help them get there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let me explain.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most coding schools follow the same mold.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For one reason or another, a founder decides to start teaching a
class. This works pretty well so it starts to grow into a
business. For many of these coding schools, the teaching staff comes
from the program's own graduates.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The key point here is that most coding schools have little to no
interaction with real, experienced educators.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, why do they work? Well, to start, there's plenty of low hanging
fruit. Right now, as these programs are in high demand,  programs can
cream top applicants. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Many programs also have applicants complete
pre-work - that is a program of self study before starting the coding
school. This pretty much ensures that your classes are going to be
composed of hard working, intelligent self starters - that's a recipe
for a successful student body.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Given the student population and the fact that the skill set for an
entry level programmer can be taught fairly formulaicaly, it's a recipe
for success.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, I don't mean to imply that these schools are bad or doing bad
things - all of them are taking people and giving them a chance at a
new career. It's good and it's important. Even more so for
organizations that provide a step up for the have nots.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teaching kids is another matter. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For adults you're teaching a specific skill set for a specific job
market. For kids, you're setting a foundation and opening doors. You
can't just take your adult model and apply it to kids. Well, you can,
and it will even look good, but it won't have real substance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's what impressed me about NYCDA - when &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jeremysnepar"&gt;Jeremy&lt;/a&gt; came to me it was
clear - they knew what they did and what they did well. He also knew
that as they ramp up their youth offerings, it was important to
involve real, experienced educators - that it was about having true
expert teachers even more than it was curriculum. He understood that
while NYCDA is doing a great job, how much better could it be to
include CS educators who have been sending kids into industry
successfully for years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was even more delighted when my partner in crime JonAlf
Dyrland-Weaver - one of the best teachers I know, CS or otherwise,
agreed to teach one of our NYCDA youth courses this semester.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
NYCDA is the only coding school working to bring the best teachers out
there to their youth programs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's why I joined on and that's why I'm really excited for the
programs we're going to roll out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How it all began</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-09-be-a-cs-teacher.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-10-09T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-10-09T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-09-be-a-cs-teacher.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This past week, Garth Flint wrote a couple of posts on how he
got to be a CS teacher and on being a CS teacher. You can find them here:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gflint.wordpress.com/2015/10/07/so-you-want-to-be-a-cs-teacher-part-1/"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gflint.wordpress.com/2015/10/08/so-you-want-to-be-a-cs-teacher-part-2/"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They're both well worth a read.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It got me thinking about how I got my start.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I never planned on being a teacher. I figured I'd just work in
tech. After working my way through college, fresh CS degree in hand, I
landed at Goldman Sachs. I had other opportunities but the tech scene
was very different. You could (basically):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work for a financial house or insurance company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do niche consulting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;travel out of the city to Bellcore, AT&amp;amp;T or IBM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, I didn't drive and wasn't going to do consulting so I ended up
on Wall Street. I worked there for a bit but it didn't do it for me,
then tried a consulting gig. No better. Wall street never appealed to
me and at the time, more programming type jobs involved you working
alone on a computer in an office or a cube all day. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, for no particular reason, I decided to give teaching a go.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I always wonder, if I had come along a few years later if I would have
stayed in pure tech.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had zero teaching credentials but there was a math teacher shortage
at the time. By taking a couple of CS classes as math classes
(numerical methods, algorithms) they justified giving me temporary
license. I would have to take a handful of Ed credits within a couple
of years and later get a masters (which I knew would be in CS, no way
was I getting an Education degree).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgheadline2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgheadline2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgheadline2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, I started at Seward Park High School as a math teacher. Best thing
that could have happened to me. I was working with an incredibly
diverse population - high achieving kids, low achieving kids,
immigrants, multi-generational Americans, delightful kids and kids on
parole. That's where I developed my chops.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Knowing that I was a CS guy the math chairman started having me teach
the basic programming course and later APCS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of years later, I was bumped to Stuy. Taught math and the
rest of my history can be seen &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/09/17/stuycs-spectator.html#.VhfhBt8qcbw"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Garth talks about requirements and Alfred Thompson, in his &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2015/10/an-inside-look-at-being-computer.html"&gt;link to
Garth's posts&lt;/a&gt; talks about the problems of CS teacher isolation. It
took a long time and it was hard work, but I started in a school with
no CS to speak and no CS teachers and now we have a required course,
between six and 10 CS teachers depending on the year, and a thoroughly
oversubscribed program. Of course, if you're at a small school, you
can't really do that. I remember in the early years, when it came to
course signup time, I'd have to visit every math class in the building
on one day to hock my courses. I'm glad those days are gone.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Garth also makes a great point about all there is to learn as a real
CS teacher. The best math teachers I know love doing math and love
solving problems but by and large, they're not learning new subfields
every year. Over my time as a teacher I've learned, either by choice
or necessity:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new fields such as
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relearning AI, which is radically different then when I was in
college&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data mining&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OOP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UX&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HCI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new languages
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Java&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C++&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Javascript&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Haskell (a bit)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perl&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And tons of technologies
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unix as a toolset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;system administration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;network administration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Git
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and many more.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, since I do work with many other CS teachers, I
might be a little bit of an outlier. Some of my colleagues also work
to keep current and learn new things while others are content with
their knowledge base and are happy to teach what they're currently
teaching. That's not to say that they don't work on their craft, but
rather, they're in a comfort zone of knowledge.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So what's next? As initiatives like CS4All progress, CS education will
become more formalized. You all know my fear about the current
efforts - CS Ed will go the way of Math Ed and we'll be left with Meh
CS education for all. If that's the case, and I hope I'm wrong, many
of Garth's issues will disappear. CS across the nation will become
more generic but more accessible and CS teachers will hopefully know
how to teach their courses but maybe not too much more. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even if that is the case, there will hopefully still be places for us
old time gluttons for punishment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I guess some people like the blues</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-01-fans.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-10-01T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-10-01T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-01-fans.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Funny story from yesterday.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Devorah, my better half, is an assistant principal at another high
school. Yesterday evening, she was at work late for "curriculum
night." Parents came to the school after hours to hear a variety of
presentations.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
During her presentation, Devorah mentioned her name, that she had two
former public school kids in college, and that's about it for the
personal info.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After the session, two parents approached Devorah to say "we're big
fans of your husband!"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since when do teachers have fans?????????
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I mean, I understand "my daughter/son was in your husbands class and
really enjoyed it," but "I'm a big fan?" She wasn't sure how to take
it. Obviously we both took it as an honor and compliment but we also
both got a chuckle out of the turn of phrase.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've already said that teachers aren't &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2014/12/14/rockstar-godfather.html#.Vg264t8Sr0o"&gt;rock stars, we're blues men&lt;/a&gt; so
I guess this shows that some folks still like the blues.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Suspension if disbelief and the Mikado</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-21-mikado.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-09-21T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-09-21T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-09-21-mikado.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was brought up on Gilberg and Sullvan. My father, who always wanted
to be an opera singer sang with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Light_Opera_of_Manhattan"&gt;LOOM&lt;/a&gt; back in the day and there was
always classical music playing. Either from the Hi Fi or my father
singing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Recently, there's been a kerfufle over what was to be &lt;a href="http://nygasp.org"&gt;NYGASP's&lt;/a&gt;
production of Mikado.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	My son, Natan wrote a terrific blog post on it and the suspension of
	belief in opera. It's long but well worth a read.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you like G&amp;amp;S or opera in general, take a look.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It can be found &lt;a href="http://seccorecit.blogspot.com/2015/09/imagine-if-you-will.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy. 
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Just another day at StuyCS</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-08-antother-day-stuycs.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-03-08T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-03-08T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-08-antother-day-stuycs.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
.photo {width:60%;}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;img class="photo" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/just_another_day/pic.jpg"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last post was a little heavy so just a short fun one for today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
"Just another day at StuyCS." That was the subject of the email Brian
sent with the photo above. What's going on?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We're working on advanced JavaScript while also looking at
&lt;i&gt;Backbone.js&lt;/i&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, as sometimes happens, Batya, while in her CS class up at college,
decided to open up a Google chat with me. This happens now and then. We try to
have some fun with it. We actually have a plan to mess with the kids
later this term, but I'll keep that to myself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, Batya, of course, was sitting in her CS class in college. I told
her what we were doing and continued with the lesson.  She responded
that Zach, her boyfriend and my former student said not to forget to
emphasize certain things. I also asked Batya if her professor was
having a chat with his kid while he was teaching. Everyone was having a
laugh.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then things got sillier. Another chat popped up. It was Natan, my son,
who happens to be in that class. So, the insanity continued on when I
get a video call -  it was from Aida sitting in row 1 - that's what you
see on the screen. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now it was getting a little ridiculous and it all started with Batya
and Natan. So, what's a a teacher to do? I had to contact their
parent, my wife, to tell her to discipline her children. That's the
third chat. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, just another day at StuyCS.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="community" label="community"/>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A chocolate treasure in a city losing its soul</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-02-13-myzels.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-02-13T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-02-13T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-02-13-myzels.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/myzels/myzels.jpg" alt="myzels.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm a born and bred New Yorker and more and more I'm lamenting what
the city's becoming. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
New York used to be a collection of neighborhoods. Yes, we were the
city that never slept, but there were scores of mom and pop stores,
sole proprieterships. You could become a "regular." I'm reminded of
Tom Shachman's book &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Around-The-Block-Business-Neighborhood/dp/0151000778"&gt;Around the Block&lt;/a&gt; which looks at the businesses
around a single NYC block, mostly all gone now. If you can get your
hands on the book. It's worth a read.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any event, here's a story:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday. JonAlf and I were at the Apple store on Fifth avenue talking about
&lt;a href="http://cstuy.org/"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;. We had four of our talented students presenting their work.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After the event, JonAlf had gone and one of our student presenters had
left with his parents. I was left with our other three presenters.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I told them that I'd love to take them by this amazing chocolate shop
a few blocks away and I had to explain why:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/myzels/candy.jpg" alt="candy.jpg"&gt;]]
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
A number of years ago, after a morning in Central Park, Batya, Natan,
and I were winding our way home. We ended up passing &lt;a href="http://www.myzels.com/"&gt;Myzel's
Chocolates&lt;/a&gt; on the south side of 55th street between fifth and sixth
avenue. That's when we met Kamila, the shop owner. We chatted for a
while got some chocolate and went on our way. Kamila was amazingly
warm and sincere and the chocolates really really good. I noted that
we would have to return.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/myzels/kamila.jpg" alt="kamila.jpg"&gt;]]
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
That didn't happen until months later but when it did, I was shocked
that Kamila remembered us, what we were doing that day and we just
picked up the conversation where we left off.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This pattern repeated over the years. We didn't get to that
neighborhood and thus Myzel's often, but whenever we did, we had to
stop by. Great candies from a truly special person.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Alas, my schedule has been such that I hadn't been back to Myzel's in
years. I think three or four. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, I was with Nadia, Miranda, and Leslie - three of my incredibly
talented students. They just did an awesome job presenting their work
and I figured I could give them some thank you chocolate as well as
visit one of my  favorite places in the city.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I told them that Kamila probably wouldn't remember me but I recounted
my story of Myzel's and how amazing Kamila and the store were. I got
the feeling that they didn't believe me when I told them about Kamila
and the store.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We got to Myzel's went in and started to place our order. When Kamila
came out, her first word to me was "professor…" and we picked up
where we left off. As usual, she was charming and sincere. We
reminisced and chatted and then we were off.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In a city that's fast becoming cookie cutter we need more places like
&lt;a href="http://www.myzels.com/"&gt;Myzel's&lt;/a&gt; and more people like Kamila.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Unfortunately rents are rapidly dispatching shops like &lt;a href="http://www.myzels.com/"&gt;Myzel's&lt;/a&gt; and
people like Kamila are few and far between.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, when you're around City Center or midtown in general, please treat
yourself. You won't be disappointed.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>CS Ed Predictions 2015</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-01-04-predictions-2015.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-01-04T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-01-04T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-01-04-predictions-2015.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I just read &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred Thompson's&lt;/a&gt; predictions for next year. I was going
to leave a comment but since it would have gotten somewhat long
winded, I thought I'd comment in a post of my own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you haven't read Alfred's post yet, check it out:
&lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2015/01/computer-science-education-predictions.html"&gt;http://blog.acthompson.net/2015/01/computer-science-education-predictions.html&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-unnumbered-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="unnumbered-1"&gt;On more states allowing CS to count for a graduation requirement:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-unnumbered-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Alfred's probably right but I'm leery. Sure, it could end up terrific
but I could see a number of ways this could play out badly.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We could end up with non-cs classes to count as CS or we could see
schools allowing real CS to count but there would be no incentive for
a school to actually create any meaningful CS classes
much less for kids to take them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I guess the root of my concern probably relates two of my concerns
about education in general:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Real, experienced teachers aren't driving policy in education in
general and CS is and will  be no different. We're going to be left
with something forced down from above and I fear it will be bad.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm not a big fan of education education. As schools of education
get involved they will have more of a voice. I think one of the
worst things to happen to math education over the course of my
career has been "Math Ed." I fear CS Ed will have the same effect
on K12 CS education.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Maybe I'm a pessimist or maybe I've just been burned one to many times
or maybe it's that as a public school teacher I see the negative
effect of politics and money on public education but at least in NYC I
see where the decision making is coming from and I'm not encouraged.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, even if I'm right and the powers that be really
screw things up,there should always be at least a few people who see
through they hype and that's where I can continue to do positive work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-unnumbered-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="unnumbered-2"&gt;On Python continuing to grow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-unnumbered-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It's been one of my go to languages for a while now. I've been using
it in and out of classes since some time in the mid 90s.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't see it replacing Java in AP CS and it looks like Scratch has
the inside track CS Principles but it's good for so many things and
has such a low cost of entry, I again feel that Alfred's right. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The fact that it's easy for a non-cs teacher to pick up, at least to a
limited degree, will certainly help the charge. I'm not sure if long
term, this is a good thing, but it will help to push python's growth in education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a side note on Java – I'm not personally a fan, but there good things in there that would be lost 
with a total shift to languages like Python.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-unnumbered-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="unnumbered-3"&gt;On CS Principles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-unnumbered-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I do see a time where the course is forced on Stuy but I'm
not worrying about it for the moment. I think we already teach a
stronger course and by the time CS Principles becomes an issue at
Stuy, I'll probably be gone.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-unnumbered-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="unnumbered-4"&gt;Chromebooks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-unnumbered-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could see chromebooks working out for CS but only if schools don't
lock them down. Out of the box, you can only use cloud based
development environments. This is surely limiting but if you have the bandwidth, between
&lt;a href="http://codesters.com/"&gt;codesters.com&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://koding.com/"&gt;koding.com&lt;/a&gt;, cloud9, Dr.Racket and assorted other tools
you can certainly do some good CS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The upside comes when you can drop into the Linux shell. I've been
playing with a C720 Intel chromebook recently. It's small and
lightweight and once I set it up, it was running Dr. Racket, NetLogo,
Python, Java, Processing (all with a fairly hefty Emacs install).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Will it run everything? I don't know, but if I can get a new lab of
computers and have the freedom to custom install the machines, I'm
seriously considering chromebooks. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm also recommending them to my kids looking for a cheap portable
development environment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-unnumbered-5" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="unnumbered-5"&gt;Closing thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-unnumbered-5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've never been one for my own predictions - maybe because I'm more of
a continuous journey rather than destination type of guy so I'll hold
off on my own predictions for now, but I'll close with a direct
shoutout – Hey Alfred - thanks for posting your predictions - good food for thought 
as is your blog in general.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
    <category term="netlogo" label="netlogo"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Boys, Girls, Arts, Tech, and Vacation</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-01-03-vacation.html/</id>
    <updated>2015-01-03T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2015-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-01-03-vacation.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Spent most of vacation relaxing. Finished off the remaining college
recs, tried to catch up on sleep, and worked on a few project.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We've had an interesting December break dynamic in our household for
the past few years. My son, Natan is very much into his music, both as
a performer and a composer. A few years ago we discovered &lt;a href="http://www.livingtraditions.org/docs/index_kk.htm"&gt;KlezKamp&lt;/a&gt;. It
spoke to both Natan and Devorah. Batya, coming back from college
wasn't so into it and I was somewhat indifferent. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The end result is that for most of the first half of the break, Batya
and I were left on our own in the city while Natan and Devorah were up
in the Catskills. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what did we do? In addition to playing tourist, we rebuilt the
CSTUY web site (with a little help from her boyfriend Zach) - check it
out: &lt;a href="http://cstuy.org/"&gt;cstuy.org&lt;/a&gt;. I'm really happy with the result and now have a code
base that I'm happy with and can maintain.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I can't describe how awesome it is to be able to collaborate on
something real with ones daughter and I hope we can work on more
projects in the future. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, I had my Natan time when he and Devorah got home. We spent
new years eve at the &lt;a href="http://nygasp.org/"&gt;NYGASP&lt;/a&gt; production of HMS Pinafore. Natan loves
opera and is something of a Savoyard and he's also a terrific
singer. Something he must have inherited from my father, although he
never met him.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, we had our own project:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="100%" height="450" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/184357024&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
His is the good voice singing Dick Deadeye and I'm the not so good one
doing Captain Corcoran. We recorded it A Capella and he added the midi
after the fact. I think he had to change the key and I'm sure he had
to mess with the tempo.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some of you might have noticed that I worked on the tech project with
Batya and the artsy one with Natan but don't worry - Natan's planning
on majoring in &lt;a href="https://github.com/NZamansky"&gt;Computer Science&lt;/a&gt; and Batya's the musical director and
an alto in &lt;a href="http://www.thechainotes.com/"&gt;The
Chai Notes&lt;/a&gt; up at Cornell. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So that was my break. Back to work in a couple of days.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A birds eye view of my career</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-09-17-stuycs-spectator.html/</id>
    <updated>2014-09-17T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2014-09-17T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-09-17-stuycs-spectator.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's hard to believe that this is my 25th year teaching and that my
first StuyCS class graduated in June 1995. It's really hard to believe
that I'm now looking at the end of a significant part of my life and
career.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the summer, Mariya, Kachun, and Stella, all writers for Stuy's
Spectator worte an article that chronicled StuyCS. It's a really nice
piece. It skirted the battles I've had and the fact that we get no
love or support from Stuy or the DOE, but still, as I said, it's a
really nice piece.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
the original can be found &lt;a href="http://www.stuyspec.com/features/how-to-hack-yourself-a-class"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; but I've copied the article (with
permission) below.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Two decades in about two pages.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;How to Hack Yourself a Class&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
By Mariya Gedrich, Kachun Leung, and Stella Ma
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Imagine Stuyvesant without a computer science program. Aspire to pursue a career in software development? Nope, but perhaps you could go into the ever-lucrative handmade telescope business after taking a telescope assembly class. Want to explore all the features of your laptop? Well, that’s probably not happening at school. Want to take Advanced Placement (AP) Computer Science? Good luck getting into that one class taught by that one teacher. If this seems like a hassle to you, it was definitely a problem 20 years ago when this was the reality.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today, every Stuyvesant student is expected to graduate with at least one semester of Introductory Computer Science, and for those who are interested in continuing with the course, there are plenty of classes offered. In fact, AP Computer Science is one of the most sought after classes every year. Last year, around 400 students applied to take the class, and an extra section had to be added to accommodate the disappointed students who did not get in. In 1994, however, Stuyvesant had only a few classes dedicated to the use and study of computers. There was no official computer science program other than one AP Computer Science class taught by a math teacher who was much more passionate about teaching math than about teaching computers.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
A new math teacher at the time, Michael Zamansky, was teaching geometry. Zamansky, felt out of place teaching a math class. “I’m not a mathematician, I’m a computer scientist,” Zamansky explained. Before long, it was clear that the switch was inevitable. Zamansky enthusiastically recalls the day he was taken out of a class to talk to math chairman Richard Rothenberg: The previous teacher said, “‘Richie, I don’t want to teach computer science—Mike does.’”
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And that was when the ball started rolling.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the fall of 1994, Zamansky started teaching the AP Computer Science class. In turn, enrollment skyrocketed as there was now an enthusiastic and passionate teacher. Juniors and seniors filled four sections of the class, more than ever before.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The classes fostered a new interest in computer science among students. Feeling that there was much more to be done with this new enthusiasm, Zamansky asked his class if they’d like to have a spring class in Systems Programming, a class in which students would learn about memory organization, interrupts, and computer representation of numbers. Although both his students and the administration approved of this idea, Zamansky was unable to fit the class into the students’ 8-period schedules, especially since they had other commitments like math team in the morning. The solution came when students volunteered to stay an extra period after school, making Systems Programming a ninth period class. Students readily signed up; Zamansky was now staying after school every day with a group of students eager to learn. Noticing how popular the Systems Programming class was, Zamansky decided to create a fall semester supplementary course in Advanced Computer Graphics, in which he taught students how to use C and Pascal. Because of the popularity of these classes, the electives were incorporated into the schedule and staying after school was no longer necessary by the fall of 1995.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The classes proved to be a massive success. Computer science students were getting involved in international competitions, claiming top spots wherever they went. The result of the newly formed computer science classes was a very close-knit subculture. All of his students shared a common interest and now had a venue for developing it. “That cohort from Mike’s first class really bonded as a group,” recalled alumnus Yu Ping Hu (’95) in an e-mail interview. “I remember cutting all my classes for days on end to spend time in the lab with other kids in the class to work on our projects and hang out (and Mike kicking us out when he found out about it, not that it stopped us from doing it again when he wasn’t in the room).” In addition, “Hackers,” a film about a young boy who was arrested for writing a computer virus, was filmed at Stuyvesant, and a real life hacking incident took place. These events helped create traditions and lore for that community, according to Hu.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Zamansky also helped foster a community by teaching with a fun, playful attitude. According to former computer science teacher and alumnus Boris Granovskiy, students and teachers constantly played pranks on each other. “I definitely remember one day when there were several bake sales at Stuy, and so Mr. Zamansky and some of my friends bought up a bunch of pies and ambushed me when I got to the classroom, leading to a chase around the classroom and a lot of flying pastry,” he recalled.The annual Halloween tradition of all the computer science teachers dressing up and performing skits for their classes has its roots in Zamansky’s enthusiasm for dressing up in an elaborate costume. “The first year I taught, Mr. Zamansky and I dressed up as Hans and Franz from Saturday Night Live and walked around trying to teach in character the entire day,” Granovskiy recalls. The following year they both dressed up as the Hulk and had to somehow teach by only using grunting noises.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even though a vibrant culture had formed around the classes, only a small portion of the student body was a part of it. “A lot of kids won’t even think about computer science,” Zamansky explained. The ones who did, however, often fell in love with it. Alumnus and computer software developer Anita Verma remembers how she originally took Zamansky’s Introduction to Computer Science (Intro) class when it was an elective during her sophomore year. “I had heard great things about Mr. Zamansky, and I always loved computers, so I was very excited to take his class,” she said in an email interview. Although computer science was new to her, she quickly became fond of the class. “Classes never felt like a grind, like most of my other classes did. Looking back at these classes now, I understand that this is what learning is supposed to feel like, when you find something that you are passionate about,” she said. “I retained everything I learned in those classes, and used that as the foundation of the computer science education I would receive at college and in the workplace.”
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Verma is just one of many of Zamansky’s students who have gone on to have jobs in the tech industry, with some working at Google and others at the National Security Agency. “When one of my students got his doctorate, he gave me a copy of [it], and he’s a good friend of mine now…when another student wrote a book, I’m in the acknowledgments,” he said. “So I know these guys appreciate me but I’m like, ‘can’t I do more?’”
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That was when Zamansky decided to pursue a required Intro class for all students by what he considered “hacking” the school’s system. He started working on his idea for this program in 1997, but did not get the chance to make it a reality until 2002, when drafting teacher Timothy Pon left Stuyvesant. Since Pon left behind a drafting class, Zamansky was able to swoop in and substitute one of his Intro classes for the drafting class as a graduation requirement, a move that pleased a large portion of the student body. “Students began to say, ‘Hey, this is ridiculous. Computer science is so much more valuable,’ since the whole idea was that we want to give you the basic tools to inspire you and get you to think like a computer scientist,” Zamansky said.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The additional Intro class added yet another teacher to the computer science faculty,  Boris Granovskiy. It was the students in Granovskiy’s class who were allowed get a graduation credit for their Intro class to replace the drafting requirement. Students, however, began to complain that it was unfair for only one Intro class to satisfy the graduation requirement. “If you were in my class you didn’t get credit because it was only for this one substitute,” Zamansky explained. After the complaints increased, the administration caved in and allowed all Intro classes to get credit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once a single semester of Introduction to Computer Science (MKS21) was officially a graduation requirement, Zamansky began to work on creating a second semester class for his intro program, MKS22. “The whole idea behind Intro to Computer Science is that during MKS21, the first half, you learn to think like a computer scientist. But in MKS22, you’re gonna use real stuff. We do data analysis…and this is something that no matter what field you’re going to go into, they’re gonna help you,” he explained. Finally with the success of creating a whole year of Intro, Zamansky was able to achieve his goal of teaching computer science to the whole student body.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Although the wide array of computer science classes has grown into one of the most popular programs in Stuyvesant, it still faces several obstacles. The most prominent of these problems is that this program is not classified as a separate department because there is not a separate licensing for computer science teachers. Since the computer science programs are classified as math, it leads to several conflicts of interest, namely the daily functions of the program. This includes hiring and evaluating teachers and transferring students between classes. Furthermore, some of the computer science teachers are also math teachers, which causes problems when creating schedules each year. Assistant Principal of Mathematics Maryann Ferrara in particular has to deal with these problems; while hiring teachers, she has to find a fair way to allocate money for teachers between both the math department and the computer science program, according to Zamansky.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even though Zamansky and his program have faced problems to this day, he continues to take pride in what he has done with it. During his interview, he joyfully recounted memories of his students and their achievements of working for companies like Electronic Arts, Google, and Facebook. Besides the individual student accomplishments, the program has grown beyond the walls of Stuyvesant to include an organization called Computer Science and Technology for Urban Youth, a computer science program at St. Joseph’s College that pioneered this summer. Taught by several of Stuyvesant’s computer science teachers including JonAlf Dyrland-Weaver and Samuel Konstatinovich, the goal of the program is the same as it was in the beginning: to expose more students to computer science and to give them a venue to develop their skills.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And so, from a single section of AP Computer Science taught by a single teacher in 1994, Stuyvesant’s computer science program has grown into a sophisticated program that is one of a kind. “We had investors who wanted to invest in our student projects before they graduated. That doesn’t happen anywhere. We’ve got this very special thing that is nowhere else in the country,” Zamansky said. “There’s really nothing comparable to it.”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dream It, Code It, Win It</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-05-01-dream-it.html/</id>
    <updated>2014-05-01T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2014-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-05-01-dream-it.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
div.center {text-align:center;}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last night, I attended the Dream It, Code It, Win It awards. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'd actually write up the event but Fred Wilson's already done a
better job at that than I could:
&lt;a href="http://avc.com/2014/05/dream-it-and-code-it/"&gt;http://avc.com/2014/05/dream-it-and-code-it/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
As Fred stated on his blog, it's a real shame that the high schooler's
didn't get to show off their work but it was great to see that there
were entries from a variety of schools including The Academy for
Software Engineering and The Young Women's Leadership Academy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As part of the application process, the teams made short videos. Here
are three of the Stuy entries. I'll add the fourth once I get it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first two were written by teams in our senior SoftDev class the
third by juniors currently in APCS using mostly what they learned in
the second half of our intro class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Cartwheels:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/gJRik3aBxrI" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Tour de City:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/ztRGdRlzNYU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fun Time Projects:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/r4itvjf7UHY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tapia 2014</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-09-tapia.md/</id>
    <updated>2014-02-09T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2014-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-09-tapia.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spent the past few days at the &lt;a href="http://tapiaconference.org"&gt;Tapia Conference&lt;/a&gt; in Seattle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tapia conference is billed as a "Celebration of Diversity in
Computing." The bulk of the attendees seemed to be
students. Undergrads and grads. The undergrads were mostly juniors and
seniors, but a bunch of freshmen and sophomores were there as well. Of
course there were faculty members to join them as well as people from
industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was I doing there? Well, 20 high school teachers were given
scholarships to attend a workshop run by
&lt;a href="http://www.eecs.berkeley.edu/Faculty/Homepages/garcia.html"&gt;Dan Garcia&lt;/a&gt;. Dan
is the driving force behind one of the implementations of CS
Principals course - a new course being rolled out by the College
Board. As you're all well aware, I'm not a fan of the College Board
but I'm interested in Dan's work as common friends speak well of
him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll talk about his course next time, after I've gone through his
workshop. For now, let's talk about the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn't sure what to expect but let me tell you, I was blown
away. Many of the break out sessions didn't "speak" to me as a high
school teacher, but that's fine - the conference was for the
youngsters. I can't say for sure, but it seemed to me that they really
hit the breakout sessions on the head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there were the plenaries. Great speakers and a great range of topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They had:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cieko Asakawa talking about assistive technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dan Garcia on CS Education&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Latanya Sweeney - transparency and privacy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;James McLurkin - robotics (and some computational geometry)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kathryn McKinley - Systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marcus Mitchel - A general talk on hard problems, winding paths, and more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An incredible rage of topics. All the speakers were terrific - they
all talked about their life and career paths and were all
inspirational&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also presented a smorgasbord of computer science possibilities
for the students. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish this could be bottled up and given to all aspiring technologists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only got to attend because I was on scholarship as a high school CS
teacher. It was an amazing few days and I can't recommend the Tapia
conference highly enough for young computer scientists out there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What I learned from Pete Seeger</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-30-pete-seeger.md/</id>
    <updated>2014-01-30T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2014-01-30T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-30-pete-seeger.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/VucczIg98Gw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past Monday I, like may woke to hear about the passing of
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pete_Seeger"&gt;Pete Seeger&lt;/a&gt;. Ten days
earlier we were up at Symphony Space for the "Woody's Children" 45th
Anniversary Concert. Pete was supposed to perform but was ill. At 94
years of age, I wondered if the end was near. I was at the concert
with my family as well as with my buddy Ben. Fitting since Ben and I
grew up on Pete's music while many of our peers did not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're not familiar with Pete Seeger, his life and his work, I
really encourage you to check out the 2007 documentary &lt;a href="http://video.pbs.org/video/2365166823/"&gt;The Power of
Song&lt;/a&gt;. He was truly a
remarkable man. One of the most influential singer, songwriter,
activists of our times yet remarkably humble and approachable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember seeing Pete when I was a schoolboy. He would have been in
his fifties at the time. Thirty years later, he was singing for my
son's second grade class in the same public school in New York City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pete's been eulogized by far better writers than I so let me just
share some of Pete's influences on me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something that Pete said, highlighted in the PBS documentary - "Think
global, act local." Peter attributed it to Rene Dubos. As a teacher
and someone trying to make a difference through education, I think
about this a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As teachers, we have to act locally. We work with our kids every day
and can make a difference in individual lives. While we're doing this,
the global picture is a mess. Teachers are vilified, schools are
closed, and policy is set by people who have never been in the
classroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is hope, however. Just like Pete and the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hudson_River_Sloop_Clearwater"&gt;Clearwater
movement&lt;/a&gt;
local action, spearheaded by the likes of Diane Ravitch seems to be
taking hold. We're starting to see common core exposed and the types
of evaluation systems pushed by the Gates foundation debunked. Think
global, act local.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as you know, I'm a computer science educator and there are many
similarities between CS education and general education. Most of the
noise you hear is from non educators, or at least non K-12
educators with actual real experience and a real track record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These voices range from well informed, to well meaning, to
misdirected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year the CSTA held a twitter conversation with K12
CS Education thought leaders and there wasn't a k-12 teacher amongst
the listed participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code.org, a well meaning organization that has done a great job
exciting people abotu CS Ed has a quotes page. The closest thing to a
teacher there is Randi Weingarten and she was just in the classroom
for a cup of coffee. The only other person on the list with "teach" in
their title is Wendy Kopp who believes that poorly trained temps make
better teachers than experienced pros.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how will the conversation turn? Will groups and individuals with
influence engage those of us on the ground with actual results, or
will will receive dictates from on high? Time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, all I can do is continue to act local. I can't say what
will happen in the greater CS education landscape but I know that
every day I will see 150 kids and 20 more every Saturday. My kids, who
will be part of the Stuy CS and now CSTUY family. They might not know
now what they're getting, but I do and I know I've made a difference.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Plans for the New Year</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-01-new-year.md/</id>
    <updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2014-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-01-new-year.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've never been one for New Year's resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I'm working on something specific, I might set a goal to finish it,
but the idea of goals for a year never struck a chord with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's one of the things that I find absurd about the current teacher
rating system - I have to decided on my three goals for the year. I
always have one goal with respect to my profession - to be better at
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any event, even though I don't have specific overall goals for me,
there are some projects that I plan on pouring myself into this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year closed with a lot of national hype over CS Ed. What remains
to be seen is where we go with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll continue to try to work within the system - try to convince the
new administration that supporting and replicating Stuy CS is something worth
doing but I've been burnt enough to know not to
put all my eggs in that basket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, I'm hoping to put a lot of time into
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-01-01-new-year.md/http//cstuy.org"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;. We're just about a year old and it's been a
slow road but we're making some real progress - and this is just as a
grass roots organization - it's just us and the StuyCS Alumni family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what are the plans?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;More Hacking Sessions&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started Hacking Sessions in October. Twenty New York City public
high school students getting together to geek out and do CS every
Saturday. We're off to a great start but there's a lot of work to be
done. We'd love to get more students involved in the coming semester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;Start Summer Hackers&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the big effort. A summer program. Since we designed and
implemented Google CAPE NYC back in 2010, I've known the effect you
can have with a strong summer program taught by master teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've got the teachers and the program, but it's still going to take a
lot of work.We have yet to finalize on a location (we have a tentative
offer for space but I'm hesitant to say anything until it's more
concrete) and we have to do it early enough so that we can get to the
students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we can get CSTUY's Summmer Hackers off the ground I'm pretty sure
we can use that to launch a community of both hackers and teachers
just as we've done at Stuy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;Get more people involved&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said that so far CSTUY has been grass roots only. In order for us to
succeed, we'll need to grow our community. The hope and plan is to get
the NY Tech community behind our efforts. I'm hoping that when they see
us taking our proven programs out from Stuy to the greater public
they'll come out in droves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least that's the hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, those are my goals for the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should be exiting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A New Year and a New look</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-12-30-new-year-new-look.md/</id>
    <updated>2013-12-30T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2013-12-30T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-12-30-new-year-new-look.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;We're practically at the close of 2013 and it's high time I wished
everyone wonderful things for the year to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also time for a new look to this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why the rewrite? Partly because I was tired of the look, but mostly
because, when I put it together, it was the first time I used that
toolset and was just figuring things out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm still no expert, but I thought it was time to clean things up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's still a &lt;a href="http://jekyllrb.com/"&gt;jekyll&lt;/a&gt; generated blog hosted on
&lt;a href="http://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub pages&lt;/a&gt; but instead of using
&lt;a href="http://getbootstrap.com/"&gt;Twitter Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; I decided to use
&lt;a href="http://weice.in/ivory/"&gt;Ivory&lt;/a&gt;. It's much smaller and only does the
basics. Even the menu I'm using was the result of some online
searching for CSS stuff. I figure that this way, I'll actually learn
more about styling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should be an interesting year. I've got a number of projects that
I'm working on. Some within Stuyvesant, some revolving around &lt;a href="https://cstuy.org"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;, and some I can't talk about right now. Hopefully I'll
be able to write about some of them in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm also hoping to write more this year. I only posted 30 times this
past year. On the other hand, that's up from 18 times in 2012 and only
4 posts in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to updates on CSTUY, pedagogical posts and the occasional
rant, I'd like to do a series on how I use tools like the Linux shell
and Emacs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll see how things go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, I wish you all a happy and healthy new year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Summer Project 1 - Citibike Data</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-14-summer_projects.md/</id>
    <updated>2013-07-14T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2013-07-14T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-14-summer_projects.md/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, the Citibike program has been running for a bit. I like the idea,
but I have some reservations -- it's great for getting around in the
zone - I've been using it for short shopping trips - run cross town to
&lt;a href="http://www.fairwaymarket.com/"&gt;Fairway&lt;/a&gt; or take a quick trip from
work to &lt;a href="http://www.portorico.com/store/"&gt;Porto Rico Importers&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href="http://pasticceriarocco.com/"&gt;Rocco's Pastries&lt;/a&gt;. On the other hand,
the zone doesn't get to the residential neighborhoods of upper
Manhattan or the boroughs and the price per day is way too expensive
for regular working class joes, particularly on top of a subway trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any event, I was curious about station use patterns. Cool thing is
that you can get live data from
&lt;a href="http://citibikenyc.com/stations/json"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. This was a great
opportunity to play with some tools to see if I want to use them in
class next year. In particular, &lt;a href="http://backbonejs.org"&gt;backbone.js&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-14-summer_projects.md/d3js.org"&gt;d3.js&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I'm grabbing the station data every 5 minutes, storing it in a
Mongo database, and threw together a little map and graph app:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cb.zamansky.net"&gt;
&lt;img width="50%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/2013-07-14-summer-projects/citibike-1.png" class="" alt=""&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can check it out &lt;a href="http://cb.zamansky.net"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code is up on GitHub:
&lt;a href="http://github.com/zamansky/citibike-1"&gt;citibike-1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might play around and add more graphs as I collect more data or
maybe I'll just move on to the next project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Graduation</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-02-graduation.html/</id>
    <updated>2013-07-02T00:00:00</updated>
    <published>2013-07-02T00:00:00-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-07-02-graduation.html/"/>
    <summary type="html">One week ago today was Stuyvesant's graduation. 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I usually know a number of seniors pretty well but, since I like to
cycle through classes, every couple of years I have a group that I've
been with from 10th grade to 12th. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This was one of those years
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
It was extra special because it was also my daughter Batya's graduating class.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
It's been an amazing gift to be able to work at her school for the past four years and she's been amazingly tolerant. Particularly with both her and her boyfriend in my class this year.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Actually, they're both terrific and I think I only embarrassed her a
couple of times.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Every few years, my seniors ask me if I want them to nominate me as
faculty speaker at graduation. Usually I say no - stage fright. This
year, Batya asked. I thought it would be really cool. I said yes and
the troops came through and voted me in. I wasn't sure I would be the
winner, but as Peter commented "but you lead the most popular cult at
Stuy!"

It would have been enough of an honor to speak to the graduating
class, including many students that I feel connected to and it would
have been a great honor to speak at Batya's graduation. To add to it
all, the guest keynote speaker was my dear childhood friend Ben Fried.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Truly a career highlight.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Ben was terrific. I was watching the audience as he spoke - he
delivered a great message and really kept the classes attention. No video as of yet, but Ben published the text on Google+.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
You can find it 
&lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/108690239590381459413/posts/addaYWp36R2"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Here's a video of my speech. Jennifer said some very nice things to
introduce me. I was tempted to go off script right at the beginning
and point out that many of the nice things she said were really about
our CS team and not just me:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/beFQc2U9Kls" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I really didn't read the speech, just used the printed text as notes,
but here's what I worked from:

&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/07-02-2013-graduation/gradspeech.pdf"&gt;gradspeech.pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; The graduating class seemed to enjoy it, at least as much as
one can enjoy any graduation speech, but, for me, as I said, a
career highlight.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="misc" label="misc"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
