<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about pbl</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/pbl.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-08-03T15:30:05Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/pbl.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/pbl/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Two Faces of Project Based Learning</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/two-faces-of-pbl/</id>
    <updated>2018-07-28T15:59:45-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-07-28T15:59:45-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/two-faces-of-pbl/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org11ad9ed" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org11ad9ed"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org11ad9ed"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If one looks at my twitter feed they'll notice that in addition to CS
Ed, another issue I'm passionate about is school reform or rather
resistance to what is popularly known as and mislabeled as school reform. I'm anti
vouchers, charter schools, high stakes testing and more. One of the
heroes of this resistance is education historian Diane Ravitch. I'm a
big fan of Diane's and she's one of the true great champions of public
schools, kids, and teachers. She blogged today about how a superintendent on Long Island &lt;a href="https://dianeravitch.net/2018/07/27/new-york-district-on-long-island-shows-that-problem-based-curriculum-produces-better-results-than-test-prep/"&gt;replaced test
prep with project based learning&lt;/a&gt;. The post which talks about how this
superintendent improved test results  is worth a read. My only
quibble was that we shouldn't read anything into the results for a
variety of reasons including the fact that the group of students who
did the project based learning (PBL) units instead of test prep were
self selecting volunteers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the comments caught my eye: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
PBL is just another “student-centered” fad…
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
PBL operates on the myth of “transference” perpetuated by non-educators.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
…
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The comment continues on with a number of good points.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why am I writing about it here? Because PBL is a big CS Ed buzzword
and like most buzzwords there's both truth at the root of the hype and
hype that distorts the truth.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When done right with the right group of kids, project based learning
can be wonderful but it takes a lot of time and effort. You can't just
set the kids loose to learn. You've got to train them to work
together, set up the project, as the teacher, you've got to know the
subject so as to know when to guide, when to tell, when to prod, and when to leave
them alone. Doing it right, at least for most students, is certainly
not giving them the instruction sheet and going off the check your
email. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, it's easy to do it wrong. If you've got high
performing kids, they'll figure things out. If you've got a few high
performing kids, they can mask the fact that the majority of a group
isn't getting things. You might have an assignment where a kid figures
out a formula from discovered data and might be able to then use it to
make predictions but there's a good chance they won't understand why
it works or it's root derivation. That's where we need the teacher. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the dangers of bad PBL is that it's sexy. Kids are engaged and
it appears to work - particularly when the teacher doesn't know the
subject area. This is my great fear whenever I hear things about
teachers being "Lead Learners." Sure, when you're a converted
something else teacher moving into CS you won't know the subject
matter but that has to change over time. I've seen enough instances of
cases where teachers never develop their chops and just throw projects
at the kids augmented by scripted curricula or computer driver
content. The kids get through the class or program but are not
prepared for the next class or next level. I've seen this with the old
Cisco curriculum, any number of after school and summer programs -
some VERY highly regarded ones and I think we'll see more and more of
this in states that are pushing CSforAll without developing the
necessary pre and in service programs for their teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Don't let my last two paragraphs leave you feeling that I'm anti
PBL. I'm not. It's great when done right and if you have thee time and
resources in your school and classes you should be using it when
appropriate. 
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
If you want some pointers on how to get going in the right direction with PBL in CS  check out &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Computer-Science-K-12-Imagining-possibilities-ebook/dp/B07DYDXBSH/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1532808363&amp;amp;sr=8-1&amp;amp;keywords=doug+bergman"&gt;this
book&lt;/a&gt; by my buddy Doug Bergman. It's a great getting started guide by a
great teacher. He's basically Mr. PBL and he does it right.  If you're new to CS you'll still need to learn content
and if you're new to teaching, you'll be developing your chops for
your entire career but it's a great resource to get you and then your
kids started on the journey.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="csed" label="csed"/>
    <category term="pbl" label="pbl"/>
    <category term="pedagogy" label="pedagogy"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
