<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about pdf)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/pdf.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2018 21:31:46 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Using Emacs 44 - An org-mode workflow for application processing</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-44-pdf/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orga34b33a" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orga34b33a"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orga34b33a"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of my titles at Hunter College is Director of the Daedalus CS
Honors program. It's something like a Hunter specific, CS specific
version of the CUNY Macaulay Honors program. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hunter gives all its students the ability to get a great computer
science education at a fraction of the cost of a private institution
and if you're a Daedalus scholar you also get a scholarship, a laptop,
special classes (with me :-) ), activities and more. Just the other
day we visited  &lt;a href="http://samsungnext.com/"&gt;Samsung Next&lt;/a&gt; accelerator and earlier in the year we
made our annual visit to &lt;a href="http://www.catskillsconf.com/"&gt;Catskills Conf&lt;/a&gt;, arguably my favorite event of
the year. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When deciding on which students to recommend for acceptance, I try to
glean as much information as I can about each applicant. When I feel
there's not enough information, I've been known to reach out to
recommenders and other sources for more. But first I go through the
applications. For each student, I'm provided with a pdf file with a
bunch of data and also an entry in an internal Hunter online form with
even more.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For the first cohort, this wasn't a big deal. I hadn't even started at
Hunter when the applications closed so there was no
outreach. Everything was after the fact so there were very few
students to evaluate.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last year, I was able to do some outreach and we had around 60 or so
applications for a little over 20 spots.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This year, there are well over 100 applicants (and we're looking to
grow the program by a large number of students). All of a sudden, it
wasn't so easy to navigate all the pdf files.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Emacs to the rescue. Using a combination of org-mod,  &lt;a href="https://github.com/politza/pdf-tools"&gt;pdf-tools&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href="https://melpa.org/#/org-pdfview"&gt;org-pdfview&lt;/a&gt; I've come up with a workflow that I very much like.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Take a look and let me know what you think:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LFO2UbzbZhA" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>emacs</category><category>pdf</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-44-pdf/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 12:05:45 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>