<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about pedagogy)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/pedagogy.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 21:26:55 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>A new first language? What's the follow up plan?</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-language-changing/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This morning, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; wrote about Stanford possibly &lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/2017/04/21/cs-department-updates-introductory-courses-java-is-gone/"&gt;moving away
from Java&lt;/a&gt; as their intro language. This comes on the heels of a
semi-regular thread on one of the lists I'm on asking about what
languages are used at assorted colleges around the country. Invariably
the Pascal -&amp;gt; C++ -&amp;gt; Java progression of APCS turns up in these
threads.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are plenty of arguments to be made both for and against pretty
much any language or platform. There's no single best universal
answer. Each choice giveth and each choice taketh away. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I'm really curious about is who's looking at intro languages in
the context of complete programs or even complete educations that
could span multiple institutions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Early language choices can make a big difference in engaging and
exciting newcomers but there are ramifications later on that few seem
to consider.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Take the APCS change from C++ to Java. It removed memory management
from the first year course. It also simplified issues relating to
pass by value vs pass by reference (or, rather, passing address by
value), bought much more strongly into OOP and moved more towards
using built in implementations of data structures like Lists rather
than rolling your own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Removing memory management from the first year course in and of itself
isn't a problem as long as it's taught and taught effectively
somewhere later on. It could be argued that "memory is already covered
in our required systems course." That could be the case, but there are
many concepts that kids don't get the first time around. Is an
institution that covered memory management in CS1/2 and then came back
to it in a later Systems course giving their students the same
understanding now that they've eliminated the CS1/2 experience? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What about OOP buy in. Personally, I've never been a big OOP fan but
that's neither here nor there. What I have found is that depending on
how a student is exposed to programming in CS1/CS2 can have a big
influence on how they approach problems later. Did the move to Java
cause more of our students to try to use shoehorn OOP into a problem
that really shouldn't be approached in an OOP manner?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I suspect that the use of built in data structures has had a
negative impact. A few years after the switch to Java, I was talking
to a senior tech worker. He was having a bad day - interviewing
potential internees and full time engineers. My friend was complaining
that the kids couldn't come up with solutions to what he thought were
pretty straightforward questions. He felt that had the kids actually
implemented algorithms like the nlogn sorts rather than just learning
java .sort method and just talking about the algorithm they'd be
better prepared. I've heard this sentiment repeated over and over
throughout the years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is not to say that Java is a horrible language or horrible for
teaching - that's another debate. The point is that you can't just
look at the intro class and who it draws in. You have to consider how
it will prepare students for the next level and you have to look at
the big picture – will our students get everything they need by the
time they leave us.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Many schools have moved to Python. Will that effect students take on
type systems later on? Will the flexibility and constructs like list
comprehensions make it harder to teach recursion since there are
"easier" ways to do it? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
None of these are really problems so long as the CS1/2 (or even CS0)
isn't taught in a vacuum. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I fear, however that too often we're paying attention to the intake of
the pipe and not so much the output.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>langauges</category><category>pedagogy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-language-changing/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 18:46:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GitHub as a tool for education</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-4/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
When I started using git and GitHub with my students it was a natural
progression having started with started with CVS and then, as
technology changed moving through Subversion and then Mercurial. It
was all about using sensible professional software development
techniques while making it easier for students to submit work and for
me to evaluate their submissions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over time, I found that git and GitHub in fact provided some extra
support for educators right out of the box.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-3"&gt;last github post&lt;/a&gt; I talked about using the results of &lt;code&gt;git log&lt;/code&gt;
and looking at diffs. Both provide ways of seeing what a student did
and when. The commit log and history make it easier to hold students accountable to working
through a project and not leavings for the last minute. The diffs make
it easier to see what's changed both to see progress and also to help
support students as they develop their projects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you use Emacs, as I do, you can use the &lt;a href="https://github.com/pidu/git-timemachine"&gt;git timemachine&lt;/a&gt; package
which does a great job visualizing changes:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/sigcse-github/timemachine.gif" alt="timemachine.gif" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Other editors might have a similar feature.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The contribution graphs also provide a quick snapshot which shows what
team members are contributing and when:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/sigcse-github/githubgraph.png" alt="githubgraph.png" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The punchcard graph is also useful to see when students actually do
their work.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/sigcse-github/githubgraph2.png" alt="githubgraph2.png" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
GitHub also make it easy to set up starter code or to have students
"take over" each others projects by forking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm very happy using git and GitHub as is but if you want more
support, check out &lt;a href="https://classroom.github.com/"&gt;GitHub Classroom&lt;/a&gt;. Had it existed when I started,
I'd probably have used it but since I had already gotten used to my
work flows I've stuck with raw git and github.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In case you missed the earlier posts describing the process I use to
introduce github to my classes here they are:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-1"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-2"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-3"&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm hoping some of you have found this set of four posts useful or at
least interesting.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>pedagogy</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-4/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 23:11:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A free multi-state clicker with built in redundency</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/thumb_clickers/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org13f1744" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org13f1744"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org13f1744"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last Friday, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; wrote about the woes of &lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/2017/03/31/the-need-for-better-software-and-systems-to-support-active-cs-learning/%0A"&gt;using clickers&lt;/a&gt; in a
class. The amount of effort required to use his school's approved
clicker technology sounds ridiculous so while we need tools to better
engage students in large class settings we need better tools that can
be integrated into our classes more easily.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've never used clickers. On top of stories like Mark's, there are  a
number of problems with using clickers in a public school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can't force students to buy them and in NYC, until recently,
students couldn't use their phones (which they also might not have).
Forgetting the expense, if the school provides them, is it one per
student? If so, who's going to administer the clicker to student
mapping and how will that be communicated to the teachers. If college
tech infrastructures are sometimes lacking, high schools are orders of
magnitudes worse. The resources just aren't there. Then we have to
deal with loss and breakage.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If a teacher somehow gets a class set of clickers, they have to deal
with mapping clickers to students for all of their classes and make
sure the right student has the right clicker. Again, loss  and
breakage is a problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then you have to create the question content and hope that everything
works in class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The value added given the overhead just doesn't seem worth it
particularly since high school classes, while large, are not in the
hundreds and there are other methods of student engagement.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's what I use instead. It's not perfect but it's low cost and low
effort with a pretty high return.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The basic configuration, is a simple three state broadcast device.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not without its problems and I don't think it would work as well
in a large lecture but given the cost, it's well worth it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what is it?
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/fonzup.jpg" alt="fonzup.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Thumbs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org31bdbad" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org31bdbad"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org31bdbad"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Periodically, I'll poll my class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
&lt;img width="30%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/sidethumb.png"&gt;
&lt;img width="30%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/upthumb.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img width="30%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/downthumb.jpg"&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Thumb to the side? Everything's OK. Keep going as you're going. I get
it. Basically, things are good.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thumb up? Speed up, you're going too slow, I got it five minutes ago or
some similar big positive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thumb down? I have no idea what you're talking about.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's cheap, easy, quick, and once you can get your class to buy in,
you can get a quick sense of the class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The downsides?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The class has to have a level of comfort so that students vote
honestly and don't just give you positive feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No data collection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The upsides?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;quick&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cheap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;works on any topic on the fly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;even if the votes are artificially skewed towards positive, it does
forces the class to be at least a little attentive and to engage in
some physical response&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can get analog responses by allowing students to adjust wrist
rotation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As to the redundancy? I've never had a kid leave their thumb at home
or lose it and even if they did, they've got a second hand.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/fonztwo.jpg" alt="fonztwo.jpg" align="center" height="200"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This also works in extreme environments. Try using a clicker or mobile
app with gloves or mittens on or underwater.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't teach large lectures so I don't know how this would work in a
huge class. I'd imagine it's still worth it given that it's so low
friction and low cost of entry even if it's not perfect.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>pedagogy</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/thumb_clickers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 21:23:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Teacher looks at Advent of Code 2016 #2</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016-2/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Today we're looking at &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; 2016 &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/2016/day/2"&gt;number 2&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To change things up, I thought I'd do a video where I live code a solution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The solution I present is pretty straightforward - use a 2D array (or
technically, an array of strings) to represent the keypad, parse the
input, and follow the input instructions to build the code. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the things I really like about Advent of Code is that every
problem has two parts and depending on how you solved part 1, you may
or may not have extra work to do for part 2.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of years ago, I wrote about one of the coding techniques I
try to convey to my students. The idea of &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-02-26-change-the-data.md"&gt;changing the data&lt;/a&gt; to take
away edge and special cases. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Part two of this problem is a perfect time to use that technique.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's the video, I hope you enjoy it:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EC8gSrYQ11g" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>programming</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016-2/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2016 13:40:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Teacher looks at Advent of Code 2016 #1</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-code-2016-1/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I recently &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-of-code-2016/"&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; - a series of programming
problems relseased one a day. While they vary in terms of level of
difficulty, a number of them make nice problems for introductory to
mid level programming classes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I thought I'd share some of my thoughts on a few of them starting with
the first problem from this years competition.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com/2016/day/1"&gt;Take a minute to read it over.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At first glance, it might seem to a young programmer that this problem
requires a two dimensional array - all about (x,y) coordinates but
then there's a problem - there are no limits on coordinates and we
can't make an unlimited size array.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After thinking a bit, hopefully the programmer realizes that all they
need to do is keep track of the how the &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;(x,y)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; location changes over
time. In the solution below, we start at &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;(0,0)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and count the steps as
we update two variables &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;x&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;y&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When we finish processing the moves, we have our current location in
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;(x,y)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; and we have the number of steps taken to get there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The solution below hsa a couple of niceties that a beginning
programmer might not know or use (and I'm not arguing that what's written is
superior in any way, it's just what I ended up writing).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I make use of tuple destructuring:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
which assigns &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;x&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; to the first item in the tuple and &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;y&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; the
second. I used that a number of times 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also use a list  I call &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;dirs&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; to hold dx and dy values for the
four direcitons:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dirs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This made it easier to to update the location based on the 4
directions. I could also have just used if statements.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's all the code:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# assume our starting location is 0,0&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# we start with d=0 -&amp;gt; facing north&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# as we turn left or right, we can just increment or decrement d&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# and dirs[d] will give us the appropriate dx and dy to update&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# our locatoin for the next step&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;dirs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)]&lt;/span&gt;   
&lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# This is only needed for part 2  - We track visited locations&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# by adding them to the dictionary. If we try to add a location&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# that's already been visited we know that we've found our final &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# location&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# locs={}  # uncomment this line for part 2&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="n"&gt;totalsteps&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# the first char in i is the direction to turn in (L or R)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# the rest represents the number of steps.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;dir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;steps&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:])&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;dir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"L"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dirs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;steps&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;totalsteps&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;totalsteps&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Uncomment this block for part 2&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# each time we have a new location, see if it's already in&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# locs, if it isn't, add it.&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# if it is, we're visiting somewhere twice so we're done.&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#if ((x,y) not in locs):&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#    locs[(x,y)]=1&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#else:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#    print((x,y))&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#    print(abs(x)+abs(y)) # the answer&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#    sys.exit(0)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;#    break&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;abs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;abs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# the answer&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Overall, a nice little problem for beginning and intermediate
students.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>programming</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-code-2016-1/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 15:46:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New Term, New Tool - repl.it</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/new-term-new-tool-replit/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf4e9c8c" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgf4e9c8c"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgf4e9c8c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We're now a week in to my first class at Hunter. It's a little early
for me to really compare and contrast the high school to college
experience but I thought I'd share some thoughts on a tool that I've
recently started to play with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My students were all supposed to be issued laptops at the beginning of
the semester. The plan was to have them learn Linux, the command line,
and a little DevOps along the way. I guess I shouldn't have been too
surprised to learn that the laptops weren't going to come in until
late September.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Scratch all that advance lesson planning. A brief scramble and I was
able to relocate the class into a computer lab but now we can't
customize the kids environments. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Time to look for an online solution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We're starting the kids off in Python, a choice that I'll talk about
in some future post and normally my online go to for Python is
&lt;a href="http://codesters.com"&gt;codesters.com&lt;/a&gt;. I'm a big fan of the codesters team and product. This
time, though, I decided to try something else. Specifically &lt;a href="http://repl.it"&gt;repl.it&lt;/a&gt;. Partly because, as with
codesters, I like the people behind it. It's also pretty simple and it
supports a lot of different languages:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
APL, ES2015 ,Bloop, BrainF, C, CoffeeScript, C++, C++11, C#, Emoticon,
Forth, F#, Go, Java, JavaScript, LOLCODE, Lua, Nodejs, PHP, Python,
Python3, QBasic, Roy, Ruby, Rust, Scheme, Swift, Unlambda, and HTML, CSS, JS
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's still a pretty new product so there are occasional hiccups but
I'm really liking things so far. Some of the things I like include:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a simple clean interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sharing and embedding code:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;script src="//repl.it/embed/DF3m/19.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;project mode which allows multi file projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;examples to get you started&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But the thing I'm really liking are the teacher features they're
working on. The teacher interface isn't fancy. I like that. Things are
simple and clean and they let me get the job done.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had two extra minutes in class yesterday and in that time, I was
able to:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a classroom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Invite all my students by email&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create 2 quick assignments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The assignment page lets you give starter code as well as instructions
and it also lets you put in tests that are run when a student submits
their work for instant feedback.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I really like the tests feature on projects. So far, I've only played
with Python unit tests. Repl.it uses a really easy to follow
interface and has a sample test to guide you. There's also an option
for input/output matching which includes flexible matching and regular
expressions but I haven't played with it yet.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Overall, I'm liking this tool. When the kids get their laptops we'll
probably use it somewhat less as they start to learn to use their own
systems but I'm glad to have repl.it in my teaching arsenal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>pedagogy</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/new-term-new-tool-replit/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2016 13:26:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Lesson plans - scripts to springboards</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/lesson-plans/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I spent last Saturday up at the Microsoft offices in Times Square
observing a &lt;a href="https://www.tealsk12.org/"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; training session. My fried &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nathanielgranor"&gt;Nathaniel Granor&lt;/a&gt;, Teals
Regional Manager in the east has invited me a number of times and this
time I was able to make it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you don't know, TEALS is a program that takes volunteers in the
tech industry and places them in classrooms. Unlike other programs,
the TEALS volunteers work with the teachers while the kids learn some
CS. The idea is that the teacher will learn about CS from the
volunteer and the volunteer will learn something about teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not the same as having a strong, knowledgeable CS teacher in the
classroom but until we get there, TEALS is doing great work giving
kids something that they need and otherwise wouldn't get.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At one point, Nathaniel started to talk to the volunteers about lesson
plans emphasizing the fact that TEALS would provide all the lesson materials and
the plans so these new to teaching tech volunteers wouldn't have to
make curricular decisions. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The lesson plan form was pretty traditional and pretty formulaic:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;warm up
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hook
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;instruction 
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;practice
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assessment
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Very similar to what I was shown back in the day during my two day
"teaching boot camp" that kicked off my career &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/lesson-plans/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and very
appropriate as an effective and efficient way to prepare these
volunteers for their first days. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking about my lesson planning over the years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I started, I was teaching math but I wasn't really a math
guy - I was CS all the way. I had to remember the math from high
school, learn the new topics, and figure out how to teach it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I had a very supportive department but they were busy with their own
classes and this was pre internet. Fortunately, the NYC DOE published
lesson plan books. They were basically bound volumes of xerox copies
of hand written and typed lesson plans provided by experienced
teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I spent many hours copying them, studying  them, and then later
tweaking them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They were a life saver back then. How was the teaching? OK. Not
great. I got the material to the kids but I was nothing special. This
is where I started to form my bias against the scripted teaching
that's being pushed down today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I developed my chops, I started to design my own experiences for my
classes and things improved. By the time I was done teaching math -
maybe 4 years in, I was just scratching the surface of being a math
teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One year in, I started teaching CS along with math at Seward
Park. When I was bumped to Stuy, I went back to math for  a year and a
half and then it was all CS all the time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For CS, we didn't have lesson plan books so I had to craft everything
from scratch. It was a lot of work but the results were much better.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At first, I would actually write out lesson plans a la math lesson
plans. A "do now," "instructional objectives," "applications,"
"Homework," etc. The only thing I never formally wrote out was a
"medial summary."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over time, my lessons got better but my lesson plans looked worse and
worse. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were times a lesson plan might look something like this:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/lesson-plans/plan.jpg" alt="plan.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
OK, not exactly but as I developed at my craft, I didn't need a laid
out script to follow line for line  rather, just a set of little
reminders and maybe some printed out code. If we were going to develop
a complicated algorithm or derivation, though, I would still write out
all the steps.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This doesn't mean that as my career progressed I planned any less. It
might appear that I'm winging it but even if little to nothing is
written down, there is a plan and there's always a lot of pre work
before class begins.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, to bring this back to TEALS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's interesting how what's good in one context is not so much in
another.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What TEALS is doing is great - they've got to get a lot of
technologists in to classrooms quickly but once there, they'll be with
real, hopefully experienced teachers. What they're doing gets them
ready to go. It's a starting point, not an end.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, when I see scripted curriculum being sold as the
special sauce, be it in CS teacher "training," Teach for America
summer prep or in the name of charter school uniformity, I run the
other way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's prepare curricular  materials for important programs like TEALS
and for beginning teachers just starting out but let's not confuse a
scripted lesson that can be delivered by one and all to be anything
close to the work of a master educator and craftsman.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/lesson-plans/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;full disclosure: I
came in to teaching with zero education credentials and took the
minimum number of ed classes for my license after I started.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>curriculum</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>teals</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/lesson-plans/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2016 23:31:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Robots platforms and practicalities</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/robot-survey/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I received an email from a friend the other day asking me about a
particular robotics platform she recently saw.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've played with robotics on and off over the years ranging from
building them from (not using) scratch using Atmel chips and programming them in
assembly to using Arduino based platforms to using pre-built robot
platforms. They're really cool and since they interact with the real
world you can do all sorts of interesting and motivational things with students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've done these on my own as a hobbyist and also with students either
individually or in small groups, but never as part of a class I had
been teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why not?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The biggest reason is that the classes I've taught are already so
packed full of CS goodness that we can't even get everything done
that's theoretically on the syllabi.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other has to do with practical concerns.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Equipment costs - Let's say we can get our platform at $100 a pop. I
just can't see a public school with 34 kids in a class getting one per
student or one for every two.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what's the robot to student ratio and how much actual access do
the kids get? If they're designing  building, do they all get to
design and build? Same question with coding and operating.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then there's space – if we're talking about a mobile platform as
opposed to something that sits on the desk and is near stationary, we
have a problem. The classrooms I've taught in can barely hold the
students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are also issues with breakage, loss, theft and long term
maintainability - will we be able to or even want to fill in with
compatible units in a few years as needed or will we have to reboot
the program from scratch.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All that to deal with before we even get to the fun of teaching and learning.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm really curious about the experiences of those of you who do teach
using robots and similar platforms. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you are such a teacher, could you please fill out this form or
leave a comment for anything that the form doesn't cover?
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;iframe src="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1FlppDbeiK8uPxh_RkXoCbbdE_UDY_4qXmZWbXlZ0gGg/viewform?embedded=true" width="760" height="500" frameborder="0" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0"&gt;Loading...&lt;/iframe&gt;</description><category>hardware</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>robotics</category><category>robots</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/robot-survey/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2016 13:08:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Navajo Math Circles</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, I saw the New York Premiere of &lt;a href="http://www.zalafilms.com/navajo/"&gt;Navajo Math Circles&lt;/a&gt;, a
documentary on a &lt;a href="http://www.mathcircles.org/"&gt;Math Circle&lt;/a&gt; put in place to support and enrich the
currently under-served community in the Navajo educational system.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At their core, Math Circles are math outreach and enrichment
programs. I'm most familiar with the &lt;a href="https://www.nymathcircle.org/"&gt;New York Math Circle&lt;/a&gt;. I'm friends
with many of their teachers and organizers and my son took part in
their summer program for a couple of years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over in the southwest, these Math Circles have been bringing together
students, frequently across great distances each day to explore
problem solving and creativity through mathematics.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As someone who's worked hard to bring educational opportunities to the
have nots, I love the program. Some of the highlights include the kids
working on open ended problems, focusing on process and techniques
more than specific results, working both collaboratively but also
developing self sufficiency, and more. I also love the fact that
they've started teacher math circles to help to bring some of that
math circle magic to the everyday classroom.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I enjoyed the film and recommend you check it out to see what's
possible and I want to share my two big takeaways.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, early on in the film, one of the people running the program
talked about developing a math enrichment program through and with
Navajo traditions and culture. This is HUGE and I feel it's something
we're losing. America is so diverse from coast to coast and here in
New York City you can see radically different ways of life living
right across the street from each other. Everyone pays lip service to
"making the work interesting and relevant to the student" but few
people walk the walk. These folk do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Second, I left the documentary with a sour taste in my mouth. Not
because of the program but because the Navajo Math Circle project and
projects like it are scraping together what little resources they can
to try to do what the school systems should be doing to begin with.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
As we move to scripted lessons, national standards, curricula dictated
or at least influenced by large private concerns and standardized
tests, our schools are moving further and further away from community
and local culture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the documentary, one student pointed out that in math class, they
have to use the textbook. They learn the process and then have to
solve the problems. In Math Circle, there are no textbooks. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Afterwards, the students in from the Math Circle did some Q&amp;amp;A. I asked
them to elaborate - what's the difference between there Math Circle
experiences and their in school ones. I got:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Math Circle is fun!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think that says it all.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know many great teachers who try to bring culture and community to
their classes. One of my son's best teachers, &lt;a href="http://www.heinemann.com/authors/828.aspx"&gt;Paula Rogovin&lt;/a&gt; did it all
the time. Many of my friends and colleagues try to do so as well but
the powers that be make it harder and harder. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Until we win back public education it's important to support programs
like Math Circles (and, if I do say so myself, programs like our own
&lt;a href="http://cstuy.org"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;) and it's also critical that we work to try to bring community
and culture to our regular classes.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>curriculum</category><category>education</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 11:03:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>As curricula changes, what's falling through the cracks?</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/semaphores/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;Edit:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just a brief note to clarify a couple of things. As indicated in the
comments, this post isn't  about what's appropriate for HS CS. It's
more about what kids have after they finish their education - be it
high school, college, code school, or other. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some of my thoughts are the results of pondering on the exacerbations
of friends after interviewing people for entry level positions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The two examples are just to illustrate the point. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;Original Post:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I enjoy reading blogs. It's one of the ways I keep current. Not only
in terms of what's going on in CS Education, but also trends in CS -
academic or professional as well as on a range of other topics.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the blogs I enjoy is authored by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/b0rk"&gt;Julia Evans&lt;/a&gt;. I don't know
Julia, but we do have some mutual friends. I've enjoyed her &lt;a href="http://jvns.ca"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;. She
does a nice job talking about any number of systems related
issue. I've tried to leave comments a few times but for some reason,
my comments always end up deleted or otherwise not showing up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One recent post, one on &lt;a href="http://jvns.ca/blog/2016/03/29/thread-pools-part-ii-i-love-blocking/"&gt;concurrency&lt;/a&gt; got me thinking. Since the comment
I left there didn't take, I thought I'd write about it here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a nice post but the thing that caught my eye was when Julia
said that she " didn't know what a semaphore was until I read this
code and I was like OH THIS IS AMAZING AND SO USEFUL AND WOW." I was a
little surprised, semaphores seem to be one of those basic concepts
that you just know but that is, of course incorrect. I first learned
about semaphores in my honors Systems class with my mentor, the late
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Dewar"&gt;Robert Dewar&lt;/a&gt;. We started from test and set and worked our way up. I
had two other undergraduate classes that at least mentioned the topic.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then again, I knew that many undergrads would never get a good
treatment of concurrency so I tried to build a bit in to the System
Level Programming  course I designed while at Stuy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This got me thinking - according to her linked in, Julia was a CS
major at McGill - a university that I hold in high regard but either
semaphores were never covered or their treatment didn't make enough of
an impact to be worth remembering. What topics do we cover in our
classes that kids just let fall to the wayside and what topics do we
end up losing as curricula change and we don't have an eye on the big
picture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One big one is memory management. When APCS and college 101 classes
went to Java, memory management went out the window. Not a problem, as
long as memory issues are covered in some other course. Unfortunately
the don't seem to be. You can make a case that kids don't need to
understand memory management or anything about garbage collection but
I'd argue that while one might never have to do their own memory
management a good CS person should have some understanding of what's
going on under the hood or as my friend Gerry says "never use a
technology you couldn't write yourself."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another biggie that I lived through was the IBM PC era. Prior to the
mid to late 80's when the IBM PC ruled the world, kids learned about
CS on timesharing systems. Once the PC took hold, every kid learning
programming or studying CS was working on their own machine. They had
full access to everything and the machine just supported a single
thread. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the one hand, it was nice since you could easily play with low
level programming and hardware but on the other hand, a hole
generation didn't learn about the complexities of multiple users and
multiple processes. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Early in my career I designed courses and only later did I realize
that you can't just design a course, you have to look at the full arc
of a students education. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think it's interesting to think about what concepts are getting left
on the side of the road and I wonder if the big players driving CS
education spend any time thinking about this bigger picture.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>pedagogy</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/semaphores/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 13:08:36 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>