<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>C'est la Z (policy)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/policy.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2016 15:44:41 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Computational Thinkers in Scotland</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/scotland/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I'm way behind on my &lt;a href="http://cacm.acm.org/"&gt;Communications of the ACM&lt;/a&gt;. I generally only read
them when I use my trainer in the mornings and with summer running and
outside riding, I'm still on the December 2015 issue.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This morning, I read a viewpoint by Jeremy Scott and Alan Bundy on &lt;a href="http://cacm.acm.org/magazines/2015/12/194638-creating-a-new-generation-of-computational-thinkers/abstract"&gt;a
program in Scotland&lt;/a&gt;. If you're an ACM member, and if you're a CS
practitioner, student, academic, or teacher you should be, you can read the piece for details.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
Me? I noticed a number of similarities between what Bundy and Scott
described and efforts here in the USA including some of the red flags.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not here to talk about the program described in detail or their
successes and failures. I don't have enough information to fairly
comment on that. I'm here in my usual role of curmudgeon to highlight
common red flags that if unheeded could cost all of us the opportunity
to get really great CS Ed to all of our students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One red flag right away were a number of references to the program
being curriculum and materials driven, not teacher driven. The
viewpoint states that materials "were designed to be used by even
non-specialist teachers." We see the same thing here in the USA and
not just in CS Ed. Teaching overall is being devalued with the elite
pushing programs that handcuff good teachers to a script (which leads
students towards "success" in passing a nonsense standardized exam)
all the while sending their own kids to elite private schools with
knowledgeable teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know i didn't want my kids to be taught chemistry history or any
other subject by a teacher that hasn't studied the content yet here we
go saying it's okay for CS. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The counter argument is that we have to do something now and we'll do
better later. We all go in with the best of intentions but more often
than not, once a politician has their sound bite and once a cheap
apparent solution is in place, it's good enough and we're done. I
ranted about that a while back both &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-04-expedient-vs-good.html/#.V-5UqN9vGAk"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-07-learning-takes-time.html/#.V-5Uot9vGAk"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. To their credit,
Bundy and Scott talk a bit about this concern in the piece.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The piece also said "It is also necessary to employ a pedagogy that is
informed by the latest research into the most effective ways to teach
computing." This sounds good but the truth is, education research
doesn't have the best reputation among educators. Last month, I
asked one of the best math teachers around what was being bandied
about as best practices in math education according to "the
research?" He basically said "the research says do &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;fad du jour&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
but that doesn't work for me so I just do &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;actually good technique&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the years, I've spoken to many teachers and by and large the best
ones discredit "the research." Of course, my comment will be
discredited by ed researchers saying that "you're just giving
anecdotes" but then, if I did the same thing while employed as a
researcher, did a couple of surveys and submitted it for publication,
then it would be "research." So much of teaching is a craft and the
truth is, practitioners know best.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Related to this is authentication by citing authority. Particularly
dangerous in our field because many people with little to no real
background in teaching CS are anointed as experts and thought leaders
(see this post: &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-26-self-appointed-experts.html/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). In this case, the viewpoint cites Cameron
Fadjo. I've only met Cameron once or twice and he seems like a sharp
guy but when he was given the post of Director of Software Engineering
for NYC, according to his linked in profile, he had neither taught k12
nor had any real CS background.  This is of course the profile of many
CS Education thought leaders. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My overall take. It sounds like just like here, Scotland has people
trying to make a difference and trying to do good. It also sounds like
they're falling into the same traps and pitfalls as we are on this
side of the Atlantic.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/scotland/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2016 11:28:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Federal Aid for Code Schools - is this a good thing?</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/fed-aid-for-code-schools/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I saw this headline earlier today: &lt;a href="http://www.inc.com/salvador-rodriguez/coding-bootcamps-just-got-a-big-boost.html"&gt;The U.S. Just Made a Bold Move to Improve Diversity in Tech&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The article talks about a program by which a number of code schools
will be able to accept federal student aid. I don't know if we're
talking student loans or  grants but I'm not sure it matters.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The headline sounds great. I'm not so sure that this is a good thing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My thinking's evolved over the years but right now, everything tells
me that public funds and for profit education don't mix.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What we, more often than not, end up with is a cash cow for a private concern. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Example one: The edTPA - a required exam for teacher licensing, at
least in NY. Prospective teachers pay hundreds of dollars to pass this
gatekeeper. Pearson, a private company (and not even an American one)
is essentially in charge of teacher licensing. They make the
assessments, they grade them, they decide who passes. A foreign
company is deciding who teaches our kids and at great expense to those
prospective teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We'd be much better off going back to the old days. To become a
teacher, you had to pass through "The board of examiners." Basically,
to get your permanent license you had to do an oral defense. Teachers
would be placed in a room of principals, supervisors, and master
teachers for an open grilling. It was cheaper and MUCH more
effective. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Example two: The PSAT 8/9, PSAT, and SAT. These are exams that tell us
one thing: how kids will do on future PSAT and SAT tests. They're not
good predictors of college success but the college board (a non-profit
in name only) has convinced us, or at least "convinced" our
politicians of the exams importance. So, rather than having
individuals make a choice as to whether or not to take these exams, NY
forks over who knows how much money per year so that our kids can take
a test with the belief that the exam will mystically make them college
ready. To make matters worse, students lose a day of instruction and
teachers have to proctor the exam instead of teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Example three: Common core tests. Made in secret, graded in secret
with cut off scores designed after the fact. Absolutely no educational
value but once again, public funds flow freely into testing companies.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem is that these private concerns never really have to show
results and they're never held accountable and since the money we pay
them is hidden in city and state budgets, the taxpayer is none the wiser.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what about code schools?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In a similar vein, money will flow from the government to the code
schools. The question is, do they really have the secret sauce.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have lots of friends who run and work in code schools and have met
many more. Some code schools are trying to really educate and some
not so much. In any case, let's take a look.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You frequently hear about the success stories but for every one of
those, you can also find a manager talking about the fact that the
code school graduate can't do anything other than ape the narrow tool
that they were exposed to in the three or so months at the code
school. So, the truth is that results are probably a mixed bag.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Is this good? Well, when you consider the typical code school MO it
really isn't.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To attend a for profit code school you have to not only afford the
tuition but also be able to sustain yourself for the duration of the
program. That makes most code schools options for the well to do -
those already well positioned for success.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then they make the candidates go through pre-work – frequently online
course work. So, before you even step into a code school, they know
you're likely going to succeed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once in, they train the candidates in a narrow slice of tech. I've
talked to a number of code school leaders about that. I've asked how
well the kids would be able to adapt given the constraints of their 3
month or so training. The typical answer was that the candidate could
just re-up and pay again to learn the next limited time only skill.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Should taxpayer dollars go to this? Probably not. There's no
indication that code schools can provide meaningful long lasting
education to even those who are best prepared to learn on their
own. Whats' more, we haven't seen evidence that they have the answers
for the under-served. Combine that with government's history of not
keeping an eye on and not holding accountable private education
providers, I think we're just setting up a new line of corporate
welfare that will, on the surface help some but it is in no way the
answer. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Too often public/private means that the private entity gets the money
and the public gets stuck holding the bag. Better would be to have
tech companies foot the bill. Some coding schools already do
this. Tech companies that are happy with coding school graduates can
finance the program. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What we should be doing is focusing on things like community
colleges. Organizations that are supposed to be real, long term,
community centers. With moderate tweaking, there's no reason why a
community college, not to mention 4 year schools, couldn't provide far
superior preparation than even the best code school.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/fed-aid-for-code-schools/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 19:42:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ed Disruption - why it's different</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ed-disrupt-why-diff/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Earlier today I read &lt;a href="http://www.eliothorowitz.com/blog/2016/07/25/innovate-vs-appropriate/"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/eliothorowitz"&gt;Eliot Horowitz&lt;/a&gt;, founder and CTO of MongoDB.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Eliot titled the post "Innovate vs Appropriate" and talks about the
importance of knowing when to come up with something new vs when to
use the accepted tool, technique, or method. Eliot, of course is
discussing this as it applies to MongoDB and it's well worth a read
but it got me thinking about the ever popular need to "disrupt"
education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've witnessed this disruption or Ed Reform for the last decade
plus. The basic notion that public education isn't working so we need
to disrupt things. We've suffered through:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vouchers
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charters
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Online "learning" replacing teachers
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teach for America and other temp type efforts
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Merit pay
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VAM for teacher evaluation
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and more
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These disruptions are brought to you by your friendly neighborhood
billionaire "philanthropist" or your politicians.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
By and large, they haven't worked.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Bill Gates got us to close down community schools and create small
ones. While we did need more small schools, overall it didn't work
(&lt;a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/marc-epstein/small-schools-miracle-or_b_2641400.html?utm_hp_ref=new-york"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/answer-sheet/wp/2014/06/09/how-much-bill-gatess-disappointing-small-schools-effort-really-cost/%0A"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;). VAM teacher evaluation is &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/answer-sheet/wp/2014/06/09/how-much-bill-gatess-disappointing-small-schools-effort-really-cost/%0A"&gt;arbitrary and capricious&lt;/a&gt;,
merit pay has &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/answer-sheet/post/ravitch-why-merit-pay-for-teachers-doesnt-work/2011/03/29/AFn5w9yB_blog.html"&gt;never worked&lt;/a&gt;, nor does the &lt;a href="http://educationnext.org/online-charters-mostly-dont-work-forum-virtual-schools-greg-richmond/"&gt;online thing&lt;/a&gt;. Meanwhile, charter
schools by and large &lt;a href="http://www.nea.org/home/32999.htm"&gt;don't do better&lt;/a&gt; than public schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Rather than saving our schools, these efforts have lowered teacher
morale and done little for our most vulnerable children.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what's the difference between ed disruption and the tech world?
Well, for starters, those disrupting education totally ignore the very
advice that Eliot posted about today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Disruption to and of our public schools hasn't been a matter
appropriating what works and innovating what needs to be innovated but rather
a playground for pet projects of politicians and well meaning rich
folk.  Rather than looking at something simple that works, like, say,
smaller class sizes, we get computerized testing. Instead of
experienced teachers, we get inexperienced newbies that leave after
their commitment is up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why the difference? It hit me while reading Eliot's post. When a
founder is "disrupting" he has skin in the game - it's his company -
sink or swim. Not so for education reformers. Politicians merely need
to be re-elected.Sso as long as something looks good short term, it is
good. Those who disrupt schools are never held accountable. We got
small schools and VAM from among other places, Bill Gates. He admitted
his reforms didn't work but was there any penalty for disrupting so
many lives? Nope. For politicians, it's the same story. As Mayor Mike
Bloomberg once said "If they don't like my education policy, they can
boo me at parades."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Can we fix this? Sure, but not unless those forcing the changes have
real skin in the game. Will it happen? I'm not holding my breath.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>disruption</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ed-disrupt-why-diff/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2016 23:32:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hillary and Student Loans</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I read over Hillary's briefing on her initiative on
&lt;a href="https://www.hillaryclinton.com/briefing/factsheets/2016/06/27/hillary-clintons-initiative-on-technology-innovation/"&gt;Technology and Innovation&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A lot of it sounds good but, at least for the education piece, I have
my doubts. My feeling is that she's pretty much aligned with the
current administration education wise and the current administration
has been as bad if not worse than the previous with respect to public
education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While I have issues with some of the education pieces and very much
like some of the others, I don't want to get into that today. I want
to focus on one specific part of her plan. The part that defers
college debt for up to 3 years for founders and entrepreneurs. This
sounds great but is this really a good thing?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some initial responses from the education community is "what about
young teachers, don't they deserve some help on college debt? What
about nurses?…" and of course they're right. On the other hand, I
don't want people to go into teaching for 2 or 3 years just to get
some debt relief benefit and then jump ship. That's the Teach for
America model that I feel has become so harmful.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But again, that's not where I'm going with this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's start with "who are these founders?" I don't have any hard data
but I have read a couple of recent pieces that indicate that founders
right out of college are typically from well to do backgrounds. This
of course makes sense. A kid up to his or her eyes in debt from a poor
background. No savings, no property, likely a family, that is siblings
and parents who are also treading water can ill afford to take a big
financial risk. A kid from a monied family? Much more so. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This alone makes Hillary's plan a boon for the wealthy but not so
much for the people we need to give a hand up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Next, this plan talks about the founders and only says it will
"explore similar incentives"  for early employees, citing "10 to 20."
This doesn't seem right to me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now let's look further into the benefits. I don't know what the
success and failure rates are for startups. I've seen a bunch of
figures including:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;90% of startups fail within the first three years
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three out of four startups fail 
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Of 10 startups, 3 or 4 totally fail, 3 or 4 break even and the
others turn a profit.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know where the truth lies but I'd imagine that the success
rate for startup by a recent college graduate, wet behind the ears is
probably higher than for a more season professionals.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hillary's plan defers debt for up to three years. If any of the
failure numbers cited above are near correct it means that these kids
will have burned through up to three years with the experience of a
failed startup to show for it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've always advised my students, all things being equal, start at a
big or mid size company, develop your chops, learn how they do it,
further build out your network, and then go out and do your
thing. Most kids are better served not going directly from college to
their first startup.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So there it is. A plan that makes for great "press release" but is it
really addressing the issues?
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><category>tech</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 21:38:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>PDF 2016 - How we lost the open web</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pdf2016-lost-in-the-silo/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I spent the last couple of days attending &lt;a href="http://go.personaldemocracy.com/"&gt;Personal Democracy Forum
2016&lt;/a&gt;, described on their landing site as:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The world’s leading conference exploring and analyzing technology's
impact on politics, government, and society.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's the reason why I haven't posted my latest Emacs video.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
PDF is a great conference and raised a huge number of important
issues. I'll probably blog about a few over the next few weeks. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One topic that I've already lamented about has been the way we as a
society are allowing so much information to be silo-ed in platforms
like Facebook.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I use Facebook as much as the next guy but it always irks me when I
see a CS Education post followed by rich discussion hidden within
Facebook's walls and not available for discovery to the outside world
and the future.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I generally don't get a lot of comments on my posts, but when I do,
more appear in the Facebook link to my post rather than publicly on
the post itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the conference, we watched a video by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hossein_Derakhshan"&gt;Hossein Derakhshan&lt;/a&gt; which
talked about the direction the web is moving in and the red flags it
should raise with all of us. He echoed my concerns and beyond but in a much more
eloquent way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm urging you to take the less than ten minutes to watch this
video. I know school's winding down for all of us but for those of you
who are teachers out there - share this with your students. I'm sure a
rich discussion will follow.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/oBLAZZd_Xqc" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description><category>civic tech</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pdf2016-lost-in-the-silo/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2016 18:41:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Navajo Math Circles</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, I saw the New York Premiere of &lt;a href="http://www.zalafilms.com/navajo/"&gt;Navajo Math Circles&lt;/a&gt;, a
documentary on a &lt;a href="http://www.mathcircles.org/"&gt;Math Circle&lt;/a&gt; put in place to support and enrich the
currently under-served community in the Navajo educational system.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At their core, Math Circles are math outreach and enrichment
programs. I'm most familiar with the &lt;a href="https://www.nymathcircle.org/"&gt;New York Math Circle&lt;/a&gt;. I'm friends
with many of their teachers and organizers and my son took part in
their summer program for a couple of years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over in the southwest, these Math Circles have been bringing together
students, frequently across great distances each day to explore
problem solving and creativity through mathematics.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As someone who's worked hard to bring educational opportunities to the
have nots, I love the program. Some of the highlights include the kids
working on open ended problems, focusing on process and techniques
more than specific results, working both collaboratively but also
developing self sufficiency, and more. I also love the fact that
they've started teacher math circles to help to bring some of that
math circle magic to the everyday classroom.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I enjoyed the film and recommend you check it out to see what's
possible and I want to share my two big takeaways.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, early on in the film, one of the people running the program
talked about developing a math enrichment program through and with
Navajo traditions and culture. This is HUGE and I feel it's something
we're losing. America is so diverse from coast to coast and here in
New York City you can see radically different ways of life living
right across the street from each other. Everyone pays lip service to
"making the work interesting and relevant to the student" but few
people walk the walk. These folk do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Second, I left the documentary with a sour taste in my mouth. Not
because of the program but because the Navajo Math Circle project and
projects like it are scraping together what little resources they can
to try to do what the school systems should be doing to begin with.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
As we move to scripted lessons, national standards, curricula dictated
or at least influenced by large private concerns and standardized
tests, our schools are moving further and further away from community
and local culture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the documentary, one student pointed out that in math class, they
have to use the textbook. They learn the process and then have to
solve the problems. In Math Circle, there are no textbooks. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Afterwards, the students in from the Math Circle did some Q&amp;amp;A. I asked
them to elaborate - what's the difference between there Math Circle
experiences and their in school ones. I got:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Math Circle is fun!!!!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think that says it all.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know many great teachers who try to bring culture and community to
their classes. One of my son's best teachers, &lt;a href="http://www.heinemann.com/authors/828.aspx"&gt;Paula Rogovin&lt;/a&gt; did it all
the time. Many of my friends and colleagues try to do so as well but
the powers that be make it harder and harder. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Until we win back public education it's important to support programs
like Math Circles (and, if I do say so myself, programs like our own
&lt;a href="http://cstuy.org"&gt;CSTUY&lt;/a&gt;) and it's also critical that we work to try to bring community
and culture to our regular classes.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>curriculum</category><category>education</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/navajo-circles/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 11:03:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Collaborative Coding or Cheating</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/collaborative-coding-or-cheating/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I haven't been teaching this past semester. That's why I haven't been
writing much about lessons. I miss working with students but that will
resume in the fall and this semester has allowed me to get a jump on
new projects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's also allowed me to look at some student issues from a bit of a
distance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One issue that keeps coming up is cheating. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some of it, classroom cheating. my friend &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cscheerleader"&gt;Ria&lt;/a&gt; recently asked a
question on Facebook about it. A nice thread ensued but unfortunately,
it's locked in the Facebook silo. I've got a lot to say on that and
hope to explore it soon but today let's focus on project
cheating - something that could just as easily apply to homeworks and
student essays and research papers as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One part of the question is on students using code they find out in
the wild. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred&lt;/a&gt; wrote a bit about it on his blog &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2016/05/copying-codesteal-from-best.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; where he points
out some pluses, some minuses, and raises some good thought points.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I want to keep it in the class - code sharing amongst students,
project and source code submission, and group projects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teachers have all sorts of options these days including:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using a CMS like Blackboard or Moodle
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dropbox based solutions
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emailing projects
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using development tools and sites such as git with GitHub, BitBucket
or other repository hosting services
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've always been a fan of having the kids learn real software
engineering skills along with the CS so Git, GitHub and public repos
have been my weapon of choice.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Interesting enough, I've gotten an earful both from fellow teachers
and professors and online for my stance on public repos. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I keep hearing "the kids will copy from each other" or something like
that. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As Alfred said in his post: "Students have been copying from
classmates for years."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Students who want to copy assignments have done so long before we've
been teaching CS and they'll be doing it for years to come. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Using a hidden submission system doesn't help and could hurt.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Far better to create an open environment. You get an opportunity to
talk about code sharing, attribution, learning from each other,
supporting each other, and where to draw the line.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On top of that, the students learn a real tool set and have a chance
to learn real development methodologies.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a win all around.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Will open repos stop cheating and irresponsible copying? Certainly
not. It could, however, raise awareness. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So what do I do on the cheating front?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Besides trying to create a culture where cheating is discouraged,
cooperation is encouraged but where students know the line, I will try
to keep them honest. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Frequently, the day a big project is due, I'll give a quiz on the
project. Students will have to describe parts of the project and what
they did. Either a student will have had to contributed or at least
will have had to have studied the rest of the teams code to pass the
quiz.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
GitHub also gives tools that help. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's the GitHub graph for a project:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/github-graph.png" alt="github-graph.png" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can see who did what and when. The teacher can drill down further
to examine the diffs – what code did each student write, when, and
from where. If two students submit very similar code, the commit
timestamps will even tell you who was first.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The tooling for teachers could be better but the infrastructure is
there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Technology isn't going to prevent cheating and more often than not, it
seems that measures taken don't stop the bad guys but inconvenience
those trying to do it right.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Much better to build a class culture where the kids want to do it the
right way.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cheating</category><category>git</category><category>github</category><category>policy</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/collaborative-coding-or-cheating/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 11:25:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A World Without Advanced Placement</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/world-without-college-board/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some good points in the Facebook comments on my &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-we-dont-trust-teachers/#.Vy5aAd9vH0o"&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;. One notable
comment was the fact that many teachers wouldn't be able to gain the
traction needed to teach CS without an AP designation. This is true
but also sad that we've awarded such educational authority to a
private company that's accountable to no one. Schools should run
courses because they're good for kids not specifically because they're
AP.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Stuyvesant just implemented a policy that every student has to take at
least one AP class to graduate and that now every student in an AP
class has to take the AP exam. There's also been a push for Stuy to
run APCS Principles in spite of the fact that the current home grown
intro course is superior.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These policies and pushes at Stuy are purely for the sake of ratings
and in no way for the benefit of the student.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But let's imagine a world without the college board.  To do this we're
going to have to take off our computer science hats and look at
another, more established high school subject area - mathematics.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, setting the stage.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's the mid 1990's. High school students across the nation are taking
math classes. Some are even taking calculus. This makes the College
Board happy since they offer two AP Calculus exams. But the College
Board notices that many students aren't ready for calculus. To fill
this gap, they create &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AP_Statistics"&gt;AP Statistics&lt;/a&gt;. First offered in 1997 to 7,667
students it was given to almost 200,000 students last year.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
According to wikipedia, the course was created to give an AP
mathematics option for students not ready for calculus. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't seem to recall any huge demand for an AP statistics course but
it was created and adopted. It turned into one of the fastest growing
AP classes and a nice money maker for the college board. I don't know
how the class was pushed or perceived in other schools but at Stuy it
was seen as a way to get an easy AP math course on the
transcript. Before any statisticians get the torches and pitchforks -
I'm just relaying the student perception. I haven't looked into the
course sufficiently to form an opinion on it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, let's imagine a world without the College Board.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
An individual school would look at it's students needs and decide if
they needed an additional math course. Maybe they'd conclude that what they
were doing was fine or maybe they would conclude that a new class was
needed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If they decided they needed a new advanced course the school would
either have the expertise to create it in house or they'd probably
turn to the local college or university for guidance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They might end up with a course very similar to AP Statistics or they
might end up with something very different. They might
end up with another class like Discrete Math or they might end up
partnering with the college and having students take classes there. In
all cases, since math teachers generally have a pretty good math
backgroud, schools could make good decisions and design sound
educational experiences for their kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All of these seem to be better results for the students than blindly
following the College Board - keeping
education and education decisions local.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What about CS?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I admit that's a tougher nut to crack.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most schools generally don't currently have the in house expertise
needed to build their own solutions or even to really critically judge
what's out there. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That said, even if you need join the cult of the College Board to get
your school to run some CS you can:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grab all the materials you can find - those labeled AP and those not
labeled AP.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't bother with AP Syllabus certification. Teach what you think is
best. Designate the class as honors to differentiate them from other
classes.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engage with your local college and tech sector. They're not high
school educators but they are valuable resources.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unrelated side note - be wary of code schools - most don't really
have any educational chops.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't force kids to sit for the exams and only encourage them to do
so if the exam will likely do something for the kid.  
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think that's it or my College Board rants.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then again, I also thought that when I wrote Friday's post.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/world-without-college-board/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2016 21:07:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Advanced Placement - Because We Don't Trust Teachers</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-we-dont-trust-teachers/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/college-board/"&gt;Yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I ranted on about the College Board. This led to a Facebook
hosted discussion which got me thinking a little more:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Advanced Placement exams basically exist because we don't trust our
high school teachers. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I usually use phrases like "society doesn't trust" but let's
personalize it this time – for parents, think about whether or not you trust your
kids teachers? Do you a large private, unaccountable organization
more?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you teach an advanced placement course, in order for your class to
be listed as AP you have to submit your syllabus to the college board
for approval. This sounds like they're setting a standard but it's
not. I can point to a bunch of teachers who have submitted identical syllabi
where sometimes it's accepted but ofttimes it's rejected. This is the
syllabus we submitted originally for Stuy. Yes, we have high achieving
kids, but given the fact that the syllabus was approved originally and
that Stuy students just about all score 4 or 5 on APCS-A should tell
you something about the level of care or competence of the College
Board.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then you teach the class and in May, one to two months before the end
of the semester the kids take the AP exam - you don't see results
until the summer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In theory, if the kids do well they can receive placement or
credit. The problem is, fewer and fewer schools are giving credit,
when they do, it might not help due to the way undergrads pay for
courses and placement can generally be achieved by appealing to
college departments or by taking college administered placements.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back to the trust thing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In college, you take a course, the final exam is created by the
professor or a group of professors and it's graded by the people that
teach the course - possibly as a committee. Kids final grades include
these exams but a student can fail a final or even miss one and still
pass the class whereas an AP exam is a one shot deal and even if you
"pass" you might not get anything from it. I'm not even getting into
questioning the quality and content of the exams. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Kids get their grades and college credit. There are no outside
"standardized exams" and we trust that the professors and the colleges
are educating our kids. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, in high school, teachers make their lessons, teach their classes,
create, administer, and grade final exams and kids get grade - but not
for college level classes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know multiple high school physics, chemistry, math, and computer
science teachers who are far better at teaching than their college
counterparts yet my friend the math teacher isn't trusted to assess
his calculus students for the purpose of college credit - we don't
trust him but we trust the faceless entity known as the College
Board. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Think about that for a minute.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You trust your child's teacher with your child's well being every
day but you don't trust him to say whether or not your kid knows
calculus?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is a real problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have a friend who frequently doesn't quite finish the BC Calculus
test topics because he actually teaches the material in depth –
instead of "follow the scripts" the kids go through proofs and
derivations. It costs the kids - I know a number of them who got a 4
on the BC exam rather than a 5 but come the end of June when the class
is done, they know more calculus more deeply than a lot of kids who've
taken the class in college. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The lines of college have been blurred with more and more "remedial"
classes being taught at the college level and more and more "college
level" being taught in the high schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a really sad state of affairs when we trust our professors - many
of whom are hired more for research than for their teaching chops
and we don't trust our teachers during our kids more formative years.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-we-dont-trust-teachers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 07 May 2016 10:59:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Remember, school is all about profit, wait no, I mean testing, no, I mean...</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/college-board/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
It's important to remember, the college board is about making money
for the college board. It's not about supporting teachers and it's
certainly  not about educating kids.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Kids took the AP Computer Science A exam last week and the College
Board just released the free response questions. There seems to me
more chatter about them in social media than in past years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm just left wondering how AP became the be all and end all.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From where I stand, the College Board, who runs AP, SAT, and PSAT
exams is all about making money for the College Board - they're a
non-profit in name only.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's all about market share and dominance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Looking at APCS A, it's not a great exam or course. At Stuy, I taught
a super-set of the old AB and pretty much ignored the parts I didn't
like (that is, the case study) but many schools can't do that. In my
case, most of the schools my kids went to didn't award credit, even
for a 5. They did sometimes award placement but I've had just as many,
if not more kids gain placement just by showing their work to the CS
department at their chosen school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now they're rolling out APCS Principles. I do get the fact that many
schools don't have people to roll their own courses, but I'm not
overly impressed by much of what's come out. I think what we've
developed is stronger and time proven.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Regardless, and moving beyond just CS, the College Board has somehow
bamboozled the public to think AP = Good. Colleges are awarding less
and less credit but everyone's telling the kids to take more and more
AP classes. What's worse, somehow US News and World Report magically
became an authority on school ratings and now the more AP classes your
kids take the better.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know of at least one school with a highly lauded principal boast
about all his kids came in behind in math and by their senior year
passed honors calculus. Looking at the data unfortunately showed that
while all his seniors took the class, all failed, scoring below
a 3. It made the school look great but I'd argue that it was child
abuse.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The principal of course parlayed that gig to an even higher profile
one.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, you could just file the stupid paperwork so that you can run
classes labeled as AP and have kids take the classes but not the exam
but the College Board's working on that - there are rumblings in NY
on using &lt;a href="http://www.chalkbeat.org/posts/ny/2016/04/13/new-york-considering-using-scores-on-ap-exams-and-sat-subject-tests-in-teacher-evaluations/#.VyyRlN9vGAk"&gt;student AP scores in teacher ratings&lt;/a&gt;. Using student test
results for teacher ratings is already a bad idea - using AP is even
worse.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, to really get the cash cow going, AP is entering deals with
agencies and municipalities for large scale testing – in NY students will have to take the
SAT and &lt;a href="http://nymag.com/daily/intelligencer/2015/10/nyc-will-give-free-sat-testing-to-hs-juniors.html"&gt;take it for free&lt;/a&gt;. Then there's code.org's deal free PD for
school's that have their kids take &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-19-code-org-college-board.html/"&gt;yet another meaningless exam&lt;/a&gt;, the
new PSAT/8-9.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, none of this is free - it's our taxpayer money hard at work
being shuttled right into the college board.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What are we getting? Tests that they create and control and are
EXTREMELY secretive about that don't tell us anyhting that we don't
already know about our kids. Oh, and teachers lose instructional time
and have to &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-10-13-psat.html/#.VyzHNN9vGAk"&gt;proctor&lt;/a&gt; these exams instead of teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Great deal if you can get it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, what's the value of this – more meaningless tests for the
kids. I don't know if there's a record of this anywhere but in the
pre-internet day, I remember watching a news report where a College
Board representative stated that the SAT was a valid predictor of one
thing - how students would do on future SAT exams.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, were left with more money flowing to an outside company with
students taking more meaningless tests.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I wish more schools showed the backbone that Fieldston, an elite
private school in NY had when it &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/01/nyregion/high-school-drops-its-ap-courses-and-colleges-don-t-seem-to-mind.html"&gt;dropped A.P. courses&lt;/a&gt; over 10 years
ago. They still seem to be well regarded as a school and their kids do
just fine in terms of college acceptance.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/college-board/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2016 11:03:36 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>