<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about politics</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/politics.atom</id>
  <updated>2017-03-01T15:24:50Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/politics.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/politics/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>It's not one issue, it's the President and his enablers</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/trump-issues/</id>
    <updated>2017-01-29T10:39:53-05:00</updated>
    <published>2017-01-29T10:39:53-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/trump-issues/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Like many of my fellow bloggers and tweeters, I generally keep this
site clear of political issues with the exception of those that are
directly related to education. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Also, like many of my fellow bloggers and tweeters, this week has
provided a reason to break with that tradition.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Many people, including some friends, all more eloquent than I have
already posted, tweeted, and Facebooked  about the behavior of our
President and government.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Long time blogger &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/davewiner"&gt;Dave Winer&lt;/a&gt; put together &lt;a href="http://trumpstatus.org/"&gt;trumpstatus.org&lt;/a&gt; where he's
collecting many of the issues that we're all so alarmed with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I would add cabinet appointments to his list with my particular
personal concern over DeVos and the department of education. I've been
meaning to blog about that for a while - perhaps this week.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
My concern for today is something else. Every day, I see a new Trump
induced crisis and every day I see a different subset of my circles
respond. It's not quite as bad as:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First they came for the Socialists, and I did not speak out—
Because I was not a Socialist.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then they came for the Trade Unionists, and I did not speak out—
Because I was not a Trade Unionist.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then they came for the Jews, and I did not speak out—
Because I was not a Jew.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then they came for me—and there was no one left to speak for me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
People are indeed speaking out, but I am concerned that people
are going to rise up for their personal issue and when placated go
back to business as usual - this is &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;NOT&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; the time for business as
usual.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With the ACA repeal, I saw concerns from my working class friends and
friends that work with lower earning populations. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Going into the DeVos hearing, mostly educators - real educators not
astroturf reformers. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With Friday's order, the whole tech community came out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's part of a thread by tech activist &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anildash"&gt;Anil Dash&lt;/a&gt; calling out,
calling on, and crediting assorted tech players.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;When net neutrality was the issue, Google, Twitter, Wikipedia, Reddit, Tumblr, etc. had a blackout, and it worked. This is far more grave.&lt;/p&gt;— Anil Dash (@anildash) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anildash/status/825414889908928517"&gt;January 28, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;A powerful, straightforward statement from the CEO of Box — another publicly-traded company. &lt;a href="https://t.co/wz5mQmTh6P"&gt;https://t.co/wz5mQmTh6P&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Anil Dash (@anildash) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anildash/status/825470308463280130"&gt;January 28, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We have to remember that all these order, policies, appointments, and
plans are coming from the same place - Donald Trump and those
politicians that are enabling him.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If he backs off on immigration, education issues remain, if he backs
off there, we still have ACA, if that eases up, what about Women's
rights and on and on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This means we all have to get involved and stay involved. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What have I been doing?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I finally joined the ACLU and set up a monthly donation.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I subscribed to &lt;a href="https://dailyaction.org"&gt;Daily Action&lt;/a&gt; so that I get a reminder each day of
someone I can call to make a difference.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm starting to accumulate my representatives phone numbers as I
make those calls and am trying to make at least a call a day to
remind our representatives who they work for.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Education and advocacy
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
And if you suggestions for me - please post them here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thus ends my not business as usual post. What's going on in America is
not someone else's problem - it's all of our problem and we all have
to be active and vigilant to make it through tough times to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
    <category term="politics" label="politics"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
