<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about policy)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/policy.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2018 21:31:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Giving control of NYC's specialized schools to a political appointee</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat-part2/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgda4fee7" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgda4fee7"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgda4fee7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I shared my thoughts on Bill de Blasio's plans to "fix" the
selection criteria for New York City's specialized high schools. If
you haven't read the post, you can find it &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was going to get back to CS and CS Ed related blogging today but
there's more to the story.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In spite of what BdB stated, it's not enough for him to switch to another
measure - the middle school state exam along with some modifiers. This
is about ending the exam altogether and not replacing it with anything
better. Here's a link to information on the proposed legislation for
&lt;a href="https://legiscan.com/NY/bill/A10427/2017"&gt;New York Assembly Bill 10427&lt;/a&gt; including links to the actual text.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's a lot of beurobabble but the end game is to basically allow
the chancellor (not sure if this means city or state) to do whatever
they want.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here are some of the key points:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seats would ultimately go to the top 5 to 7 percent of each middle school's
class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These students would have to also be classified in the top 25% city wide.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Top is defined by a composite score of multiple measures as
determined by the chancellor which means anything goes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remaining seats will be filled by
lottery of all students with a 3.7 GPA or greater.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's not clear how the students would be allocated to each of the
specialized schools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what does this all mean? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Multiple measures could mean the state test + average. It could mean
average + recommendation. It could be shoe size + favorite color. The
chancellor also decides how to weight these multiple measures. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This means that the politicians can do whatever they want to paint any
picture they want regardless of how their ideological and political
games hurt kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Any teacher, in fact, any rational adult  will tell you that middle
schools are not interchangeable. The top students at one middle school
are typically not at the same level as top students at another
one. I'm sure you can cluster middle schools in terms of the students
they graduate, what the students know and can do and the clusters will
likely fall on economic lines. This is the problem that BdB should be
addressing not how to rig the specialized school admissions stats. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even if this is done right, you're assuming an even distribution of
top gifted students across all the middle schools. If one school has
higher concentration of gifted students, they're out of luck. The end
result is that if you attend an SP or other gifted program for eighth
grade you'll likely be locked out of the specialized schools. What if
a particular middle school is attractive to all of our top math team
talent? Only a couple will get in to the specialized schools under the
new system since each school is allocated a fixed number of slots. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I guess this does make sense if you don't believe in gifted students
or gifted education but then why not just get rid of the specialized
schools to begin with rather than playing these games. This "solution"
will result in parents having to decide - do I send my kids to the
gifted middle school program and hurt their chances to get into a
specialized high school or do I try to find the lowest performing
school I can find and have my kid stand out. This is pretty messed up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day, though, you have to remember that any change to
the process can help one group and hurt another. Stuy, for example has
46% of it's students on free or reduced lunch and is about 70%
Asian. If in the new system you're increasing the percent population
of an under represented group, you're likely reducing the percentage
of Asian students. So, you're creating opportunities for a number of as of yet
undetermined students (who might not be properly prepared for the
experience) at the expense of economically disadvantaged Asian
students who have proven to be prepared for the experience. Wouldn't
a better solution be to fix the opportunities presented at the middle
schools rather than rig the system of high school acceptance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Going further, a response on another blog noted that BdB probably
refused to do anything with the admissions criteria of the non big
three because they all had numbers that he would consider more
diverse. The commenter provided the Black / Latino percentages, I added the
free and reduced lunch numbers:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="border" border-spacing="10px"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;School&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Percent Black / Latino&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Free / Reduced Lunch&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Brooklyn Latin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;28%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;61%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSMSE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;26%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;46%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSAS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;17%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;25%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Queens Sci&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;12%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;64%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All the more reason to run some tests or analysis there. Of course, if
you look further you'll note that HSAS only has 25% of its students on
free or reduced lunch so is it really doing better than Stuy or Sci
with ~45% low income students  each  or Brooklyn Tech which supports
62% or are we to say that there's low income and then there's the
right low income?
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Certainly the education system needs work but the proposed legislation
is not a solution. It's taking a flawed but objective measure and
replacing it with essentially chancellor's discretion. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If the legislation passes, by the year 2022 we will have admissions to
what used to be some of the nations finest high schools determined by
a political appointee rather than an objective test.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a shame. It was very important to my wife and me to have our kids
go to public schools and I was very happy to have been able to
navigate the system with them from first grade through high school
graduation with only a few bumps along the way. With this nonsense
from the political left and the privatization push from the political
right (or actually both sides) pretty soon there will be nothing left.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>gifted</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat-part2/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 12:00:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Changing Admissions to the NYC Specialized High Schools</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgdb72ea1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgdb72ea1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgdb72ea1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, Bill de Blasio, the current Mayor of New York City outlined
how he would "fix" our specialized schools. The schools he was
referring to were the "big three" of Stuyvesant, Bronx Science, and
Brooklyn Tech and then five additional schools - The High School  for
Math Science and Engineering at CCNY, The High School for American
Studies at Lehman, Brooklyn Latin, The Queens Arts and Science High
School at
York College, and Staten Island Tech.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All use a single SAT style test, the SHSAT, for admission. The Big Three are
locked into that system unless there are changes made by the state
legislature. The Mayor can make changes to the admissions criteria of
the other five on his own.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem, as stated by Chalkbeat writers Alex Zimmerman and  Monica
Disare is that: 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The city’s specialized high schools — considered some of the crown
jewels of New York City’s education system — accept students based on
a single test score. Over the last decade, they have come under fire
for offering admissions to few students of color: While two-thirds of
city students are black or Hispanic, only about 10 percent of
admissions offers to those schools go to black or Hispanic students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I normally don't write about things like this but given my history at
and with Stuyvesant I thought I should.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Before getting started, my biases - I believe in public schools, not
charters, I also believe that a system should have gifted programs and
magnet schools and also a mix of large comprehensive schools and
smaller niche ones. Additionally, while I do believe in gifted
programs I'm not sure at what point it makes sense to start offering
them. When we were looking at elementary schools for our own kids we
opted for a neighborhood public school rather than applying to the
district gifted program as we felt it offered a better overall
education. On the other hand, had our kids not made Stuyvesant, I'm
not sure what we would have done. Part of that was due to the fact
that the Bloomberg administration destroyed just about all the large
comprehensive schools so, other than that large test schools and
LaGuardia, good luck finding a school that was strong in the
humanities, sciences and offered a robust music program. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org2eb1006" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org2eb1006"&gt;The overall picture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org2eb1006"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For reference, here are &lt;a href="http://www.theschoolboards.com/showthread.php/4324-Specialized-High-School-SHSAT-Cutoff-Scores-for-2018"&gt;unofficial cutoff scores&lt;/a&gt; for the specialized
schools from 2018 along with the NY State data on free and reduced
lunch for 2017. Note that there's overlap between the schools. I
separated out SI Tech since geography probably affects it's numbers
more than the other schools and I separated the big three from the
remaining four because I think the three are all substantially larger. The
free and reduced lunch percent is important because I believe an
entire school qualifies for Title I funding if the number's
over 40 so while these schools are not populated entirely by low
income students, all but HSAS has a substantial number and there's a
chance, some say a good one that at best BdB's plans will merely
shuffle which low income kids get in rather than actually solving the
root problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="border" border-spacing="10px"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;School&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Lowest Score admitted&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;High Score&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Pct free or reduced lunch&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Stuyvesant&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;559&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;698&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;46&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Bronx Science&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;518&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;637&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;45&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Brooklyn Tech&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;493&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;668&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;62&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSMSE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;516&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;616&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;46&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;HSAS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;516&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;633&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Brooklyn Latin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;482&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;555&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;61&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Queens Sci&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;538&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;542&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;64&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;SI Tech&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;519&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;660&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;div id="outline-container-org23e0e41" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org23e0e41"&gt;The plan&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org23e0e41"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org69604f3" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org69604f3"&gt;Part 1 - test prep&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org69604f3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There's idea here is that test prep is rampant for SHSAT and that the
test can be gamed. This may or may not be true but if it is then it's
safe to assume that a lot of low income kids are doing test
prep either by prioritizing test prep programs in family budgets,
working off of an SHSAT test prep book or by attending a middle school
that has some form of prep. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There has long been a program on the books called "The Discovery
Program" which has a free city run test prep component and also a
summer component. The summer component is for low income students who
score within "a few points" of the school in question's cutoff
score. At the end of the summer, I believe the students retest and in
general make the school in question.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;This program is a good thing and should be reinstated&lt;/b&gt; but I don't
know if it will result in the changes that BdB is looking for. More
likely Stuy will get its discovery kids from Science and Science from
Tech. As there are already many low income students at all of the
schools there's no indication that this would increase the number of
under represented groups which is BdB's goal. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's also worth noting that there's a sizable chunk of Brooklyn Tech
students that don't perform particularly well on regents exams.
Everyone knows I'm not a fan of standardized tests and I don't
believe that students that score a "few points" lower on the SHSAT are
any less qualified to be in a specialized school but at the lowest
performing end of these schools, one has to ask how specialized is it
really?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org1c2c479" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org1c2c479"&gt;Part 2 - use state test scores instead of the SHSAT&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org1c2c479"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This &lt;b&gt;could be&lt;/b&gt; a &lt;b&gt;very&lt;/b&gt; good thing with one major caveat. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Twenty one middle schools produce over half the students that
ultimately are accepted to the specialized schools. For the rest,
there are a few reasons
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many students don't take the SHSAT.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There have been stories of schools steering kids away from the
specialized schools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's no culture in those schools of striving for specialized
school acceptance or attendance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The academic programs at those schools don't prepare students for
the SHSAT exam for reasons that we're not going to delve into here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All students already take the NY State middle school Math and English
exams. Yes, it would further raise the stakes for those exams but it
would ensure that the specialized schools are on the map for everyone, 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The big question here is "do the current state exams cover enough
material in enough depth to select and differentiate for gifted
programs." I don't know the answer to this question. If they don't
then using state test scores will be a disaster. If they do, then they
could be a suitable alternative.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgba9f00c" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgba9f00c"&gt;Part 3 - admissions from every middle school&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgba9f00c"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is the third part of BdB's proposal - guarantee admissions to the
top 10% of students at every middle school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This could be a real disaster either for the students or for the
schools. There's no question that students coming out of different
middle schools are at different levels of preparedness for the
specialized schools. Arguably the most obvious difference is that some
middle schools offer algebra and others don't. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For better or worse, the specialized school's curricula, classes, and
overall programs have evolved hand in hand with the exam. If you all
of a sudden end up placing a large number of students with a
different and arguable weaker academic profile into these schools one
of two things will happen. Either the students will struggle immensely
or the school will have to lower its standards. There's no two ways
about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you set standards for academic preparedness for the specialized
schools either by making a hard cutoff on an exam score be it state or
SHSAT and then spread those acceptances across all the schools maybe
it could work. If not, you're setting up students with high grades at
schools with weak programs up for failure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another problem is what to do with non-public school students -
private schools, charters which take public money but act as private
schools, parochial, and home school students. Where do they fall in to
this equation?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org0feac6f" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org0feac6f"&gt;Is one measure bad?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org0feac6f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So there you have my thoughts on BdB's specific proposals but I also
want to address his contention that a single measure is bad and makes
the comparison to colleges where they by and large use multiple
measures. This is a ridiculous comparison. Yes, colleges look at
multiple measures but after watching decades of Stuy students go off
to college, it's clear to me that the process is by no means fair or
consistent. Elite schools can easily game their acceptances and
they still can have 100% of their applicants with off the charts SAT
scores. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A single test might not be ideal but it can only be gamed by test prep
and test prep can be as cheap as buying a test prep book.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As to other measures that come up from time to time - interviews,
portfolios, essays - who does that help? The low income kid or the
well to do one?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're going to add another measure for admission it has to be
something that can't be gamed or politically influenced,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org21307c7" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org21307c7"&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org21307c7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Should the city address the fact that there are groups that are under
represented at the specialized schools? Certainly, or rather, the city
should address deficiencies in opportunities that are like the causes
of this under representation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Should the city be doing things differently? Also yes. Here are some
thoughts on what the city can and should be doing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-org076106b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org076106b"&gt;Do the experiments in the non-big three.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org076106b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are five specialized schools that aren't covered by state
legislation. Why not run your experiments there. You've got  the big
three as a control group and what's more if you look at the
"acceptance score windows" in the table above, you'll see that there's
enough overlap that you can probably get some real data out of these
experiments.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why not change the admissions criteria for one or two of them and see
how it goes before jumping in whole hog. Figure out if anything works first.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org3408140" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org3408140"&gt;Check existing data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org3408140"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We've got SHSAT results and State Test score results along with
student grades for years. Why not study correlations between
them. Rather than making a specious claim about middle school grades
in NYC Public Schools vs state tests vs the SHSAT, run the
numbers. Take a look at student high school performance based on these
predictions. This shouldn't be guess work and city should have the
data to do better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd0a1c65" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="orgd0a1c65"&gt;Fix the middle schools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-orgd0a1c65"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This one is more pie in the sky because no politician really wants to
take this one but you've got to look at what's going on in the middle
schools and why. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I tweeted this the other day:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;would love to see this experiment - take the entire staff / faculty / admin of one of the 20 or so middle schools that are the primary feeders to the spec schls and swap them with another middle school and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;— Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/1003074760786501632?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;June 3, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The truth is that if you did this, the high performing school would
probably continue to be high performing and the low performing one
would still struggle. There's only so much a teacher can do. A school
with a disadvantaged population needs the resources to succeed - lower
class sizes for a start. Add wraparound services, extensive after
school and weekend opportunities - make the schools a part of the
community and maybe we can get somewhere.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another question relating to our schools in general is to look at
attrition rates to private schools - how many students in our under
represented groups are being siphoned off to private schools on
scholarship. I don't have any data for this. It could be an
insignificant amount or it could go a long way in explaining the
downturn in the numbers over the decades. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org6093a20" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org6093a20"&gt;So where are we&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org6093a20"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are a lot of changes I'd love to see in our public schools and I
do believe BdB's heart is in the right place. I'm concerned that some
of the solutions that he and other politicians come up with will hurt
the current low income students at the specialized schools and
unintentionally advantage the well to do while not helping those that
at least BdB may honestly want to help.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
He should enact Discovery and research the State Tests but proceed
with caution. The test schools have always been and continue to be a
gateway for poor and immigrant students and any changes that are
proposed should be weighed carefully and &lt;b&gt;tested&lt;/b&gt; before taking steps
that could real harm when good is intended.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>gifted</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/shsat/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 11:01:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Should CS for All be implemented at the college level?</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csforall-in-college/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orge360915" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orge360915"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orge360915"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There's been a lively discussion on pushback to CS for All at the K12
level over on Facebook. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; started a sub thread asking if CS
for All should first be implemented at the undergrad level rather than K12. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's an interesting question and as good as anything to get me out of
my month long non-blogging rut.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark was right when he said that if Colleges implement CS for All, K12 will 
likely do so to follow - just look at AP. Colleges have been saying
that students should take more AP classes (while giving less credit)
and we all know where that's led. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, can colleges really do CS for All, what does it
mean and what would it look like.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Much like there is no single K12 - it's 50 states and who knows how
many independent school districts, there won't be a single CS for All
at the college level but let's think about how things could play out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Many colleges have distribution requirements. Students must take one
course from bucket A, two from bucket B etc. Many schools that I've
looked at already  count CS courses in one of their distribution
buckets. This doesn't mean every student will take CS but in theory
means they can. Colleges could in theory create a required CS bucket
or even a required CS course but I don't think it's as easy as
that. It might be at a private institution but while I don't know all
the ins and outs of Hunter's governance rules I do know that adding a
universal student requirement is a HUGE undertaking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So my take is that while it might be easy for a private college
to add a CS requirement I'm guessing other public institutions are
more similar to Hunter and it's not going to be an easy task.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Regardless, let's say we have a required class on the books. Will we
have the capacity to teach it? It seems that schools are struggling to deal
with their existing CS majors and running sufficient electives and
courses for them. Just a month or so ago there was an article about a
college ending its CS minor due to lack of resources. It doesn't sound
like a radically different problem then that faced in K12. Maybe it's
harder given that at least in NY, there is &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall"&gt;room for a required CS
course&lt;/a&gt; if you can find the teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even so, assuming we have the capacity to enroll every undergrad in a
CS course what would that be? I think most people would be in
agreement that it shouldn't be CS 101. Maybe existing pre-major
courses but even there I don't know if that's always the best
path. There could be a great pre-major course to give students the
basics and lead some into the major but what about a CS course for
students in majors that need some deeper but focussed programming
skills. The appropriate course for them isn't the same as a
general/pre-major course. Using Statistics as an example, at Hunter,
many majors require a statistics course which is off loaded to the
Stats department. Each major has slightly different requirements. Over
years, the end result is a course that it seems that nobody is happy
with - a least common denominator course. CS for All at the college level
could give us a least common denominator course that doesn't serve
anyone.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now, if you have the resources, none of these are issues. A well
heeled private institution can run tons of sections of specialized
classes no problem but this means just like on the K12 level we'll
get the CS for All tale of two cities that I see coming in NY where
the rich schools have good programs and the poor get a substandard
experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With all of this said, I'm finally getting to the big red flag with
college CS for All and it's an issue that everyone conveniently
ignores. I'm talking about teacher quality. One of my big takeaways
from SIGCSE is that college faculty are well behind K12 teachers in
terms of pedagogy and I don't see this changing anytime soon. This is
to be expected given that professor's career advancement is really
based on research. Having a good teacher is always important but it's
even more important for non-major students since a student in the
professor's major will at least be passionate about the subject
area. To me, this is not a recipe for success.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One can certainly make the claim that we aren't any better off right
now at the K12 level because we don't have teachers who know either
the subject nor how to teach it and at least at the college level they
know the subject matter. This is very true and it's why pre-service CS
teacher preparation is so critical to getting this right even though
it will take time. That's something that both Mark and I have been
vocal about but more on that subject next time.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>csed</category><category>csforall</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/csforall-in-college/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2018 20:23:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Is there room for CS for All</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org59c958b" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org59c958b"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org59c958b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A fear revolving around CS For All concerns where will the money
come from and how will we fit in the new classes. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One suggested solution is to integrate CS into other subjects. I
thought I'd write today about why I don't think the fear is valid and
while integrating CS into other classes can have value, it probably
isn't a long term solution for CS education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's start with the integration solution. The idea is to bring CS
into an existing class. &lt;a href="http://www.bootstrapworld.org/"&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;, a program I've written about before
and one of the programs I like does this, primarily in Algebra. The
idea is that this supports the student's learning Algebra while
exposing them to CS. It's a nice program but a math teacher using
Bootstrap shouldn't be confused with a computer science
teacher. They're bringing some CS to their student and engaging the
students in a different way mathematically and that's all great but in
general you can't take two classes worth of material and concepts and
fit them into one class and the number of teachers who are truly
knowledgable in any two academic subject areas both in content and
pedagogical content knowledge is few. I'm guessing that one of the
reasons that Bootstrap works in Algebra is the alignment of the
toolset and Algebra and how you can teach it. The other is that
Algebra is frequently given more time for fewer topics. In some
struggling schools, students might have two years of algebra or a
double period so there's time to add in some CS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm all for cross curricular work. You can look at applications of
science in math classes, do mathy work in a CS class, run stats and
data analysis in math and CS classes on materials from History classes
and all of this is great. You can even create great combined curricula
where you do indeed teach multiple subjects in an integrated way but
to think that you can take what is typically taught in two different
classes and you can combine both so that they're taught in one class
with one teacher sounds fishy to me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, at the end of the day, if you go the integration approach you're
either going to have to dedicate a similar set of resources both in
time and personel to having independent courses. The alternative is
that CS will be the second class subject.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, let's look at actually bringing in CS For All as a separate
course. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here are the New York State Graduation Requirements &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="2" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="6" rules="groups" frame="hsides"&gt;


&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-left"&gt;

&lt;col class="org-right"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt;Subject&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th scope="col" class="org-right"&gt;Number of semesters&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;English&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Soc Studies&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Science&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Math&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;LOTE&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Arts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Phys Ed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Health&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Electives&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt;Total&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-left"&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td class="org-right"&gt;44&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It can be difficult to fit Phys Ed in since it has to be offered every
semester so let's double the Phys Ed requirement to 8 semesters. What
is actually normally done is to have 7.5 periods of science a week and
2.5 periods of Gym.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This means that the basic student program uses 48 class slots and
includes 7 elective slots.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In terms of exit exams, students have to pass the following Regents:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;English&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any single math (Algebra, Geometery, Alg 2 / Trig)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any single Social Studies (US History or Global History&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any single Science (Living Env (bio), Chem, Phys, Earth Science)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any additional Regents exam&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The requirement of passing a single Math regents is what leads to the
extra time allocated to Algebra that I mentioned when discussing
integrating CS into Algebra above.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To get an Advanced Regents diploma you have to pass additional exams -
both history, all three math, three science and maybe more.  
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Using a Typical 7 period plus lunch day, we have room for 56 single
semeter classes in a high school career. This means that assuming
students aren't failing too many classes, even with the extra Phys Ed
allocation I mentioned above  we can easily fit computer
science into our day. In fact, we can technically fit in four full
years assuming a student doesn't have to repeat any class. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So in New York state we certainly have the time but what about the
budget? That's not an issue either. The state also requires that
students recieve 5.5 hours of instruction a day exclusive of
lunch. At 47 minute periods, that translates to students being
assigned 7 instructional classes a day which means we can't just give
the kids the required 44. We have to fill all 56 available class slots
over those four years. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course it's not really that simple. Students fail classes and have
to repeat them and some classes might be assigned more time than
others but it looks to me like we should be able to fit
computer science in without any big budgetary or scheduling
changes. The challenge will be finding the teacher and working the
internal politics and policies since as computer science comes in it
will mean removing some electives even if those electives are additional years
of science, math, or English.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Programs like &lt;a href="https://www.tealsk12.org/"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; and Bootstrap are important transitional programs
and even when we do have qualified CS teachers they will play an
important role - TEALS in providing industry support and resources and
Bootstrap by integrating curricular areas and over time as preservice
programs start to appear the rest will work itself out.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;The state
lists by credits which are a year, I doubled the numbers to map to semesters&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>csforall</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/room-for-csforall/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2018 20:29:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Unfunded Mandates and CS For All</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/unfunded-mandates/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbc4dc60" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgbc4dc60"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgbc4dc60"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This morning, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; wrote about &lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/2018/04/27/lack-of-funding-leads-to-lack-of-teachers-leads-to-lack-of-cs-classes-we-may-need-to-change-our-strategy/"&gt;unfunded mandates and CS for
All&lt;/a&gt;. Unfunded mandates frequently wreak havoc on schools in a number
of ways but in the long run, I don't think it should have a severe
effect on CS for All. Rather, it could have a big impact on the number
of CS courses we offer beyond that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark relay's a story from the Cambridge Rindge and Latin School where
at the time many students wanted more CS classes but the school wasn't
planning on hiring a new CS teacher. The money quote is:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Over 50 percent of students signing up for Level 2 [computer science] courses next year identify as African Americans,
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No, I'm not talking about the diversity issue raised by the quote, I'm
talking about &lt;b&gt;Level 2 [computer science]&lt;/b&gt;. This implies that the
students already had &lt;b&gt;Level 1 computer science&lt;/b&gt;. Level 1 would cover
CS For All so now we're talking about CS electives vs other
electives. This is something I had to deal with for most of my career
even after we got a CS requirement at Stuy. It was always a battle to
hire enough CS teachers to meet demand. The hard part was politics -
there were always older more entrenched subject areas who would rather
force kids into their electives rather than allow them to take my CS
electives. This is a whole other kettle of fish than CS for All. It's
an issue for some schools now and will become a &lt;b&gt;BIG&lt;/b&gt; issue in five to
fifteen years when a single CS required course is more the norm. The
issue raised here is a new CS elective vs entrenched teachers and
classes which shuld lead to a discussion of the relative value of CS
electives vs other electives. That said, the reality is that it
usually comes down to school and local power and politics. Also to be
considered is the potential ebb and flow of interest - there might be
demand for 5 more CS classes and 5 less something else this year but
there might not be next year and then we're in real trouble staffing
wise.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Schools, public high schools in particular are zero sum endeavors. You
have a fixed number of periods a day, specific class requirements, and
certain mandates as to a the minimum and maximum number of classes a
student can take. In New York City, I believe students are required to
have a "full" schedule which basically means they can't come in for
English, Math, and History and then go home.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With CS for All, you're basically allocating reallocating some amount
of time to computer science. It might be hard to find a qualified
teacher. particularly in a small school where the population won't
support a full time CS teacher and it might ruffle the feathers of the
teachers that will be losing the time but it shouldn't make much of a
dent or really any dent on the budget.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark also raises the possibility of embedding CS into other subject
classes. &lt;a href="http://www.bootstrapworld.org/"&gt;Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt; is a program that I'm rather fond of that does
just this in Algebra classes (although more recently they're working
to branch out into other subject areas). Even though I'm a big
Bootstrap fan I don't think that's the answer to CS for All or CS in
the high schools in general. I think that one of the reasons why
Bootstrap works so well is the alignment between the CS tool they use
and the way Algebra is or can be taught. Another reason is the fact
that while Algebra is the lowest level of the traditional high school
classes, it's frequently the one for which the most time is
allocated. Students in low performing schools might take Algebra over
two years or have a double period. This won't be the case for other
subject areas. What this means is that there's more likely extra time
to embed another subject, cs, into the Algebra class. Long term,
embedding CS into another subject area requires:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a teacher that really knows both subjects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;enough time so you can add all the cool CS content while still
preparing the students for both the next level of whatever subject
you're embedded in  as well as for whatever standardized
assessments come at the end of the year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I said, I'm a Bootstrap fan but I don't think that's the answer for
CS in K12.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back to the original topic there are certainly issues with
implementing CS for All but I don't think school funding is the
biggest hurdle. For me there are other big challenges. One is having a
supply of qualified teachers. In the long run as states outline CS
requirements and pre-service programs crop up this will work itself
out. Until then, yes, we will have an issue and yes it will take some
funding for stop gap and transitional teacher preperation. A second issue is
working the internal politics. Adding CS does mean removing something
else or more likely a piece of something else. The third one is what
I'm noticing in NY where CS for all seems to at times forget about
the CS. If we have knowledgeable teachers we can work around that one
but I still think that might be my biggest concern.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>csforall</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/unfunded-mandates/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 12:43:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Strong K12 Teacher Certification is Important</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org44a29a0" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org44a29a0"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org44a29a0"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
About a week ago New York State's new regulation creating a &lt;a href="http://www.crainsnewyork.com/article/20180327/NEWS/180329893/new-york-will-finally-have-certified-computer-science-teachers"&gt;K12 CS
teacher certification&lt;/a&gt; went live. Just the other day I was honored to be
interviewed by  &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mflamm_reporter"&gt;Matt Flamm&lt;/a&gt; of Crain's New York in a &lt;a href="http://www.crainsnewyork.com/article/20180410/TECHNOLOGY/180419999/asked-answered-teacher-changed-jobs-to-push-for-new-york-states-new"&gt;follow up piece&lt;/a&gt;
about it. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Having K12 CS teacher certification is big and having quality programs
that lead to certification is &lt;b&gt;HUGE&lt;/b&gt;. In my view, it's a game changer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's Focus on high school, my wheelhouse.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From a course offerings point of view it's the wild west. I don't mean
this as a bad thing, it's just that there's a huge range of offerings
from AP to home brew, physical computing, game based, cyber security,
you name it, there's a curriculum. The long and short of this is that
schools need teachers to teach all of these experiences. Without a
strong certification pathway we're going to be stuck with the current
training based model where teachers are trained to deliver canned
curricula rather than truly teach. With strong teacher preparation
programs teachers will be prepared not only to deliver all the
existing curricula but, arguable more importantly design their own
learning experiences appropriate for the populations they work with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is important and alone would make having CS certification
worthwhile but to me the BIG win is that it creates a viable career
path. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
People say we'll never find enough CS teachers because the tech
industry pays so well. I've never believed that. We find math teachers
even though many could flee to finance and chem teachers in spite of
big pharma's call so why can't we find CS teachers? Because we've
never provided a path into the profession and a viable career track. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Certification means that over time schools will be able to build CS
teachers and the discipline will be treated as the other
subjects. Prior to certification, a CS teacher might be cut if a
school's math department downsized. With certification, the career
track for a CS teacher is the same as the track for any other teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It also means that young people starting out who are interested in
both teaching and computer science will have a way of getting into the
profession - something that has never before existed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Having CS certification alone won't woo a
plethora of current tech professionals into teaching but over time,
we'll start to have CS Ed majors or CS majors pursuing CS ED Masters
degrees and entering the profession. This won't happen in a press or
election cycle but it will happen.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This all hinges on quality prep programs. I think I've hit the sweet
spot with what I've designed at Hunter. The critical components are of
course content and pedagogy. Teacher candidates must have both
sufficient depth and breadth in the subject and all the pedagogical
content knowledge that comes along with it. I don't agree with the
common approach of taking a course to teach a course - that is, having
courses like "APCS - Principles for teachers" or "APCS - A for
teachers."  I want my teachers to be able to teach any reasonable
curriculum or design their own so we'll be rolling out courses that
examine the commonly offerd curricula but prepare teachers for a whole
lot more.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's been an exciting week in NY CS Ed and there's a lot more to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>certification</category><category>cs</category><category>policy</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 21:39:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fixing the Absent Teacher Reserve (ATR) situation</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/atrs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org7bd5371" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org7bd5371"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org7bd5371"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the New York City department of education a recurring hot topic is
the Absent Teacher Reserve or ATR pool. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A teacher or administrator in the ATR pool is a licensed, most likely
tenured teacher not assigned permanently to a school. Each year these
educators get shuttled from school to school and denied a chance to
actually settle in a position.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The ATR pool was created under the Bloomberg administration. Prior to
that, when there was an opening school transfers were basically
seniority based and when school had too many teachers the least senior
was excessed or basically out of a job until a school with an opening
could be found. The Bloomberg plan allowed teachers to use criteria
other than seniority for transfers but so as not to violate the
contract agreed to by both parties, teachers who were excessed, as
they might not be least senior, were kept on as employees and put in
the pool.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
ATR's would rotate from school to school. Sometimes for a couple of
week but more recently for a year at a time. When at a school for only
a couple of weeks they could only be used as subs or for grunt work
but even when there for a year they're treated like second class
citizens.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The ATR pool grew in size when the Bloomberg/Klein DOE went on the war
path, set schools up to fail and closed them left and right. If you
had the bad luck being at a close out school when it closed then, hello
ATR pool.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the years, the press, ed reformers and politicians have unfairly
bashed this group of educators. They've falsely claimed that these are
criminal teachers or unsatisfactory teachers. That's a blatant
lie. Teachers up on charges are removed from schools and await a
hearing in another draconian process set up to violate teacher's
rights. If a teacher is ultimately found guilty, they are disciplined
or fired. If exonerated, they're returned to their schools. In any
case they're not ATRs. Teachers that are repeatedly found to be
unsatisfactory are likewise removed (although the process here is
ridiculous and unfair as well).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
ATRs like any pool of teachers run the gamut. Some are great, some are
poor, many will fall in between. All are stigmatized and treated like
damaged goods.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
People ask, how can a good teacher get into the ATR pool? As I said,
be at a closeout school. In the year before I was able to bring my friend
and former colleague JonAlf over to Stuy, he was at Brandeis High
School - a
closeout school. I tried to bring him over that year but his principal
wouldn't release him. Had I not been successful in bringing him over
the following year he might very well have ended up in the ATR pool
and he's one of the best teachers I know. What about the teacher that
doesn't want to abandon those kids that the DOE abandoned when they
decided to close the school. That martyr teacher surely ends up in the
ATR pool but that's the type of dedicated teacher every principal
should want.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So now we have a bunch of stigmatized teachers looking for work in a
system that won't give them a chance. Not only due to them being
considered "damaged goods" but also because they're expensive to
hire. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When a school gets an ATR to them, it's free - the cost isn't added to
their budget - they keep them as extra manpower for the year and then
throw them out with the trash. At times, they get some credit for
keeping them a second year and even beyond they can get rid of them
whenever they want. Great way to bust the contract.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A clear example of this is Stuy's  current math chair. He's an ATR
Assistant Principal. They got him for free for the first year and I
believe at a 50% discount for the second and even now they can dump
him whenever they want. This is rubbish – he's either good enough for
the position or he's not. If he is, he should be given the job for
real and if he isn't then what is he still doing there. I'm not making
any value judgment on him or the department but it's either one or the
other.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, a big reason for this ATR mess is about budgets and money. The
problem is that it's a big lie. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The DOE pretends the we have a situation like this:
&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/atr1.png" alt="atr1.png" align="center" height="250"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The DOE has money and schools have money. The schools pay for their
teachers, supplies, and everything else but the ATRS are paid for by
the DOE. Of course this isn't the case. The truth is that the DOE pays
for everything:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/atr2.png" alt="atr2.png" align="center" height="250"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
ALL the money comes from the DOE.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the past the DOE has come up with poorly conceived and poorly
received plans on how to deal with the ATR situation but it's really
quite simple.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Start by recognizing that ALL the money comes from the DOE. Once you
do that you can address the problem:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assign the ATR to a school&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the school likes the ATR and the ATR likes the school, they keep
them and the DOE picks up the tab or rather adjusts the schools
budget to compensate. The DOE will continue to do so until a real
opening occurs at the school in the ATR's area at which point the
ATR fills the position officially and the budget is readjusted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the school or ATR don't like each other the ATR gets rotated,
however you create a 3 strikes (or maybe 2 or 4 or some number)
rule.
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the school keeps sending away ATRs semester after semester hit
them with a penalty or force an ATR placement when they have an
opening (assuming the ATR is amenable).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the ATR keeps declining positions after a set number of
schools force the placement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's it. Simple and solves the problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/atrs/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 13:01:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New York State moving forward with CS Teacher Certification</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/NY-CS-Certificate/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org266c823" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org266c823"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org266c823"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last April I woke up early and trekked up to Albany along with a few
of my Hunter College colleagues to share our thoughts on K12 Computer
Science teacher certification with the Board of Regents. We gave a
presentation to the Regents Higher Education Committee and afterwards
had a chance to talk with some of the Regents as well as other members
of the New York State Department of Education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I left feeling that our proposals were well received and I think
everyone present - both the Hunter and NYSED contingents hoped that
things would move forward on this important issue.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward to today, December 8, 2017. I was up at the crack
of dawn. Driving in the dark in the snow from NYC to Albany to once
again attend a Board of Regents Higher Education Committee
meeting. This time, the agenda item was:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Proposed Amendments to Part 30 of the Regents Rules and Section 52.21
and Part 80 the Regulations of the Commissioner of Education Relating
to a New Certification Area and Tenure Area for Computer Science 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No discussion or debate this time around just the proposal. If I
understand the process correctly, this should come up again at the
March meeting at which point it will be voted on. If approved, it
looks like we'll have a pathway towards certification for CS teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I haven't had a chance to dive into the details but at the meeting a
few key points came up:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As the proposal indicates this will be a subject area in which a
teacher can be certified and be awarded tenure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be a traditional pathway for new teachers - Bachelors /
Masters degree&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an alternative pathway for people entering from the
workforce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an extension for teachers with another license so they
won't have to give up tenure in their current license.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There will be an "individual evaluation" pathway which sounds to me
like it could catch people who fall through the cracks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There looks to be a sensible ramp up period - until September 2022&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's a grandfathering provision that looks to last 10 years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This sounds like a smart sensible plan. Multiple pathways, shallow
ramp up and provisions to protect existing teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, the devil is in the details. What's an approved program?
Can a grandfathered teacher teach all CS classes or just intro ones?
etc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I said, I haven't had a chance to dive into the details yet but
this is very exciting.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Prior to the meeting I was chatting with a few other people
attending. One, a &lt;a href="http://www.uft.org/"&gt;UFT&lt;/a&gt; representative was very excited about the
prospect. Another contingent, a group from &lt;a href="https://www.nysut.org/"&gt;NYSUT&lt;/a&gt; was very much against
a new certification area. Their position was that this would create a
teacher shortage because no one would have a CS license and no one
would get one due to the difference in salary between teaching and the
tech industry. I've already written on how I feel that this is a &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry"&gt;red
herring&lt;/a&gt;. What shocked me though was their feeling that "we already
have many non-CS teachers effectively teaching CS across the
state. They're doing a great job and don't need any additional content
or pedagogical knowledge." I think they're wrong and I also think that
when we as a community talk about how our summer professional
development is all that's needed, we undercut CS education and
the teaching profession as a whole.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any event this was a big step for New York. I tried to individually
thank as many of the participants as I could for helping shepherd this
along but could only speak to a few so I'll just give a blanket thank
you here to the NY State Board of Regents, Board of Education and
State Education department.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>certification</category><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/NY-CS-Certificate/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 23:57:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A test result is just a test result</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgdadccb8" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgdadccb8"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgdadccb8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This past weekend was &lt;a href="http://catskillsconf.com"&gt;Catskillsconf&lt;/a&gt; - my favorite event of the
year. I spent the weekend up in Ulster County with a bunch of my
students. some great friends old and new, and Devorah. It was a great
weekend but I was mostly offline.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a result I missed a rather heated discussion in the CS Ed Facebook
groups. The debate was over whether or not Strong AP CSP exam results
are indicative of a good curriculum or good professional development (PD).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org9ce82fd" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org9ce82fd"&gt;TL;DR - NO!!!!!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org9ce82fd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Further, anyone who thinks that a set of exam results can tell you
that a particular PD sequence or curriculum is good shouldn't be
allowed to call themselves a teacher and I don't want them anywhere
near my kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I guess that language is strong, even for me but it's true.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tests are designed to assess students and many tests don't even do
that well. They shouldn't be used to measure something further
removed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The last time this idea made its rounds was using student test results
for teacher evaluation. They do that in NY. A judge called the
practice "capricious" and "arbitrary." My friend and former
colleague Gary Rubinstein showed a year or so ago that standardized
test scores varied enough from year to year so as to make the ratings
useless &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Using test scores to say a PD sequence is good? What if that PD
focused on test prep? What if it did nothing in particular? When I was
at Stuy and when I was at Seward Park the Calc teachers' students had
great AP results. I can tell you that none of those teachers had any
quality PD specific to AP Calc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Curriculum? My mentor and friend Danny Jaye told me many times - "A
great teacher can save a class from a  horrible curriculum but a great
curriculum will do nothing for a class with a horrible teacher." He
was right. Again, what if the curriculum encourages test prep. What if
pressure on the teacher encourages them to focus on test prep
regardless of curriculum or PD (see my recent &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/standards-who-for"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
An AP test measures one thing - how well the student did on the AP
test. There are so many variables that go into a class:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it first period at 8:00am?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it the last class of the day?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it before lunch or right afterwards?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What about right after Gym.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's the mix of students - every class is different&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the teacher teaching the subject once a day? Two times? Five
times?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How large is the class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many other classes are the kids taking?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The list goes on and on. There are so many contributing factors that
you just can't say "Good test results = good curriculum" or "good test
results = good PD."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Want to know if a curriculum is good - have experienced teachers who
know their subject run it a few times through and ask them. Same for
PD.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teachers know education a lot better than test makers, curriculum
developers and PD providers. How about listening to them for a change?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;div class="footpara"&gt;sorry, I just got back from the weekend trip and am too tired
to find the link. You can go to his site and search and while you're
there, there's lots of good stuff to read.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>assessment</category><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-results-measure-of-curriculum/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 Oct 2017 00:17:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Standards - Who are they for?</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/standards-who-for/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgae3fcf5" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgae3fcf5"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgae3fcf5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The big push at last year's CSTA conference was the release of the new
CSTA K12 standards. It seemed that every other session was pushing
them in one way or another. I've been meaning to share my thoughts
about them or, more specifically, learning standards in general for a
while but with announcement about federal funding for CS coming from
the White House last week I thought it was time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Before diving into CS standards lets talk about math.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start I have yet to meet a math teacher that needs
"the Standards" to know what to teach. Some how or other math teachers know
they're supposed to teach in an algebra or geometry class. When NY
moved to "integrated math" teachers were able to re-sequence classes
without the benefit of "the standards" and when NY went back to
Algebra, Geometry, then Alg 2 and Trig, teachers had no problem
reorganizing classes again.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
New teachers didn't go to "the Standards" to learn the ropes. Schools
defined syllabi, teachers observed each other, shared resources, used
lesson plan books and in general knew what they were supposed to teach
and at what level.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my quarter century of teaching, always in a math department we
spent a lot of time talking about what we taught, when we taught it,
how we taught it and at what level but until common core was forced
down our throats we NEVER discussed "the Standards." We discussed our
students, where we thought we could take them, and how to get them
there. Somehow our students did alright.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
More recently, the push has been on "The Standards," common core in particular.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Common standards sound good - kids in every school will learn the same
things at the same level - but I contend that they aren't about
learning. They're about testing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's look at a few of the math standards. These were pulled directly
from the Common Core:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Derive the equation of a circle of given center and radius using the
Pythagorean Theorem; complete the square to find the center and radius
of a circle given by an equation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Use coordinates to prove simple geometric theorems algebraically. For
example, prove or disprove that a figure defined by four given points
in the coordinate plane is a rectangle; prove or disprove that the
point (1, √3) lies on the circle centered at the origin and containing
the point (0, 2).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Derive using similarity the fact that the length of the arc
intercepted by an angle is proportional to the radius, and define the
radian measure of the angle as the constant of proportionality; derive
the formula for the area of a sector.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These aren't about deep thinking and problem solving. They're about
very specific skills or techniques. They're also easy to put on a
test. Much easier then assessing a students real problem solving ability.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Common Core comes hand in hand with standardized testing which is then
used to punish students, teachers, and schools. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We keep hearing about individualized instruction - meeting the kids
where they are but the standards tell us that kids MUST know specific
things at specific times. You can't have both. In the best case, with
"the standards" we can only meet students "where they are" within
annual bands.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What has this led to? Narrowing curriculum for one thing. Since schools are
evaluated based on the standardized exam in core subjects focus
narrows and other subjects fall by the wayside. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Arguably worse is selective teaching within common core subjects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Take for example, Geometry. The course is really "Logic and Deductive
Reasoning using Euclidean Geometry as a Platform" but it's generally
called Geometry. This class is supposed to be about getting kids to
think. I've already shared a few standards above but let me tell you
about an open secret - many schools don't really teach proof -
arguably the most important part of the class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my last year at Stuy I graded Geometry regents for the city. I
graded exams for two highly regarded unscreened schools. One that was
lauded in a State of the Union address and the other equally hyped. I
graded all of each school's students geometry regents so it wasn't
just a sampling. Out of all the papers, only two or three scored more
than 2 out of 9 points for the proof question and most were entirely
left blank.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What happened? Proof is hard to teach and hard to learn but it's also
only a small part of the standardized exam. It's critical for a
school's survival and for the student to graduate that a passing score
is earned. Rather than spending a large amount of time on few points
and probably get a limited return I've been told that many schools
spend much more time on topics that area easier to teach and have more
weight on the exam. This makes the school look better and helps the
student graduate but arguably the most important aspect of the course
has been minimized.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
High stakes testing leads to gaming the system. Common core standards
come hand in hand with high stakes testing. We see the same with AP
exams - there are schools that force students to take exams even when
they are woefully prepared and mostly fail because this helps the
school shoot up in the ratings.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is what the common core math standards have given us. They're not
for teachers - we don't need them - we know what to teach and only
wish that the bean counters would indeed allow us to meet students
where they are. Standards are about testing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's move on to CS standards. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It might not be fair to compare CS to math since K12 math education
has been around much longer and is more well defined and in theory
having a set of standards gives us a common language to discuss,
compare, and contrast all the content providers and curriculum
developers out there. On the other hand, I also believe that with well
prepared teachers who understand content and pedagogy the value isn't
all that great. It's also worth considering the fact that nothing
really makes the CSTA Standard  writers special. There's no reason to
think that another group - be they a handful of teachers or a content
provider can't do a comparable job.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here are some selections from the CSTA standards:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Design and develop a software artifact working in a team. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Compare and contrast various software licensing schemes (e.g., open source, freeware,
commercial). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Design, develop, and implement a computing artifact that responds to an event (e.g., robot
that responds to a sensor, mobile app that responds to a text message, sprite that responds
to a broadcas
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Demonstrate the value of abstraction for managing problem complexity (e.g., using a list
instead of discrete variables). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Design algorithms u sing sequence, selection, and iteration. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Discuss techniques used to store, process, and retrieve different amounts of information
(e.g., files, databases, data warehouses). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Compare and debate the positive and negative impacts of computing on behavior and
culture (e.g., evolution from hitchhiking to ridesharing apps, online accommodation rental
services). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Use simple encryption and decryption algorithms to transmit/receive an encrypted
message. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Decompose a problem by creating new data types, functions, or classes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Evaluate algorithms (e.g., sorting, searching) in terms of their efficiency, correctness, and
clarity. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Use data analysis to identify significant patterns in complex systems (e.g., take existing data
sets and make sense of them). 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There's nothing wrong with these. They aren't specific enough to
develop lessons from but, they can provide a
consistent framework to discuss different offerings. Were the much
more specific, we'd have the same issue I railed about with the math
standards so this is a good thing. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Actually, in general, I don't have a problem with these standards. I
might agree with some parts and disagree with others but that's
neither here nor there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To me the big concern on standards is what will they actually be used
for. It's nice to think that it's a set of guidelines from which we
can develop strong local experiences but I think this is somewhat
naive. As states and the federal government bring CS Education into
the fold there's no reason to believe that CS will be special. CS Ed
will go the way of other subject areas. That means that whatever
standards governments adopt, they will likely be used for high stakes
tests rather than for true education. If you look to see how the
sausage is made you can see the harm standards and standardized
testing has wrought  in subjects like math. CS Ed won't be far behind.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While we should be proud of all the work that's going on in our
community it's more important now than ever to keep an eye on the
overall big picture and be aware of how work intended for one purpose
within the community can be used very differently by those outside of
it. This is particularly important for advocates  not in public schools. Public
schools educate the majority of American students so CS4All means
public schools. Standardized testing won't affect private schools (or
private charters in many cases) nor will they affect colleges and in
fact will be a boon to EdTech companies selling there wares. Many of
the loudest voices in CSEd come from these contingents - it's
important that they look to the greater issues, form their own
opinions, and then act on what they believe is right.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>ed</category><category>policy</category><category>standards</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/standards-who-for/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2017 18:05:35 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>