<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about policy)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/policy.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 21:00:25 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Cost of AP Exams</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cost-of-ap-exams/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that I'm back from vacation and summer's winding down I thought
I'd start getting back to more classroom related posts. I still have a
few summer topics I want to write about – standards and side projects
in particular but I'm also looking forward to talking more about the
classroom since, after all, at my core, I'm a teacher. When I saw &lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/future_tense/2017/08/how_online_textbooks_could_help_more_students_take_ap_exams.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;
article in my inbox this morning I thought I'd talk about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the piece, Lindsey Tepe since more kids are taking AP classes and
they're very expensive, schools should look to lower other costs
related to AP classes so as to provide financial support so that
students can take that oh so important end of year exam:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While the College Board continues to reimburse about one-third of the
test cost for eligible low-income students, only about half of states
are now offering any further financial assistance for students.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Ms. Tepe's solution? Lower text book costs. As a way of lowering
school costs, I'm all for it. I've used free online resources in lieu
of textbooks for years but the savings should go somewhere where it
can make a difference. Perhaps lowering class sizes. The fatal flaw in
Ms. Teps's piece is that it continues spinning the misplaced narrative
that AP Exams are a very important part of a child's education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's be reminded of something: The AP Exam is one thing - an exam - a
single test at the end of the year. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The narrative is that students should take more and more AP classes,
that they're somehow better for kids. Part of this is due to the
potential college credit and part is because the public has been
bamboozled by the ridiculous school ratings that give credit for AP
classes taken. Back in "the day," AP classes were basically early
college. You could then argue that they were the most rigorous classes
offered in a school. AP Calc was basically college Calc. Same for
APCS-AB, AP-Bio and the rest. Now, with classes like APCS-P aimed to
be accessible to typical high school students in the lower grades,
they can't (but still will) make that claim. In fact, at Stuy, my
former school, there are plenty of non AP classes that are more
rigorous than AP classes and the best AP teachers don't always cover
the whole syllabus because they're more concerned with their students
actually learning rather than scoring 5 on an exam.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the college credit front, if a student has a high probability of
saving money through AP credit then I'm all for it but otherwise, it's
just money going to the college board.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It seems ridiculous for me to have to write this but the important
part of a class is, you know, the class. Not the single exam given by
an outside agency at the end and graded after the semester concludes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My suggestion? Offer college level work to students that are ready for
it but don't push the AP exam. This would save a ton of money. What value
does the college board actually bring to the table? Remember, they're
making a pretty penny on all of this testing. A math teacher should be
able to teach calculus with or without AP. A good text being used by
that teacher in class - be it free or paid for is actually much more
important to a student learning calculus than a single exam taken at
the end of the year. I'd go further and say that I'd trust the
teacher's exam more than the college board's. If a teacher knows the
math but needs to see some sample syllabi, they're a web search
way. The same is true for most other college courses that have AP
equivalents and maybe even more so for computer science.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the end of the day it should be about students learning not about
students taking high stakes exams.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ap</category><category>csed</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cost-of-ap-exams/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 11:07:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Thoughts on non educator  influences on CS Education</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/outside-influences-on-cs-ed/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; blogged about a NY Times piece discussing
&lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/2017/07/28/silicon-valley-pushing-coding-into-american-classrooms-through-code-org-nytimes/"&gt;Silicon Valleys influence on education through Code.org&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mark questioned the validity of the piece. If you don't read Mark's
blog and you're in CS Ed you probably should. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I tried to leave a comment on Mark's blog - not about the NY Times
article but rather my thoughts on why I think it's important that we
remain wary and vigilant to industry and outsiders influence and
impact on CS education and on education in general.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know if my comment is sitting waiting for Mark to moderate or
if I'm experiencing WordPress weirdness but since it hasn't shown up
there, I thought I'd share it here:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While the article might not make a strong case it's important to be wary of outside influences on education policies. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm a fan of a lot of what code.org does but speaking about outsiders in general…
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Bill Gates and Co. directly or indirecty gave us such delights like stack ranking teachers, improving, I mean evaluating, I mean firing teachers based on test scores of students they don't teach, more and more high stakes nonsense testing for kids, and  at least in NY the destruction of neighborhood schools. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They've also pushed the current charter movement that, aided by misleading stats appear successful but in truth are no better and frequently worse than public schools while not sharing back a single "best practice."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then we have private companies like the College Board and Pearson both of whom have an outsized influence on US Ed policy and curriculum.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't doubt the good intentions of code.org - as I said, I'm a fan. I am concerned when they and others take actions that can affect ed policy. I'm concerned when code.org representative pushes students to take an AP exam - not a great CS course with a great CS teacher but the actual exam. I'm even more concerned when code.org offers free PD when a school signs up for the PSAT8/9 - another high stakes meaningless test at taxpayer expense. For code.org it's a means to  get more CS ed out there. To me it's setting up a new cash cow for the college board at my expense and at students expense.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've seen many Ed Tech people, armed with the best intentions, enter the lions den – a school, district, or municipality only to see their best intentions corrupted in the name of cost cutting, profits, or politics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/outside-influences-on-cs-ed/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 15:40:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>CS Ed advocates should pay attention to greater ed issues</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cd-ed-and-all-ed/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For anyone involved in K12 CS education, the past few years have been
a wild ride. When I first tried to make inroads in the DOE decades ago
I couldn't get through the door. Now, CS Education is everyone's
darling. It's really amazing. It's been a combination of grass roots
efforts by teachers, non profit education efforts such as &lt;a href="http://teals12k.org"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt;, advocacy of
groups like &lt;a href="http://code.org"&gt;Code.org&lt;/a&gt; and amazing individuals like &lt;a href="http://avc.com/2017/06/bearing-witness/"&gt;Fred Wilson&lt;/a&gt; who has
probably done more to move the needle of CS Ed in NY than any other 10
people combined.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While everyone agrees that to do CS education right at the K12 level
we need great teachers and lots of them, everyone also knows that
teachers voices are often unheard. The voices with the greatest weight
belong to the large non-profits, principals, superintendents and
local politicians. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today's post is a plea to those with voices to think about the effects
of their advocacy for CS Ed to the greater education landscape.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started thinking about this recently as I've been developing the
CS teacher certification programs for Hunter College. As I spoke to
people across the nation I found that many of the efforts to
developing teacher certification are what I call the "you take it you
teach it" model. You take an abbreviated version of APCS-A and APCS-P
and you're a certified CS teacher. Just about every real educator feels
that this is ludicrous. Some feel that this can be a first step - get
these credentials to get in the door and then you have three to five
years to really learn your subject and craft. I'm good with that but I
have a problem with anyone who says "you take it you teach it" is good
enough and I've heard of a number of regions that are seriously
considering it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why is this so bad and, I'd argue, dangerous? Not merely because we'll
end up with substandard CS teachers for the foreseeable future but
also because it undermines the teaching profession as a whole.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's no secret that public education is under attack. A number of
states including Wisconsin, Arizona, Oklahoma, New York and Michigan
have considered relaxing the standards to become a teacher to address
a teacher shortage. In their twisted logic, the politicians and
"reformers" say that we can't find enough qualified teachers because
we've made it an untenable career so let's lower standards. You can
argue that any current state's requirements are overly cumbersome but
that's another conversation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When CS Educators say that all that's needed to teach CS is to sit in
on a two week APCS institute is saying that to teach any subject you
don't need content expertise. This is dangerous to education as a
whole and when power players in the CS Ed movement don't speak up
otherwise or even worse that the stance that "you take it you teach
it" is OK, we're undermining teaching as a profession. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We need our heavy hitters to publicly and privately say that we need a
short term entry into the profession but we absolutely need plans and
pathways so that at the end of the day we have the best prepared
teachers in our schools for CS and for all subjects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another issue is when as CS Educators we don't pay attention to the
whole child. I was at a meeting of CSTA people  from about thirty
states a few years ago. Someone asked "how can we advocate for CS when
the school might use it as an excuse to get rid of music?" Cameron
Wilson, at the time a lobbyist for the ACM said something to the
effect of "I'm not concerned with other subjects, my concern is
getting CS into the schools." I get it, he was employed to stump CS
but we have to remember that we're only a piece of the puzzle. We want
a seat at the table but we have to make sure that the table is
populated with everyone needed to provide a great education for our
kids. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A final issue I'll mention here is how so many CS educators are so
close to the College Board. It was very disturbing that so many CS Ed
players were pushing for more students to take the APCS exam. Not the
class, not some other CS class but the APCS exam. AP is an extremely
controversial subject among teachers and many of us feel that too many
kids take too many AP classes and certainly too many exams. Remember,
the College Board is the organization that pushes things like the
PSAT8/9 another meaningless but high stakes exam inflicted upon our
kids at taxpayer expense. I understand that AP makes things easy -
they have courses, curricula, etc. but we've given the college board
an outsized influence on CS education and we're not paying attention
to their outsized influence on education in general. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm just a small time teacher. I don't have a national voice. I'm
urging those that do:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look into what's going on in greater education. Look at the way
public education has been under attack and why.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look at the side affects of our choices - who we partner with and
what policies we push.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We might not agree on the right path but everyone with a voice in CS
Education should be having hard conversations about this and then
strongly advocating for the positions they feel correct.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cd-ed-and-all-ed/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 23:51:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Self Certification - not a good idea</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/dont-self-certify/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You've probably seen an image like this:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/dont-self-certify/self-signed.png" alt="self-signed.png" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's what you see when you try to access a secure web site but the web
site itself certified itself as being secure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When people see this on a professional site it sets off all manner of
red flags. We feel much more comfortable when go to a site and we
don't see that error. When we see the secure green lock in the url bar
indicating that this site is certified through an external trusted
source.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's take this a step further. If you needed surgery would you go to
a board certified surgeon or would you go to Dr. Nick Riviera or some
other "self certified" doctor? Likewise you wouldn't want to be
represented in court by someone who hasn't passed the bar. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We might not feel that these certification and licensing processes are
perfect but when we need the services of a doctor or lawyer, we're
happy these gatekeepers exist.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So we should all be extremely concerned with today's announcement that
the deal for mayoral control just brokered in NYC came with strings
attached and one of those strings looks to open the doors to give some
charter chains the ability to self certify their teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's a story on it in &lt;a href="http://www.politico.com/states/new-york/city-hall/story/2017/07/06/with-city-charters-poised-to-win-certification-deal-education-schools-fret-113243"&gt;Politico&lt;/a&gt; and one in &lt;a href="http://www.chalkbeat.org/posts/ny/2017/07/06/some-charter-school-teachers-could-become-certified-without-a-masters-under-proposed-new-suny-rules/"&gt;Chalkbeat&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One might think that some requirements to become a teacher are
ridiculous. I'll get to them later  but this is really giving the fox
the keys to the henhouse.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Charters appear to have extremely high rates of teacher attrition so
it makes sense that they want to control their teacher pipeline. This
alone should be a red flag against self certification but what else
are charter chains known for?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Misleading stats - claiming amazing passing numbers on standardized
exams while neglecting to mention that somehow or other big blocks
of students were removed from the school prior to the test year
(&lt;a href="http://www.shankerinstitute.org/blog/student-attrition-and-backfilling-success-academy-charter-schools-what-student-enrollment"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The gotta go list
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forcing high levels of parent involvement (tough for single working
parents)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charging &lt;a href="http://www.houstonchronicle.com/news/education/article/KIPP-schools-collected-millions-in-unallowable-11257006.php"&gt;illegal fees&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Top this off with as taking resources from public schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Charters operate in anything but a transparent manner and we're
expected to trust them to prepare "highly effective" teachers? I don't
think so. Since there is no real accountability for charter schools -
they can easily game the system through student attrition, selective
admissions (by putting up barriers to enter the lottery) and test prep
they can pay lip service to teacher preparation and the public will be
none the wiser. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If we had a reasonable way of holding principals accountable and no,
test scores are not the answer then we could pretty much do away
with teacher certification. If principals were held to task to run an
effective school, something we can easily define but not measure, then
they would have every incentive to hire the best
teachers. Unfortunately we're nowhere near that place.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since we're not, we're left with the current systems of teacher
certification that has it's own slew of problems. A big part of it, in
my opinion is that schools of education have lost the high
ground. While there are some institutions doing great work, reputation
wise, schools of education are held in very low regard. Strong
teachers trade stories of the watered down content classes and waste
of time classes where professors share their pet theories of
education. I can't tell you how many times I've heard the new
definitive way to teach. At the same time, education research is
frequently held in low regard by teachers and the general public. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the one hand we have charters run by and support by non-educators
wanting us to trust them and on the other we have institutions that
are questioned by the teachers they produce and the general public.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What a mess.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know the answer. I'm working on teacher certifications
programs at Hunter and it's a balancing act. How much content is
sufficient and how much is too much. Can any of the general content be
streamlined or is it all necessary. If it isn't necessary do we need
it anyway to satisfy the bean counters?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you don't have enough then we're sending unprepared teachers into
the classroom. Too much and we'll drive potential teachers away.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As computer science education is defining itself we see similar
struggles. We have some people advocating certifications analogous to
existing teacher certifications. On the other extreme we have
advocates for two weeks summer training and you're a CS teacher. I'd
like to think that I'm advocating for the sweet spot. Strong content
knowledge not tied to a specific course and matching content related
pedagogy. Time will tell becomes the certification standard and time
will tell whose approach was right.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For now, it's important not to give away the store. Private charter
schools should not be the driving force behind teacher certification
and they certainly shouldn't be allowed to train their own teachers
and then 'teach' our students without much greater scrutiny.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;Addendum:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'm sure some of my friends will point out that private schools aren't
held to any particular standard for teacher certification. This is
true but private schools don't take public funds. Actually they do but
in my opinion, they shouldn't. I maintain that charter schools are
publicly funded private schools in that they take public money but
operate as private entities. As such they should be held under the
greatest of scrutiny and standards – they aren't
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>certification</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/dont-self-certify/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2017 19:34:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>CS Teachers - teacher first or content first</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teacher-to-cs-or-cs-to-teacher/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Is it easier to take CS people and teach them to teach or is it easier
to take teachers and teach them CS?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The question gets batted around from time to time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This time via twitter:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Some think it's easier to teach a teacher to teach CS than to teach a CS pro to teach. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;@alfredtwo&lt;/a&gt; is not one of them &lt;a href="https://t.co/QCUP8d8llZ"&gt;https://t.co/QCUP8d8llZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Diane Levitt (@diane_levitt) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/diane_levitt/status/881874056911388673"&gt;July 3, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Agreed. It takes a lot of work. More than a week long workshop.&lt;/p&gt;— Alfred Thompson (@alfredtwo) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo/status/882243591090962432"&gt;July 4, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The conversation was referring to blog posts by &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/06/become-computer-science-teacher-in-five.html?spref=tw&amp;amp;m=1"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://gflint.wordpress.com/2017/06/20/a-week-of-in-service-another-python-course/"&gt;Garth flint&lt;/a&gt;. 
Alfred's key point - one that I've spoken about before is that short
term professional development does not a CS teacher make.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As to the lead in question? I've seen both routes succeed and both
routes fail. Both can be heavy lifts but there's a missing part of the
equation that's never addressed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The claim is that it's easier to teach CS to a non-CS teacher because
they already know how to teach. The problem is, particularly in the
later grades that teachers of different subject areas have very
different tool sets. Sure, there are common factors – get the kids
involved, layer, spiral, etc. but you don't teach a CS lesson the same
way you teach a math lesson let alone a literature, history, language
lesson. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In a math class, it's common to have students write solutions to
problems up on the board. If you try that in a CS class, you'll be
waiting 20 minutes while the kids transcribe the problems. Likewise,
math homework will likely consist of a certain amount of repetitive
practice problems whereas a CS class won't have something directly
analogous. This is not to say that you don't have opportunities for
students to present at the board in CS class or that there isn't
worthwhile homework but rather that even at this simple level, there
are differences. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, if we're going to teach a non-CS teacher the CS content, beyond
the challenge of giving them the necessary depth and breadth of
content knowledge we have to teach them how to teach CS.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've inventoried some of the techniques my colleagues and I have used
in our classes and the collected methods could easily fill a couple of
graduate education courses. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what's the answer to the question? It doesn't matter where you
start but if we want to do right by our kids we need to prepare them
in not two but three areas:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CS Content
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CS Pedagogy
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General education and pedagogy
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Short term PD (professional development) won't do it and neither will
scripts for "teachers" to follow. It's going to take time, will, and
effort.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's hoping that municipalities look at the long game. It's fine to
do PD now to get something started but it's not enough. I wanted my
kids math teachers to know math and how to teach it. We should demand
no less from our CS teachers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teacher-to-cs-or-cs-to-teacher/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2017 20:39:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>On Retaining Teachers</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-retaining-teachers/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back in February, I shared my thoughts on &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry"&gt;losing CS teachers to the
tech industy&lt;/a&gt;. TL;DR - I don't think it will be a CS Ed problem. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That said, I do think that it will be hard to find good CS teachers
but the reason is because it will get harder and harder to find good
teachers in general.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are plenty of reasons why it's harder to become a
career teacher but I don't want to talk about those today. There are
also plenty of powerful forces working to destroy public schools and
teaching as a career but this post isn't about that either.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This post is my attempt to tell people what teachers are actually
looking for. Some people assert that merit pay or similar "real world"
incentives will keep good teachers teaching but teachers are a
different breed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, I can't speak for all teachers but I can talk about myself
and teachers I've known and worked with over the years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I never thought I'd be a teacher, it was just something I tried when I
was dissatisfied with Wall Street. I tried it, it stuck. I didn't feel
at the time that teaching was my calling but somehow or other, I made
a career of it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start, schools are not factories, companies, stores, or any other
type of business. Teachers spend most of their days with students and
little time with each other. Most of their time is allocated for
them. A high school teacher in NY will likely teach 5 class of 34 kids
each, have 1 period for lunch, 1 for preparation and 1 assigned to
some school task. You probably won't see your supervisor much. Mostly
at monthly meetings and when they observe you. Observations are
ostensibly for teacher evaluation and improvement but the system is
does neither well. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teachers also don't have the same types of career paths as a other
professionals do. If you want to remain a classroom teacher, there is
no career path. You could become an assistant principal or principal
but those opportunities take you away from the kids and from your
subject area. They say teaching is a calling and for career classroom
teachers it probably is. For those who spent a few years in a
classroom and left for what they see as greener pastures, maybe not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So instead teachers make a career by honing their craft, creating electives,
working with clubs and teams, or doing something similar that doesn't
remove them from the classroom.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my case, I developed some electives and one thing led to another
and I ended up where I am today.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The career situation of the teacher is why things like merit pay never
work. As a teacher, I want, in fact need my colleagues to do well. I
might have your kids next year and if you do a poor job I'll end up
suffering with the results. Sure, I'd like to be recognized as one of
the better teachers but it's not healthy for my students, my school,
or my career if I'm pitted against my fellow teacher. We're all in
this together. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teachers do accept merit pay when it's forced on them though. As a
friend of mine once said - it's like the teacher lottery - the way
they assign the merit bonuses are based on those bogus state exams so
the distribution is pretty random, one year I'll get it, another year
someone else.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is not to say that teachers couldn't use a higher salary but even
then, teachers are not driven by the same motivations as business
people. I don't know of any teacher who feels that they'd work harder
for more pay or that they work any less hard if they're paid less.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teachers work and fight for their kids because that's what we
do. Right before I left Stuy for Hunter, the teachers and city agreed
to a new contract. All of a sudden I got a pay raise. I can tell you
that I was neither a better or worse of a teacher the day after the
contract went into affect than the day before.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My mentor and friend &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2014-11-07-rich-rich.html"&gt;Richard Rothenberg&lt;/a&gt; talked to me about the deal we
make with society as teachers early in my career. He said, once you
get a few years in and have some seniority you're pretty secure and
you're only worry has to be teaching. We don't do great in the good
times but we do OK. On the other hand, we still have jobs in the bad
times although, again, we don't do great. We put in a lifetime of
service knowing that we won't get any significant financial reward but
at the end of the day between our contributions and the city/state's
investments we'll get a pension and won't be out in the cold in our
retirement. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The point is that those of us meant to be teachers were never looking
for the fast track to the upper class. We work to make a difference
and want society to enable us to make that difference. Teachers don't
have to be paid like they are in "the real world" but they do need to
put a roof over their heads, send their kids to college and have a
vacation now and again.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not too much to ask but in this day and age it's apparently too
much to give.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/on-retaining-teachers/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2017 15:35:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Mayoral Control - only when your guy's the mayor</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/mayoral-control/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The hot debate this past week in NY Education circles is Mayoral
Control. When I started teaching, New York City schools were
controlled by the Board of Education. The board appointed a
chancellor. The system was supposed to balance community control as
well as some centralized decision making. The system was created in
the late 60s and was entrenched through my schooling. By the time I
was a teacher I think it was pretty much a given that the system
didn't work.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In 2002, everything changed with Mayoral control under Michael
Bloomberg. Under mayoral control, the mayor appoints the chancellor
who appoints superintendents an on down the line. This was supposed to
create a chain of accountability leading up to and including the
mayor. To address concerns that parents voices would be heard, we had
the Panel for Educational Policy or PEP which was supposed to vet and
vote on policy and initiatives.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sounds good.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, it was all a farce. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Parents may or may not have had a voice under the old system but they
certainly didn't have a voice with mayoral control. The majority of
members of the panel were mayoral appointees and if they didn't vote
100% in line with their masters wishes, they were removed for someone
who would. Schools were closed and initiatives were passed that were
wildly unpopular with parents.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What did we get under mayoral control? There was some good, but we
also got: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;100% buy in to the pet education theories of non-educators like Bill
gates.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;School leaders who barely taught and had little experience as
educators. 
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Destruction of neighborhood schools 
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Destruction of just about all of the large comprehensive high schools
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open doors for private charter schools that follow questionable
practices.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flawed (at best)  school and teacher evaluation models 
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ATR pool 
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, reformers - those out to privatize education loved mayoral
control under Bloomberg. It destabilized teaching as a career
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Did results improve?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some would say yes but it's debatable. Graduation rates and test
scores are controlled by the politicians. When you have tests made,
graded, and curved in secret (except for those charter schools that
are exempt or grade their own tests), you've got to question any gains
or losses.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Bloomberg's failing was (and possibly still is) that he and his
appointees didn't understand education or teachers. Education not a
business and can't be treated the same way.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Did this help with accountability? To quote Mr. Bloomberg: "They can
boo me at parades." 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward to the de Blasio administration. Personally, I was not a
fan of Bloomberg's educational policy and I also feel that de Blasio's
also doing a poor job. Regardless of my opinion, Mayoral control under
de Blasio has certainly felt more community friendly. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This hasn't sat well with the reformers upstate and while Michael
Bloomberg was granted mayoral control for his entire term, Bill de
Blasio has had to fight for it every year and every year control has
come with strings attached – generally involving the flow of money
into private charter schools - still with questionable practices and
results.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The funny thing is that many of those saying mayoral control was bad
during the Bloomberg era say it's a necessity now  and many against it
under Bloomberg are fans under de Blasio.  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What's even funnier, in a tragic way is that it isn't really even
control. So much is really controlled in Albany under Governor
Cuomo. When de Blasio wanted to charge private charters for space
(rightfully so, in my opinion), Albany stepped in and gave the
charters a free pass. How is that mayoral control?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Regardless of your political leanings, it's pretty clear that mayoral
control is only a good thing when the mayor is your guy. We need
something brand new that supports our communities. I was at the
&lt;a href="https://personaldemocracy.com/conference"&gt;Personal Democracy Forum 2017&lt;/a&gt; a couple of weeks ago and a recurring
theme, one which we really need now for our schools is:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;build with, not for&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If we don't get there we'll be stuck booing our politicians at parades.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/mayoral-control/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2017 11:54:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Will we lose CS teachers to industry?</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we properly prepare CS teachers, won't they just jump ship and take
tech industry jobs?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I hear that a lot.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Tech pays big. Teaching? Not so much. Tech workers are respected and
have flexible jobs. Teaching? Again, not so much.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Those chanting these refrains advocate the current simple teacher
"training" - scripted lessons, minimal pedagogical content knowledge,
even less real content knowledge. That  will keep them in the classroom.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They're wrong.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
People fearing an exodus of prepared CS teachers don't get
education. True, many young CS teachers will leave the profession but
that's because &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;many young teachers leave the profession&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;. Why do young
teachers leave? Regardless of subject area some of the reasons are:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's much harder than everyone thinks it is
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Low pay
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lack of respect
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overworked
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lack of autonomy
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being scapegoated for poverty
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's become about testing, not teaching
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
None of these are unique to computer science teachers so the argument
that CS teachers who know too much will leave is really saying, "we
have to keep our teachers dumb enough to stay - make sure they don't
have outside options" rather than "let's make teaching a desirable
profession to be in."  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, this is bred from a lack of understanding about what drives
teachers. It's typical of politicians and business leaders and short
term temps like TFAers who came in for a cup of coffee and now know
how to solve the education problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teacher don't become teachers to
get rich or to do better than the other guy – I know I didn't. We
enter it to do good - to uplift the have nots. This is why business
models like stack ranking and bonus or merit pay just don't work. A
school is a team and we're all in it together. Our job is to take care
of our kids, not to be better than that other guy. We wish we had more
time to work together and to improve things for our entire population.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Back to computer science.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My contention is that you might lose some teachers to industry but
they either weren't meant to be teachers anyway or they couldn't
afford to be teachers or the system beat them down. None of these are
reasons not to properly prepare them. Besides, all teachers in all
subject areas could work their way into an entry level tech job via a
summer coding boot camp.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We can also look to the past to allay concerns. While it's true that
for hiring purposes, English teachers are a dime a dozen and
candidates typically
have fewer outside options (although great English teachers are harder
to find), Math and Science teachers generally have options. I know
many top Math and Science teachers who could easily get non teaching
jobs - the Math teachers in finance the science, certainly in
pharmaceutical companies over in NJ. These options exist yet we manage
to populate our classes with teachers. True, it's difficult at times,
particularly in Physics, but these are due to the lack of respect
teaching gets as a profession.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If we prepare CS teachers properly, yes, we'll lose some, but we'll
keep the ones we're supposed to or if we lose them it will be due to
other factors. Additionally, by having proper CS teacher
preparation programs, we'll also provide an entry path to those people
meant to be teachers but prior had no way of getting in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a nation, we're moving away from prepared, knowledgeable teachers
and towards drill-masters. Let's not let CS Education go the way of
all ed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/will-we-lose-cs-teachers-to-industry/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 11:41:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Should CS Ed be in bed with the College Board</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'm guessing my views  on this aren't very popular -that's OK, every
community needs a curmudgeon.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A few years ago, I cautioned if we weren't careful, once the big
players got involved, CS Ed would go the way of other disciplines, and
not in a good way. It looks like indeed we're well on our way down
that road.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've ranted before about things like non-profits, drop in and summer
programs. &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-07-learning-takes-time.html/#.WJXSS99vHmE"&gt;STEM Oil Salesmen&lt;/a&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
selling easy fixes, exciting kids and parents, using the Think Method
just like Professor Harold Hill only to send the kids off where they
can blame a future teacher for failure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've also ranted about teacher preparation and how all the rage is
short term, &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/scotland/#.WJXT999vHmE"&gt;Superficial PD and scripted curricula&lt;/a&gt;  and my concern that   
once the politicians can say CS is in the schools, &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-03-04-expedient-vs-good.html/#.WJXT7d9vHmE"&gt;we'll be done&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've been working towards getting CS to all students for most of my
career and while it's wonderful to see us getting closer to the goal,
I'm seeing more and more signs that my caution is becoming
reality. and CS Ed is going the way of other Ed - aligned to testing
and more to the whims of the power players and politicians than to
teachers and students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other week I noticed, &lt;a href="http://teacherblog.code.org/post/156278055294/ap-cs-principles-could-make-history-how-can-we"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; by Code.org trying to encourage
more students to take the APCSP exam - not encourage more students
take the class or some other class or to have more students be exposed
to CS but to actually sit for the APCSP exam. That post was followed
by &lt;a href="http://teacherblog.code.org/post/156689658029/ask-your-cs-principles-students-to-star-in-our"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; which also highlights actually taking the exam.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This didn't sit well with me. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What does the exam do for the kid? It doesn't drive instruction - by
that time, any good teacher knows their student and is better served
by using their own &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ap-we-dont-trust-teachers/#.WJXbA99vHmE"&gt;assessments&lt;/a&gt;. The college credit thing? I'm
skeptical. Fewer and fewer schools are giving credit for APCSA let
alone this new CS0 non major course. Blanket credit? Since full time
students pay for a range of credits, I'm still skeptical
here. Placement? It's a course for non-majors - what exactly are you
placing out of?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Reasons not to take the exam?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it doesn't do anything for the kid, why take it
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stress of taking the exam
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are other ways of placing out of courses once in college
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the expense
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a general rule, I'm against forcing students to sit for
AP exams. At the extreme case, since we've been brainwashed to think
that a school that has lots of kids sitting for exams is good, I've
seen at least one case of a principal having all his kids sit for, and
just about all &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;fail&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; AP Calculus - that is, get a 1 or 2 on the exam. This
principal had all his students take the exam, and only 2 scores were 3
or higher. This principal then parlayed his success into a higher
profile gig - he's moved up in the world while setting up his students
to fail.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This follows last year's announcement that code.org was &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2015-05-19-code-org-college-board.html/#.WJXbm99vHmE"&gt;partnering with
the College Board&lt;/a&gt; - offering PD to teachers for free if the schools
signed up their students for the PSAT 8/9 - another meaningless
exam. So, we get teacher training light &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.2" name="fnr.2" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fn.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; as long as the school pays for
the PSAT8/9 for every kid so that the kid can take yet another test
with really no value&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.3" name="fnr.3" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fn.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why should students pay for an AP exam that doesn't do anything for
them? Why should Jane Q Taxpayer pay for exams that only server to
enrich the College Board.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
True, The College Board is a big player. They already have much more
influence of American High School education than they should. It's
easy to climb on board the AP train for entre into our schools. The
question is, should we use positions of influence to push efforts that
might help our end but leave collateral damage to students and the public.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't doubt code.org's sincerity in wanting good CS in all schools
nor the efforts or value as an advocate for CS Education. I'm
concerned that the desire to win big and win now is moving us in a
direction that we'll regret years from now.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;Not my term, but I really like it&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.2" name="fn.2" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fnr.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;If you think that PD based
teacher training is OK, ask yourself if you want your own child's
chemistry teacher to be a history teacher with a few weeks summer
training in chemistry&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.3" name="fn.3" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/#fnr.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I'm guessing the exam will be offered
during the day so teachers will proctor for free rather than be
allowed to, you know, teach their students.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>education</category><category>policy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-ed-in-bed-college-board/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 11:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>It's not one issue, it's the President and his enablers</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/trump-issues/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Like many of my fellow bloggers and tweeters, I generally keep this
site clear of political issues with the exception of those that are
directly related to education. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Also, like many of my fellow bloggers and tweeters, this week has
provided a reason to break with that tradition.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Many people, including some friends, all more eloquent than I have
already posted, tweeted, and Facebooked  about the behavior of our
President and government.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Long time blogger &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/davewiner"&gt;Dave Winer&lt;/a&gt; put together &lt;a href="http://trumpstatus.org/"&gt;trumpstatus.org&lt;/a&gt; where he's
collecting many of the issues that we're all so alarmed with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I would add cabinet appointments to his list with my particular
personal concern over DeVos and the department of education. I've been
meaning to blog about that for a while - perhaps this week.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
My concern for today is something else. Every day, I see a new Trump
induced crisis and every day I see a different subset of my circles
respond. It's not quite as bad as:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First they came for the Socialists, and I did not speak out—
Because I was not a Socialist.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then they came for the Trade Unionists, and I did not speak out—
Because I was not a Trade Unionist.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then they came for the Jews, and I did not speak out—
Because I was not a Jew.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then they came for me—and there was no one left to speak for me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
People are indeed speaking out, but I am concerned that people
are going to rise up for their personal issue and when placated go
back to business as usual - this is &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;NOT&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; the time for business as
usual.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With the ACA repeal, I saw concerns from my working class friends and
friends that work with lower earning populations. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Going into the DeVos hearing, mostly educators - real educators not
astroturf reformers. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With Friday's order, the whole tech community came out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's part of a thread by tech activist &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anildash"&gt;Anil Dash&lt;/a&gt; calling out,
calling on, and crediting assorted tech players.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;When net neutrality was the issue, Google, Twitter, Wikipedia, Reddit, Tumblr, etc. had a blackout, and it worked. This is far more grave.&lt;/p&gt;— Anil Dash (@anildash) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anildash/status/825414889908928517"&gt;January 28, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;A powerful, straightforward statement from the CEO of Box — another publicly-traded company. &lt;a href="https://t.co/wz5mQmTh6P"&gt;https://t.co/wz5mQmTh6P&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Anil Dash (@anildash) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/anildash/status/825470308463280130"&gt;January 28, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We have to remember that all these order, policies, appointments, and
plans are coming from the same place - Donald Trump and those
politicians that are enabling him.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If he backs off on immigration, education issues remain, if he backs
off there, we still have ACA, if that eases up, what about Women's
rights and on and on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This means we all have to get involved and stay involved. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What have I been doing?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I finally joined the ACLU and set up a monthly donation.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I subscribed to &lt;a href="https://dailyaction.org"&gt;Daily Action&lt;/a&gt; so that I get a reminder each day of
someone I can call to make a difference.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I'm starting to accumulate my representatives phone numbers as I
make those calls and am trying to make at least a call a day to
remind our representatives who they work for.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Education and advocacy
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
And if you suggestions for me - please post them here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thus ends my not business as usual post. What's going on in America is
not someone else's problem - it's all of our problem and we all have
to be active and vigilant to make it through tough times to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>policy</category><category>politics</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/trump-issues/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 15:39:53 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>