<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>C'est la Z (polocy)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/polocy.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 May 2016 17:08:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Why I'm no longer an effective teacher - part 2</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-25-effective-teacher-2.md/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/2013/09/06/why_i_might_no_longer_be_an_effective_teacher.html#.UmhWzN__umg"&gt;Earlier&lt;/a&gt;
I wrote about the new teacher evaluation system and why a teacher such
as myself might now be considered ineffective and two ineffectives in
a row can cost you your job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the New York City and New York State Departments of Education
are the departments that just keep on giving. Here's the latest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This coming Wednesday, I won't be teaching during my usual 8:00 to
10:15 block of three AP classes. Instead I'll likely be
proctoring. Classes will be shorter and start at around 9:35.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What will we be proctoring? A preliminary assessment. I, and in
fact all Stuy teachers, will be judged by how our students perform on
English and Math Regents exams vs how the DOE thinks they should
do. So, the DOE needs to issue a preliminary assessment. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this Wednesday, instead of having their normal allocation of class
time, they will start a day taking an exam whose only purpose is to
evaluate (and some of us believe fire) teachers. So, since I don't
teach English or Math, the closest I come to having some impact on the kids whos grades will determine my effectiveness will
be proctoring this exam. Well, that's a fair measure of my value as a teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, that's 40% of my evaluation, 60% comes from observation but
there's a loophole. If the school doesn't perform at a satisfactory
level, even if I ace the 60%, I will be deemed ineffective. Now, I
know I don't have a large readership, but I'm guessing there are
enough of my former students out there that can vouch for the fact
that I do a pretty decent job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as to that 60%, that doesn't seem much better. I'm reluctant to
say anything specific since I don't know whose reading this, but let's
just say, word on the street says that it's more about filling out
lines on forms than actual education and teacher improvement.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless things change soon, I expect good, experienced teachers to
start leaving in droves.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>polocy</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-10-25-effective-teacher-2.md/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2013 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>