<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about presentations</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/presentations.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-09-05T21:31:57Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/presentations.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/presentations/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Using Emacs Episode 50 - presentations</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-50-presentations/</id>
    <updated>2018-06-30T14:10:24-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-06-30T14:10:24-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-50-presentations/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org37b1bdd" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org37b1bdd"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org37b1bdd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next weekend I'll be attending the Computer Science Teachers
Association's &lt;a href="https://www.csteachers.org/general/custom.asp?page=2018Conference"&gt;annual conference.&lt;/a&gt; It's probably the biggest conference
focussed on K12 Computer Science education. This year, in addition to
attending, I'll be giving a talk on preservice and inservice CS
teacher preparation programs. I'll be talking about the new New York
State certification requirements along with what we're rolling out at
Hunter College. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This means putting together a slide deck for the session. When I have
to work collaboratively with non-Emacs users, I will usually go to
Google Docs for presentations. It works and the collaborative aspects
are nice but tools like Google Docs and Powerpoint are designed around
composing slides manually. I much prefer to use a tool where I can
focus on writing my presentation and have the tool turn it into a
presentation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Org-mode is of course the ideal tool. As an outliner, it lends itself
to organizing a talk:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;* topic 1
   the content for slide one
* topic 2
   the content for slide two
* topic 3
   etc.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I can embed code, tables, images, and more. I can also cycle
visibility so I can focus on individual sections. Org-mode also has a
number of export options to take a plain org file which is just ascii
with markup and export it as a presentation. In the video, I'll take a
quick look at &lt;code&gt;ox-beamer&lt;/code&gt;, which exports to a Beamer presentation in LaTeX and then a PDF,
&lt;code&gt;epresent&lt;/code&gt; which presents right in Emacs and finally &lt;code&gt;ox-reveal&lt;/code&gt; wich
creates a &lt;code&gt;reveal.js&lt;/code&gt; presentation. I ultimately decide to continue to
use &lt;code&gt;ox-reveal&lt;/code&gt; as it's pretty simple and flexible and I can also directly serve
the final presentation from my own laptop, a usb drive, or directly
from GitHub. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Check out the video to see how. If you want more information on using
&lt;code&gt;ox-reveal&lt;/code&gt; check out my earlier &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-11-reveal"&gt;Using Emacs post and video&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;





&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bRoSpJ23Kzk" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="emacs" label="emacs"/>
    <category term="presentations" label="presentations"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
