<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about problem solving</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/problem-solving.atom</id>
  <updated>2017-12-24T20:46:04Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/problem-solving.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/problem-solving/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Breaking down problems and writing</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/whats-next/</id>
    <updated>2017-12-14T12:14:33-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-12-14T12:14:33-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/whats-next/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc5ebedd" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc5ebedd"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc5ebedd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This question appeared on Facebook a few days ago:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Does anyone have an effective way to teach students how to break down
a problem into steps and then solve each step one by one? I think my
students are struggling with a large question and breaking it in
subsequent parts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were some good suggestions. I wanted to add something but didn't
have time then so I thought I'd write it up now.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As an aside, it took me forever to find the post again over on
Facebook. If there's a way to mark posts or save a direct link I'd
love to hear it. I had to look through all the CS Ed groups I belong
to manually until I found it again.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When I read the program I was reminded of a PD session we had to
attend back at Stuyvesant. Back then the fad was &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Writing_across_the_curriculum"&gt;Writing Across the
Curriculum&lt;/a&gt;. Every teacher in every class was to give some significant
writing assignment, evaluate it and provide feedback. Let's forget the
fact that most of us never had any training or preparation to do so.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On that PD day the guest speaker was &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Zinsser"&gt;William Zinsser&lt;/a&gt;. The first thing
he said was that what we were being asked to do by our principal was
bunk. He then proceeded to give advice on  simple good writing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The procedure he recommended following was to ask yourself (or have
the student ask themselves) "what does my audience need to know next?"
That's your next sentence. Then ask the question again. Rinse and
repeat until done.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was simple and it made sense. It also applied to introductory CS
problems. When starting out, students have a limited CS / programming
tool box so a good question for them to ask when trying to solve a
problem is not only "what do I need to do next? but also "what can I
do next?" 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When students have a limited CS vocabulary and set of idioms - loops,
conditionals, functions, whatever, there will only be so many things
they can do to move a problem along. If they go through the things the
&lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;can&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; do they will likely fall on to what they &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;should&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt; do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's similar to doing a proof in geometry. Students have a set of
givens. Given that set, what can they do? They only know so many
theorems at the beginning. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over time, they'll recognize patterns and develop as problem solvers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're part of the AP CS A teachers facebook group you probably saw
the question. Many good answers were posted. I just wanted to add this
thought to the collection.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="problem-solving" label="problem solving"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
