<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about programs)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/programs.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Apr 2018 23:33:04 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>TEALS Time</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teals-time/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgc173508" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgc173508"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgc173508"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Everybody know's I'm the Statler and Waldorf of the CS Education
world.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://media1.giphy.com/media/nPxVvyTWo1aIU/giphy.gif" alt="giphy.gif"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've been known to be "prickly," which is a nice way of putting it and
I'm openly critical of many programs out there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One program, however, that I very much like is &lt;a href="https://www.tealsk12.org/"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt;. They've been
around since 2009 founded by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/KevinKWang"&gt;Kevin Wang&lt;/a&gt;, a former teacher. The basic
idea was to have tech professionals go to a school on the way to work
and team teach a CS class with one of the school's teachers. The tech
person would provide the CS expertise and the teacher would provide
the education chops. They'd both learn from each other and the
students from both of them. I didn't know what to make out of it when I
first heard about them and in general, I am  pretty skeptical about drop in
programs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After a couple of years, I started hearing from my former students. As
it turns out, a number of them had independently discovered TEALS and
become volunteers. They all talked about how rewarding the experience
was and how much the kids were getting that they wouldn't have gotten
otherwise.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was sold.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
TEALS has expanded considerably in the decade since they started. Now
they support multiple classes at multiple levels, have different
models from the original team teaching to a model where the volunteer
is more of a general tech / programming resource and the teacher is
more self sufficient.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most importantly, they provide quality training and materials to both
the teachers and the tech volunteers. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
No drop in program can ever replace well prepared knowledgeable
teachers but in K12 CS very few of those teachers exist and it will
take us years to produce them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Until then, TEALS is one of the best programs to get CS education to
our kids and even when we do get there, their ability to connect
schools with volunteers and resources can't be understated.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you're a tech professional and want to do some real good, volunteer
with TEALS - here's a link to more information:
&lt;a href="https://www.tealsk12.org/volunteers/"&gt;https://www.tealsk12.org/volunteers/&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cseducation</category><category>programs</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/teals-time/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 14:14:13 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>