<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about resources)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/resources.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2018 19:18:12 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Awesome Cs Revisited</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awesome-cs-revisted/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb142b51" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgb142b51"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgb142b51"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Saw this tweet the other day so I though I would try to plug the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education"&gt;Awesome CS Education&lt;/a&gt; list I started on GitHub:
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/csteachers?src=hash"&gt;#csteachers&lt;/a&gt;...didn't I see a list of CS teacher blogs here recently?&lt;/p&gt;— Pam Whitlock (@PamWhitlock1) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PamWhitlock1/status/910662628757864448"&gt;September 21, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;





&lt;p&gt;
To answer the tweet, the closet thing I know to a list is &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred
Thompson&lt;/a&gt;'s blog roll which is actually a post he wrote on his blog
in 2012. Unfortunately his list can be hard to find and is somewhat
out of date. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The idea of an "awesome" list is publicly hosting a simple site that
is community driven and anyone can suggest additions and edits. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I put up a starter &lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and a few people have contributed but I'd love
to get more people involved. Awesome lists have a number of advantages
over other repositories.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unlike blog posts, the site is easy to find.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unlike private mailing lists or Facebook, anyone can see the content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone can suggest additions (although you need to create a Github
account).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone can download or fork the site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's essentially plain text and is easy to edit (just read the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education/blob/master/contributing.org"&gt;contribution guide&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, there you have it. If you have a blog or resource to share please
submit a pull request. Over time this could be a terrific single
starting point for educators to get to a wealth of resources.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>pd</category><category>resources</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awesome-cs-revisted/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 20:34:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Community Curated List of CS Education Resources</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awesome-cs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
One of the things I mentioned in my post on the &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-educators-stackexchange/"&gt;CS Educators
StackExchange&lt;/a&gt; was the fragmentation of resources for CS Educators. My
friend and fellow CS teacher Ben pointed out that this is appropriate
as we're so young as a community. He's absolutely right but until we
mature, discover-ability can be a problem. We all have our resources
and I for one am frequently surprised when talking to a friend and
discovering that they don't know about a site or a mailing list that
I've known about for years. Likewise, I'm appreciative when others
share resources with me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There are some collections of information, for instance, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo"&gt;Alfred
Thompson&lt;/a&gt; has a list of CS Education bloggers but it's not so easy to
discover and it certainly shouldn't fall on Alfred to maintain such
a list making sure the links are all active and always being
responsible for adding new ones.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Recently I've noticed a proliferation of &lt;b&gt;&lt;b&gt;awesome&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
lists. These are community curated lists hosted up on GitHub for a
variety of projects. I find myself using &lt;a href="https://github.com/emacs-tw/awesome-emacs"&gt;awesome-emacs&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/vinta/awesome-python"&gt;awesome-python&lt;/a&gt; more and more and there are tons of other such lists.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I thought we, as a community could benefit from such a list. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started one off. It's over at
&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education"&gt;https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education&lt;/a&gt; with instructions on
contributing at
&lt;a href="https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education/blob/master/contributing.org"&gt;https://github.com/zamansky/awesome-cs-education/blob/master/contributing.org&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I seeded it with a few items but I'd love everyone to get involved. I
also started it with a few categories and a specific format but I'd
love to see that evolve into something most useful for the community
as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you agree that this could be something useful, please contribute to
it and help spread the word.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>CS Education</category><category>resources</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/awesome-cs/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 16:39:20 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>