<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about software engineering</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/software-engineering.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-02-19T14:37:04Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/software-engineering.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/software-engineering/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Testing, Testing</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/testing-testing/</id>
    <updated>2018-02-19T08:26:16-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-02-19T08:26:16-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/testing-testing/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgfd6f350" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgfd6f350"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgfd6f350"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With CS4All being the buzzword of the day we're paying a lot of
attention to the fact that when we teach a CS class for all students,
most of them won't end up studying CS or going directly
into a tech heavy field. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Among those that do study CS though, there is another division. Those
studying CS as an academic exercise or to go on to graduate studies
and those who are going in to the tech sector. For those going into
the tech field, it's important that they're prepared in terms of
software development, design, and all those goodies not covered in CS
classes. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not advocating removing the good stuff currently in most colleg CS
curricua, although I will say that most CS programs I've reveiwed could benefit by
trimming some requriements and adding some electives. I am advocating
doing more than telling your students "comment your code," - a refrain
many undergrads have heard frequently with little guidance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm advocating to begin by bringing in tools and practices that either
don't detract from current CS classes or in fact can add to or
streamline them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last year I wrote about &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-github-4/"&gt;using Git and GitHub&lt;/a&gt; in my classes. Students
have to submit projects anyway and frequently have to work in teams so
using Git and a Git hosting service can actually make both student's
and instructor's class experiences better while introducing them to an
industry best practice.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today I want to talk kabout testing. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Students are always told to test their code but frequently not given
tremendous guidance. The results can be:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;projects that don't compile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;projects that compile and run but not the way they're supposed to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;wonky input or interfaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;projects that don't work for all cases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
On the instructor side, we have to evaluate the student's
submissions and deal with all of this. Some teachers use auto graders
to help. I have mixed feelings on them. On the one hand they can speed
up grading but on the other hand it's important for me as the teacher
to actually dive into the student's code. In any case, using an auto grader
is actually somewhat similar to running a test suite.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why not have the students create their own test suites? If done right,
this should encourage students to evaluate their own code more
carefully and also cut down on the time it takes the intructor to
evaluate a given submission. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This means that we have to use a testing framework with a very low
cost of entry.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I ended up finding &lt;a href="https://github.com/onqtam/doctest"&gt;doctest&lt;/a&gt; for C++. It's really simple and just a
single include file. This means that students don't have to actually
install anything on their machines. Here's the sample code from the
project page:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://github.com/onqtam/doctest/blob/master/scripts/data/using_doctest_888px_wide.gif" alt="using_doctest_888px_wide.gif"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="software-engineering" label="software engineering"/>
    <category term="tools" label="tools"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
