<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about startups</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/startups.atom</id>
  <updated>2017-06-29T16:40:56Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/startups.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/startups/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Learning about VC</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/learning_about_vc/</id>
    <updated>2017-05-05T08:57:15-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-05-05T08:57:15-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/learning_about_vc/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;style&gt;
.figure-number {
    display: none;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/peter-boyce-talk.jpg" alt="peter-boyce-talk.jpg" align="center" height="250"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="figure-number"&gt;Figure 1:&lt;/span&gt; Peter Boyce imparting VC Wisdom on the Daedalus Scholars&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday, the Daedalus Scholars were visited by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/badboyboyce"&gt;Peter Boyce&lt;/a&gt;. Peter's
been a friend for years and is my go to guy when I'm looking talk
startups, venture capital and many things tech. Peter's with General
Catalyst Partners and is a co-founder of &lt;a href="http://www.roughdraft.vc/"&gt;Rough Draft Ventures&lt;/a&gt; - a fund
that invests in student entrepreneurs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm teaching Hunter's first class of Daedalus Scholars - Hunter's new
CS Honors program. They're young and just getting their feet wet and
have unlimited potential and possibilities in front of  them. It helps if
they have some idea as to what some of those possibilities can be. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Everyone knows you can work for a big tech company or a bank but few
really know or understand how the tech startup ecosystem works. That's
why I was so excited when Peter agreed to visit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Peter talked about his path. About how he and a group of friends,
while in college, got together once night a week to work on their own
projects. Not on problem set, assignments, or studying but
specifically to work on something else. He talked about struggling to
balance grades, early projects and relationships and how much he
learned and grew from the experience. He talked about his path to
being a VC and he told the class about possibilities.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If the class left one tenth as inspired as I was the day was a
resounding success. Based on the brief conversations I had with a few
of my students after class and last night on email, I'm pretty sure it
was.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One thing that struck me was what Peter seemed to be most proud of was
his ability to help others realize their goals and their dreams. I've
gotten to know a few venture capitalists and investors over the years
and the ones I like and identify best with seem to have this
trait. They're investing in people. I seem to recall &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/fredwilson"&gt;Fred Wilson&lt;/a&gt;, a VC
I very much admire telling me that when talking to young entrepreneurs
he very much looks at the people as much (maybe more) than the
product. The product might not be right but if the people and team
are, at some point they'll hit. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a teacher, my whole career has been about trying to enable
others. I spent a lot of time yesterday thinking about the parallels
between some of the investors that I know, like, and respect and the
best teachers I know and while we work in very different arenas, in
some ways we're driven by similar voices.
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="startups" label="startups"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
