<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about stuycs</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/stuycs.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-02-12T19:18:12Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/stuycs.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/stuycs/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Reunion Season</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/reunion-season/</id>
    <updated>2017-11-26T07:41:51-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-11-26T07:41:51-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/reunion-season/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgd7745f1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgd7745f1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgd7745f1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thanksgiving is reunion season. Stuyvesant and I'm guessing other high
schools traditionally hold their reunions, at least the five and ten
year ones over the holiday weekend. It makes sense since grads who've
moved away might still be coming to town for family celebrations.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This year, I was invited to the Stuy07 ten year reunion. I considered
crashing the Stuy97 20 year but it was at the same time and too far
away.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm always really flattered and honored when I get a reunion
invite. I've been to my share but I was never the hip popular teacher
that gets invited to these things. On the other hand, I'm sincere,
honest, and loyal so when I do connect with students it's meaningful
and lasting. As one of my students remarked when I was nominated to be
graduation speaker a few years ago and I doubted I would be elected
"hey, you lead the most popular cult in the school" and I guess in
some way the community is a cult, or as I'd rather say, a family. In
any event, whenever I'm invited to a reunion I make my best effort to
attend.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I find the role of faculty at reunions as somewhat amusing – we're
something of a prop. The grads are there and should be there to
reconnect with each other. The teachers are and should be secondary.
From my point of view, there are three groups of students. The ones
that are now part of my alumni family - now friends who I'm in touch
with to varying degrees, the ones that never knew me and the ones that
knew me a bit. For the second and third groups, as a faculty member,
I'm there to remind them of the glory days as a representative of the
institution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As with all reunions I had plenty of "I was never in your class
but …" conversations. I also a number of "I majored in
fill-in-the-blank but just found my way back into tech
so….. thanks." I love these conversations - it gets someone
new into "the family." I also had one conversation that was really a
nice ego boost. One of my guys introduced me to his wife. She
immediately exclaimed "it's so great to finally meet you, he talks
about you all the time!" That was kind of weird until she went on
"…every time he talks about Stuy." That made more sense. It's like
all those times when me and my buddy Ben would reminisce about our
Junior High school days and we'd always get back to talking about
&lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2012-05-09-my-favorite-year-teacher.html"&gt;Herb&lt;/a&gt;, one of our best and favorite teachers and a major influence on
me while Devorah looked on confused. Eventually she met and got to
know Herb and it all made sense. Another grad added "you think we all
forget about you but you come up more than you know" so I take that as
a shout out to all of the teachers out there who never get to hear
back about how much they are remembered and appreciated.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
With tools like email and Facebook it's easier to remain connected to
former students but it's always nice to connect in person. For the
StuyCS family, we have our periodic meetups but for the rest, I love
being included in class reunions and hope to be invited to more in
years to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="community" label="community"/>
    <category term="reunions" label="reunions"/>
    <category term="stuycs" label="stuycs"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
