<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about supervision)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/supervision.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 21:26:57 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Observing CS Teachers</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teacher-eval/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgcdafb65" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgcdafb65"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgcdafb65"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another set of tweets god me thinking:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;How do we help school administrators help and evaluate CS
teachers? asks &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/lsudol"&gt;@lsudol&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CSForAll"&gt;@CSForAll&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/csta2017?src=hash"&gt;#csta2017&lt;/a&gt;
Many don't understand CS&lt;/p&gt;— Alfred Thompson (@alfredtwo)
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo/status/884427047635795969"&gt;July
10, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;If the current system is any indication, checklists are not
the answer&lt;/p&gt;— Mike Zamansky (@zamansky) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zamansky/status/886220912110043136"&gt;July 15,
2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I get the intent. CS teachers should be evaluated by people who have
some clue about the subject. Leigh Ann's reporting that some people
are working on checklists got me wondering if it really matters? Sure,
it matters if teacher observations were actually set up to improve
instruction but given what we have in NY does it really?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In New York City, teacher observations are a major part of a teacher's
annual rating and the other part is still &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2013-09-06-why_i_might_no_longer_be_an_effective_teacher.md/#.WWqzc9_6yEI"&gt;that standardized test
nonsense&lt;/a&gt;. Teachers are observed at least 4 and commonly 6 times
or more per year. There might be pre and
post observation conferences.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sounds good but the system is amazingly flawed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start, the DOE uses the &lt;a href="http://schools.nyc.gov/NR/rdonlyres/8A4A25F0-BCEE-4484-9311-B5BB7A51D7F1/0/TeacherEffectivenessProgram1314Rubric201308142.pdf"&gt;Danielson Framework&lt;/a&gt; which provides a basis
for teacher evaluation. The framework is at best &lt;a href="https://tedmorrissey.wordpress.com/2014/03/23/fatal-flaws-of-the-danielson-framework/"&gt;flawed&lt;/a&gt; with even
Danielson coming out to say &lt;a href="https://tedmorrissey.wordpress.com/2016/04/27/danielson-framework-criticized-by-charlotte-danielson/"&gt;it's being misused&lt;/a&gt;. Of course I'm sure she
protested all the way to the bank. A teacher can be a "Danielson
style" teacher and be great but a teacher can also check all
the Danielson boxes and be mediocre at best. Likewise, some of the
best teachers I know break the Danielson mold and if a supervisor
rigidly adheres to the framework these great teachers would be found
ineffective.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To make matters worse, the rubric is so large that the DOE just
focuses on small parts which means even if the framework was
comprehensive and correct, teachers are only evaluated on a small
part.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When a supervisor evaluates a teacher, they have a checklist with the
rubric where they can rate a teacher 1 (ineffective), 2 (developing),
3 (effective), and 4 (highly effective) and write down some notes. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I guess the hope was to have some consistency but the truth is the
process is very subjective. I know a supervisor who gave a teacher a
ratings of 2 (which is basically failing) for the professional
development category even though the teacher fulfilled all contractual
obligations and then some. There are also supervisors who won't give a
rating of 4 out of principle. On the other side, I've met supervisors
loathe to give low scores.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The tweets at the top of this post refer to the current situation
where CS teachers are never observed and evaluated by supervisors who
are knowledgeable about CS. Even if someone designs a checklist -
something I'm skeptical about given the fact that there are so few
people strong in CS, experienced as teachers and with an eye for
teacher evaluation out there, if the application of the Danielson
framework is any indication, a CS checklist won't help.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Besides, CS won't be any different from any other subject. Since the
destruction of the comprehensive neighborhood high school we've had a
proliferation of small schools. Some people think that small schools
are universally better. They're wrong. You need a mix. One of the
problems with small schools is that you don't have subject area
supervisors. You have a principal and an assistant principal. The
result is that most teachers are evaluated by supervisors with no
subject area expertise and no subject area pedagogical expertise.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The old system, even though it was also subject to abuses was much
better - at least in the hands of a good supervisor. The observation
system is inherently flawed. Observations are snapshots out of context
and the mere presence of an observer changes the tone of the
room. That said, if a supervisor knows the heartbeat of their school
and has ongoing conversations with their staff, they can both ensure
teachers are doing an honest job and also help them to improve.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The method of observation also doesn't have to be complicated. My
first supervisor made it very simple. He said he looked for one basic
thing - "was learning going on?" The conversation would then go from
there. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sometimes you have to look beyond the lesson. In my first year, I
frequently observed a friend's history class. One day the class seemed
to do very little. It seemed like all talk and play. I talked to the
teacher about this. He said "that was what they needed today." He was
a master and he was right. You might drop in on his class to see
amazing instruction or you might come in and wonder why he wasn't
fired long ago but at the end of the year when you looked at how much
his kid learned and loved his class you realized that he was an
amazing teacher. No rubric or framework needed. Just the eyeball test.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
They also used to have more peer observations.They had to be coordinated
by the department supervisor and he or she had to be in the loop but
the peer observation model helped cross pollinate ideas in a
department, build camaraderie and it also eased the workload of the
supervisor.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To answer Alfred's question from his tweet, how do we help
administrators help CS teachers? Get other teachers involved, keep an
open mind and look at the big picture.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>supervision</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/cs-teacher-eval/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2017 00:13:38 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>