<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about teaching</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teaching.atom</id>
  <updated>2016-12-18T00:23:15Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teaching.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teaching/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Rookie Season Redux</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/rookie-season-redux/</id>
    <updated>2016-12-12T18:41:28-05:00</updated>
    <published>2016-12-12T18:41:28-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/rookie-season-redux/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
Today was the last day of classes at Hunter thus ending my first
semester of teaching at Hunter College.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I very much enjoyed the semester and my class and look forward to
working with the same group when the spring term starts in a few
weeks. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the same time, even though I'm a quarter century veteran teacher,
in many ways this was like my rookie season all over again.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My class was an honors intro class so the material wasn't new to me
but there were a number of adjustments going from high school to college.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I taught a few college classes as an adjunct back in the nineties but
I was a young teacher at the time and that was a lifetime ago.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The biggest difference is that we only met two days a week. Monday and
Thursday and we met for 1:45 rather than 45 minutes. The longer class
is nice but the twice a week means that you don't get that every day
reinforcement you have in high school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It also means that there were times when we would go a week between
classes due to a single day off. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The biggest challenge, one that I'm continuing to work on, is figuring
out how much we can do in a class, what and how much to assign between
classes and what's the best way to motivate the student's to space out
the work while doing something every day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That wasn't much of a challenge at Stuy. Having been there so long, I
had a good feel for my students as well as the pace and rhythm of
Stuy. Hunter has it's own rhythm and pace and I'm still figuring it
out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We also had to pivot early on as the student laptops didn't arrive
until a third of the semester was over.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, much of my work these days has to do with
developing the overall honors program as well as Hunter's forthcoming
teacher education programs in CS so I'm only teaching a single class
right now and it's small.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
If there are any rookie teachers reading this, congratulations on
getting through your first semester. I know you guys go a little bit
longer, but you're in the home stretch.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teaching right, particularly in public schools with large classes  will
always be an all in activity - certainly harder and more draining than
anything I ever did in industry but it does get easier as you learn
your school and students and develop your craft. 
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>First day back, or not</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-day-back/</id>
    <updated>2016-09-06T10:56:56-04:00</updated>
    <published>2016-09-06T10:56:56-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-day-back/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
The day after Labor Day. The day NYC teachers traditionally return to
work. For the first time in a quarter century, I'm not one of them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's weird.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Instead, I'm in the second week of Hunter College's fall semester. So
far so good on that front. I'm getting to know my students, planning
activities and overall having a good time. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But, I do have to reflect on some of the things I'm not going to get
to do this week:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not going to have the opportunity to be blindsided by a CS
schedule made without consulting me or any other CS teacher and having
to work frantically to fix it so that the CS teachers have the
programs and rooms they want.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not going to be able to have that panic attack when the NFS/NIS
server isn't working and no one can log in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not going to sit through a mindless faculty meeting where nothing
is really ever accomplished.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
More seriously, I am going to miss seing my friends and colleagues
after the summer and Thursday - the day the kids get back is always a
thrill and I'm going to miss that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In a way, I'm experiencing a version of what retired teachers go
through. Many teachers retire in June but it's not until after Labor
Day when the change really sinks in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Soon, I'll start posting CS teaching content again but for today, I
want to tip my cap to all the public school teachers in NY that are
going back to work today and who will shortly be teaching their five classes
of thirty four kids each &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-day-back/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-day-back/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;also tipping my cap to my favorite TJ
teacher who's students are back today. I got called to task for
failing to mention her on my facebook shoutout.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>West coast trip - a nice close to act I</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</id>
    <updated>2016-07-18T13:18:06-04:00</updated>
    <published>2016-07-18T13:18:06-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;

&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/facebook.jpg" alt="facebook.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If I look at my leaving Stuyvesant and the NYC Department of
Education to join Hunter College as the end of Act I of my teaching
career, then our family's West Coast swing was a nice way to pull
down the curtain.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The impetus for the trip was visiting Batya - she's interning at
Facebook this summer and having an absolute blast.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The plan was to spend a few days in San Francisco, then a little south
to Mountain View, where Batya was staying, and then fly up to Seattle
for a couple of days.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, while out there, why not see if some of the StuyCS family
wanted to get together.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I knew I had a lot of former students out on the West Coast but still, I was
overwhelmed and humbled by the number of people who wanted to spend
time and catch up. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We kicked things off at Bloomberg Beta thanks to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/roybahat"&gt;Roy Bahat.&lt;/a&gt; Roy was
never actually my student but we've gotten to know each other over the
years and I value him as a friend and advisor. Roy provided the food
and the space and about 60 former students + a few old timers showed.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/bloomberg.jpg" alt="bloomberg.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of days later, we had a lunch meetup for the Googlers:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/google.jpg" alt="google.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and a happy hour at Facebook (sorry, no picture). Then in Seattle, a
nice dinner to close things out.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/seattle.jpg" alt="seattle.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Between these events there were some lunches, a barbecue at Batya's
place  and even a drive by visit with a former student at
Microsoft. Overall, it was easily over 100 students over the course of
the week or so we were out there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've often said that one of the things I'm proudest of is helping to
build the StuyCS family. A community of people spanning decades. Over
the week, we had events mixing students from the mid 90's to
youngsters currently in college and on their internships.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Seeing all these people meeting and supporting each other gave me a
"proud pappa" type feeling even though I didn't do any more than set
the stage for them getting together.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the week, the conversations were also great - not the straight
tech ones, but the ones that really made me proud of the crew. From
Seth talking about how to better get good CS Ed to more kids, to PJ
discussing why he feels it's so important to be an active mentor to
his young programmers and how to get them to be real thinkers, to
Mike, Sam, Kathy, and Leo discussing the disconnect between
privileged families and those struggling to get by. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What more could a teacher want than their former students being both
happy in their lives and careers as well as good people seeking to
make the world better for everyone.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The only thing that made me sad about the trip is that with all the
big events, I really didn't get a chance to spend the time I wanted
with everyone. I hope to do better next time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, I've now been at Hunter for one semester and things will really
ramp up in the Fall. I'm still a proud part of our StuyCS family and if
being a part of pulling it together is the legacy I left, I can live
with that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The trip was a nice symbolic way to lower the curtain on act 1. I'm
counting on the StuyCS family and all the other players to help so
that we can make sure act 2 is a success and we can build something
similar for more young people throughout the city and perhaps the country. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="community" label="community"/>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
    <category term="tech" label="tech"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
