<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about teaching cs</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teaching-cs.atom</id>
  <updated>2017-06-29T16:40:54Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teaching-cs.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teaching-cs/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>SIGCSE 2017 - Recap</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-recap/</id>
    <updated>2017-03-14T08:19:18-04:00</updated>
    <published>2017-03-14T08:19:18-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse-2017-recap/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a high school teacher, I was never able to attend SIGCSE, the
conference of the ACM's Special Interest Group on Computer Science
Education. Between the number of instructional days I would lose and
the cost, I could never justify going. Instead I looked over the
proceedings and read many of the papers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now that I'm at Hunter, I was finally able to attend. This year in
Seattle, the conference ran from Wednesday through Saturday. I was
part of a panel on "Tools we can't live without." Over the next few
weeks, I hope to blog about a number of things I thought and talked
with people about over the conference including:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The path I use to teach git and why GitHub a good teaching tool
(my talk).
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The relationship of different CS Ed stakeholders - teachers,
researchers, organizations, etc.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teaching at the high school level vs college - perceptions and
reality.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The challenges of tech tool adoption in schools.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's going on in K12 CS Certification.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maybe some other stuff.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today, some overall thoughts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;The good&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As with many conferences, the "hallway track" along with receptions
sponsored by &lt;a href="https://csnyc.org/our-work/cs4all"&gt;the CS4All consurtium&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://tealsk12.org"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://code.org"&gt;Code.org&lt;/a&gt; were terrific. I
was able to finally meet in person many people who I've only known
virtually and got to know many more as well. I left the conference
with a much larger address book and a long list of follow up
items. Being in Seattle, I also enjoyed being able to spend time with
people from &lt;a href="http://tealsk12.org"&gt;TEALS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://code.org"&gt;Code.org&lt;/a&gt;, two of the CS Ed groups working hard
to do some real good (yes - I do like and support these guys even
though I call them out on things I disagree with, but that's the
subject of another post). 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I attended sessions on CS certification, teacher preparation,
assessments, POGIL based instruction to name a few. They ranged from
valuable to interesting and to be honest, a couple of "what were they
thinking" but the overall experience was very much worth the trip. I
also got to speak to a number of wonderful students at the
poster sessions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The keynotes are also well worth a read (sorry if you don't have ACM
digital library access). &lt;a href="http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3025045&amp;amp;CFID=738971273&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=22106692"&gt;Jeannette Wing&lt;/a&gt; talked about the importance of
probability and statistics in CS Ed, and aspects of  &lt;a href="http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3025047&amp;amp;CFID=738971273&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=22106692"&gt;Gail Chapman&lt;/a&gt;'s talk
"Inspire, Innovate, and Improve…" keynote and &lt;a href="http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3025046&amp;amp;CFID=738971273&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=22106692"&gt;Mitch Resnick&lt;/a&gt;'s
"Fulfilling Papert's Dream" both spoke to the educator inside me. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;The bad&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biggest downside to me was that I found very little value added in
a number of the paper sessions over just reading the papers. Part of
this is probably because of my own over-inflated expectations given the
number of years I've waited to attend. Part of it though, was the fact
that sessions were so tightly packed that I didn't have time to follow
up with presenters before having to run to the next
thing. Unfortunately, in some
cases, it was because the presenter merely
"read" the paper much as a professor sometimes just reads the slides
or the book to his class.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;Other thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One paper presentation I very much liked was &lt;a href="http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3017701&amp;amp;CFID=738971273&amp;amp;CFTOKEN=22106692"&gt;Exam Wrappers: Not a
Silver Bullet&lt;/a&gt; presented by &lt;a href="https://michellecraig.github.io/"&gt;Michelle Craig&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://pages.cpsc.ucalgary.ca/~bdstephe/"&gt;Ben Stephenson&lt;/a&gt;. I
actually came in late since I was hustling over from the Code.org
lunch. The result was that I didn't actually know what "Exam Wrappers"
were until well after the talk when I ran into &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jkhuggins"&gt;Jim Huggins&lt;/a&gt;. Exam
wrappers, in short, are merely when you require the students fill out something
for some credit when picking up their exams. The funny thing is that
it's a strategy that high school teachers have used for years without
a special name and we already knew the good and bad of it without the
research but that's not what I want to get at here. What I loved about
the talk, besides the fact that Ben and Michelle are clearly strong
presenters is that this was a negative result that was being
presented. I also loved the fact that they didn't present their
research as gospel but rather pointed out the strengths and weaknesses
of their approach - they made a case to what and why we should pay
attention to and what should be taken with a grain of salt.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was a major breath of fresh air after being exposed to so much
education 'research' over the course of my life that the author or
presenter felt was just as strong as a mathematical proof rather than
an indication based on a specific experience or small set of
experiences.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also felt a little weird at times during the week when west coast people seemed
to know me. I know I'm a loud mouthed curmudgeon and I go on my
periodic ed rants but given the dearth of comments on this blog I was
really surprised to get as many as "great to meet you in person after
reading your blog" or "we know you and your work" all week. It was
weird and somewhat humbling.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, another highlight f`or me was that I got to catch up with
some of family.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/sigcse-seattle.jpg" alt="sigcse-seattle.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Already planning to submit something to present at SIGCSE 2018 in Baltimore.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="csed" label="csed"/>
    <category term="cseducation" label="cseducation"/>
    <category term="teaching-cs" label="teaching cs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Essential topics for an intro course (not)</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/essentials-for-an-intro-course/</id>
    <updated>2017-01-09T15:56:08-05:00</updated>
    <published>2017-01-09T15:56:08-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/essentials-for-an-intro-course/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
What essential topics should we teach in our intro courses? This seems
to be a recurring topic recently. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It can be an important topic but, unfortunately, too often, it seems
that people have too myopic a view
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I remember thinking about this years ago when APCS moved from C++ to
Java. Both languages have good and bad points both for practical and
educational use. A big loss in the move to Java was memory management
and the topics you could cover when memory issues arose. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course one might say that memory management shouldn't be in the
first year of CS. That's fine, as long as you put it back in somewhere
later on - something that didn't seem to happen universally. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's the myopic view - far too few look at the overall picture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
C++ to Java ended up in removing a topic. I've also seen the reverse. 
I was talking to a friend about intro topics. He told me that it was
critical to cover (insert topic here) in an intro course. Why, I
asked? Because the kids absolutely needed to know that material in the
third year course he was teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I pressed a bit – "how many kids actually remember (insert topic
here) and do you have to reteach anything." The answer - pretty much
no one remembered and he always retaught the subject.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Did this mean that no one taught the topic in the earlier class?
Unlikely. More likely is that the topic was taught without purpose or
context, just because it was supposed to be taught and thus the
knowledge wasn't retained. Sounds to me like the topic wasn't in the
right place to begin with. Maybe it should have just been taught in
that 300 level course to begin with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alfredtwo?ref_src=twsrc%255Etfw"&gt;Alfred Thompson&lt;/a&gt; wrote a post earlier today asking about &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/01/how-important-are-number-bases-for-pre.html"&gt;teaching
number bases&lt;/a&gt;. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Is it important? Maybe. Is it essential for an intro course? Probably
not. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Binary makes sense when you start talking about low level stuff. If
your intro course never gets close to the machine then why muddy the water
with a topic that's out of place. The topic probably won't be
appreciated and retention and understanding will be low. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If your intro course gets close to the machine or if you decide to
talk about compiled code or similar topics, you have an entre to talk
binary which leads to the convenience of hexadecimal. At Stuyvesant,
it was much more sensible to talk about number bases in our systems
course when we looked at C code in a debugger rather than in our intro
our AP course. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You also might work on some application where bitmaps or similar as
useful. That might be another good time to talk about number bases.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Is it important for a CS person to understand binary and it's relation
to digital computers? Certainly. Does it have to be studied day one?
Certainly not.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We need to keep an eye on the big picture. You can't get everything
into a single class or a single yea. The question to ask is - do our students know what they have to by the time they
leave our charge?
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="curriculum" label="curriculum"/>
    <category term="teaching-cs" label="teaching cs"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
