<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about teaching)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teaching.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2018 21:25:28 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>PD for people who know CS</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pd-for-cs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org9bb6680" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org9bb6680"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org9bb6680"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I saw a couple of tweets from Sarah Judd this morning:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;A lot of CS Ed PD assumes you are new to CS. I really want CS Ed PD for people like us that came from a CS background and want to understand the pedagogy for CS in particular better. Do you know of some?&lt;/p&gt;— Sarah Judd (@SarahEJudd) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SarahEJudd/status/1011785286693552139?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;June 27, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Yes! I love SIGCSE and CSTA. I just feel like... Math teachers don't get PD that starts with "and this is how you add and subtract!" and I'd love more CS PD that assumes the content is there, and can focus on the pedagogy.&lt;/p&gt;— Sarah Judd (@SarahEJudd) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SarahEJudd/status/1011966102795059200?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;June 27, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It wasn't the first time I've heard this refrain. Last year I attended
my first CSTA conference. I had numerous conversations with CS
teachers on the fact that everything was on an intro level in terms of
both content and teaching. Further conversations with local teachers
with stronger CS backgrounds led me to run a professional development
session at Hunter this past election day for more experienced CS
teachers at schools that offered more than the basics.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While it's not surprising that most of the PD opportunities for CS teachers are
rather rudimentary given that nationally most programs are new and
most teachers are new to the subject but there are a few deeper
reasons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To start, there are big players in the CS Ed movement that are pushing
curricula and specific programs and that leads to scripted PD for
their products and not depth of knowledge nor deep pedagogical content
knowledge let alone basic pedagogy. Add to this the fact that many of
the "thought leaders" in the space don't have experience teaching CS
at the K12 level and in many cases don't have a background either in
teaching nor tech and you can see where the problem comes from. On top
of this we have the erosion of respect for teaching as a profession
where reformers are trying to take the teacher out of teaching and are
trying to reduce pedagogy to following scripts. This problem goes well
beyond CS Ed but as the new kid on the block it probably hits us
hardest.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any case, preparing beginners is both necessary and appropriate for
the time being but we can and must do a better job than what's
currently "state of the art." At the same time we have to do something
with the CS teachers who indeed do have strong content knowledge but
don't feel comfortable with imparting that knowledge.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what should we do?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For new teachers the solution will ultimately have to come
from pre-service programs but what we end up getting is going to
largely be dictated on what's required by individual states. If states
merely require passing an exam like the Praxis CS exam which, from
what I can gather isn't a horrible content exam then we're going to
see CS teachers bumble through their early to mid careers while trying
to figure out how to teach CS much like I did way back when. If they
end up endorsing pre-service programs that are focused on specific
curricula - APCS-A for teachers, APCS-P for teachers, &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/math-for-math-teachers/"&gt;Math for Math
teachers&lt;/a&gt; if you will but for CS, we're also not going to get strong
well prepared pedagogues. On the other hand if you can design a
program that has a strong pedagogical component to go along with the
content, you have a chance. Even with a well designed program
implementation will still be a challenge. Who will teach it? Education
professors who don't have CS backgrounds? CS professors with little
pedagogical training? Neither of those groups necessarily have any
real experience as actual K12 teachers. If you can find honest to
goodness experienced, strong K12 CS teachers to teach your pedagogy
courses that's a big win but that's going to be hard in most cases. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think we designed a great program at Hunter and have a practical and
strong implementation plan. If you're going to be
at CSTA2018 you can hear all about it and why we designed it as we did
in the talk I'm giving. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For the more experienced I don't have a universal answer but I can say
what I'm planning. Teachers in NY have to complete 100 CTLE hours
every five years. For beginners, there are plenty of options, at least
content wise. For teachers who know CS, not so much. I was at a meetup
talking to a few friends a couple of weeks ago and one mentioned that
they get most of their hours in Math for America CS
workshops. Unfortunately more than a few of my CS teacher friends who
are in MFA tell me that the CS content in these workshops, while they
do satisfy the hours, are somewhat lacking on the CS / CS pedagogy
side.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's what I'm planning - we (Hunter) will host a once a month
dinner/session for CS teachers who are a little farther along CS
wise. I haven't worked out all the details yet but I've got a few tech
companies that are already interested in sponsoring and helping out
should we need anything and we'll probably set most of our agenda for
the year at the first session where I'll make my best guess at a
useful agenda. This is something I'm pretty excited about. It should
help create a network of more experienced CS teachers which will both
help bolster that segment of the community and provide a long term
resource to newcomers and it should be a lot of fun.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In some ways, this is why I ended up joining Hunter. Regardless of
what the city and state do, we're going to prepare the teachers and if
you have a well prepared teacher, you've got a shot.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>csed</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/pd-for-cs/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 18:41:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Tech or the Teacher</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tech-or-teacher/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org523157b" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org523157b"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org523157b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Every morning one of the first things I do is quickly glance at my
emails and other notifications. I really should wait until I'm more
awake but old habits die hard. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As some of you know over the past couple of years I've been making a
series of &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs"&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; and related post on using my editor of choice,
Emacs. I've done 48 videos, have over 2500 subscribers on
YouTube and people seem to find some value from the series. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This morning one of my emails was a new comment on one of my videos:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thanks for not describing a single key combination and how that fits
into basic usage of org mode.  I was going to subscribe but if all
your videos are going to be about showing off how fast you are at
typing emacs commands on your annoyingly noisy keyborad, then no
thanks!﻿
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
My first reaction was "you know, you could have said something like
'if you slow down an actually say the keys it would be much easier to
follow and would be more valuable' and it would be much better received" but
then I started to think about instructional videos in general. I
started to make these videos for my students. I thought they might be
helpful and then found that the Emacs community by and large liked
them. They're not teaching anything deep or complicated just how I use
a programmable editor. Even so, I was reminded by this comment about
the limitations of videos and ed tech in general.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Videos provide some nice features - you can watch them at any time,
you can pause and replay, and in some cases you can watch at super
speeds. What you can't do is slow the video down and most importantly
you can't ask questions or interact with the instructor. You can leave
comments if the video is on a platform like YouTube but that's pretty
limited.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, if this was a class, we would have been able to
interact and I as the instructor would have had a much better chance
to make sure this "student" was up to speed. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, this wasn't a class. I don't have the time to teach tools
like Emacs in class and since it is a mechanical skill, it can be
offloaded to a video. The video has the ancillary benefit of living on
and being discoverable and viewable by the public at large. This is a
good thing. Videos are tech and tech scales. Unfortunately, good
education doesn't. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Videos are tech and tech is the rage. Lots of people are working hard
to get more tech in front of our kids - usually at the expense of
having a great teacher. This is something we don't need. Technology is
nice but I'd rather have my kids in a small class with a knowledgable
teacher and a piece of chalk than all the tech in the world. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a computer science guy and a computer science teacher I think it's
good to remind myself that tech is cool but a good teacher is way cooler.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>edtech</category><category>teaching</category><category>tech</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/tech-or-teacher/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2018 21:43:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>No Magic Bullets - Discovery Learning</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/no-magic-bullets-constructivism/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb255dab" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgb255dab"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgb255dab"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The most recent NYC CSTA chapter meeting was "How do I assess CS?" I
wanted to go but it's been such a crazy month I was just too wiped
out. Fortunately, the meetup was &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XIMKAZbHAiA&amp;amp;index=83&amp;amp;list=WL&amp;amp;t=1796s"&gt;recorded&lt;/a&gt;. I was able to watch the
first half this morning while working out on my &lt;a href="https://www.staczero.com/hero"&gt;stationary trainer&lt;/a&gt;
which leads me to today's rare Saturday morning blog
post. The meetup consisted of two panels. The first was made up of K12
teachers who taught CS. I can't talk about the second panel yet since I'm
only halfway through but there were a couple of points made by my
friend &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/KatieJergens"&gt;Katie Jergens&lt;/a&gt; who teaches at Dalton that I thought were worth
talking about.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first was when Katie noted that through working with the panel,
one of her takeaways was that:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Giving students an explicit strategy for solving a problem - "this is
how I would do it….," - giving them an explicit strategy first and then giving them a
problem for which that strategy would apply is much more effective than
having them discover it on their own.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was refreshing to hear after being beaten over the head on
discovery learning and constructivism for the past five or so
years as being the magic bullet for teachers. I shared more thoughts
on this a few weeks ago when I wrote about a SIGCSE paper presented by
&lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-bootstrap/"&gt;Bootstrap World&lt;/a&gt; that I very much liked. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Katie went on to talk about how the group found that while "discovery
learning" can be effective it can also be frustrating and lose kids
along the way. It also takes a lot of time and preparation, something
that's short on supply in most public schools.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This made me think about the recent flurry
of discussion around the debunking of learning styles which had
previously been the magic bullet. When I started, the secret sauce was cooperative
learning. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course any good teacher knows there's no magic bullet. You fill
your tool belt and chest with as much as you can and use what's
best based on your strengths as a teacher combined with what will work
best with your students.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another point that Katie made that I found refreshing had to do with 
something she does with her classes. A good portion of a student's grade is
based on what she calls a "booster." Each student has to work one on
one with her on some project. The student either scores a 0 or a 100 -
the student keeps working with the direct support of the teacher until
it's perfect. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The important thing that Katie said with respect to this is "I can
do this because my largest class is sixteen students." No way could
this ever scale to a public school where a teacher can meet with over
150 students a day and barely has time eat lunch let alone
work one on one with a student in a suitably quiet place like an
office. The refreshing thing to hear was the acknowledgment of the
fact that what works in a rich private school won't work in a public
school. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All to often education and yes, CS Ed is driven by people who
really have no clue. They're anointed as thought leaders but they
don't walk the walk. Some have some knowledge and experience but many
don't. Until you've gotten a few years under your belt in a strap
cashed public school that takes all comers, don't tell them how they
should do it. Katie didn't - she acknowledged the problem - too bad so
many others don't. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm looking forward to watching the rest of the video during a future
workout and might have more to share then. For now, take a look for
yourself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>assessment</category><category>csed</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/no-magic-bullets-constructivism/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 21 Apr 2018 11:40:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Strong K12 Teacher Certification is Important</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org7fcb981" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org7fcb981"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org7fcb981"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
About a week ago New York State's new regulation creating a &lt;a href="http://www.crainsnewyork.com/article/20180327/NEWS/180329893/new-york-will-finally-have-certified-computer-science-teachers"&gt;K12 CS
teacher certification&lt;/a&gt; went live. Just the other day I was honored to be
interviewed by  &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mflamm_reporter"&gt;Matt Flamm&lt;/a&gt; of Crain's New York in a &lt;a href="http://www.crainsnewyork.com/article/20180410/TECHNOLOGY/180419999/asked-answered-teacher-changed-jobs-to-push-for-new-york-states-new"&gt;follow up piece&lt;/a&gt;
about it. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Having K12 CS teacher certification is big and having quality programs
that lead to certification is &lt;b&gt;HUGE&lt;/b&gt;. In my view, it's a game changer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's Focus on high school, my wheelhouse.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From a course offerings point of view it's the wild west. I don't mean
this as a bad thing, it's just that there's a huge range of offerings
from AP to home brew, physical computing, game based, cyber security,
you name it, there's a curriculum. The long and short of this is that
schools need teachers to teach all of these experiences. Without a
strong certification pathway we're going to be stuck with the current
training based model where teachers are trained to deliver canned
curricula rather than truly teach. With strong teacher preparation
programs teachers will be prepared not only to deliver all the
existing curricula but, arguable more importantly design their own
learning experiences appropriate for the populations they work with.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is important and alone would make having CS certification
worthwhile but to me the BIG win is that it creates a viable career
path. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
People say we'll never find enough CS teachers because the tech
industry pays so well. I've never believed that. We find math teachers
even though many could flee to finance and chem teachers in spite of
big pharma's call so why can't we find CS teachers? Because we've
never provided a path into the profession and a viable career track. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Certification means that over time schools will be able to build CS
teachers and the discipline will be treated as the other
subjects. Prior to certification, a CS teacher might be cut if a
school's math department downsized. With certification, the career
track for a CS teacher is the same as the track for any other teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It also means that young people starting out who are interested in
both teaching and computer science will have a way of getting into the
profession - something that has never before existed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Having CS certification alone won't woo a
plethora of current tech professionals into teaching but over time,
we'll start to have CS Ed majors or CS majors pursuing CS ED Masters
degrees and entering the profession. This won't happen in a press or
election cycle but it will happen.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This all hinges on quality prep programs. I think I've hit the sweet
spot with what I've designed at Hunter. The critical components are of
course content and pedagogy. Teacher candidates must have both
sufficient depth and breadth in the subject and all the pedagogical
content knowledge that comes along with it. I don't agree with the
common approach of taking a course to teach a course - that is, having
courses like "APCS - Principles for teachers" or "APCS - A for
teachers."  I want my teachers to be able to teach any reasonable
curriculum or design their own so we'll be rolling out courses that
examine the commonly offerd curricula but prepare teachers for a whole
lot more.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's been an exciting week in NY CS Ed and there's a lot more to come.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>certification</category><category>cs</category><category>policy</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/strong-teacher-certification/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 21:39:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Refactoring</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/refactoring/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgb8cefc1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgb8cefc1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgb8cefc1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of my laments on teaching computer science is that students are
rarely taught and given the chance to develop  good programming
practices. There's usually not enough time. Beginners work on small
"toys" which don't lend themselves to good software development
practices and later on, there's so much other material like
algorithms, data structures etc. to teach and
learn that programming practices usually amount to lines like:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
"Make sure to comment your code.."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
"Indent properly…"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
"Use functions…"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
"It's important to test your code…"
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
so when I see an opportunity to use a simple example to drive home a
good practice,  I try to jump on it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Drawing shapes with text is a typical early project. I've seen it in
text books and online and have been doing it for years. I recall doing
it back in the 80s in Fortran IV when the programs we wrote were on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Punched_card"&gt;punch cards&lt;/a&gt;, run
overnight on an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_1130"&gt;IBM 1130&lt;/a&gt;, and printouts picked up the next day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's a nice use of nested loops. The students will write functions to
create assorted shapes out of asterisks  like rectangles and
triangles. Typical solutions look like this:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cpf"&gt;&amp;lt;iostream&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;box&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;""&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"*"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tri&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;""&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"*"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Which results in shapes like these:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class="example"&gt;

| ****            |    | *               |
| ****            |    | **              |
| ****            |    | ***             |
| ****            |    | ****            |
| ****            |    |                 |
|                 |    |                 |
|                 |    |                 |
| *************** |    | *               |
| *************** |    | **              |
| *************** |    | ***             |
| *************** |    | ****            |
| *************** |    | *****           |
| *************** |    | ******          |
| *************** |    | *******         |

&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then there will be more interesting shapes including things like:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class="example"&gt;

   *       *            *****
  **      ***           *   *            and more
 ***     *****          *   *
****      ***           *****
           *   

&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is a great time to talk about refactoring.  All of the shape
drawing functions follow the same pattern - there's an outer loop for
the height and then one or more inner loops to draw each line. We can
factor out the inner loops in to a separate &lt;code&gt;line()&lt;/code&gt; function.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cpf"&gt;&amp;lt;iostream&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;box&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;""&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"*"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;                    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// &amp;lt;----- This can be factored out&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;                                 &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tri&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;""&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"*"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;                   &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// &amp;lt;---------------- along with this&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;                               &lt;span class="c1"&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's just like factoring in algebra:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="LATEX"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
(RectangleOuterLoop × Line) + (TriangleOuterLoop × Line) ⇒ Line  (Rectangleouterloop × TriangleOuterloop)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We end up with:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cpf"&gt;&amp;lt;iostream&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;""&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;box&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;""&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"*"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tri&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;""&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"*"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
It's simpler, cleaner, and also can lead us to thinking about the
"harder" shapes in an interesting way. Instead of looking at the right
justified triangle as a triangle, we can think of each level as two
lines - one of spaces (shown here as dashes) followed by a line of
stars:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;pre class="example"&gt;
----*       *
---**      **
--***     ***
-****    ****
*****   *****

&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Noticing that  for a height of 5, the dashed lines count down in
length 4,3,2,1,0 and the star lines count up 1,2,3,4,5, we get:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tri2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;""&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"-"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"*"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tri2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;cout&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;endl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here we have typical early CS assignment that really lends itself to
talking about structuring programs and refactoring. Where else can we
inject good programming practices in ways that make sense early on?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/refactoring/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 12:11:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Sigcse2018 Bootstrapworld on Creativity in CS classes</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-bootstrap/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org1622e3f" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org1622e3f"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org1622e3f"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I really didn't know what to expect at the &lt;a href="https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3159471"&gt;Creativity, Customization,
and Ownership: Game Design in Bootstrap: Algebra&lt;/a&gt; session. I've been a
big fan of &lt;a href="http://www.bootstrapworld.org/"&gt;Bootstrep&lt;/a&gt; for years and looking at the authors, &lt;a href="http://blog.acthompson.net/2017/10/cs-teacher-interview-emmanuel.html"&gt;Emmanuel
Schanzer&lt;/a&gt;'s been a freind forever. I've never met &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ShriramKMurthi"&gt;Shriram Krishnamurthi&lt;/a&gt;
in person but am looking forward to it. We've traded emails and blog
comments. I'd like to consider him a friend and I certainly respect
him and his work even though we frequently disagree around the
edges. The third author and presenter, Kathi Fisler was new to me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Bootstrap program is embedded in algebra classes. In it, students
use Racket (nee scheme) to reinforce math skills while building
computer science skills. The big student project is a graphical game.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When designing the project, students are asked to decide on and find
four resources:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The background image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The player image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The target image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The enemy image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Students are given a short amount of time to decide on and find these
four images. I think it was about ten minutes and that's it. That's
all the "creativity" in the assignment. After that, all the students
are essentially creating the same game with different skins.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This design makes sense. You can't have students going all over the
place. Constraining the assignment in this way allows teachers who
might now be strong in computer science to guide the kids through the
program to completion.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the time I was thinking: I really like all of this but is it really
open ended creativity and discovery with respect to math or computer
science? As it turned out, Fisler addressed this point at the end of
the talk in a way that made me vary happy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fisler went on to describe the rest of the student experience and then
went on to talk about the statistics they gathered. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One big takeaway was that while all the students were essentially
writing the same game varying only the graphical elements, this
encouraged students to create very different themes. They also created
rich stories around their games. The project might not have been
"creative" with respect to the CS or Math directions but it was certainly
creative in other important areas. The other takeaway was that
survey's indicated all sorts of positives from the program as a whole
so the project didn't seem to have suffered by having the students
essentially write the same program. Participants were proud of their
work, they felt their games were different from their peers and in
general the experience was good.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
During questions, someone asked about adding a fifth element - a
projectile or missile. It turns out that at one point the program had a
projectile component but that led to the vast majority of projects to
be themed in very similar ways. Even though not the same, it reminded me to something Randy
Pausch said in his &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ji5_MqicxSo"&gt;Last Lecture&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You make whatever you want. Two rules: no shooting violence and no
pornography. Not because I’m opposed to those in particular, but you know, that’s been done with
VR, right? [laughter] And you’d be amazed how many 19-year-old boys are completely out of ideas
when you take those off the table.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the very end, Fisler addressed my questions about creativity and
discovery. She posed these questions of her own: "Do we overstate the
case for creativity?" and "Is pure constructivism a win?"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've ranted on contructivism before. It can be great but a
constructivist lesson takes a knowledgeable educator and a lot of time,
preparation, and effort. It's a big ask for, say, a high school
teacher who's already taking home hours of work every evening. Too
often I've seen the following "contructivist" model instead:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take an isntructor that doesn't know their craft, the content, or
niether.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let the kids play with stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show off the couple of autodidacts that figure it out as success
stories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'll rant more about this "model" with respect to the new buzz word
"lead learner" at some point in the future.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the creativity side, it's important but there are also times for
the instructor to lead and for guidelines to be followed.
We want to foster creativity but that doesn't mean that it's 100%
creativity 100% of the time. Education is like life, a balance. The
Bootstrap program had to constrain the CS and math learning but
allowed for creativity in other areas. It's smart and it's a win.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I still want to meet Shriram in person one day and now also Kathi
Fisler. I didn't know what to expect walking in but I left the talk
reminded of why I'm such a fan of Emmanuel, his team, and their work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-bootstrap/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2018 13:27:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tools can shape how we think</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-2016-6-4/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org4a42606" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org4a42606"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org4a42606"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've been having fun with this years &lt;a href="http://adventofcode.com"&gt;Advent of Code&lt;/a&gt; competition. So
far, I've been able to keep up but with I expect that to change in
another couple of days since I'll be traveling for the weekend.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After solving a problem, I like looking over some of the other
solutions on the Advent of Code &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/adventofcode/"&gt;subreddit&lt;/a&gt;. Even with similar
agorithmic solutions there's a decent amount of variation in the
actual code and solutions in different languages can look radically
different.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That got me thinking about how the tools we know and use both shape the ways we
approach solving problems and creating things and either limit or
empower us to go from a mental model of a solution or creation to an
actual artifact. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Relating to this are the common themes that come up in the CS
Education world. The idea that it's computer science not programming
and certainly not merely coding. That's true but the tools and
languages we use shape the whole thinking part and can also give the
students a valuable practical tool that they can leverage to great
advantage in both future classes and work and life endeavors.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I decided to do this rant as a video. I hope you enjoy it:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/x8cZgEogWNw" frameborder="0" gesture="media" allow="encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>adventofcode</category><category>pedagogy</category><category>teaching</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/advent-2016-6-4/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 20:01:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Thoughts On A Hackathon</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/thoughts-on-a-hackathon/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org8c82a89" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org8c82a89"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org8c82a89"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I was one of the judges at &lt;a href="http://stuyhacks.com/"&gt;StuyHacks&lt;/a&gt;. A one day hackathon at
Stuyvesant run by and organized by the students. I don't have attendee
stats but there were kids from all over the city and at least one team
from New Jersey. The youngest student that I met was in sixth grade
and the oldest were high school seniors. The judging was at the end
but I decided to stop by earlier to see how the hackers were doing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There was an incredible variety of projects using a wide array of
tools. There were projects built with:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Java&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C#&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scratch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A-Frame&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python / Flask&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTML/CSS/JS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A personal highlight for me was running into Sophie - the daughter of
two of my students from #Stuy95. Well, both a highlight and a reminder
that I'm getting old.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The StuyHacks team did a terrific job running things and at the end I
told them I'd love to help with future events.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I did notice a couple of things at the hackathon that echo things I've
learned as a teacher over the years and I thought they were worth
sharing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first was the a number of the beginner groups needed more
direction. This didn't seem to be related to grade level or age as
much as CS experience. This isn't a hackathon only issue. It exists in
all learning environments. If as teachers we're too prescriptive
students end up with a single formula to follow. Sure, that'll get
them through a standardized exam like APCS-A but too much of it can
hinder them in becoming creative problem solvers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, not enough structure will leave many kids staring
at a blank page. I remember I gave a quiz years ago. It had one
problem: "You have 20 minutes to prove to me that you learned
something about the past unit on Cellular Autmata" or something like
that. Some kids absolutely loved it but many hated it. Stuy kids are
trained test takers. They're prepared for structure. This threw many
for a loop.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I noticed this issue with some of the hackers at StuyHacks. Some
beginners really had a hard time figuring out what they could do and
what they should do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A hackathon isn't a classroom so I think the problem is pretty easily
remedied. Groups that were able to latch on to a good mentor seemed to
get the guidance they needed. A beginners hackathon should make sure
they have not only plenty of mentors but they should make sure that
the mentors are prepped with a number of project ideas in a number of
the standard beginner platforms. A hackathon could also provide an
assortment of ideas in a list.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The second thing I noticed was at the end of the day as I was
judging. It started with one particular group. They were pretty
apologetic about their project. Basically because it wasn't
finished. Personally, I thought what they accomplished in essentially
7 hours was pretty impressive. What became clear as we talked is that
this group was deathly afraid of failure. Their deepest fear at that
moment was that I was going to give them high marks and they might
have to show off their incomplete (yet rather impressive) project to a
room full of strangers. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This fear of failure was prevalent in groups that ultimately didn't
submit their projects for judging and it seemed to be common among
students from high performing, high expectation schools where
frequently one associates a test score or grade with ones value. I'm
not happy to say that Stuy has always had this problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This isn't really a problem that a hackathon can or should be able to
address. It's just something I noticed. It's a problem for schools and
also for a society that's test obsessed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I hope nobody reads too much into these observations. The day was a
tremendous success. A whole bunch of kids had a great day working
together to build cool things with technology. Congratulations to the
StuyHacks team. They did a terrific job putting it all together. If
you're a middle or high school student or know one, keep an eye on the
StuyHacks &lt;a href="http://stuyhacks.com/"&gt;web page&lt;/a&gt; and make sure to attend their next event.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>hackathons</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/thoughts-on-a-hackathon/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Dec 2017 12:47:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Early Interesting Problems - Happy Ladybugs</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/happy_ladybug/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org857d5fd" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org857d5fd"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org857d5fd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We all love interesting problems. The trouble is that it's hard to
find suitably interesting problems for students when they're just
learning the basics. In the very beginning the problems practically
dictate the solution:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;loop over a list and add all the elements or calculate the sum of a
list of integers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine if  number is prime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Convert a word into pig-Latin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not that there's no thought involved in solving these but the
students already know the mechanics of solving these by hand so it's a
direct translation into a program.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This isn't a bad thing and it is important but it's fun when we get to the next
level. I've found that a number of the &lt;a href="http://hackerrank.com"&gt;Hacker Rank&lt;/a&gt; archived
competitions have "easy" problems that can be a good fit for
beginners. One that I found and really like is &lt;a href="https://www.hackerrank.com/challenges/happy-ladybugs"&gt;Happy Ladybugs&lt;/a&gt; problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problems is basically as follows:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You get a string of letters. Each letter represents a ladybug of a
different color. Each letter also represents a location of the
ladybug.  A space (or underscore in the actual problem) represents a
free space. For example "AABC DDA" is a line of 2 A colored ladybugs
followed by a B colored one, C colored one, a blank space, 2 D colored and then one
more A colored. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can rearrange the line of ladybugs by swapping any ladybug with a
blank space.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A ladybug is happy if it is next to another ladybug of the same
color. The challenge is to determine if all the ladybugs can be made
happy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I like this problem because while it is non-trivial it is very
approachable. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To me, the key is that while you can rearrange the list you
don't have to. You only have to determine if it is possible to make
the ladybugs happy. You don't actually have to do so.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The edge cases are pretty easy to deal with - a string of length one
or two but then a little thought is required.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first insight is that if there are no spaces, you can't rearrange
the ladybugs so all you have to do is scan through the string to test
to see if every ladybug has a neighbor of the same color.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The next insight, and the big one is that if you have at least one
space you can arbitrarily re-order the string. You can show this is
possible  by using a single space to swap any two elements. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;space&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;someletter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;someletter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;someotherletter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;someotherletter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;space&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The final insight is that since you can arbitrarily re-order the
ladybugs as long as you have at least 2 of each color, you can make
them all happy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since my class is currently just starting dictionaries in Python we
solved this with lists and then transitioned to dictionaries.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's a dictionary based solution:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;are_happy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="sd"&gt;'''&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    This might miss some of the real edge cases in the hackerrank&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    problem. I haven't read the problem carefully in over a year and &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    forget what it specified for things like lists of only spaces,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    lists with only one bug etc.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    Also, the Hackerrank question uses an underscore (_) instead of a space.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="sd"&gt;    '''&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# handle a string of less than 2 ladybugs&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# handle the string of 2 ladybugs - both must be the same and not a space&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;' '&lt;/span&gt;


    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# handle the case of no spaces &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;' '&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# no spaces, every item must be next to one of the same color&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# so we loop from 1 to len-1 and for each item&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# check the one before and the one after&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# if we ever have an unhappy bug, we can just return False&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
	    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]:&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;

	&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# if we ever get here every bug has at least one neighbor of the same color&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# if we get here it means there's at least one space so we can rearrange the bugs&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# however we please so as long as there are at least 2 bugs of each color&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# we can make them all happy&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# replace the spaces with "" since we don't want to count them&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Since we know they were in the string we can rearrange but&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# they're no longer needed&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;replace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;" "&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;""&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# tally up all the bugs to see if there are at least 2 of each&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;bugcounts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;bug&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;bugcounts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;setdefault&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# set to 0 the first time we see this key&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;bugcounts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bugcounts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bug&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;


    &lt;span class="n"&gt;counts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bugcounts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;values&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;())&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# if there is any value of 1 in the counts then there's a lone ladybug&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# that can't be made happy&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# so we return True (happy) if there are 0 counts of 1 in our list &lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;counts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;count&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; 


&lt;span class="n"&gt;bugs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"abaccbe ff eggggggg"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bugs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;are_happy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;bugs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I love problems like these. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I just wish there was an easy way to find all contest problems of a
certain level like "easy" or "medium." If anybody knows please share
in the comments.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>problems</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/happy_ladybug/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2017 12:47:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Programming Idioms</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/programming-idioms/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org93083df" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org93083df"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org93083df"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I just read Jeff Yearout's recent post titled &lt;a href="http://k12csteaching.blogspot.com/2017/10/the-beginners-garden-of-concepts.html"&gt;The Beginner's Garden of
Concepts&lt;/a&gt;. Not directly related but it got me thinking about
programming idioms.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've been using the phrase "programming idiom" for years to describe a
short useful recurring code construct. I didn't realize that it was
officially "a thing" until doing a web search on the phrase years
later.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As our students grow from newbies on I think it's helpful for them to
see recurring and related patterns and programming idioms gives us a
name to apply to many beginner patterns. An early idiom might be
"finding the smallest in a list:"
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dataset&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;min_index&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dataset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dataset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dataset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;min_index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;min_index&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another is the very similar and more general "do something on every
item in a list:"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dataset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# do something to or with dataset[i]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
By talking about constructs like these as idioms it helps students see
and develop coding patterns. It also helps them to build mental
abstractions. Each of the above idioms are a few lines of code but
each are also a single concept. Students learn to think of them as the
concept.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
When students learn about list comprehensions in python they'll
rewrite the "do something…" more like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;dataset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
but the pattern or idea is the same.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Other early idioms might include swapping variables:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;tmp&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tmp&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and loops until an exit condition are met:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;not_exit_condidtion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# do stuff&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;modify&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;variable&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;that&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;checks&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;exit&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;condition&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even more difficult concepts like recursion can be described in an
idiomatic way:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;BASE_CASE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;something&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;new_x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;modify_to_eventually_get_to_base_case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="n"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;new_x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Patterns like these, or idioms, come up over and over again. We don't
have to explicitly mention them in our teaching but I think it's
helpful to our students if we do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>programming</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/programming-idioms/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 15:51:46 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>