<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about teachers)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teachers.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2018 21:34:41 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Ethics In CS Education</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-in-cs/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org79446d6" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org79446d6"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org79446d6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've been meaning to write about ethics in CS education for a
while. Probably since I saw &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/02/12/business/computer-science-ethics-courses.html?smid=fb-share"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; in the NY Times but got sidetracked.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was reminded when I saw this tweet by Hadi the other day:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;This message is bigger than Facebook. Computer science faces an ethics crisis. That’s why &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/codeorg?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@codeorg&lt;/a&gt; covers ethics and digital citizenship in our computer science courses. (And we’re thankful that most of the largest tech companies support us) &lt;a href="https://t.co/roSkAzANQM"&gt;https://t.co/roSkAzANQM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Hadi Partovi (@hadip) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hadip/status/977673429485731840?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;March 24, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think we can all agree that bringing ethics and digital citizenship
and, frankly, citizenship in general to our students is important. What I wonder is
what approaches will lead to meaningful results and what methods will
lead us to checking off the "covered that" box.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm skeptical of throwing an ethics course into the curriculum as some
places seem to be doing. A class might be required, might fulfill an
elective requirement or it might just be an extra course. If it's
required, what does it replace or are you just going to add more to
the student load. If it fulfills an elective credit, will it be
perceived as "the easy course" as opposed to say, theory and if it's
just an extra course, who's going to take it? Will it just become
preaching to the choir. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Better is what Hadi mentioned in his tweet - embed ethics throughout
all of your courses and while I think this type of embedding is
important and I'd argue necessary, I'm still betting it won't be
enough to make a difference.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When teaching a course, teachers cover the curriculum but when you
drill down to where they focus their time, it comes down to:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what they think is important for the kids to know.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what they think the kids will need for that high stakes exam.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If a teacher feels embedding ethical concerns is important they'll
spend time on it, if not, it will be lip service. Even if it's on the
high stakes exam, unless the teacher really believes that this is
important it will just be teaching to the test.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'd argue that it has to go even further since teachers can only do so
much. How many schools have honor codes and how many of us know
graduates from those schools who exhibit less than ethical behaviour.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So what do we do?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, of course we do have to embed ethical concerns across the
curriculum. Teachers should be armed with both the materials and time
needed to address ethical concerns but beyond that, we need teachers
for which ethical CS is important.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My friend &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ed_saber"&gt;Saber Khan&lt;/a&gt; has been facilitating a monthly #ethicalCS
twitter chat for close to a year now. I don't take part in too many
twitter chats but do recognize that they're important in raising both
awareness and community. I've also seen ethical CS issues more
frequently appear as conference sessions and professional development.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The next big step is to start at the beginning - pre service teacher
training and in my opinion, not with a course but rather embedding
ethical issues throughout teacher preparation. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If we want to crack this nut it can't just be from curriculum and from
the choir. Pre service CS teacher training is in it's infancy and has
not yet really found its form.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Much to my chagrin, a lot of CS Ed has gone the way of other Ed: Math
Ed, Science Ed, etc. and not in a good way. Let's see if we can make
sure that pre service CS teacher preparation develops to attract and
create great teachers for which ethical CS is part of their core. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>ethicalCS</category><category>preservicexs</category><category>teachers</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/ethics-in-cs/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Mar 2018 20:59:36 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>