<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about teaching)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/teaching.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 23:14:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Python - Editor or IDE</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/python-editors/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Earlier today I read Garth Flint's latest post on &lt;a href="https://gflint.wordpress.com/2017/05/25/python-editors-simple-wins/%0A"&gt;choosing a Python
environment for his classes&lt;/a&gt;. While our classes and populations are
different it looks like Garth and I share a lot of thoughts on the
subject.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started to write a comment to leave on Garth's blog but since it was
getting a little long I thought I'd write it up as a post.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The question of development environment can be an important one and
can make a big difference. When I designed the intro course at Stuy,
the fact that Dr. Scheme existed made the use of Scheme in the class
an option. Without it as a supportive and simple environment for the
students I probably wouldn't have been able to use Scheme even though
I really liked it as a teaching and learning tool.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Garth writes about issues relating to choosing a local development
environment so that's what I'm going to stick to here. If you want an
online environment check out &lt;a href="http://codesters.com"&gt;Codesters&lt;/a&gt; - a terrific online Python
environment with lots of educational support materials and features
and &lt;a href="http://repl.it"&gt;repl.it&lt;/a&gt; - an online environment that supports many languages and
is also developing great teacher and class support – I very much like
both of these platforms.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The first question is editor or IDE?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a user, I'm very pro editor. Learn a tool that you can customize to
your tastes and that will work for all sorts of text editing chores
from coding to document preparation to scheduling and more and you're
in great shape. Personally, I'm an &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs"&gt;Emacs wonk&lt;/a&gt; but there are other
choices as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a teacher, though, Emacs or another programmers editor can be
overwhelming for younger students and rank beginners. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This can make IDEs attractive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some IDEs are too big and cumbersome and can add even more cognitive
load than an editor - think Eclipse for Java development. If you think
writing
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kd"&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;args&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
is a lot of overhead, just wait until you have a novice try to start a
Java project in Eclipse.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Other IDEs are more streamlined. One common choice is
Idle. It's big advantage is that it's always available and is "part"
of Python. On the other hand, it doesn't seem to add much to a bare
editor and I've found that it can be somewhat confusing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Garth seems to have settled on &lt;a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/pycharm/"&gt;PyCharm&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="https://jetbrains.com"&gt;JetBrains&lt;/a&gt;. It's pretty
streamlined and really easy to get up and running. JetBrains also
provides a free community edition as well as a heavier professional
one available for purchase. Garth notes that it's a Python only IDE
but JetBrains has similar IDEs for a whole bunch of languages and I
seem to recall you can add plugins across their IDEs to basically make
them multi-language development environments.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I really like the JetBrains products and if I used an IDE I'm pretty
sure I'd use their products. As a teacher though, I find their IDEs a
little too powerful for my tastes. I want a learner IDE to provide the
bare minimum of features - an interactive REPL, a code window, run and
debug buttons, some completion and help - but to make those features
really easy to use. JetBrains does a little too much. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I ended up using in the past is &lt;a href="http://drpython.sourceforge.net/"&gt;Dr Python&lt;/a&gt;. For me it hit the
sweet spot. As an added bonus we were already using Dr. Racket (nee
Dr. Scheme) and Dr. Java so our students had a similar environment
across languages and even NetLogo looked and behaved similarly. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Is there a right answer? Probably not. Just as with choosing a first
language there are always trade offs. Besides, if you don't have the
right solution, there will be another one next week. Just recently I
saw &lt;a href="http://thonny.org/"&gt;this project&lt;/a&gt;. A new beginners IDE for python. It looks interesting
and worth checking out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The right IDE can make a big difference while keeping the overhead low
and giving just the right amount of support. For me, the last time
around it was Dr. Python. For Garth, it looks like PyCharm fits the
bill. Looking at the overall plan, I usually start the kids off with a
simple learners IDE and then transition them to a programmers editor
like Emacs as they gain more comfort and experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a postscript, let me share these links on how I use Emacs for
Python development (each with a video) as well as my series on how I
use Emacs in general:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs/"&gt;http://cestlaz.github.io/stories/emacs/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-12-python"&gt;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-12-python&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-13-yasnippet"&gt;http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-13-yasnippet&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>teaching</category><category>tools</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/python-editors/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 19:47:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Designing a course with constraints</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/design-course-with-constraints/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the hats I wear at Hunter is to build a new &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/2016-03-29-hunter-cs.html"&gt;CS Honors program&lt;/a&gt;
and to bring my particular brand of insanity to &lt;a href="https://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-cs-important"&gt;Hunter College CS&lt;/a&gt; as a
whole.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday was my last class for the semester so I thought I'd write a
bit about the course.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For the Fall semester, I taught an intro programming course to the
entire cohort. For some in the cohort, this was their first exposure
to CS. Others had one or more classes under their belt. It was a
Python based programming class and a big part of it was to start
building the cohort into a community. I'm going to work on tweaking
what I taught for next time around but the constraints of designing
such a course are pretty common – an intro course where the students
all want to be there the level of previous experience varies to some degree.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Second semester was more of a challenge. The "next" course was CSCI
135, CS 100 - like APCS but in C++. I could teach that but since some
of my students had APCS credit, they didn't need 135. This would break
up the group. There was also the issue of the students getting credit
for the course without showing any proficiency in C++.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately, Hunter requires students in 135 to take CSCI 136. A 1
credit programming lab. It meets once a week in a computer lab and the
students complete a weekly programming assignment. The lab meets for 2
hours. The instructor goes over anything that's needed for the lab
that hasn't been covered yet and then the students work independently
(with the instructors support) on the lab. Overall it works well. It
makes sure the students are spending at least a couple of hours a week
coding in a supported environment.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
How did 136 help me? I taught a 3 credit course where 1 day was
basically the lab component (what the students were to do in 136) and
one day was enrichment - the stuff I was going to do with them. This
enabled us keeping the cohort together and it also made sure that by
taking the class, the honors cohort members with AP credit would
indeed get up to speed in C++.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I was happy with the basic structure. I was able to cover some topics
in project development, testing, debugging, and software engineering but the
designing and teaching the class proved to be challenging for a number
of reasons.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One was timing. The lab class meets 1 day a week for 1 hour. My class,
2 days a week for 1 hour 15. This meant that if we were to keep the
lab to one day either the students would have less time or I'd have to
impose on them to stay late or come early. I wasn't happy with that
but given the inconsistency in the way the other sections handled lab
timings, I think it worked out OK.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some of the other difficulties included:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-1" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-1-1"&gt;The language was C++:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since the labs were to be done in C++, I had to use that as the
language for the class. That meant no "fun" libraries or frameworks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-2" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-1-2"&gt;The labs were solo assignments:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since the labs were solo projects and there was one per week it made
it very difficult to structure group experiences. I wanted to cover
things like group development, code review, working off of other
peoples code bases but this proved difficult with an outside separate
lab being handed down each week.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-3" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-1-3"&gt;Someone else dictated the language sequence:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The labs were designed to support what the students were learning in
135 and were only distributed a day or two before the week was to
start. This meant that I couldn't plan too far ahead and had to adjust
frequently. This should be easier next year.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-4" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-1-4"&gt;Labs didn't match the supplemental material:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The best example of this was when we were talking about testing. We
ended up using &lt;a href="https://github.com/philsquared/Catch"&gt;Catch&lt;/a&gt; as a testing framework. The problem was that
right afterwards the lab (and also 135 project) didn't lend themselves
to using a testing framework like catch. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were more challenges but overall I think the class went fairly
well. I'll know more when I get feedback from the students and when we
all look back next year with some perspective.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's been an interesting experience designing a class that had to
interleave with another, existing class. I've designed many classes
over the years and I know that whatever you plan, it probably changes
once you're actually in the classroom and working with the kids, or as
Mike Tyson said: "Everyone has a plan until they get punched in the
mouth." This has been a little more of a challenge but I think the
first go through went well and that the course will get better and be
better defined as we go through a couple more iterations. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>curriculum</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/design-course-with-constraints/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 15:38:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>It feels good to be helpful</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/feels-good-to-be-helpful/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I got some nice feedback today from a couple of disparate places. It
was another reminder that being a teacher isn't just about the kids
currently in your class but it's about who you are and everyone you
interact with. It's not just about teaching a subject but rather about
helping people get to where they can potentially go. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
About a year ago I started putting together a &lt;a href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/using-emacs-introduction"&gt;series of posts and videos&lt;/a&gt; showing
how I use Emacs. There were a couple of motivating factors. One, I
wanted to put together some resources for my students - something that
would take them from the Emacs tutorial to a point where they would
hopefully see the power of the environment and not buy into the IDE or
editor of the month hype but either really use Emacs proficiently or
use another editor (Atom, Vim) in a similar fashion.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The other reason was that I wanted to give something back to the
Emacs community. I don't create Emacs packages or otherwise contribute
but I figured, I'm a teacher, I can do what I do.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, earlier today I got an email thanking me for my videos and also
noticed that over on &lt;a href="http://irreal.org/blog/?p=6218"&gt;irreal.org&lt;/a&gt;, jcs wrote about moving over to
dumb-jump after seeing one of my videos. It's been nice seeing that
I've been of some value to jcs since I've learned a lot from his
blog. Emails, comments, and notes like this have driven me to continue
the series (even though It's been a busy couple of months). It's
gratifying that even without writing a line of code, one can give
something back to a community that they've found value in for years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A month or so ago, I had a chat with a former student who's finishing
up his last year in college. He was having trouble finding a job, I
couldn't figure out why he wasn't getting offers - he's really
talented. I tried to give him words of encouragement and reminded him
that I was available to help him - as I try to be for the entire
"family" in any way I could.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fast forward to today - I got an email telling me that he got a job
that he's very excited about. He felt the interviews with this company
were going well so he was waiting for them to resolve before reaching
out to me. He also told me that our talk was very helpful to him. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sometimes it's not just in a class where we can have a positive effect
but sometimes just a talk on the side. Sometimes many years later.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/feels-good-to-be-helpful/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 23:12:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A free multi-state clicker with built in redundency</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/thumb_clickers/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last Friday, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/guzdial"&gt;Mark Guzdial&lt;/a&gt; wrote about the woes of &lt;a href="https://computinged.wordpress.com/2017/03/31/the-need-for-better-software-and-systems-to-support-active-cs-learning/%0A"&gt;using clickers&lt;/a&gt; in a
class. The amount of effort required to use his school's approved
clicker technology sounds ridiculous so while we need tools to better
engage students in large class settings we need better tools that can
be integrated into our classes more easily.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've never used clickers. On top of stories like Mark's, there are  a
number of problems with using clickers in a public school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
You can't force students to buy them and in NYC, until recently,
students couldn't use their phones (which they also might not have).
Forgetting the expense, if the school provides them, is it one per
student? If so, who's going to administer the clicker to student
mapping and how will that be communicated to the teachers. If college
tech infrastructures are sometimes lacking, high schools are orders of
magnitudes worse. The resources just aren't there. Then we have to
deal with loss and breakage.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If a teacher somehow gets a class set of clickers, they have to deal
with mapping clickers to students for all of their classes and make
sure the right student has the right clicker. Again, loss  and
breakage is a problem.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Then you have to create the question content and hope that everything
works in class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The value added given the overhead just doesn't seem worth it
particularly since high school classes, while large, are not in the
hundreds and there are other methods of student engagement.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here's what I use instead. It's not perfect but it's low cost and low
effort with a pretty high return.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The basic configuration, is a simple three state broadcast device.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's not without its problems and I don't think it would work as well
in a large lecture but given the cost, it's well worth it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, what is it?
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/fonzup.jpg" alt="fonzup.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Thumbs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Periodically, I'll poll my class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;span&gt;
&lt;img width="30%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/sidethumb.png"&gt;
&lt;img width="30%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/upthumb.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img width="30%" src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/downthumb.jpg"&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Thumb to the side? Everything's OK. Keep going as you're going. I get
it. Basically, things are good.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thumb up? Speed up, you're going too slow, I got it five minutes ago or
some similar big positive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thumb down? I have no idea what you're talking about.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's cheap, easy, quick, and once you can get your class to buy in,
you can get a quick sense of the class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The downsides?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The class has to have a level of comfort so that students vote
honestly and don't just give you positive feedback.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No data collection.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The upsides?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;quick
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cheap
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;works on any topic on the fly
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;even if the votes are artificially skewed towards positive, it does
forces the class to be at least a little attentive and to engage in
some physical response
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can get analog responses by allowing students to adjust wrist
rotation
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As to the redundancy? I've never had a kid leave their thumb at home
or lose it and even if they did, they've got a second hand.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/thumbs/fonztwo.jpg" alt="fonztwo.jpg" align="center" height="200"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This also works in extreme environments. Try using a clicker or mobile
app with gloves or mittens on or underwater.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't teach large lectures so I don't know how this would work in a
huge class. I'd imagine it's still worth it given that it's so low
friction and low cost of entry even if it's not perfect.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>pedagogy</category><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/thumb_clickers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 21:23:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Rookie Season Redux</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/rookie-season-redux/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Today was the last day of classes at Hunter thus ending my first
semester of teaching at Hunter College.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I very much enjoyed the semester and my class and look forward to
working with the same group when the spring term starts in a few
weeks. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the same time, even though I'm a quarter century veteran teacher,
in many ways this was like my rookie season all over again.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My class was an honors intro class so the material wasn't new to me
but there were a number of adjustments going from high school to college.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I taught a few college classes as an adjunct back in the nineties but
I was a young teacher at the time and that was a lifetime ago.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The biggest difference is that we only met two days a week. Monday and
Thursday and we met for 1:45 rather than 45 minutes. The longer class
is nice but the twice a week means that you don't get that every day
reinforcement you have in high school.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It also means that there were times when we would go a week between
classes due to a single day off. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The biggest challenge, one that I'm continuing to work on, is figuring
out how much we can do in a class, what and how much to assign between
classes and what's the best way to motivate the student's to space out
the work while doing something every day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That wasn't much of a challenge at Stuy. Having been there so long, I
had a good feel for my students as well as the pace and rhythm of
Stuy. Hunter has it's own rhythm and pace and I'm still figuring it
out.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We also had to pivot early on as the student laptops didn't arrive
until a third of the semester was over.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On the other hand, much of my work these days has to do with
developing the overall honors program as well as Hunter's forthcoming
teacher education programs in CS so I'm only teaching a single class
right now and it's small.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
If there are any rookie teachers reading this, congratulations on
getting through your first semester. I know you guys go a little bit
longer, but you're in the home stretch.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Teaching right, particularly in public schools with large classes  will
always be an all in activity - certainly harder and more draining than
anything I ever did in industry but it does get easier as you learn
your school and students and develop your craft. 
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/rookie-season-redux/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 23:41:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>First day back, or not</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-day-back/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
The day after Labor Day. The day NYC teachers traditionally return to
work. For the first time in a quarter century, I'm not one of them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's weird.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Instead, I'm in the second week of Hunter College's fall semester. So
far so good on that front. I'm getting to know my students, planning
activities and overall having a good time. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But, I do have to reflect on some of the things I'm not going to get
to do this week:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not going to have the opportunity to be blindsided by a CS
schedule made without consulting me or any other CS teacher and having
to work frantically to fix it so that the CS teachers have the
programs and rooms they want.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not going to be able to have that panic attack when the NFS/NIS
server isn't working and no one can log in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm not going to sit through a mindless faculty meeting where nothing
is really ever accomplished.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
More seriously, I am going to miss seing my friends and colleagues
after the summer and Thursday - the day the kids get back is always a
thrill and I'm going to miss that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In a way, I'm experiencing a version of what retired teachers go
through. Many teachers retire in June but it's not until after Labor
Day when the change really sinks in.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Soon, I'll start posting CS teaching content again but for today, I
want to tip my cap to all the public school teachers in NY that are
going back to work today and who will shortly be teaching their five classes
of thirty four kids each &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-day-back/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-day-back/#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p&gt;also tipping my cap to my favorite TJ
teacher who's students are back today. I got called to task for
failing to mention her on my facebook shoutout.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>teaching</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/first-day-back/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2016 14:56:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>West coast trip - a nice close to act I</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;

&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/facebook.jpg" alt="facebook.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If I look at my leaving Stuyvesant and the NYC Department of
Education to join Hunter College as the end of Act I of my teaching
career, then our family's West Coast swing was a nice way to pull
down the curtain.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The impetus for the trip was visiting Batya - she's interning at
Facebook this summer and having an absolute blast.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The plan was to spend a few days in San Francisco, then a little south
to Mountain View, where Batya was staying, and then fly up to Seattle
for a couple of days.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, while out there, why not see if some of the StuyCS family
wanted to get together.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I knew I had a lot of former students out on the West Coast but still, I was
overwhelmed and humbled by the number of people who wanted to spend
time and catch up. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We kicked things off at Bloomberg Beta thanks to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/roybahat"&gt;Roy Bahat.&lt;/a&gt; Roy was
never actually my student but we've gotten to know each other over the
years and I value him as a friend and advisor. Roy provided the food
and the space and about 60 former students + a few old timers showed.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/bloomberg.jpg" alt="bloomberg.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of days later, we had a lunch meetup for the Googlers:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/google.jpg" alt="google.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and a happy hour at Facebook (sorry, no picture). Then in Seattle, a
nice dinner to close things out.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/seattle.jpg" alt="seattle.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Between these events there were some lunches, a barbecue at Batya's
place  and even a drive by visit with a former student at
Microsoft. Overall, it was easily over 100 students over the course of
the week or so we were out there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've often said that one of the things I'm proudest of is helping to
build the StuyCS family. A community of people spanning decades. Over
the week, we had events mixing students from the mid 90's to
youngsters currently in college and on their internships.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Seeing all these people meeting and supporting each other gave me a
"proud pappa" type feeling even though I didn't do any more than set
the stage for them getting together.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the week, the conversations were also great - not the straight
tech ones, but the ones that really made me proud of the crew. From
Seth talking about how to better get good CS Ed to more kids, to PJ
discussing why he feels it's so important to be an active mentor to
his young programmers and how to get them to be real thinkers, to
Mike, Sam, Kathy, and Leo discussing the disconnect between
privileged families and those struggling to get by. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What more could a teacher want than their former students being both
happy in their lives and careers as well as good people seeking to
make the world better for everyone.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The only thing that made me sad about the trip is that with all the
big events, I really didn't get a chance to spend the time I wanted
with everyone. I hope to do better next time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, I've now been at Hunter for one semester and things will really
ramp up in the Fall. I'm still a proud part of our StuyCS family and if
being a part of pulling it together is the legacy I left, I can live
with that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The trip was a nice symbolic way to lower the curtain on act 1. I'm
counting on the StuyCS family and all the other players to help so
that we can make sure act 2 is a success and we can build something
similar for more young people throughout the city and perhaps the country. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>community</category><category>teaching</category><category>tech</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 17:18:06 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>