<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>C'est la Z (tech)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/tech.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 11:33:28 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Hillary and Student Loans</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I read over Hillary's briefing on her initiative on
&lt;a href="https://www.hillaryclinton.com/briefing/factsheets/2016/06/27/hillary-clintons-initiative-on-technology-innovation/"&gt;Technology and Innovation&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A lot of it sounds good but, at least for the education piece, I have
my doubts. My feeling is that she's pretty much aligned with the
current administration education wise and the current administration
has been as bad if not worse than the previous with respect to public
education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While I have issues with some of the education pieces and very much
like some of the others, I don't want to get into that today. I want
to focus on one specific part of her plan. The part that defers
college debt for up to 3 years for founders and entrepreneurs. This
sounds great but is this really a good thing?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some initial responses from the education community is "what about
young teachers, don't they deserve some help on college debt? What
about nurses?…" and of course they're right. On the other hand, I
don't want people to go into teaching for 2 or 3 years just to get
some debt relief benefit and then jump ship. That's the Teach for
America model that I feel has become so harmful.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But again, that's not where I'm going with this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's start with "who are these founders?" I don't have any hard data
but I have read a couple of recent pieces that indicate that founders
right out of college are typically from well to do backgrounds. This
of course makes sense. A kid up to his or her eyes in debt from a poor
background. No savings, no property, likely a family, that is siblings
and parents who are also treading water can ill afford to take a big
financial risk. A kid from a monied family? Much more so. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This alone makes Hillary's plan a boon for the wealthy but not so
much for the people we need to give a hand up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Next, this plan talks about the founders and only says it will
"explore similar incentives"  for early employees, citing "10 to 20."
This doesn't seem right to me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now let's look further into the benefits. I don't know what the
success and failure rates are for startups. I've seen a bunch of
figures including:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;90% of startups fail within the first three years
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three out of four startups fail 
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Of 10 startups, 3 or 4 totally fail, 3 or 4 break even and the
others turn a profit.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know where the truth lies but I'd imagine that the success
rate for startup by a recent college graduate, wet behind the ears is
probably higher than for a more season professionals.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hillary's plan defers debt for up to three years. If any of the
failure numbers cited above are near correct it means that these kids
will have burned through up to three years with the experience of a
failed startup to show for it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've always advised my students, all things being equal, start at a
big or mid size company, develop your chops, learn how they do it,
further build out your network, and then go out and do your
thing. Most kids are better served not going directly from college to
their first startup.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So there it is. A plan that makes for great "press release" but is it
really addressing the issues?
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>education</category><category>policy</category><category>tech</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 21:38:01 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>