<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about tech</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/tech.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-02-16T13:07:17Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/tech.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/tech/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>West coast trip - a nice close to act I</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/</id>
    <updated>2016-07-18T13:18:06-04:00</updated>
    <published>2016-07-18T13:18:06-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/end-to-act-1/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf0fcac3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgf0fcac3"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgf0fcac3"&gt;

&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/facebook.jpg" alt="facebook.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If I look at my leaving Stuyvesant and the NYC Department of
Education to join Hunter College as the end of Act I of my teaching
career, then our family's West Coast swing was a nice way to pull
down the curtain.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The impetus for the trip was visiting Batya - she's interning at
Facebook this summer and having an absolute blast.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The plan was to spend a few days in San Francisco, then a little south
to Mountain View, where Batya was staying, and then fly up to Seattle
for a couple of days.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, while out there, why not see if some of the StuyCS family
wanted to get together.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I knew I had a lot of former students out on the West Coast but still, I was
overwhelmed and humbled by the number of people who wanted to spend
time and catch up. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We kicked things off at Bloomberg Beta thanks to &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/roybahat"&gt;Roy Bahat.&lt;/a&gt; Roy was
never actually my student but we've gotten to know each other over the
years and I value him as a friend and advisor. Roy provided the food
and the space and about 60 former students + a few old timers showed.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/bloomberg.jpg" alt="bloomberg.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A couple of days later, we had a lunch meetup for the Googlers:
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/google.jpg" alt="google.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
and a happy hour at Facebook (sorry, no picture). Then in Seattle, a
nice dinner to close things out.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/end-act-1/seattle.jpg" alt="seattle.jpg" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Between these events there were some lunches, a barbecue at Batya's
place  and even a drive by visit with a former student at
Microsoft. Overall, it was easily over 100 students over the course of
the week or so we were out there.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've often said that one of the things I'm proudest of is helping to
build the StuyCS family. A community of people spanning decades. Over
the week, we had events mixing students from the mid 90's to
youngsters currently in college and on their internships.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Seeing all these people meeting and supporting each other gave me a
"proud pappa" type feeling even though I didn't do any more than set
the stage for them getting together.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Over the week, the conversations were also great - not the straight
tech ones, but the ones that really made me proud of the crew. From
Seth talking about how to better get good CS Ed to more kids, to PJ
discussing why he feels it's so important to be an active mentor to
his young programmers and how to get them to be real thinkers, to
Mike, Sam, Kathy, and Leo discussing the disconnect between
privileged families and those struggling to get by. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What more could a teacher want than their former students being both
happy in their lives and careers as well as good people seeking to
make the world better for everyone.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The only thing that made me sad about the trip is that with all the
big events, I really didn't get a chance to spend the time I wanted
with everyone. I hope to do better next time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, I've now been at Hunter for one semester and things will really
ramp up in the Fall. I'm still a proud part of our StuyCS family and if
being a part of pulling it together is the legacy I left, I can live
with that.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The trip was a nice symbolic way to lower the curtain on act 1. I'm
counting on the StuyCS family and all the other players to help so
that we can make sure act 2 is a success and we can build something
similar for more young people throughout the city and perhaps the country. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="community" label="community"/>
    <category term="teaching" label="teaching"/>
    <category term="tech" label="tech"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hillary and Student Loans</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/</id>
    <updated>2016-06-30T17:38:01-04:00</updated>
    <published>2016-06-30T17:38:01-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hillary-loans/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday I read over Hillary's briefing on her initiative on
&lt;a href="https://www.hillaryclinton.com/briefing/factsheets/2016/06/27/hillary-clintons-initiative-on-technology-innovation/"&gt;Technology and Innovation&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A lot of it sounds good but, at least for the education piece, I have
my doubts. My feeling is that she's pretty much aligned with the
current administration education wise and the current administration
has been as bad if not worse than the previous with respect to public
education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While I have issues with some of the education pieces and very much
like some of the others, I don't want to get into that today. I want
to focus on one specific part of her plan. The part that defers
college debt for up to 3 years for founders and entrepreneurs. This
sounds great but is this really a good thing?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some initial responses from the education community is "what about
young teachers, don't they deserve some help on college debt? What
about nurses?…" and of course they're right. On the other hand, I
don't want people to go into teaching for 2 or 3 years just to get
some debt relief benefit and then jump ship. That's the Teach for
America model that I feel has become so harmful.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But again, that's not where I'm going with this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's start with "who are these founders?" I don't have any hard data
but I have read a couple of recent pieces that indicate that founders
right out of college are typically from well to do backgrounds. This
of course makes sense. A kid up to his or her eyes in debt from a poor
background. No savings, no property, likely a family, that is siblings
and parents who are also treading water can ill afford to take a big
financial risk. A kid from a monied family? Much more so. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This alone makes Hillary's plan a boon for the wealthy but not so
much for the people we need to give a hand up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Next, this plan talks about the founders and only says it will
"explore similar incentives"  for early employees, citing "10 to 20."
This doesn't seem right to me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now let's look further into the benefits. I don't know what the
success and failure rates are for startups. I've seen a bunch of
figures including:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;90% of startups fail within the first three years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three out of four startups fail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Of 10 startups, 3 or 4 totally fail, 3 or 4 break even and the
others turn a profit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't know where the truth lies but I'd imagine that the success
rate for startup by a recent college graduate, wet behind the ears is
probably higher than for a more season professionals.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Hillary's plan defers debt for up to three years. If any of the
failure numbers cited above are near correct it means that these kids
will have burned through up to three years with the experience of a
failed startup to show for it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've always advised my students, all things being equal, start at a
big or mid size company, develop your chops, learn how they do it,
further build out your network, and then go out and do your
thing. Most kids are better served not going directly from college to
their first startup.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So there it is. A plan that makes for great "press release" but is it
really addressing the issues?
&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="policy" label="policy"/>
    <category term="tech" label="tech"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
