<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>C'est la Z (Posts about tech community)</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/tech-community.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 15:00:20 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Hunter CS and NY Tech - it takes a village</title><link>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-tech-kickoff/</link><dc:creator>Mike Zamansky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf3adf97" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgf3adf97"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgf3adf97"&gt;

&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hunter-tech/hunter-tech1.jpg" alt="hunter-tech1.jpg" align="center" height="400"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="figure-number"&gt;Figure 1: &lt;/span&gt;The NY Tech community and Hunter CS at Yext&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
One of my goals when I came over to Hunter was to help establish
Hunter CS as the place to be for CS in the city. Hunter already had a
solid CS program before I joined but it isn't well known. It also
doesn't have an established tech culture.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It's an ambitious goal but if it can be done, what a game changer. A
lot of people talk about equity, diversity, and social justice but if
we can establish Hunter as the place to be for CS in NY, what a
win. An affordable, accessible institution where you can get a great
CS education.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The truth of course is that I can't accomplish this - at least not by
myself. I'm just one person. Fortunately, there are so many wonderful
people in the New York Tech community that want to help bring
opportunities to the kids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Last Thursday evening we got the ball rolling. Twenty five
representatives from the tech community got together at &lt;a href="http://yext.om"&gt;Yext&lt;/a&gt; with
about a dozen of our Hunter College CS students. The conversation
started with a discussion of perceptions of Hunter and the students
sharing what their experiences were like. By the end we were all
brainstorming as to how we can work together to best prepare Hunter
students to become members of the New York Tech community. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I know the students left the evening energized and I did as well. I
hope our friends in Tech felt the same.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://cestlaz.github.io/img/hunter-tech/hunter-tech-max-jess.jpg" alt="hunter-tech-max-jess.jpg" align="center" height="400"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="figure-number"&gt;Figure 2: &lt;/span&gt;Max talking about Hunter to Jess and the rest of the table&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had representatives from (in alphabetical order)
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Animoto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beeswax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Civic Hall&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eBay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genacast Ventures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JW Player&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meetup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MongoDB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Motivate (Citbike)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quentin Road Ventures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two Sigma&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Union Square Ventures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workbench&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yext&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
at the event and then there were plenty of people who want to be part
of this who couldn't make it on Thursday.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I told the participants at the event that I can't make this happen. I
can merely get the people together who actually can. I'm grateful to
all my friends who are now a part of this and I'm looking forward to
working with  them, my students and my colleagues  to create 
a Hunter CS to Tech Community pipeline that's second to none.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>tech community</category><guid>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/hunter-tech-kickoff/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 23:09:33 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>