<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="http://cestlaz.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Posts about theory</title>
  <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/theory.atom</id>
  <updated>2018-04-18T21:34:41Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/theory.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/categories/theory/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Sigcse2018 Making theory more acccesible</title>
    <id>http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-theory/</id>
    <updated>2018-03-13T19:21:43-04:00</updated>
    <published>2018-03-13T19:21:43-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>Mike Zamansky</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://cestlaz.github.io/posts/sigcse2018-theory/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div id="outline-container-org30b5456" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org30b5456"&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org30b5456"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next up from SIGCSE 2018 is John MacCormick's session on
&lt;a href="https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3159557"&gt;Strategies for Baing the CS Theory Course on Non-decision Problems&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
MacCormicks's stance is that CS theory  is tough the first time around
and using non-decision problems is a viable approach to make theory
more accessible to beginners. As MacCormick said in his paper:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
… a decision problem may ask the yes/no question, "Does this graph
have a Hamilton cycle?" The corresponding non-decision problem is,
"Please give me a Hamilton cycle of this graph if it has one."
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This leads to writing programs to explore concepts in CS theory rather
than just living in the world of proof. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
MacCormick goes on to say that:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For this audience, the key advantage of non-decision problems
is that they are more realistic: they match the previous programming
and algorithms experience of undergraduates more closely.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I love the idea. Writing a program can make an abstract problem more
concrete and can lead to better understanding for those of us who are
less math inclined.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My next thought was that this shouldn't just be a change implemented
in theory courses. Some of these ideas should move down to more
introductory CS classes. Not the hardcore stuff but light
introductions to the topics so that we can layer the learning. If we
introduce some of these concepts in CS 1 classes then when they get to
the theory class it won't be the students first rodeo.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've had success with this when teaching recursion early. I've also
done it with other concepts. When we teach the Towers of Hanoi, yes,
it's a nice recursion problem but really it's to get the students
thinking about run time and a bit of proof. likewise, when we do a
maze solver in NetLogo we're alluding to dynamic programming, search,
and path finding.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't have too much more to say on this topic right now. I'm not
enough of a theory guy to sensibly design these experiences. The good
news is that MacCormick has written an soon to be released &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/What-Can-Computed-Practical-Computation/dp/0691170665/ref=asap_bc?ie=UTF8"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; on the subject. I
signed up for a reviewer copy at SIGCSE and look forward to receiving
a copy. Once I do I hope to be able to find some gems that I can work
into CS 1 experiences.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="cs" label="cs"/>
    <category term="education" label="education"/>
    <category term="theory" label="theory"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
